<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tmx xmlns="http://www.lisa.org/tmx14" xmlns:eft="http://read.84000.co/ns/1.0" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" version="1.4b">
<header creationtool="InterText" creationtoolversion="1.0" datatype="PlainText" segtype="block" adminlang="en-us" srclang="bo" o-tmf="TEI" eft:text-id="UT22084-059-006" eft:text-version="v-1.0.1-2020"/>
<body>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-1">
            <prop type="folio">F.144.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཕགས་པ་རིན་ཆེན་དྲ་བ་ཅན་གྱིས་ཞུས་པ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་ཐེག་པ་ཆེན་པོའི་མདོ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The Noble Great Vehicle Sūtra The Questions of Ratnajālin</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-2">
            <prop type="folio">F.144.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སངས་རྒྱས་དང་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཐམས་ཅད་ལ་ཕྱག་འཚལ་ལོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-13"/>Homage to all buddhas and bodhisattvas!</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-3">
            <prop type="folio">F.144.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདི་སྐད་བདག་གིས་ཐོས་པ་དུས་གཅིག་ན། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-14"/>Thus did I hear at one time.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-4">
            <prop type="folio">F.144.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཡུལ་ཡངས་པ་ཅན་ན། སྤྲེའུ་རྫིང་གི་འགྲམ་ན་ཁང་པ་བརྩེགས་པའི་གནས་ན་དགེ་སློང་གི་དགེ་འདུན་ཆེན་པོ་དང་ཐབས་ཅིག་ཏུ་བཞུགས་ཏེ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The Blessed One was dwelling in Vaiśālī in a mansion located by the Monkey Pond, together with a great assembly of monks.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-5">
            <prop type="folio">F.144.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱམས་པ་ལ་སོགས་པ་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སྐྱེ་བ་གཅིག་གིས་ཐོགས་པ་རྣམས་དང་། སྐྱེ་བ་གཉིས་ཀྱིས་ཐོགས་པ་རྣམས་དང་། སྐྱེ་བ་གསུམ་གྱིས་ཐོགས་པ་རྣམས་དང་། སྐྱེ་བ་བཞིས་ཐོགས་པ་རྣམས་དང་། སྐྱེ་བ་ལྔས་ཐོགས་པ་རྣམས་དང་། སྐྱེ་བ་བཅུས་ཐོགས་པ་རྣམས་དང་། སུམ་ཅུ་དང་། བཞི་བཅུ་དང་། སྐྱེ་བ་སྟོང་གི་བར་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་ཐོགས་པའི་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་བྱེ་བ་ཕྲག་བཞི་བཅུ་རྩ་གཉིས་དང་། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>In the assembly were four hundred twenty million bodhisattvas. Some of the bodhisattvas, such as Maitreya, were held back by just one birth, while others were held back by two, three, four, five, ten, thirty, or forty births, with some bodhisattvas even held back by one thousand births.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-6">
            <prop type="folio">F.144.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དགྲ་བཅོམ་པ་བྱེ་བ་ཕྲག་དྲུག་ཅུ་དང་། ལྷ་བྱེ་བ་ཕྲག་དགུ་བཅུ་རྩ་དགུ་ལ་འདོད་པ་ན་སྤྱོད་པ་དང་། གཟུགས་ན་སྤྱོད་པའི་ལྷའི་བུ་རྣམས་དང་། རྒྱལ་པོ་ཆེན་པོ་བཞི་དང་། ལྷའི་དབང་པོ་བརྒྱ་བྱིན་དང་། མི་མཇེད་ཀྱི་བདག་པོ་ཚངས་པ་དང་། ལྷའི་བུ་ཤིན་ཏུ་དཔལ་བཟང་ལྡན་དང་། ལྷའི་བུ་ཟླ་བའི་འོད་དང་། ལྷའི་བུ་ཉི་མའི་འོད་དང་། ལྷའི་བུ་གྲགས་པའི་ཏོག་དང་། ལྷའི་བུ་མངོན་པར་དགའ་བ་དང་། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Also in the assembly were six hundred million worthy ones and nine hundred ninety million gods including the gods in the desire realm and form realm, the four great kings,
Śakra who rules the gods, Brahmā who rules the Sahā world, the god Great Splendor, the god Candraprabha, the god Sūryaprabha, the god Pinnacle of Renown, and the god Joyful .</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-7">
            <prop type="folio">F.144.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཀླུའི་རྒྱལ་པོ་མ་དྲོས་པ་དང་། ཀླུའི་རྒྱལ་པོ་རྒྱ་མཚོ་དང་། ཀླུའི་རྒྱལ་པོ་ནོར་རྒྱས་ཀྱི་བུ་དང་། གཟི་ཅན་དང་། ཀླུའི་རྒྱལ་པོ་དགའ་བོ་དང་། ཉེ་དགའ་བོ་དང་། ཀླུའི་རྒྱལ་པོ་བཏང་བཟུང་དང་། ཀླུའི་རྒྱལ་པོ་བཏང་བཟུང་ཆེན་པོ་དང་། ལྷ་མ་ཡིན་གྱི་དབང་པོ་སྒྲ་གཅན་དང་། ལྷ་མ་ཡིན་གྱི་དབང་པོ་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱི་འཁོར་དང་ཡང་ཐབས་ཅིག་གོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>In attendance were also the nāga kings Anavatapta, Sāgara, Vāsukin, Manasvin, Nanda, Upananda, Mucilinda, and Mahāmucilinda, as well as the asura sovereign Rāhu and the retinues of all the other asura sovereigns. </seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-8">
            <prop type="folio">F.144.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེའི་ཚེ་གྲོང་ཁྱེར་ཆེན་པོ་ཡངས་པ་ཅན་ན་དེད་དཔོན་སེང་གེའི་བུ་ལིཙྪ་བཱི་སྟོབས་མཐའ་ཡས་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་ཞིག་གནས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-16"/>At that time, in the city of Vaiśālī, there was a Licchavi named Limitless Strength, who was the son of Siṃha the captain.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-9">
            <prop type="folio">F.144.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེའི་ཚེ་སེང་གེའི་བུ་སྟོབས་མཐའ་ཡས་དེའི་བུ་གཞོན་ནུ་ལིཙྪ་བཱི་རིན་ཆེན་དྲ་བ་ཅན་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Limitless Strength, son of Siṃha, himself had a son, a young Licchavi boy known as Ratnajālin.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-10">
            <prop type="folio">F.144.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སངས་རྒྱས་མང་པོ་ལ་བསྙེན་<tei:ref folio="F.144.b"/>བཀུར་བྱས་པ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Since this child had previously served many buddhas, </seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-11">
            <prop type="folio">F.144.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཆོས་ཀྱི་ཚུལ་སྣང་བ་མཐའ་ཡས་པའི་སྒྲོན་མ་དང་ལྡན་པ་ཡང་དག་པར་འཛིན་པ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>he had come to possess the lamp that shines with the immense light of the Dharma way.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-12">
            <prop type="folio">F.144.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ན་ཚོད་ལོ་བརྒྱད་ལོན་པ་འདྲ་བ་ཞིག་གཉིད་ལོག་སྟེ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>One time, when he was around eight years old, he had a dream as he slept.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-13">
            <prop type="folio">F.144.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེའི་རྨི་ལམ་དུ་རྨིས་པ། ལྷའི་བུ་ཡོངས་སུ་དགའ་ལྡན། དགའ་ལྡན་གྱི་གནས་ནས་བབས་ནས་ཚིགས་སུ་བཅད་པའི་དབྱངས་ཀྱིས་བསྐུལ་ཏེ་མངོན་པར་སྨྲས་པ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>In his dream, the god Santuṣita descended from the Heaven of Joy and spoke to him, encouraging Ratnajālin with this melodious song:</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-14">
            <prop type="folio">F.144.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སེམས་ཅན་སྙིང་པོ་རྒྱལ་བ་སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱིས། །སྟོང་གསུམ་འཇིག་རྟེན་སྣང་བ་མཛད་ནས་བཞུགས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-17"/>“The essential being, the Victor, the Buddha, Abides, illuminating the entire trichiliocosm.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-15">
            <prop type="folio">F.144.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བསོད་ནམས་བརྒྱ་བསགས་གསེར་གྱི་མདོག་འདྲ་བ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>With vast accumulations of merit, he appears in golden hue.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-16">
            <prop type="folio">F.144.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བདག་ཉིད་ཆེན་པོ་གཟུགས་ཀྱི་མ་ལུས་མཛེས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The appearance of this great being is beautiful in all respects.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-17">
            <prop type="folio">F.144.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དཀྱིལ་འཁོར་བྱེ་བ་རབ་ཚང་གང་ཡིན་པ། །ཟླ་བ་སྟོང་ངམ་ཡང་ན་བྱེ་བ་ཡི། །འོད་ཟེར་དག་གི་དཀྱིལ་འཁོར་དེ་སྣང་བྱེད། །ཇི་ལྟར་གང་གཱའི་ཀླུང་གི་བྱེ་མ་སྙེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-18"/>“He is endowed with the light of ten million suns And shines like a thousand or even ten million Luminous full moons— As many as there are grains of sand in the Ganges.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-18">
            <prop type="folio">F.144.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་འདྲའི་དཀྱིལ་འཁོར་བྱེ་བར་ཚང་བ་ནི། །ཤར་ཕྱོགས་དཀྱིལ་འཁོར་མཆོག་ནི་སྣང་བྱེད་ཅིང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-19"/>“Shining like many millions of suns, He shines like the supreme disk in the east,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-19">
            <prop type="folio">F.144.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་བཞིན་ལྷོ་ཕྱོགས་དེ་བཞིན་ནུབ་ཕྱོགས་དང་། །དེ་བཞིན་བྱང་ཕྱོགས་དཀྱིལ་འཁོར་མཆོག་སྣང་བྱེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Those in the south and the west, And the supreme disk in the north.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-20">
            <prop type="folio">F.144.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇིག་རྟེན་མགོན་པོ་འོད་མཛད་སྤུ་ཡི་ཁུང་། །རེ་རེ་ནས་ནི་འོད་ཟེར་གང་དག་འབྱུང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-20"/>“The light rays that stream forth From each pore of this shining protector of the world Will,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-21">
            <prop type="folio">F.144.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རེ་རེ་ནས་ནི་འོད་བྱུང་དེ་དག་གིས། །ཟླ་བའི་དཀྱིལ་འཁོར་ཐམས་ཅད་མོག་མོག་མཛད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>each and every one, Make all full moons appear gloomy.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-22">
            <prop type="folio">F.144.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཀུན་གཟིགས་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་སྤུ་ཁུང་རེ་རེ་ནས། །འོད་ཟེར་འབྱུང་ཞིང་སྤུ་ཁུང་རེ་རེ་ནས། །འོད་ཟེར་བྱུང་བ་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་གང་གཱའི་ཀླུང་། །དྲུག་ཅུ་རྩ་དྲུག་བྱེ་སྙེད་རབ་གསལ་མཛད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-21"/>“From each pore in the skin of those who are omniscient, Light streams forth. The light that shines from him illuminates as many worlds As there are grains of sand in sixty-six Ganges rivers.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-23">
            <prop type="folio">F.144.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་ལིཙྪ་བཱི་གཞོན་ནུ་རིན་ཆེན་དྲ་བ་ཅན་དེའི་མཚན་མོ་འདས་ནས། ཕ་སྟོབས་མཐའ་ཡས་ལ་སྨྲས་པ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-22"/>In the morning, the Licchavi boy Ratnajālin told his father Limitless Strength,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-24">
            <prop type="folio">F.144.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡབ་མདང་སུམ་ལྷའི་བུ་ཡོངས་སུ་དགའ་ལྡན། དགའ་ལྡན་གྱི་གནས་ནས་བབས་ནས་བདག་ལ་ཚིགས་སུ་བཅད་པའི་དབྱངས་ཀྱིས་བསྐུལ་བ་བགྱིས་པར་གྱུར་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Father, last night the god Santuṣita arrived from the Heaven of Joy and encouraged me with a melodious song.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-25">
            <prop type="folio">F.144.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདི་ལྟ་སྟེ། དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་ལ་མཆོད་པ་བགྱི་བའི་ལས་བརྩམ་པའི་སླད་དུ་ཡབ་ལ་བདག་གསོལ་བར་བགྱིད་དོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Father, I am telling you this so that we can begin the practice of worshiping the Thus-Gone One.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-26">
            <prop type="folio">F.144.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་ལིཙྪ་བཱི་གཞོན་ནུ་རིན་ཆེན་དྲ་བ་ཅན་གྱིས་ཕ་སྟོབས་མཐའ་ཡས་ལ་ཚིགས་སུ་བཅད་དེ་སྨྲས་པ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-23"/>At this point the Licchavi boy Ratnajālin sang these verses to his father Limitless Strength:</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-27">
            <prop type="folio">F.144.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སེམས་ཅན་ཀུན་གྱི་དེད་དཔོན་རྫོགས་སངས་རྒྱས། །འཇིག་རྟེན་མཁས་པ་བསམ་ཡས་བདག་ཉིད་ཆེ། །སྐྱོབ་པ་དེ་ལ་ཁྱོད་ཀྱིས་མཆོད་དོན་མཛོད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“The captain of all beings, the perfect Buddha, The great being inconceivably learned in the ways of the world— Please, may you worship this protector, </seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-28">
            <prop type="folio">F.145.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདྲེན་པ་དེ་ནི་<tei:ref folio="F.145.a"/>འཇིག་རྟེན་འབྱུང་བར་དཀའ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>For such a guide rarely appears in the world.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-29">
            <prop type="folio">F.145.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཇི་ལྟར་ཨུ་དུམ་བཱ་རའི་མེ་ཏོག་ནི། །མདོག་ལྡན་མཛེས་ཤིང་ཤིན་ཏུ་དྲི་ཞིམ་ལ། །དྲི་ངད་ལྡན་ཞིང་རྡུལ་བཅོམ་ཉོན་མོངས་མེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-25"/>“Just like the uḍumbara flower, He has a beautiful color and delicious scent and fragrance. He is stainless and without afflictions.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-30">
            <prop type="folio">F.145.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་འདྲའི་མེ་ཏོག་མཆོག་ནི་རྙེད་པར་དཀའ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Such a perfect flower is hard to find.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-31">
            <prop type="folio">F.145.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེའི་ཕྱིར་བདག་གིས་ཡབ་ལ་གསོལ་འདེབས་པ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-26"/>“Father, thus I supplicate you:</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-32">
            <prop type="folio">F.145.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ད་ནི་དགྱེས་པའི་ཐུགས་ཀྱིས་བདག་ལ་གནང་། །གང་ཞིག་འཇིག་རྟེན་མགོན་པོ་འོད་མཛད་པ། །དོན་དམ་གཟིགས་པ་ལ་ནི་མཆོད་པར་བགྱིད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Right now, may you joyfully agree To worship the luminous protector of the world Who perceives the ultimate!”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-33">
            <prop type="folio">F.145.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལིཙྪ་བཱི་སྟོབས་མཐའ་ཡས་སེམས་དགའ་བས། ལིཙྪ་བཱི་སེང་གེ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་ལ་སྨྲས་པ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-27"/>The Licchavi Limitless Strength was delighted and addressed the Licchavi Siṃha:</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-34">
            <prop type="folio">F.145.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེད་དཔོན་རྒྱལ་བ་ལ་ནི་མཆོད་མཛད་དེབདག་གི་གཞོན་ནུ་བསྟན་ལ་གནས་པར་མཛོད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“O Captain, follow my son’s advice To worship the Victorious One!”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-35">
            <prop type="folio">F.145.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདྲེན་པ་ཤཱཀྱ་སེང་གེ་མཆོད་པ་དང་། །གཞོན་ནུ་མཆོག་གི་སྤྲོ་བ་བསྐྱེད་པའི་ཕྱིར། །ཁྱིམ་པ་བྱེ་བ་དྲུག་ཅུ་བརྩོན་པར་གྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-29"/>To worship the Guide, the Lion of the Śākyas, And to delight the wonderful youth, Six hundred million householders set to work.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-36">
            <prop type="folio">F.145.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བརྒྱ་བྱིན་ལྷ་མིག་སྟོང་དང་ལྡན་པ་དང་། །ཚངས་པ་དང་ནི་དབང་ཕྱུག་དབང་སྒྱུར་ལྷ། །བདུད་ཀྱི་བུ་ཕོ་དེད་དཔོན་བཟང་པོ་དང་། །བྱེ་བ་ས་ཡི་ལྷ་དང་ལྷན་ཅིག་ཏུ། །ཡངས་པ་ཅན་གྱི་དགའ་བར་ཐམས་ཅད་ཞུགས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Śakra with his thousand divine eyes, <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-30"/>The powerful gods Brahmā and Īśvara And Susārthavāha, son of Māra, Together with ten million earthly gods, All came to the delight of Vaiśālī.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-37">
            <prop type="folio">F.145.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གསེར་ལས་བྱས་དང་དེ་བཞིན་དངུལ་གྱི་ཁྲི། །བྱེ་བ་ཕྲག་ནི་སྟོང་དུ་ཚང་བ་དག །རིན་ཆེན་བདུན་གྱིས་དེ་དག་མཛེས་བྱས་པ། །རེ་རེ་ཡང་ནི་བྱེ་བ་སྟོང་དུ་ཚང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-31"/>Here they produced Billions of thrones made of gold and silver And ornamented with the seven precious substances. Each throne had billions of precious items.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-38">
            <prop type="folio">F.145.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཁྲི་ཡི་གཡས་དང་གཡོན་དུ་རིན་པོ་ཆེ། །རིན་ཆེན་སྣ་བདུན་རྒྱལ་མཚན་བཟང་པོར་བཙུགས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-32"/>Each side of the thrones was adorned with jewels And had a fine victory banner of the seven precious substances attached.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-39">
            <prop type="folio">F.145.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཁྲི་དེའི་ཚད་ནི་དཔག་ཚད་རངས་པར་ཡོད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The size of the thrones was several leagues.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-40">
            <prop type="folio">F.145.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྒྱལ་མཚན་དག་ཀྱང་དཔག་ཚད་ཕྱེད་པར་མཐོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The victory banners were half a league high.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-41">
            <prop type="folio">F.145.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྒྱལ་མཚན་རྣམས་ཀྱི་གཡས་དང་གཡོན་དུ་ནི། །དེའི་དྲུང་དཔག་ཚད་བས་མཐོ་སྟེགས་བུ་དག །རང་བཞིན་གཅིག་སྟེ་ནོར་བུ་རིན་པོ་ཆེ། །བྱེ་བ་ལས་བྱས་དཔག་ཚད་མཐོ་བར་འཕགས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-33"/>On either side of the victory banners Was a platform higher than a league Made exclusively of a single substance— Precious jewels rising more than a league in height.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-42">
            <prop type="folio">F.145.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཁྲི་ཡི་བར་བར་ལྷ་ཡི་བ་དན་ཡང་། །དཔག་ཚད་བས་ཀྱང་རིང་བ་ཤ་སྟག་དཔྱངས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-34"/>In between the thrones divine banners were hung More than a league long.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-43">
            <prop type="folio">F.145.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བ་དན་ལྡ་ལྡི་གསེར་གྱི་དྲ་བ་དག །དྲིལ་བུ་གཡེར་ཀ་དག་གིས་མཛེས་པར་བྱས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The banners featured nets of golden tassels Adorned with strings of bells.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-44">
            <prop type="folio">F.145.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཁྲི་རྣམས་ཀྱི་ནི་འོག་ཏུ་ཀ་བ་ཡང་། །བྱེ་བ་ཕྲག་སྟོང་བྱ་བ་ལེགས་པར་སྦྱར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-35"/>Beneath the thrones were well-fastened columns, More than one billion of them.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-45">
            <prop type="folio">F.145.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་གིས་འདི་རུ་ཁྲི་མཆོག་དེ་དག་ནི། །བརྟན་པར་བྱས་པ་སྒོ་གཏན་བཅུག་པ་བཞིན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>All of these perfect thrones Were firmly placed, as if bolted to the ground.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-46">
            <prop type="folio">F.145.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཁྲི་ཡི་སྟེང་དུ་གསེར་ལས་བྱས་པ་དང་། །གསེར་ལྟ་བུ་དང་དངུལ་དང་བཻ་དཱུརྱ། །དེ་བཞིན་ཤེལ་དང་སྤུག་དང་རྡོ་སྙིང་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-36"/>The surface of the thrones was made of gold— Golden and with silver and beryl, Crystal, coral, and emerald too.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-47">
            <prop type="folio">F.145.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>
                    <tei:ref folio="F.145.b"/>དང་། །དེ་བཞིན་རྩ་བ་དང་ནི་ཁོག་པ་ནས། །བྱུང་བ་མིན་པའི་མུ་ཏིག་གདུགས་དག་བྱས། །ཙན་དན་ཤིན་ཏུ་དམར་པོས་དམར་བར་བསྐུས། །རེ་རེ་དག་ནི་བྱེ་བ་སྟོང་དུ་ཚང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Also, at the bottom and the base <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-37"/>Were placed natural pearl parasols, Numbering in the billions And colored red with deep red sandalwood.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-48">
            <prop type="folio">F.145.b</prop>
            <prop type="alternative-source"/>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཁྲི་རྣམས་དང་ནི་ཁྲིལ་ཚུལ་ལྟ་བུ་ཡི། །མཁའ་རྟེན་དག་ཀྱང་བྱས་ནས་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Having produced the thrones <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-38"/>And the heavenly ornaments,<tei:note xml:id="UT22084-059-006-39"/> clear as water, on the thrones,<tei:note xml:id="UT22084-059-006-40"/>
                </seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-49">
            <prop type="folio">F.145.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ལ་ནི། །གསེར་གྱི་དྲ་བ་དང་ནི་གསེར་ལྟ་བུ། །དངུལ་དང་བཻ་དཱུརྱ་དང་དེ་བཞིན་ཤེལ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Golden nets were placed on them And adorned with gold, Silver, beryl, and crystal.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-50">
            <prop type="folio">F.145.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྤུག་དང་དེ་བཞིན་རྡོ་ཡི་སྙིང་པོ་ཡི། །མཁའ་རྟེན་སོ་སོ་བྱས་ནས་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-41"/>Having produced the ornaments of coral and emerald,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-51">
            <prop type="folio">F.145.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ལ་ནི། །རིན་ཆེན་དྲིལ་སྒྲ་ཤིན་ཏུ་སྙན་པ་བཏགས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Affixed to those were sweet-sounding bells</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-52">
            <prop type="folio">F.145.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྣམ་འདྲེན་སྒྲ་ནི་རྣམ་པར་གྲགས་པ་ཡི། །མཆོད་པའི་དོན་དུ་བདུག་པ་རབ་ཏུ་བཞག །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Resounding with the voice of the Guide. Fumigants were placed there for veneration.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-53">
            <prop type="folio">F.145.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡངས་པ་ཅན་གྱི་སྟེང་གི་བར་སྣང་ལ། །གསེར་གྱི་སྐུད་པ་ལས་བྱས་བླ་རེ་བྲེས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-42"/>In the sky above Vaiśālī Was a canopy sewn of golden thread.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-54">
            <prop type="folio">F.145.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གསེར་གྱི་སྐུད་པ་རེ་རེ་མཆོག་ཏུ་བཟང་། །རིན་ཆེན་ཆུན་འཕྱང་སྟོང་ཕྲག་བྱེ་བ་དཔྱངས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>From each and every golden thread Hung billions of tassels of the finest jewels</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-55">
            <prop type="folio">F.145.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མུ་ཏིག་རྒྱན་འཕྲེང་སྟོང་ཕྲག་བྱེ་བ་ཡང་། །རེ་རེ་གསེར་ལས་བྱས་པའི་སྐུད་པས་བརྒྱུས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-43"/>And billions of ornamental garlands of pearl Strung with golden thread.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-56">
            <prop type="folio">F.145.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡངས་པའི་གྲོང་ཁྱེར་གནས་པའི་ལིཙྪ་བཱི། །གང་དག་གང་དུ་འདོང་བ་དེར་ཉམས་དགའ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>All the Licchavis who lived in the city of Vaiśālī Were joyful, regardless of where they went.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-57">
            <prop type="folio">F.145.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ཚེ་ས་ནི་སྐྱེས་བུ་བདུན་སྲིད་གཡོགས། །གྲོང་ཁྱེར་ཡངས་པ་ཀུན་ཏུ་རས་ཡུག་བཀྲམ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-44"/>They covered the ground of the city of Vaiśālī With pieces of cloth the length of seven men</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-58">
            <prop type="folio">F.145.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དྲ་བ་ཅན་གྱིས་ཙན་དན་དམར་བཏགས་ནས། །རས་རྣམས་ལ་ནི་ལེགས་པར་བསྐུ་བ་བྱས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Printed with lattices of red sandalwood And made of well-spun fabrics.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-59">
            <prop type="folio">F.145.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱེ་བ་སྟོང་ཕྲག་བདུན་ཅུའི་སིལ་སྙན་དག །རྣམ་པ་སྟོང་རྣམས་གཡས་ཀྱི་ཕྱོགས་ནས་འཁྲོལ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-45"/>On the right side, seventy billion instruments Of thousands of different varieties rang forth.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-60">
            <prop type="folio">F.145.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཡོན་གྱི་ཕྱོགས་སུའང་བྱེ་བ་བདུན་ཅུ་སྟོང་། །ཤཱཀྱ་སེང་གེ་མཆོད་པའི་དོན་དུ་བརྩོན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>On the left side, a further seventy billion Were also engaged in venerating the Lion of the Śākyas.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-61">
            <prop type="folio">F.145.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་འདྲའི་བཀོད་ཆེན་བྱས་ནས་ལིཙྪ་བཱི། །གཞོན་ནུ་དྲ་བ་ཅན་གྱིས་དེ་ཡི་ཚེ། །དགའ་བའི་སེམས་ཀྱིས་ཕ་མ་ལ་སྨྲས་པ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-46"/>Having set forth such a great array, The Licchavi boy named Ratnajālin Joyfully announced to his parents,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-62">
            <prop type="folio">F.145.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སངས་རྒྱས་སྤྱན་དྲངས་སླད་དུ་བདག་མཆིའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“I am going before the Buddha.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-63">
            <prop type="folio">F.145.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གྲོང་ཁྱེར་མཆོག་ནས་མཁས་པ་དེ་བྱུང་སྟེརྒྱལ་བདག་ཆེན་པོ་ག་ལ་བར་སོང་ནས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-47"/>This learned one left the city And went to where the great victorious lord was staying.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-64">
            <prop type="folio">F.145.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡོན་ཏན་རྒྱ་མཚོའི་ཞབས་ལ་མགོ་བོ་ཡིས། །ཕྱག་འཚལ་དེར་ནི་གཞོན་ནུ་ཕྱོགས་གཅིག་འདུག །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The young man bowed his head at the feet of this ocean of virtues And stood to one side.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-65">
            <prop type="folio">F.145.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་ལིཙྪ་བཱི་གཞོན་ནུ་རིན་ཆེན་དྲ་བ་ཅན་ཡངས་པའི་གྲོང་ཁྱེར་ཆེན་པོ་ནས་བྱུང་ནས། བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ག་ལ་བ་དེར་སོང་སྟེ་ཕྱིན་ནས། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-48"/>Then the Licchavi boy Ratnajālin left the city of Vaiśālī and went to where the Blessed One was staying.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-66">
            <prop type="folio">F.145.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱི་ཞབས་ལ་མགོ་བོས་ཕྱག་འཚལ་ཏེ་ཕྱོགས་གཅིག་ཏུ་འདུག་གོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He bowed to the feet of the Blessed One and stood to one side.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-67">
            <prop type="folio">F.146.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཕྱོགས་གཅིག་ཏུ་འདུག་ནས་ལིཙྪ་བཱི་གཞོན་ནུ་རིན་ཆེན་དྲ་བ་ཅན་དེ་ལ་བཅོམ་ལྡན་<tei:ref folio="F.146.a"/>འདས་ཀྱིས་ཆོས་དང་ལྡན་པའི་གཏམ་གྱིས་ཡང་དག་པར་དགའ་བར་མཛད། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>With him standing there to the side, the Blessed One delivered a Dharma discourse to the Licchavi boy Ratnajālin</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-68">
            <prop type="folio">F.146.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡང་དག་པར་འཛིན་དུ་འཇུག །ཡང་དག་པར་གཟེངས་སྟོད། ཡང་དག་པར་རབ་ཏུ་དགའ་བར་མཛད་དོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>that delighted, captivated, and uplifted him, and made him utterly delighted.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-69">
            <prop type="folio">F.146.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་ལིཙྪ་བཱི་གཞོན་ནུ་རིན་ཆེན་དྲ་བ་ཅན་གྱིས་བླ་གོས་ཕྲག་པ་གཅིག་ཏུ་གཟར་ནས་པུས་མོ་གཡས་པའི་ལྷ་ང་ས་ལ་བཙུགས་ཏེ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-49"/>The Licchavi boy Ratnajālin then stood up, draped his shawl over one shoulder, and knelt on his right knee.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-70">
            <prop type="folio">F.146.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ག་ལ་བ་དེ་ལོགས་སུ་ཐལ་མོ་སྦྱར་བ་བཏུད་ནས། བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ལ་འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་གསོལ་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>With his palms together he bowed toward the Blessed One and asked,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-71">
            <prop type="folio">F.146.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་སང་དགེ་སློང་གི་དགེ་འདུན་དང་ཐབས་ཅིག་ཏུ་བདག་གི་སྡུམ་པར་གདུགས་ཚོད་གསོལ་བར་ཅི་གནང་། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Would the Blessed One and his monastic saṅgha agree to take tomorrow’s midday meal at my home?”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-72">
            <prop type="folio">F.146.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་ལིཙྪ་བཱི་གཞོན་ནུ་རིན་ཆེན་དྲ་བ་ཅན་ལ་ཐུགས་བརྩེ་བ་ཉེ་བར་བཟུང་སྟེ། ཅང་མི་གསུང་བར་གྱུར་པས་གནང་ངོ་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-50"/>Out of love for the Licchavi boy Ratnajālin, the Blessed One showed his acceptance of the offer by remaining silent.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-73">
            <prop type="folio">F.146.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་ལིཙྪ་བཱི་གཞོན་ནུ་རིན་ཆེན་དྲ་བ་ཅན་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་ཅང་མི་གསུང་བར་གྱུར་པས་གནང་བར་རིག་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ལ་ལན་གསུམ་བསྐོར་བ་བྱས་ཏེ། བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱི་ཐད་ནས་སོང་ངོ་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The Licchavi boy Ratnajālin understood that the Blessed One had accepted through his silence, and so he circumambulated the Blessed One three times before taking his leave.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-74">
            <prop type="folio">F.146.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་ལིཙྪ་བཱི་གཞོན་ནུ་རིན་ཆེན་དྲ་བ་ཅན་ལྷའི་དབང་པོ་བརྒྱ་བྱིན་དང་། མི་མཇེད་ཀྱི་བདག་པོ་ཚངས་པ་དང་། ལྷའི་བུ་དཔལ་བཟང་ལྡན་དང་ལྷན་ཅིག་ཏུ་ཡངས་པའི་གྲོང་ཁྱེར་ཆེན་པོར་ཞུགས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-51"/>The Licchavi boy Ratnajālin then entered the city of Vaiśālī along with Śakra who rules the gods, Brahmā who rules the Sahā world, and the god Great Splendor.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-75">
            <prop type="folio">F.146.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྤྲོ་བ་དང་དགའ་བའི་གཟུགས་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་ཞལ་ཟས་རོ་བརྒྱ་དང་ལྡན་པའི་རྣམ་པ་སྦྱོར་དུ་བཅུག་གོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>With enthusiasm and delight, they began to prepare abundant varieties of food.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-76">
            <prop type="folio">F.146.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྦྱར་ནས་དེའི་མཚན་མོ་འདས་པ་དང་གདན་བཤམས་ཤིང་ཡངས་པ་ལེགས་པར་བརྒྱན་ནས། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>When the night had passed, they set out cushions and decorated Vaiśālī.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-77">
            <prop type="folio">F.146.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ག་ལ་བ་དེར་སོང་སྟེ་ཕྱིན་པ་དང་། བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱི་ཞབས་ལ་མགོ་བོས་ཕྱག་འཚལ་ཏེ་ཕྱོགས་གཅིག་ཏུ་འདུག་གོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They then returned to the Blessed One, bowed to him, and stood to one side.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-78">
            <prop type="folio">F.146.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལིཙྪ་བཱི་གཞོན་ནུ་རིན་ཆེན་དྲ་བ་ཅན་གྱིས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ལ་འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་གསོལ་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The Licchavi boy Ratnajālin then said to the Blessed One,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-79">
            <prop type="folio">F.146.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་གདུགས་ཚོད་ལ་བབ་སྟེ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Blessed One, it is time for the midday meal.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-80">
            <prop type="folio">F.146.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེའི་དུས་ལ་ད་བབ་པར་མཁྱེན་ན་གདུགས་ཚོད་ལགས་ཏེ། དུས་ལ་བབ་ལགས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>If it please you, your meal is ready. The time has come.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-81">
            <prop type="folio">F.146.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་སྔ་དྲོའི་དུས་ཀྱི་ཚེ། སྨད་གཡོགས་དང་ཆོས་གོས་གསོལ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-52"/>Accordingly, on that morning the Blessed One donned his lower garments and Dharma robes.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-82">
            <prop type="folio">F.146.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལྷུང་བཟེད་བསྣམས་ཏེ་དགེ་སློང་གི་དགེ་འདུན་དཔག་ཏུ་མེད་པ་དང་ཐབས་ཅིག་ཏུ་སྟེང་གི་བར་སྣང་ལ་མི་བདུན་གྱི་<tei:ref folio="F.146.b"/>སྲིད་ཙམ་དུ་མངོན་པར་འཕགས་ཏེ་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Bearing his alms bowl, with his infinite saṅgha of monks he rose into the sky to the height of seven men and</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-83">
            <prop type="folio">F.146.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡངས་པ་ཅན་གྱི་གྲོང་ཁྱེར་ཆེན་པོར་གཤེགས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>traveled to the city of Vaiśālī.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-84">
            <prop type="folio">F.146.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བསྐྱོད་མ་ཐག་ཏུ་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པའི་བྱིན་གྱི་རླབས་ཀྱིས་སྟོང་གསུམ་གྱི་སྟོང་ཆེན་པོའི་འཇིག་རྟེན་གྱི་ཁམས་དེ་ཐམས་ཅད་རྣམ་པ་དྲུག་ཏུ་འགུལ། རབ་ཏུ་འགུལ། ཀུན་དུ་རབ་ཏུ་འགུལ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>As soon as he moved, the transformative power of the Thus-Gone One caused all the worlds of the great trichiliocosm to shake six times as they quivered, trembled, and quaked;</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-85">
            <prop type="folio">F.146.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཡོས་རབ་ཏུ་གཡོས། ཀུན་དུ་རབ་ཏུ་གཡོས། ལྡེག་རབ་ཏུ་ལྡེག །ཀུན་དུ་རབ་ཏུ་ལྡེག །འུར་འུར་རབ་ཏུ་འུར་འུར། ཀུན་དུ་རབ་ཏུ་འུར་འུར། ཆེམ་ཆེམ་རབ་ཏུ་ཆེམ་ཆེམ། ཀུན་དུ་རབ་ཏུ་ཆེམ་ཆེམ་སྟེ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>wobbled, rocked, and swayed; vibrated, shuddered, and reeled; clattered, rattled, and clanged; and tremored, shook, and convulsed.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-86">
            <prop type="folio">F.146.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལྟས་བཅྭ་བརྒྱད་དང་ལྡན་པ་རྣམ་པ་དྲུག་ཏུ་གཡོས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Thus they shook six times with eighteen omens.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-87">
            <prop type="folio">F.146.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཞན་ཡང་ཆོ་འཕྲུལ་བྱེ་བ་ས་ཡ་བརྒྱ་ཕྲག་སྟོང་སྙེད་སྟོན་ཅིང་ཡངས་པ་ཅན་དུ་གཤེགས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He also displayed trillions of miracles as he traveled to the city of Vaiśālī.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-88">
            <prop type="folio">F.146.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེའི་ཚེ་ལྷ་བྱེ་བ་ས་ཡ་བརྒྱ་ཕྲག་སྟོང་དུ་མ་ལྷའི་མེ་ཏོག་ཨུད་པ་ལ་དང་། པད་མ་དང་། ཀུ་མུ་ད་དང་། པད་མ་དཀར་པོ་རྣམས་དང་། ལྷའི་རིན་པོ་ཆེ་ལས་བྱས་པའི་མེ་ཏོག་རྣམས་དང་། ལྷའི་ཨ་ག་རུའི་ཕྱེ་མ་དང་། རིན་པོ་ཆེའི་ཕྱེ་མ་དང་། འཛམ་བུ་ཆུ་བོའི་གསེར་དང་། ལྷའི་རིན་པོ་ཆེའི་ཕྱེ་མ་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ལ་མངོན་པར་གཏོར། མངོན་པར་རབ་ཏུ་གཏོར་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>At that time, trillions of gods scattered and tossed blue, pink, red, and white lotuses, flowers made of precious divine substances, the powdered aloewood of the gods, powdered gems, gold from the Jambu river, and powdered divine gems upon the Blessed One.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-89">
            <prop type="folio">F.146.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལྷའི་སིལ་སྙན་བྱེ་བ་ཁྲག་ཁྲིག་ཕྲག་འབུམ་མངོན་པར་རབ་ཏུ་དཀྲོལ་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Trillions of divine instruments resounded.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-90">
            <prop type="folio">F.146.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལྷའི་རྒྱན་དཔག་ཏུ་མེད་པ་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་བརྒྱན་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Unfathomable divine ornaments adorned him.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-91">
            <prop type="folio">F.146.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྟེང་གི་བར་སྣང་ལ་ཙན་དན་དམར་པོ་ཤིང་རྟའི་སྲོག་ཤིང་ཙམ་གྱི་ཆར་གྱི་རྒྱུན་ཕབ་པར་གྱུར་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>In the sky above, a steady rain of red sandalwood powder fell to the depth of a chariot axle.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-92">
            <prop type="folio">F.146.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ལིཙྪ་བཱི་གཞོན་ནུ་རིན་ཆེན་དྲ་བ་ཅན་གྱི་གནས་ག་ལ་བ་དེར་གཤེགས་ཏེ། བྱོན་ནས་གདན་བཤམས་པ་དེ་ལ་བཞུགས་ཏེ། དགེ་སློང་གི་དགེ་འདུན་དང་། དགེ་སློང་མའི་དགེ་འདུན་དང་། དགེ་བསྙེན་དང་། དགེ་བསྙེན་མའི་འཁོར་རྣམས་དང་ཐབས་ཅིག་གོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-53"/>The Blessed One then arrived at the Licchavi boy Ratnajālin’s home and sat upon the seat that had been prepared for him along with the saṅghas of fully ordained monks and nuns and the assemblies of novice monks and nuns.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-93">
            <prop type="folio">F.146.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་ལིཙྪ་བཱི་གཞོན་ནུ་རིན་ཆེན་དྲ་བ་ཅན་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་བཞུགས་པར་རིག་ནས་རང་གི་ལག་ནས་བཅའ་བ་དང་། བཟའ་བ་དང་། མྱང་བ་བཟང་པོ་རབ་ཏུ་མང་པོས་ཚིམ་པར་བྱེད་ཅིང་གང་བཞེད་པ་སྟོབ་པར་བྱེད་དོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Seeing that he had arrived, the Licchavi boy Ratnajālin personally served the Blessed One with an abundance of the finest food, drink, and sweets, to please him and serve him everything he wished for.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-94">
            <prop type="folio">F.146.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་ལིཙྪ་བཱི་གཞོན་ནུ་རིན་ཆེན་དྲ་བ་ཅན་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་ཞལ་ཟས་གསོལ་ལགས་པར་རིག་ནས་ལྷུང་བཟེད་བླངས་ཏེ་ཆབ་ཕུལ་ནས་ཕྱག་བཅབས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>When the Licchavi boy Ratnajālin noticed that the Blessed One had finished eating, he picked up the alms bowl, offered water, and covered the Blessed One’s hands.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-95">
            <prop type="folio">F.147.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱེ་བ་ཁྲག་<tei:ref folio="F.147.a"/>ཁྲིག་འབུམ་རི་བའི་ཆོས་གོས་གསུམ་གྱིས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ལ་མངོན་པར་གསོལ་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He then dressed the Blessed One with a priceless set of the three Dharma robes.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-96">
            <prop type="folio">F.147.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དགེ་སློང་གི་དགེ་འདུན་དང་། དགེ་སློང་མའི་དགེ་འདུན་དང་། དགེ་བསྙེན་དང་། དགེ་བསྙེན་མའི་འཁོར་རྣམས་ལ་ཡང་ཆོས་གོས་གསུམ་གྱིས་མངོན་པར་གཡོགས་ཏེ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He also dressed the saṅghas of fully ordained monks and nuns and the assemblies of novice monks and nuns with sets of the three Dharma robes.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-97">
            <prop type="folio">F.147.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ཅིའི་ཕྱིར་ཞེ་ན། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Why?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-98">
            <prop type="folio">F.147.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདི་ལྟར་དེ་ནི་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱི་མཐུས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He did this because he was moved by the power of the Blessed One.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-99">
            <prop type="folio">F.147.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་ལིཙྪ་བཱི་གཞོན་ནུ་རིན་ཆེན་དྲ་བ་ཅན་གྱིས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ལ་འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་གསོལ་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-54"/>The Licchavi boy Ratnajālin then asked the Blessed One,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-100">
            <prop type="folio">F.147.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གལ་ཏེ་ཞུ་བ་ལུང་བསྟན་པའི་སླད་དུ་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་བདག་ལ་སྐབས་ཕྱེ་ན། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“If the Blessed One were to grant me the opportunity to request a teaching,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-101">
            <prop type="folio">F.147.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་ལ་བདག་ཕྱོགས་འགའ་ཞིག་ཞུའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>I would like to ask the Blessed Thus-Gone One a few questions.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-102">
            <prop type="folio">F.147.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་ལིཙྪ་བཱི་གཞོན་ནུ་རིན་ཆེན་དྲ་བ་ཅན་ལ་འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་བཀའ་སྩལ་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The Blessed One responded to the Licchavi boy Ratnajālin,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-103">
            <prop type="folio">F.147.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཞོན་ནུ་ཁྱོད་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་ལ་གང་དང་གང་སོམ་ཉི་ཡོད་པ་ཞུས་ཤིག་དང་། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Young man, you may ask the Thus-Gone One anything you are concerned with.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-104">
            <prop type="folio">F.147.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ངས་དེ་དང་དེའི་ཞུ་བ་ལུང་བསྟན་པས་སེམས་རངས་པར་བྱའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Then I shall delight you with teachings that answer your questions.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-105">
            <prop type="folio">F.147.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་ལིཙྪ་བཱི་གཞོན་ནུ་རིན་ཆེན་དྲ་བ་ཅན་གྱིས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ལ་འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་གསོལ་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-56"/>The Licchavi boy Ratnajālin then asked the Blessed One,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-106">
            <prop type="folio">F.147.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་འཇིག་རྟེན་གྱི་ཁམས་གཞན་དག་ན། སངས་རྒྱས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་སྔོན་གྱི་སྨོན་ལམ་དང་ལྡན་པ་བཞུགས་ཤིང་འཚོ་བ་གང་དག་གི་མཚན་ཐོས་པ་ཙམ་གྱིས་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའི་ཐེག་པ་ལ་ཡང་དག་པར་གནས་པའི་རིགས་ཀྱི་བུའམ་རིགས་ཀྱི་བུ་མོ་སོམ་ཉི་མ་མཆིས་ཤིང་ཐེ་ཙོམ་མ་མཆིས་པར་འགྱུར། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Blessed One, in other worlds, are there blessed buddhas that through their previous aspirations have names that, when merely heard, help noble sons and daughters who follow the Bodhisattva Vehicle to end all doubt and hesitation,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-107">
            <prop type="folio">F.147.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཕྱིར་མི་ལྡོག་ཅིང་བླ་ན་མ་མཆིས་པ་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་བྱང་ཆུབ་ཏུ་ཡང་འགྱུར། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>to become irreversible and fully awaken to unsurpassed and perfect buddhahood,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-108">
            <prop type="folio">F.147.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཚེ་རབས་དྲན་པ་དང་ཡང་ལྡན་པར་འགྱུར། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>to gain recollection of past lives,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-109">
            <prop type="folio">F.147.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ནམ་དུ་ཡང་སེར་སྣའི་སེམས་དང་ལྷན་ཅིག་མི་གནས། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>to never have a stingy attitude,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-110">
            <prop type="folio">F.147.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའི་འཁོར་གྱིས་ཀྱང་ཡོངས་སུ་བསྐོར་བར་འགྱུར། ཉན་ཐོས་ཀྱི་འཁོར་དང་བྲལ་བར་འགྱུར། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>to be surrounded by the bodhisattva assembly and to be without the assembly of hearers,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-111">
            <prop type="folio">F.147.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡོན་ཏན་གྲངས་མེད་པ་བྱེ་བ་ཁྲག་ཁྲིག་ཕྲག་འབུམ་གྱིས་ཀྱང་ཡོངས་སུ་བཟུང་བར་འགྱུར། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>to acquire countless trillions of virtues,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-112">
            <prop type="folio">F.147.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སངས་རྒྱས་ཐམས་ཅད་མངོན་པར་དགྱེས་པར་བགྱིས་པས་སེམས་ཅན་ཐམས་ཅད་ཡང་དག་པར་ཚིམ་པར་བགྱིད། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>to satisfy all beings by pleasing all the buddhas,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-113">
            <prop type="folio">F.147.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བདུད་ཐམས་ཅད་ཤིན་ཏུ་སྐྲག་པར་བགྱིད། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>to terrify the māras,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-114">
            <prop type="folio">F.147.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱི་ཞིང་ཐམས་ཅད་སྦྱོང་། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>to purify all buddha realms,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-115">
            <prop type="folio">F.147.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སེམས་ཅན་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱི་སེམས་ཀྱི་བསམ་པའི་དྲི་མ་སེལ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>to cleanse the stains in the minds of all beings,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-116">
            <prop type="folio">F.147.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སེམས་ཅན་<tei:ref folio="F.147.b"/>ཐམས་ཅད་ཆོས་དཀར་པོ་ལ་ཡང་དག་པར་བསྐུལ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>to inspire all beings to the virtuous Dharma,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-117">
            <prop type="folio">F.147.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལྷས་ཀྱང་ཡོངས་སུ་བཟུང་བར་འགྱུར། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>to be protected by the gods,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-118">
            <prop type="folio">F.147.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔས་ཀྱང་བསམ་པར་འགྱུར། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>to be considered by the bodhisattvas,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-119">
            <prop type="folio">F.147.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པས་ཀྱང་བྱིན་གྱིས་རློབ་པར་མཛད། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>to be blessed by the thus-gone ones,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-120">
            <prop type="folio">F.147.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ནམས་ཀྱང་སངས་རྒྱས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་རྣམས་དང་འབྲལ་བར་མི་འགྱུར། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>to never be separated from the blessed buddhas,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-121">
            <prop type="folio">F.147.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྣམ་པ་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱི་མཆོག་དང་ལྡན་པས་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའི་སྤྱོད་པ་དག་ཀྱང་ཡོངས་སུ་རྫོགས་པར་འགྱུར། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>to perfect bodhisattva conduct by possessing the finest qualities,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-122">
            <prop type="folio">F.147.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྒྲ་དབྱངས་ཀྱི་རྣམ་པ་སྟོང་ཕྲག་བརྒྱད་ཅུ་རྩ་བཞི་ཡོངས་སུ་རྫོགས་པ་ཐོབ་པར་འགྱུར། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>to gain the entirety of the 84,000 verbal expressions,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-123">
            <prop type="folio">F.147.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཚངས་པའི་དབྱངས་སུ་འགྱུར། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>to attain the voice of Brahmā ,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-124">
            <prop type="folio">F.147.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇིག་རྟེན་གྱི་ཁམས་ཐམས་ཅད་དང་འཐུན་པའི་སྒྲ་དབྱངས་དང་ལྡན་པ་ལྟ་བཞུགས་ལགས་སམ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>and to gain a voice that is in conformity with all worlds?”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-125">
            <prop type="folio">F.147.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་སྐད་ཅེས་གསོལ་པ་དང་། བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་ལིཙྪ་བཱི་གཞོན་ནུ་རིན་ཆེན་དྲ་བ་ཅན་ལ་འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་བཀའ་སྩལ་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-57"/>The Blessed One answered the Licchavi boy Ratnajālin,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-126">
            <prop type="folio">F.147.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཞོན་ནུ་ལེགས་སོ་ལེགས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Excellent, excellent, young man.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-127">
            <prop type="folio">F.147.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་ཁྱོད་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་ལ། དོན་འདི་འདྲི་བར་སེམས་པ་ནི་སྤོབས་པ་ལེགས་ཤིང་དཔྱོད་པ་བཟང་ངོ་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Your thought to ask the Thus-Gone One about such subjects reflects excellent eloquence and fine analysis.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-128">
            <prop type="folio">F.147.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེའི་ཕྱིར་གཞོན་ནུ་ཁྱོད་ལེགས་པར་ཉོན་ལ་ཡིད་ལ་ཟུང་ཤིག་དང་ངས་ཁྱོད་ལ་བཤད་དོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Thus, listen well, young man, and bear what I say in mind. Then I will teach you.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-129">
            <prop type="folio">F.147.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་དེ་ལྟར་འཚལ་ལོ་ཞེས་གསོལ་ཏེ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Blessed One, I shall do just that.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-130">
            <prop type="folio">F.147.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་རིན་ཆེན་དྲ་བ་ཅན་སེམས་རྩེ་གཅིག་ཏུ་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱི་ལྟར་ཉན་པ་དང་། བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་དེ་ལ་འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་བཀའ་སྩལ་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-59"/>The bodhisattva Ratnajālin listened as the Blessed One had instructed, and so the Blessed One said,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-131">
            <prop type="folio">F.147.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཞོན་ནུ་འདི་ནས་ཤར་ཕྱོགས་ལོགས་ན་འཇིག་རྟེན་གྱི་ཁམས་མུ་ཏིག་ཅན་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་ཞིག་ཡོད་དེ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Young man, to the east of here there is a world called Pearled.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-132">
            <prop type="folio">F.147.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཞོན་ནུ་འདི་ལྟ་སྟེ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Young man, consider this:</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-133">
            <prop type="folio">F.147.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྲིད་པའི་རྩེ་མོ་གང་གཱའི་ཀླུང་གི་བྱེ་མ་སྙེད་དུ་གྱུར་ལ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>There are as many peaks of existence as there are grains of sand in the Ganges.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-134">
            <prop type="folio">F.147.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་དག་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱང་རྡུལ་ཕྲ་མོའི་རྡུལ་སྙེད་ཀྱིས་ཡོངས་སུ་གང་བར་གྱུར་ཅིང་། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>And all those too are filled with the smallest possible particles.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-135">
            <prop type="folio">F.147.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་སྐྱེས་བུ་འགའ་ཞིག་བྱུང་བས་དེ་དག་ལ་རྡུལ་ཕྲ་མོའི་རྡུལ་ཅིག་ཁྱེར་ཏེ</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>If a person then came along and carried away one single such particle and</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-136">
            <prop type="folio">F.147.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཇི་ཙམ་དུ་འཇིག་རྟེན་གྱི་ཁམས་སྲིད་པའི་རྩེ་མོའི་མཐས་གཏུགས་པ་དེ་དག་རྡུལ་ཕྲ་མོའི་རྡུལ་གྱིས་ཡོངས་སུ་གང་བ་ཇི་སྙེད་པ་དེ་སྙེད་ཀྱི་སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱི་ཞིང་བྱེ་བ་ཁྲག་ཁྲིག་ཕྲག་འབུམ་འདས་ནས་རྡུལ་ཕྲ་མོའི་རྡུལ་གཅིག་འཇོག་ན</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>placed it in a spot past as many trillions of buddha realms as there are smallest particles in all those world systems under the peaks of existence—</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-137">
            <prop type="folio">F.148.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཞོན་ནུ་རྣམ་གྲངས་དེ་དང་གྲངས་དེའི་གཞིས་ཡུན་རིང་པོ་འདས་པས་རྡུལ་ཕྲ་མོའི་རྡུལ་གྱི་ཕུང་པོ་ཆེན་པོའི་མཐའ་དེ་དག་ཟད་པའམ། <tei:ref folio="F.148.a"/>གཏུགས་པར་འགྱུར་རམ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>then, young man, by repeating this in the same way for a long time, would that great mass of particles eventually run out and reach its limit?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-138">
            <prop type="folio">F.148.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཞོན་ནུ་དེ་ཅི་སྙམ་དུ་སེམས། འཇིག་རྟེན་གྱི་ཁམས་གང་དུ་སྐྱེས་བུ་དེས་རྡུལ་ཕྲ་རབ་ཀྱི་རྡུལ་དེ་དག་བཞག་པའམ་མ་བཞག་པ་དེ་དག་བསམ་པའམ། བགྲང་བའམ། གཞལ་བའམ། ཉེ་བར་བརྟག་པར་སླའམ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Now, young man, tell me, would it be easy to consider, count, assess, or determine the places in the universe where that person placed or did not place those particles?”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-139">
            <prop type="folio">F.148.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གསོལ་པ་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་དེ་ནི་མ་ལགས་ཏེ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-60"/>“Blessed One, it would not be easy.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-140">
            <prop type="folio">F.148.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་དེའི་སླད་དུ་གང་ཞིག་དཔེ་འདི་བཤད་པ་ལ་ཡང་དག་པའི་འདུ་ཤེས་བསྐྱེད་པར་འགྱུར་བའི་སེམས་ཅན་དེ་དག་ནི་ཤེས་པའི་ཕུང་པོ་མཆོག་དང་ལྡན་པར་འགྱུར་བ་ལགས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Blessed One, for that reason, anyone who gets the right sense of this analogy that you have expressed would gain a great degree of understanding.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-141">
            <prop type="folio">F.148.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཞོན་ནུ་འཇིག་རྟེན་གྱི་ཁམས་གང་དུ་སྐྱེས་བུ་དེས་རྡུལ་ཕྲ་མོའི་རྡུལ་དེ་དག་བཞག་གམ། འོན་ཏེ་མ་བཞག་པའི་འཇིག་རྟེན་གྱི་ཁམས་དེ་དག་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱི་འོག་གི་ཆུའི་ཕུང་པོ་ནས་བཟུང་ནས། སྲིད་པའི་རྩེ་མོ་ལ་ཐུག་གི་བར་གྱི་རྡུལ་ཕྲ་མོའི་རྡུལ་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་ཡོངས་སུ་གང་བར་གྱུར་ལ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-61"/>The Blessed One said, “Young man, if all the worlds in which that person placed a particle, or alternatively the worlds in which that person did not place a particle— ranging from the mass of water underlying these worlds up to their peaks—were filled with minute particles, and</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-142">
            <prop type="folio">F.148.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྐྱེས་བུ་གཉིས་པ་ཞིག་བྱུང་བས་དེ་དག་ལས་རྡུལ་ཕྲ་མོའི་རྡུལ་གཅིག་ཁྱེར་ཏེཇི་ཙམ་དུ་འཇིག་རྟེན་གྱི་ཁམས་དེ་དག་གི་རྡུལ་ཕྲ་མོའི་རྡུལ་དེ་སྙེད་ཀྱི་སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱི་ཞིང་བྱེ་བ་ཁྲག་ཁྲིག་ཕྲག་འབུམ་འདས་ནས་རྡུལ་ཕྲ་མོའི་རྡུལ་གཅིག་འཇོག་ན། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>if a second person came along and removed a single particle from them at a time and placed it in a spot past as many trillions of buddha realms as there were minute particles in those worlds, then,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-143">
            <prop type="folio">F.148.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཞོན་ནུ་རྣམ་གྲངས་དེས་ན་ཡུན་རིང་པོ་འདས་པས་རྡུལ་ཕྲ་མོའི་རྡུལ་བསགས་པའི་ཕུང་པོ་ཆེན་པོ་དེ་འདོར་བར་འགྱུར་རོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>young man, by repeating this for a long time, eventually that great mass of particles would become dispersed.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-144">
            <prop type="folio">F.148.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཞོན་ནུ་རྣམ་གྲངས་དེས་ན་སྐྱེས་བུ་ཕྱི་མ་དེས་གྲངས་མེད་པ་བརྒྱ་སྟོང་དགུ་བཅུ་རྩ་དགུར་བསྒྱུར་བ་འདས་ནས་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Young man, by this way of proceeding, the latter person would travel past nine million nine hundred thousand incalculable numbers of worlds and</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-145">
            <prop type="folio">F.148.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱི་ཞིང་གྲངས་མེད་པ་བྱེ་བ་ཁྲག་ཁྲིག་ཕྲག་འབུམ་སྙེད་འདས་པ་ན་འཇིག་རྟེན་གྱི་ཁམས་མུ་ཏིག་ཅན་ནོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>thus arrive past countless trillions of buddha realms. <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-62"/>“That is where the world called Pearled is located.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-146">
            <prop type="folio">F.148.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ན་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་དགྲ་བཅོམ་པ་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་སངས་རྒྱས་རིན་ཆེན་འོད་ཟེར་ཟླ་བས་བརྒྱན་པ་མཁས་པའི་གཟི་བརྗིད་དབྱངས་ཀྱི་དབང་ཕྱུག་གི་རྒྱལ་པོ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་བཞུགས་ཏེ་འཚོ་ཞིང་གཞེས་ལ་ཆོས་ཀྱང་སྟོན་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>There the thus-gone one, the worthy one, the perfect Buddha Majestic King with the Splendorous Voice of Learning Adorned by Precious Moonlight lives, abides, and teaches the Dharma.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-147">
            <prop type="folio">F.148.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཞོན་ནུ་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའི་ཐེག་པ་ལ་ཡང་དག་པར་གནས་པའི་རིགས་ཀྱི་བུའམ། རིགས་ཀྱི་བུ་མོ་གང་ལ་ལ་ཞིག་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་དགྲ་བཅོམ་པ་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་སངས་རྒྱས་རིན་ཆེན་འོད་ཟེར་ཟླ་བས་བརྒྱན་པ་མཁས་པའི་གཟི་བརྗིད་དབྱངས་ཀྱི་དབང་ཕྱུག་རྒྱལ་པོ་དེའི་མཚན་<tei:ref folio="F.148.b"/>ལ་སོམ་ཉི་མི་ཟ་ཞིང་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Young man, those noble sons or daughters who abide in the Bodhisattva Vehicle, who have no doubt regarding the name of the thus-gone, worthy, perfect Buddha Majestic King with the Splendorous Voice of Learning Adorned by Precious Moonlight, and</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-148">
            <prop type="folio">F.148.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ངས་མཐོང་བ་ལ་ཡང་ཡིད་ཆེས་ན་དེའི་ཚེ་འདས་པའི་འོག་ཏུ་འཁོར་ལོས་སྒྱུར་བའི་རྒྱལ་སྲིད་འཐོབ་པར་འགྱུར་རོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>who trust in my vision, will attain the dominion of a universal monarch after their lives are over.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-149">
            <prop type="folio">F.148.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེའི་རྒྱལ་སྲིད་ལ་ཡང་སངས་རྒྱས་འབྱུང་བར་འགྱུར་ཞིང་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>A buddha will appear within their dominions.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-150">
            <prop type="folio">F.148.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་དེ་མཐོང་ནས་ཀྱང་མཆོད་པ་དཔག་ཏུ་མེད་པ་བྱེད་པར་འགྱུར། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>When they see that thus-gone one, they will perform boundless veneration,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-151">
            <prop type="folio">F.148.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཚངས་པར་སྤྱོད་པར་ཡང་འགྱུར། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>[When they see that thus-gone one,] they will [perform boundless veneration,] practice pure conduct, and</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-152">
            <prop type="folio">F.148.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མངོན་པར་ཤེས་པ་ལྔ་ཡང་རྟོགས་པར་ཁོང་དུ་ཆུད་པར་འགྱུར། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>[When they see that thus-gone one,] they will [perform boundless veneration,] master the five types of miraculous abilities.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-153">
            <prop type="folio">F.148.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་མཐོང་མ་ཐག་ཏུ་གཟུངས་བརྒྱ་འཁྱིལ་བ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་འཐོབ་པར་འགྱུར། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Immediately upon beholding that thus-gone one, they will achieve the hundred-swirled dhāraṇī.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-154">
            <prop type="folio">F.148.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་གཱའི་ཀླུང་གི་བྱེ་མ་སྙེད་ཀྱི་སངས་རྒྱས་དག་ལ་བསྙེན་བཀུར་བྱེད་པར་འགྱུར། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They will serve as many buddhas as there are grains of sand in the Ganges.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-155">
            <prop type="folio">F.148.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་སྙེད་ཀྱི་བསྐལ་པ་བྱེ་བ་ཉིད་དུ་འཁོར་བ་ལས་ཕྱིར་ཕྱོགས་པར་བྱེད་པར་འགྱུར། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They will turn away from saṃsāra for an equivalent number of eons.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-156">
            <prop type="folio">F.148.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེའི་སེམས་ཤིན་ཏུ་རྨོངས་པ་མེད་ཅིང་བླ་ན་མེད་པ་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་བྱང་ཆུབ་ཏུ་འགྱུར། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Their minds will be undeluded, and they will fully awaken to unsurpassed and perfect buddhahood.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-157">
            <prop type="folio">F.148.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྲེད་མེད་ཀྱི་བུའི་ལུས་ལྟར་མཁྲེགས་པའི་ལུས་སུ་འགྱུར། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Their bodies will become solid like that of Nārāyaṇa.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-158">
            <prop type="folio">F.148.b</prop>
            <prop type="alternative-source"/>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལུས་དབྱིབས་གཅིག་ལ་སྤི་ཛ་བཞི་པར་འགྱུར། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Residing in a single place, they will possess the four necessities.<tei:note xml:id="UT22084-059-006-63"/>
                </seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-159">
            <prop type="folio">F.148.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེའི་ལུས་ཀྱི་མདོག་གསེར་གྱི་ཁ་དོག་འདྲ་བར་འགྱུར། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Their bodies will take on golden complexions.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-160">
            <prop type="folio">F.148.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྐྱེས་བུ་ཆེན་པོའི་མཚན་སུམ་ཅུ་རྩ་གཉིས་ཀྱིས་ལུས་བརྒྱན་ཅིང་ཚངས་པའི་སྒྲ་དབྱངས་སུ་ཡང་འགྱུར། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They will be adorned with the thirty-two major marks of a great being. They will gain the melodious voice of Brahmā .</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-161">
            <prop type="folio">F.148.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མི་ཁོམ་པ་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱང་སྤོང་ཞིང་དལ་བ་ཕུན་སུམ་ཚོགས་པ་ཡང་འཐོབ་པར་འགྱུར་རོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They will eliminate all unfree states and attain an abundance of leisure.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-162">
            <prop type="folio">F.148.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་དོན་འདི་ཉིད་རྒྱས་པར་བསྟན་པའི་ཕྱིར་ཚིགས་སུ་བཅད་པས་བཀའ་སྩལ་པ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-64"/>In order to elaborate on the meaning of what he had taught, the Blessed One then spoke in verse:</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-163">
            <prop type="folio">F.148.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་ཞིག་འཇིག་རྟེན་མགོན་པོའི་མཚན། །ཐོས་ནས་སོམ་ཉི་མི་ཟ་ཞིང་། །ངས་མཐོང་བ་ལའང་ཡིད་ཆེས་པ། །དེ་ནི་ཡོན་གནས་འོས་པ་ཡིན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Those who hear the name of this world protector And entertain no doubt, Trusting in what I see, Shall become worthy of veneration.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-164">
            <prop type="folio">F.148.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྟག་ཏུ་འཁོར་ལོས་སྒྱུར་བ་ཡི། །རྒྱལ་སྲིད་འཐོབ་ཅིང་སངས་རྒྱས་མཐོང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-66"/>“They will attain the eternal dominion Of universal monarchs and behold buddhas.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-165">
            <prop type="folio">F.148.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མཐོང་ནས་དཔག་ཏུ་མེད་པ་དང་། །བསམ་གྱིས་མི་ཁྱབ་མཆོད་པ་བྱེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Having beheld them, they will perform Boundless and inconceivable veneration.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-166">
            <prop type="folio">F.148.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྟག་ཏུ་ཚངས་པར་སྤྱོད་པ་དང་། །མངོན་པར་ཤེས་རྣམས་རྟོགས་པར་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-67"/>“They will always practice pure conduct. They will realize all forms of miraculous abilities.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-167">
            <prop type="folio">F.148.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སངས་རྒྱས་མཐོང་ནས་བརྒྱ་འཁྱིལ་བའི། །གཟུངས་ཀྱང་དེ་ཡིས་འཐོབ་པར་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Once they see the Buddha, they will achieve The hundred-swirled dhāraṇī.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-168">
            <prop type="folio">F.148.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཇི་ལྟར་གང་གཱའི་བྱེ་མ་སྙེད། །དེ་སྙེད་སངས་རྒྱས་མཐོང་བར་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-68"/>“They will behold as many buddhas As there are sands in the Ganges.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-169">
            <prop type="folio">F.148.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་སྙེད་བསྐལ་པ་བྱེ་བ་རུ། །འཁོར་བ་དག་ནི་སྤངས་པར་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They will abandon saṃsāra For that many billions of eons.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-170">
            <prop type="folio">F.149.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་ཞིག་འཇིག་རྟེན་མགོན་པོའི་མཚན། །ཚོགས་དང་དགེ་འདུན་དག་ལ་བརྗོད། །དེ་<tei:ref folio="F.149.a"/>ཡི་སེམས་ནི་མི་རྨོངས་ཤིང་། །སངས་རྒྱས་བྱང་ཆུབ་རྒྱུ་བྱེད་དོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-69"/>“Those who hear the name of the world protector Spoken to the assemblies and saṅghas Will become undeluded, And it will be a cause for awakening to buddhahood.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-171">
            <prop type="folio">F.149.a</prop>
            <prop type="alternative-source"/>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྟག་ཏུ་སྲེད་མེད་བུ་འདྲ་ཞིང་། །ལུས་དབྱིབས་གཅིག་ལ་སྤི་ཛ་བཞི། །ལུས་ནི་གསེར་གྱི་མདོག་འདྲ་ཞིང་། །སུམ་ཅུ་རྩ་གཉིས་མཚན་འཆང་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-70"/>“They will always be like Nārāyaṇa. Residing in a single place, they will possess the four necessities.<tei:note xml:id="UT22084-059-006-71"/> Their bodies will be golden colored And display the thirty-two marks.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-172">
            <prop type="folio">F.149.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་ཞིག་མཚན་ནི་ཐོས་ནས་སུ། །ཡན་ལག་ལྔ་ཡིས་ཕྱག་བྱས་ན། །རྟག་ཏུ་ཚངས་པའི་དབྱངས་ལྡན་ཞིང་། །མི་ཁོམ་པ་ཡང་སྤངས་པར་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-72"/>“Those who hear his name And prostrate with their five points Will permanently gain the voice of Brahmā And abandon the unfree states.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-173">
            <prop type="folio">F.149.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་ཞིག་འཇིག་རྟེན་མགོན་པོའི་མཚན། །ཐོས་ནས་སོམ་ཉི་མི་ཟ་བ། །དེ་ནི་བྱང་ཆུབ་ལ་མི་འགོང་། །དེ་ནི་ནམས་ཀྱང་སོམ་ཉི་མེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-74"/>“Those who hear the name of this world protector And entertain no doubt Will not shy away from awakening. They shall never have any hesitation.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-174">
            <prop type="folio">F.149.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་ཞིག་ཉིན་དང་མཚན་བདུན་དུ། །ཚང་བར་རྒྱལ་བའི་མཚན་འཛིན་པ། །སངས་རྒྱས་བསྔགས་པ་མཐའ་ཡས་པའི། །མིག་ནི་རྣམ་པར་དག་པར་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-75"/>“Those who remember the victor’s name For a full seven days and nights Will purify the infinite seeing eyes Praised by the buddhas.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-175">
            <prop type="folio">F.149.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མི་དེ་ཡི་ནི་ཤ་ཡི་མིག །ལྷ་ཡི་མིག་ཏུ་རྣམ་སྦྱོང་སྟེ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-76"/>“They shall refine the eyes of flesh Into the eyes of a god.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-176">
            <prop type="folio">F.149.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་གཱའི་ཀླུང་གི་བྱེ་སྙེད་ཀྱི། །སངས་རྒྱས་མང་པོ་མཐོང་བར་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They will perceive as many buddhas As there are grains of sand in the Ganges.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-177">
            <prop type="folio">F.149.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཐམས་ཅད་ལ་ནི་མཆོད་བྱེད་ཅིང་། །ཐམས་ཅད་ལས་ནི་ཐོས་པ་འཛིན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-77"/>“They will venerate each of them And receive teachings from each as well.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-178">
            <prop type="folio">F.149.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མིག་གིས་ཐམས་ཅད་མཐོང་ནས་སུ། །མི་རྣམས་ཐམས་ཅད་དབུགས་འབྱིན་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Seeing all the buddhas with their own eyes, They will bring comfort to all humanity.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-179">
            <prop type="folio">F.149.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པའི་མཚན་ཐོས་པ། །སྔོན་ཆད་བསམ་གྱིས་མི་ཁྱབ་པའི། །བསྙེན་བཀུར་སངས་རྒྱས་དག་ལ་བྱས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-78"/>“Those who hear the name of this thus-gone one Have already offered unfathomable service To the buddhas,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-180">
            <prop type="folio">F.149.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་དག་ཐམས་ཅད་རྗེས་དྲན་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>All of whom they will recollect.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-181">
            <prop type="folio">F.149.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྲོག་ཆགས་གང་རྣམས་མདུན་དག་ཏུ། །མཚན་ནི་བསྟན་པར་བྱས་གྱུར་ན། །སེམས་ཅན་གཞན་གྱིས་དེ་མཐོང་ཞིང་། །ངེས་པར་བྱང་ཆུབ་འགྱུར་བ་ཡིན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-79"/>“If his name is relayed Before any being at all, When those other beings hear this name, They too will definitely proceed to awakening.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-182">
            <prop type="folio">F.149.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སངས་རྒྱས་ལ་ནི་དད་བསྐྱེད་པས། །མི་ཁོམ་ཐམས་ཅད་རྣམ་པར་སྤངས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-80"/>“By generating faith in this buddha, The unfree states are dispelled,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-183">
            <prop type="folio">F.149.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྩོད་དང་འགྱེད་པ་བྱས་པས་ནི། །མི་ཁོམ་རྣམས་སུ་སྐྱེ་བར་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>While by engaging in debate and quarreling, One will be born into the unfree states.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-184">
            <prop type="folio">F.149.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཐུབ་པ་ཆེན་པོ་དེ་ཡི་མཚན། །སེམས་ཅན་གཅིག་ཅིག་ཐོས་བྱས་ན། །རྩོད་པ་དང་ནི་འགྱེད་པ་ཡང་། །ཡིད་ལ་བྱེད་པར་མི་འགྱུར་རོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-81"/>“Once beings have heard The name of this great sage, They shall no longer be interested In debate and quarreling.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-185">
            <prop type="folio">F.149.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གལ་ཏེ་མནར་མེད་པ་ཡི་ལས། །བསྐལ་པ་གནས་པར་འགྱུར་བ་དག །ཀླད་ནད་ཙམ་ཞིག་བསྐྱེད་ནས་སུ། །ལས་ཀུན་རྣམ་པར་སྨིན་མི་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-82"/>“The actions that lead to the Hell of Ultimate Torment, Which could last for eons, As well as the actions that produce a simple headache— All such actions will not ripen for these beings.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-186">
            <prop type="folio">F.149.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ལ་མེས་ནི་མི་ཚིག་ཅིང་། །ཆུ་ཡི་ནང་དུ་འཆི་མི་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-83"/>“They shall not be burned by fire, Nor drown in water.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-187">
            <prop type="folio">F.149.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ལ་རྒྱལ་པོ་རབ་ཁྲོས་ཀྱང་། །མྱུར་བ་ཉིད་དུ་ཞི་བར་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Even when they draw the ire of the king, It shall be quickly assuaged.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-188">
            <prop type="folio">F.149.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་ཞིག་ཐུབ་<tei:ref folio="F.149.b"/>པའི་མཚན་འཛིན་པ། །ནམས་ཀྱང་ལོང་བ་ཞར་བ་དང་། །ཐེང་དང་སྒུར་དང་ལུས་ཉམས་དང་། །ནད་ནི་མང་པོར་མི་འགྱུར་རོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-84"/>“Those who remember this sage’s name Shall be spared many illnesses Including blindness, defective sight, Paralysis, hunchback, and decrepitude.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-189">
            <prop type="folio">F.149.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གནོད་སྦྱིན་དྲི་ཟ་ཡི་དགས་དང་། །གྲུལ་བུམ་སྲིན་པོ་མི་རྣམས་ནི། །སྡིག་ཅན་མ་རུངས་པ་རྣམས་དག །མི་དེ་ལ་ནི་གནོད་མི་བྱེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-85"/>“Evil and malevolent Yakṣas, gandharvas, asuras, Kumbhāṇḍas, rākṣasas, and humans Shall be unable to harm them.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-190">
            <prop type="folio">F.149.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་ཞིག་ཐུབ་པའི་མཚན་འཛིན་པ། །འབྱུང་པོ་དྲི་ཟ་གནོད་སྦྱིན་རྣམས། །ཀླུ་དང་ལྷ་རྣམས་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱི། །ཡིད་དུ་འོང་ཞིང་དགའ་བར་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-86"/>“Those who remember this sage’s name Shall be favored and preferred By all the bhūtas, gandharvas, yakṣas, Nāgas, and gods.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-191">
            <prop type="folio">F.149.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདིར་ནི་སྐྱོབ་པའི་མཚན་ཐོས་པ། །ཤིན་ཏུ་བསགས་པ་དམ་པའི་དབྱངས། །ཏིང་འཛིན་མྱུར་དུ་ཐོབ་པར་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-87"/>“Those who hear this protector’s name Shall swiftly attain vast accumulations, Sublime voices, and absorption.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-192">
            <prop type="folio">F.149.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡོན་ཏན་བྱེ་བ་རབ་ཏུ་སྒྲོགས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Their myriad virtues will be renowned.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-193">
            <prop type="folio">F.149.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་ཞིག་འཇིག་རྟེན་མགོན་པོའི་མཚན། །ཐོས་ནས་སོམ་ཉི་མི་ཟ་བ། །ཕྱི་མའི་དུས་ཀྱི་ཚེ་དག་ཏུ། །དེ་ཡི་བྱང་ཆུབ་འདི་འཛིན་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-88"/>“Having heard this world protector’s name Without doubting it, They will hew to awakening Throughout all their subsequent lives.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-194">
            <prop type="folio">F.149.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཐུབ་པ་ཆེན་པོའི་མཚན་ཐོས་པ། །སངས་རྒྱས་མྱ་ངན་འདས་རྣམས་ཀྱིས། །ལེགས་པར་གསུངས་པའི་ཆོས་ཀྱི་ཚུལ། །འཛིན་ཅིང་ཡང་དག་རབ་ཏུ་སྟོན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-89"/>“Those who hear this great sage’s name Shall uphold and preach The way of the well-spoken Dharma Taught by the buddhas who have gone beyond anguish.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-195">
            <prop type="folio">F.149.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སངས་རྒྱས་ཀུན་གྱིས་ལེགས་གསུངས་པའི། །ཆོས་དེ་རྣམས་ནི་དེས་འཛིན་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-90"/>“They shall uphold the teachings Well spoken by all the buddhas.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-196">
            <prop type="folio">F.149.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཀོད་པ་མཆོག་ནི་དེས་བྱེད་ཅིང་། །སངས་རྒྱས་ཀུན་ལ་བསྙེན་བཀུར་བྱེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They shall manifest the supreme array And serve all the buddhas.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-197">
            <prop type="folio">F.149.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་འཆི་བའི་དུས་བྱས་ནས། །སངས་རྒྱས་བྱེ་བ་དེས་མྱུར་མཐོང་། །སངས་རྒྱས་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་གསུངས་པ་ཡི། །ཆོས་རྣམས་དེ་དག་འཛིན་པར་བྱེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-91"/>“Once they pass away, They will swiftly behold myriad buddhas And uphold the teachings Spoken by the buddhas.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-198">
            <prop type="folio">F.149.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྐྱོབ་པ་དེ་ཡི་མཚན་ཐོས་པ། །སྲོག་ཆགས་བྱེ་བ་ནན་ཏན་གྱིས། །འདུལ་བར་བྱེད་ཅིང་རབ་ཏུ་འགོད། །ཐམས་ཅད་བྱང་ཆུབ་ཕྱིར་འཇོག་གོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-92"/>“Those who hear this protector’s name Shall earnestly train and establish Millions of beings on the path, Bringing them all to awakening.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-199">
            <prop type="folio">F.149.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ང་ཡིས་མཐོང་ལའང་ཡིད་ཆེས་པ། །སྐྱོབ་པ་སངས་རྒྱས་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱི། །རབ་ཏུ་བསྟན་པ་འཛིན་འགྱུར་ཞིང་། །སངས་རྒྱས་རྣམས་ཀྱང་མཆོད་པར་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-93"/>“Those who trust what I have seen Shall uphold the teachings Of all the buddhas, the protectors, And additionally venerate the buddhas.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-200">
            <prop type="folio">F.149.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སངས་རྒྱས་མཁྱེན་ལ་གང་དད་པ། །ངས་མཐོང་བ་ལའང་དེ་ཡིད་ཆེས། །འཆིང་བ་རྣམས་ལས་དེས་རྣམས་འགྲོལ། །ཀློང་ལས་རྒལ་ཅིང་འཇིགས་པ་མེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-94"/>“Those who have faith in this buddha’s wisdom, Trusting in what I have seen, Shall be liberated from many fetters. They will cross the abyss and become fearless.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-201">
            <prop type="folio">F.149.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་ཞིག་དམ་པའི་ཆོས་སྤོང་བ། །དེ་ནི་བདུད་ཀྱི་སྡེ་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-95"/>“Whosoever abandons the sublime Dharma Is among Māra ’s ranks.<tei:note xml:id="UT22084-059-006-96"/>
                </seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-202">
            <prop type="folio">F.149.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འགྲོ་བ་ལྔ་རུ་འགྲོ་བ་ཡི། །སེམས་ཅན་ཀུན་གྱི་བ་སྤུ་གང་། །དེ་ནི་སྟོན་པའི་པུས་མོ་ཡི། །ལྷ་ང་གཅིག་གིས་བ་སྤུར་སྡུད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-97"/>“The body hairs of every being Who migrates among the five types of beings Could be consolidated Within one hair on the teacher’s kneecap.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-203">
            <prop type="folio">F.150.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྐྱོབ་པ་འཇིག་རྟེན་མགོན་པོ་ཡི། །བ་སྤུ་གཅིག་གི་ཁུང་བུ་ནས། །ཇི་ལྟར་<tei:ref folio="F.150.a"/>གང་གཱའི་བྱེ་མ་སྙེད། །དེ་སྙེད་འོད་ཟེར་འབྱིན་པར་མཛད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-98"/>“From a single pore Of the protector, the guardian of the world, As many rays of light as there are Grains of sand in the Ganges stream forth.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-204">
            <prop type="folio">F.150.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་ཞིག་འཇིག་རྟེན་མགོན་འདི་ཡི། །འོད་ཟེར་མཐའ་ཡས་ལ་ཡིད་ཆེས། །ཚེ་གཅིག་གིས་ནི་སངས་རྒྱས་རྣམས། །སངས་རྒྱས་བྱེ་བ་མཐོང་བར་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-99"/>“Those who trust in the infinite light Of the world protector Shall in one life behold many buddhas— Millions of buddhas.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-205">
            <prop type="folio">F.150.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཆོས་ཀྱི་རྒྱལ་པོ་མདོ་སྡེ་འདི། །བཤད་པ་གང་ཞིག་ཐོས་གྱུར་ནས། །ནམས་ཀྱང་ཡིད་གཉིས་མི་ཟ་བ། །དེ་ནི་ང་དང་འདྲ་བར་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-100"/>“Those who hear the teaching Of this discourse by the Dharma king And never doubt it Shall become like me.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-206">
            <prop type="folio">F.150.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡངས་པ་ཅན་དུ་མདོ་སྡེ་འདི། །བཤད་པའི་ཚེ་ན་སུས་ཐོས་པ། །དེ་ནི་ཕྱི་མའི་དུས་སུ་དེས། །གཞན་ལ་ཡང་དག་རབ་ཏུ་སྟོན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-101"/>“Those who hear the teaching Of this discourse in Vaiśālī Shall themselves preach it to others At a later time.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-207">
            <prop type="folio">F.150.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཇི་ལྟར་གང་གཱའི་བྱེ་མ་དག །མི་གང་གིས་ནི་མང་བརྗོད་པ། །དེ་སྙེད་འཇིག་རྟེན་ཁམས་རྣམས་སུ། །འོད་ཟེར་གཅིག་གིས་ཁྱབ་པར་བྱེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-102"/>“Those who preach this widely Shall come to pervade as many worlds As there are grains of sand in the Ganges With a single burst of light.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-208">
            <prop type="folio">F.150.a</prop>
            <prop type="alternative-source"/>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སངས་རྒྱས་ཞིང་རྣམས་ཐམས་ཅད་དག །བགྲང་བའི་ཚུལ་གྱིས་མི་མཆོད་པ། །གསེར་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་ནི་བཀང་ནས་སུ། །འཇིག་རྟེན་མགོན་ལ་ཕུལ་བ་བས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-103"/>“One may fill with gold All the buddha realms, The numbers of which defy counting,<tei:note xml:id="UT22084-059-006-104"/> And offer it to the world protectors.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-209">
            <prop type="folio">F.150.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདི་ཡི་མཚན་ནི་ཐོས་ནས་སུ། །དགའ་བ་བཟང་པོ་སྐྱེས་གྱུར་ཏེསངས་རྒྱས་ཕྱག་འཚལ་ཞེས་བརྗོད་པ། །དེ་ཡི་བསོད་ནམས་བསམ་མི་ཁྱབ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-105"/>“Yet, in comparison, those who hear this name And who are truly delighted by it And utter their homage to the buddhas Obtain inconceivably more merit.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-210">
            <prop type="folio">F.150.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇིག་རྟེན་མགོན་ནི་ཐམས་ཅད་ལ། །ཡང་དང་ཡང་དུ་ཕྱག་འཚལ་བ། །དེ་ཡི་བསོད་ནམས་ཕུང་པོ་ནི། །ཚད་ནི་བཤད་པར་མི་ནུས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-106"/>“The mass of merit gained By repeatedly paying homage To all the world protectors Cannot be expressed by any measure.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-211">
            <prop type="folio">F.150.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་ཞིག་འཇིག་རྟེན་མགོན་པོའི་མཚན། །ཐོས་ནས་སོམ་ཉི་མི་ཟ་བ། །དེ་ཡི་ལུས་ནི་འོད་ཟེར་གྱིས། །ཁྱབ་ཅིང་རིན་པོ་ཆེ་ལྟར་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-107"/>“Those who hear the world protector’s name And do not hesitate about it Will have their bodies filled with light And become like precious gems.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-212">
            <prop type="folio">F.150.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་ཞིག་ཐུབ་པའི་མཚན་འཛིན་པ། །དེ་ནི་རྣམ་པར་འདས་གྱུར་ནས། །ལྷ་ཡི་ཙན་དན་དམར་པོ་ཡི། །དྲི་ཞིམ་ཁ་ནས་རབ་ཏུ་འབྱུང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-108"/>“After they have passed beyond, Those who remember the name of the sage Will have the sweet scent of divine red sandalwood Waft from their mouth.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-213">
            <prop type="folio">F.150.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྐྱོབ་པ་སེམས་ཅན་སྙིང་པོ་ཡི། །སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱི་ནི་མཚན་ཐོས་པ། །བ་སྤུའི་ཁུང་ནས་འོད་ཟེར་དག །བཀྱེ་བས་ལུས་ཀྱང་མཛེས་པར་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-109"/>“Those who hear the name Of the Buddha, the protector, the essential being, Will have light stream from their pores, Beautifying their bodies.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-214">
            <prop type="folio">F.150.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཚེ་རབས་དག་ནི་ཐམས་ཅད་དུ། །ཐོས་པ་མང་པོར་འགྱུར་བ་སྟེ། །ཀུན་དགའ་སངས་རྒྱས་ཅི་འདྲ་བའི། །དཔག་ཏུ་མེད་པའི་ཐོས་པའང་འཛིན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-110"/>“In all of their ensuing lives They will become deeply learned. They will retain their unfathomable erudition, Just like Ānanda does for the Buddha.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-215">
            <prop type="folio">F.150.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇིག་རྟེན་སྣང་བྱེད་དེས་མཐོང་ནས། །གཞལ་གྱིས་མི་ལང་དགའ་བ་འཐོབ། །བྱང་ཆུབ་སྤྱད་པ་སྤྱོད་པ་ན། །ཚེ་རབས་དག་ནི་དྲན་པར་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-111"/>“When they behold the one who illuminates the world, They will attain boundless happiness. As they engage in bodhisattva conduct, They will recall all their lives.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-216">
            <prop type="folio">F.150.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྒྱལ་བའི་ཐུགས་སྲས་མཐོང་ནས་ཀྱང་། །གཞལ་གྱིས་མི་ལང་དགའ་བ་འཐོབ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-112"/>“Even when they see the victors’ heart sons, They will attain boundless happiness.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-217">
            <prop type="folio">F.150.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>
                    <tei:ref folio="F.150.b"/>སྤོས་དང་མེ་ཏོག་བྱུག་རྣམས་ཀྱིས། །མཆོད་པ་དག་ནི་རྒྱ་ཆེན་བྱེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They will make extensive offerings With incense, flowers, and ointments.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-218">
            <prop type="folio">F.150.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇིག་རྟེན་མགོན་པོ་དེ་ཡི་མཚན། །བརྗོད་པ་འཛིན་པར་མི་བྱེད་དེ། །བདུད་ཀྱི་ཕྱོགས་དང་སྔོན་ཀྱང་ནི། །མུ་སྟེགས་གྱུར་པ་མ་གཏོགས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-113"/>“This does not include those who do not remember The name of this world protector when it is spoken, Or those who are on Māra ’s side, Or those who have previously been extremists.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-219">
            <prop type="folio">F.150.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ང་ཡིས་ཚུལ་འདི་བཤད་པ་ན། །སྔོན་ནི་གང་གིས་འདི་ཐོས་པ། །ཕྱི་མའི་དུས་ཀྱི་ཚེ་དག་ཏུ། །དེ་ཡི་ལག་ཏུ་མདོ་སྡེ་འཐོབ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-114"/>“As I have taught this Dharma way, Those who have heard it now Shall also receive this discourse in their hands In a future life.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-220">
            <prop type="folio">F.150.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ཡིས་མདོ་སྡེ་དམ་པ་འདི། །བཤད་པ་དག་ནི་སུས་ཐོས་པ། །སྔོན་ནི་མཆོད་ཅིང་བཀུར་སྟི་བྱས། །དེ་ཡི་ལག་ཏུ་འདི་འཐོབ་བོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-115"/>“Those who hear the explanation Of this sublime discourse Have previously venerated and served, And they shall receive it in their hands again.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-221">
            <prop type="folio">F.150.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་གིས་སྨོན་ལམ་བཏབ་པ་ནི། །ཕྱི་མའི་དུས་ཀྱི་ཚེ་དག་ཏུ། །ཆོས་ཀྱི་རྒྱལ་པོས་གསུངས་པ་ཡི། །མདོ་འདི་ལག་ཏུ་འཐོབ་པར་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-116"/>“Those who make aspirations Shall, in a future life, Receive into their hands This discourse spoken by the Dharma King.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-222">
            <prop type="folio">F.150.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་ཞིག་སེམས་ནི་རྩེ་གཅིག་གིས། །སངས་རྒྱས་གྲངས་མེད་བཀུར་སྟི་བས། །མདོ་འདི་ལ་ནི་གང་དད་པ། །དེ་བས་བསོད་ནམས་འདི་མང་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-117"/>“Having faith in this discourse Brings even more merit Than honoring countless buddhas With a one-pointed mind.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-223">
            <prop type="folio">F.150.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྟག་ཏུ་གཟུགས་བཟང་བསོད་ནམས་ལྡན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-118"/>“They forever will have beautiful bodies and lots of merit [And be fearless and wealthy].</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-224">
            <prop type="folio">F.150.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཤིན་ཏུ་འཇིགས་མེད་ལོངས་སྤྱོད་ལྡན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They [forever[ will [have beautiful bodies and lots of merit And] be fearless and wealthy.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-225">
            <prop type="folio">F.150.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དྲན་དང་ལྡན་ཞིང་མཚན་རྣམས་ཀྱིས། །མངོན་པར་བརྒྱན་པ་དག་ཏུ་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They will be mindful And ornamented with the major marks.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-226">
            <prop type="folio">F.150.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ལྟ་བས་ན་མདོ་སྡེ་འདི། །ཐོས་ནས་ཕྱི་མའི་དུས་ཀྱི་ཚེ། །བཟུང་ཞིང་ཡང་དག་བསྟན་པ་དང་། །གཞན་དག་ལ་ཡང་བསྟན་པར་གྱིས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-119"/>“Thus, having heard The teaching of this discourse, In the future retain it, teach it, And explain it to others!</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-227">
            <prop type="folio">F.150.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་གིས་སངས་རྒྱས་འཁོར་ལོས་སྒྱུར། །འབུམ་ཕྲག་དག་ལ་བཀུར་བྱས་པས། །ཕྱི་མ་ཡི་ནི་དུས་དག་ཏུ། །དེས་མཐོང་བ་ལ་སོམ་ཉི་མེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-120"/>“Those who have honored hundreds of thousands Of buddhas, universal monarchs, Shall also in the future Have vision free from doubt.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-228">
            <prop type="folio">F.150.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་གིས་སྔོན་ནི་འཇིག་རྟེན་མགོན། །གྲངས་མེད་པ་ལ་བསྙེན་བཀུར་བས། །དེ་ཡི་འཇིག་རྟེན་མགོན་འདི་ཡི། །ཐོས་ཤིང་མཐོང་ལའང་ཡིད་ཆེས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-121"/>“Those who have performed service For countless world protectors in the past Will trust what they hear and see Of this world protector.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-229">
            <prop type="folio">F.150.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་ཞིག་མཚན་འདི་ཐོས་ནས་སུ། །སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱི་ནི་གཟུགས་བྱེད་པ། །དེ་ནི་སངས་རྒྱས་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱི། །བསྟན་པ་དང་ནི་དམ་ཆོས་བསྲུང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-122"/>“Those who hear his name Will actualize the form of a buddha. They will guard the teachings And the sublime Dharma of all the buddhas.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-230">
            <prop type="folio">F.150.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་ཞིག་བྱང་ཆུབ་བསྟན་སྤངས་ན། །བསྐལ་པ་བྱེ་བ་དག་ཏུ་ནི། །ལུག་ལྟར་ལྐུགས་ཤིང་མིག་ཉམས་ལ། །མིག་མེད་པ་དག་ཏུ་ཡང་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-123"/>“However, those who abandon the teachings of awakening Shall become like sheep—mute and with poor eyesight, Or even with no eyes at all For millions of eons.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-231">
            <prop type="folio">F.150.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་ཞིག་ལག་པ་གཅིག་གིས་ནི། །མཆོད་རྟེན་གྲངས་མེད་བཤིག་བྱས་པས། །གང་གིས་མདོ་སྡེ་འདི་སྤངས་ན། །ཁྱད་ཆོས་སྡིག་པར་འདི་འགྱུར་རོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-124"/>“Compared to destroying countless caityas, With one’s own hands, It is a far viler deed To abandon this discourse.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-232">
            <prop type="folio">F.151.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ལྟ་བས་ན་ང་སྨྲ་བ། །ཕྱི་མའི་དུས་ཚེ་འདི་རྙེད་ནས། །<tei:ref folio="F.151.a"/>སངས་རྒྱས་ཡེ་ཤེས་བླ་མེད་ལ། །སོམ་ཉི་ཟ་བར་མ་བྱེད་ཅིག །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-125"/>“Thus when, at a future time, You attain that which I am preaching, Do not harbor any doubt About the unsurpassed wisdom of the buddhas.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-233">
            <prop type="folio">F.151.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མདོ་སྡེ་འདི་འདྲ་འདི་ཐོས་ནས། །མེ་ཏོག་སྤོས་དང་འཕན་རྣམས་དང་། །གདུགས་དང་ཕྱེ་མ་གོས་རྣམས་ཀྱིས། །གུས་པར་བྱས་ཏེ་མཆོད་པར་གྱིས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-126"/>“Once you have heard this discourse, Perform respectful veneration With flowers, incense, streamers, Parasols, and powders!”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-234">
            <prop type="folio">F.151.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེར་ནི་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་ཡི། །ཕྱག་མཉེན་ཤིན་ཏུ་འཇམ་པ་ཡིས། །ལིཙྪ་བཱི་ཡི་མགོ་བོ་ལ། །ཡང་དང་ཡང་དུ་བྱུག་པ་མཛད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-127"/>Then, with his soft and supple hands, The Thus-Gone One Repeatedly caressed The Licchavi boy’s head.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-235">
            <prop type="folio">F.151.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ཡི་རྗེས་ལ་ལྷ་རྣམས་ཀྱིས། །སྒྲ་སྐད་ཆེན་པོ་ཕྱུང་གྱུར་ཅིང་། །ལྷ་ཡི་མེ་ཏོག་ཀུ་སུ་མ། །ཡིད་འོང་གཏོར་ཅིང་ཞིང་འདི་བཀང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-128"/>After this, the gods Made a loud cry And scattered pleasing divine flowers, Filling the realm.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-236">
            <prop type="folio">F.151.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལྷ་རྣམས་མཁའ་ལ་འདུག་ནས་སུ། །གླུ་དབྱངས་དཔག་ཏུ་མེད་པ་ལེན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-129"/>The gods, having remained in the sky, Then sang countless songs.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-237">
            <prop type="folio">F.151.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཚངས་པ་དག་ནི་བྱེ་བ་ཡིས། །ཙན་དན་དམར་པོའི་ཆར་ཕབ་པོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Millions of brahmā gods Cast down a rain of red sandalwood powder.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-238">
            <prop type="folio">F.151.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པས་མདོ་སྡེ་འདི། །གསུངས་ཚེ་དྲ་བ་ཅན་ཐོས་ཏེ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-130"/>When Ratnajālin heard this discourse Spoken by the Thus-Gone One,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-239">
            <prop type="folio">F.151.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སེམས་ནི་རངས་ཤིང་ཡིད་དགའ་ནས། །དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་ལ་ཚིག་གསོལ་བ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He was pleased and delighted, And spoke these words to the Thus-Gone One:</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-240">
            <prop type="folio">F.151.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཕྱི་མའི་དུས་སུ་བདག་གིས་ནི། །དགེ་སློང་བགྱིས་ལ་མི་འཇིགས་པར། །གྲོང་དང་གྲོང་ཁྱེར་རྣམས་དག་ཏུ། །མདོ་སྡེ་འདི་ནི་བཤད་པར་བགྱི། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-131"/>“In the future, I will become a monk And fearlessly preach this discourse In towns and villages.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-241">
            <prop type="folio">F.151.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སངས་རྒྱས་བཀའ་བཞིན་བདག་བགྱིད་དེ། །རྫོགས་སངས་རྒྱས་ལ་དཔལ་གྱིས་གསུངས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-132"/>“I will act according to the Buddha’s teaching, Which the perfect Buddha has spoken so gloriously.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-242">
            <prop type="folio">F.151.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དཔག་ཚད་བྱེ་བར་མཆིས་ནས་སུ། །འདི་ཡི་ཚུལ་ནི་བཤད་པར་བགྱི། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Traveling millions of leagues I will preach the way.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-243">
            <prop type="folio">F.151.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལྷ་ཀུན་དང་ནི་ཀླུ་རྣམས་དང་། །ཡང་ན་མིའམ་ཅི་དང་ནི། །མི་མ་ཡིན་རྣམས་མགྲོན་གཉེར་ཏེ། །ཆོས་ཀྱི་སྦྱིན་པས་ཚིམ་པར་བགྱི། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-133"/>“I will serve all the gods, nāgas, And kinnaras, And other non-human beings, Satisfying them with the gift of Dharma.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-244">
            <prop type="folio">F.151.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བླ་ན་མེད་པའི་མདོ་སྡེ་འདི། །སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱིས་ནི་གསུངས་པ་ན། །ལྷ་མ་ཡིན་ཚོགས་དགའ་གྱུར་ནས། །མེ་ཏོག་དཔག་ཏུ་མེད་པ་འཐོར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-134"/>When this unsurpassed discourse Was taught by the Buddha, The assembly of asuras celebrated And scattered countless flowers.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-245">
            <prop type="folio">F.151.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱི་ནི་ཞིང་འདི་དག །མི་མཆོག་ཤཱཀྱ་སེང་གེ་ཡི། །ཆོས་ཀྱི་རྒྱལ་པོའི་སྤུ་གཅིག་གིས། །ཞིང་རྣམས་ཐམས་ཅད་སྣང་བར་མཛད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-135"/>A single hair of the Dharma King, The Lion of the Śākyas, Who is the supreme being in all buddha realms, Illuminated all the realms.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-246">
            <prop type="folio">F.151.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སེམས་ཅན་སྙིང་པོའི་བདག་ཉིད་ཅན། །སྟོན་པ་ཡི་ནི་ལྗགས་ཕྱུང་ནས། །གང་གཱའི་བྱེ་མ་སྙེད་དག་གི། །ཞིང་རྣམས་བྱེ་བ་ཁེབས་པར་མཛད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-136"/>Then, the tongue of the Teacher, The great being, the essential being, Emerged and covered millions of realms As numerous as the grains of sand in the Ganges.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-247">
            <prop type="folio">F.151.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་བཞིན་ཕྱོགས་བཅུའི་འཇིག་རྟེན་གྱི། །ཞིང་རྣམས་བྱེ་བ་ཁེབས་མཛད་དེ། །གཞོན་ནུ་རིན་ཆེན་དྲ་བ་ཅན། །དཔའ་བོ་དང་ནི་ལིཙྪ་བཱི། །བྱེ་བ་དྲུག་ཅུ་ཙམ་དག་ནི། །ལྷན་ཅིག་ལྷགས་ལ་བཀའ་སྩོལ་ཅིག །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-137"/>As the Thus-Gone One covered millions of realms Throughout the ten directions of the universe, The youth Ratnajālin, As well as other heroes and Licchavis <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-138"/>Numbering six hundred million, Arrived saying, “Please teach us!”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-248">
            <prop type="folio">F.151.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་དེར་ནི་སྟོན་པ་ཡིས། །<tei:ref folio="F.151.b"/>དེ་དག་ཆོས་ལ་གཟུད་པར་མཛད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The Teacher then introduced The Dharma to them all.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-249">
            <prop type="folio">F.151.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བདེ་བ་ཐམས་ཅད་སྦྱིན་མཛད་པ། །སངས་རྒྱས་སྤྱན་ནི་ཐོགས་པ་མེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-139"/>The buddhas gift every form of happiness, And their eyes are unimpeded.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-250">
            <prop type="folio">F.151.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་རྣམས་དཔག་མེད་དེ། །སངས་རྒྱས་ཆོས་ལ་ཐེ་ཚོམ་སྤོང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The countless thus-gone ones Have abandoned doubt about awakened qualities.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-251">
            <prop type="folio">F.151.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སངས་རྒྱས་ཡེ་ཤེས་ཐོགས་མེད་དེ། །དུས་གསུམ་རྣམས་ལའང་འཇུག་པར་མཛད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-140"/>The buddhas’ wisdom is unimpeded— It perceives the three times.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-252">
            <prop type="folio">F.151.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཆོས་རྣམས་ཀུན་ལ་མངའ་བརྙེས་པས། །སངས་རྒྱས་ལ་ནི་མི་མཁྱེན་མེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Given that they have dominion over all phenomena, There is nothing unknown to the buddhas.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-253">
            <prop type="folio">F.151.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཕུང་པོ་རྣམས་ནི་མེད་པའོ་ཞེས། །མི་ཡི་འདྲེན་པ་སྟོན་པར་མཛད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-141"/>The Guide of Humans preaches That the aggregates are nonexistent.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-254">
            <prop type="folio">F.151.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཁམས་བཞི་དག་ནི་གསོག་དང་འདྲ། །གང་དུའང་སྒྲ་ལ་ཆགས་པ་མེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The four elements are as if hollow, And nowhere are there sounds to be attached to.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-255">
            <prop type="folio">F.151.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཟུགས་དང་ཚོར་བ་འདུ་ཤེས་དང་། །སེམས་པ་དང་ནི་འདུ་བྱེད་དང་། །རྣམ་ཤེས་ཕུང་པོའི་སྙིང་པོ་ནི། །མེད་པ་དག་ཏུ་ཤེས་པར་གྱིས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-142"/>The essence of the aggregates Of form, feeling, perception, Thoughts, formations, and consciousness Should be known to be nonexistent.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-256">
            <prop type="folio">F.151.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱིས་ནི་གསུངས་པ་བཞིན། །དེ་ལྟར་ཕུང་པོ་རྣམས་ཕྱེ་ནམྱུར་དུ་གཟུངས་རྣམས་འཐོབ་འགྱུར་ཞིང་། །ཤིན་ཏུ་རྨོངས་པ་མེད་པར་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-143"/>Just as the Buddha has taught, If one distinguishes the aggregates, One will swiftly attain the dhāraṇīs And become undeluded.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-257">
            <prop type="folio">F.151.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཆོས་རྣམས་དག་ནི་གསོབ་དང་འདྲ། །ཐམས་ཅད་སྟོང་ཞིང་བདག་མེད་དོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-144"/>All phenomena are void— All of them are empty and without self.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-258">
            <prop type="folio">F.151.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྩོད་པ་མེད་ཅིང་རྨོངས་མེད་པ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Of this there can be no debate or delusion.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-259">
            <prop type="folio">F.151.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་སྐད་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པས་གསུངས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>This is what the Thus-Gone One has taught.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-260">
            <prop type="folio">F.151.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཞོན་ནུ་ལྷོ་ཕྱོགས་ལོགས་ན་གཞོན་ནུ་དཔེ་སྔ་མ་ལྟ་བུ་ལས་ཉིས་གྱུར་གྱི་རྡུལ་ཕྲ་མོའི་རྡུལ་བགྲངས་པའི་ཚུལ་གྱིས་སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱི་ཞིང་བཅུ་གཉིས་འདས་པ་ན་དེ་ན་ཟླ་བས་བརྒྱན་པ་ཞེས་བྱ་བའི་འཇིག་རྟེན་གྱི་ཁམས་ཡོད་དེ</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-145"/>“Young man, located in the south, past twelve buddha realms reckoned as twice the number of smallest particles in the previous analogy, there is a world called Adorned by the Moon.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-261">
            <prop type="folio">F.151.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ན་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་དགྲ་བཅོམ་པ་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་སངས་རྒྱས་མེ་ཏོག་གི་འོད་ཀྱིས་རྣམ་པར་རོལ་པ་མངོན་པར་མཁྱེན་པ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་བཞུགས་ཏེ་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>There resides the thus-gone, worthy, perfect Buddha King of Knowledge of Floral Light Displays.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-262">
            <prop type="folio">F.151.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཚོ་ཞིང་གཞེས་ལ་ཆོས་ཀྱང་སྟོན་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He is alive and well and teaches the Dharma.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-263">
            <prop type="folio">F.151.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཞོན་ནུ་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའི་ཐེག་པ་ལ་ཡང་དག་པར་གནས་པའི་རིགས་ཀྱི་བུའམ། རིགས་ཀྱི་བུ་མོ་གང་ལ་ལ་ཞིག་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་མེ་ཏོག་གི་འོད་ཀྱིས་རྣམ་པར་རོལ་པ་མངོན་པར་མཁྱེན་པ་དེའི་མཚན་ཐོས་ནས་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Young man, when those noble sons or daughters who abide in the Bodhisattva Vehicle hear the name of the blessed one, the thus-gone one King of Knowledge of Floral Light Displays—</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-264">
            <prop type="folio">F.151.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སོམ་ཉི་མི་ཟ་ལ་ངས་མཐོང་བ་ལ་ཡང་ཡིད་ཆེས་ན་དེ་ཚེ་འདས་པའི་འོག་ཏུ་འོད་ཟེར་རབ་ཏུ་གཏོང་བ་ཞེས་བྱ་བའི་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་ཐོབ་པར་འགྱུར། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>as long as they do not doubt this but trust in my vision—they will achieve the absorption of emitting light rays once they have passed away.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-265">
            <prop type="folio">F.151.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་གྱི་སྒོ་བྱེ་བ་ཁྲག་ཁྲིག་འབུམ་ཕྲག་གྲངས་མེད་པ་ཁྲིར་འཇུག་པ་འཐོབ་པར་འགྱུར། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They will become knowledgeable in ten thousand countless trillions of methods to gain absorption.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-266">
            <prop type="folio">F.152.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཟུངས་ཀྱི་སྒོ་བྱེ་བ་ཁྲག་ཁྲིག་འབུམ་ཕྲག་གྲངས་མེད་པ་དྲུག་ཅུ་པོ་རྒྱ་<tei:ref folio="F.152.a"/>མཚོ་ལྟ་བུ་ཞེས་བྱ་བའི་གཟུངས་ལ་སོགས་པ་ནས་རིན་པོ་ཆེའི་མཛོད་ཀྱི་གཟུངས་ལ་ཐུག་པའི་བར་ལ་འཇུག་པ་འཐོབ་ཅིང་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They will become knowledgeable in sixty countless trillions of dhāraṇī methods—from the oceanic dhāraṇī to the precious treasury dhāraṇī.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-267">
            <prop type="folio">F.152.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱང་ཆུབ་ཀྱི་མཐར་ཐུག་གི་བར་དུ་དེ་དག་ལ་རྨོངས་པར་ཡང་མི་འགྱུར་རོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They will be undeluded in this regard until reaching final awakening.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-268">
            <prop type="folio">F.152.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཆི་བའི་དུས་ཀྱི་ཚེ་ཤར་ཕྱོགས་ནས་སངས་རྒྱས་བྱེ་བ་གཤེགས་ནས་ཞལ་སྟོན་པར་མཛད་དེ། ཕྱོགས་ཐམས་ཅད་ནས་ཀྱང་དེ་དང་འདྲའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>When they die, ten million buddhas will come from the east and reveal themselves, and the same will occur from all other directions.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-269">
            <prop type="folio">F.152.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་སངས་རྒྱས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་དེ་དག་གིས་ཆོས་གསུང་བར་འགྱུར་བ་དེ་དག་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱང་འཛིན་པར་འགྱུར། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They will retain the Dharma that these blessed buddhas teach.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-270">
            <prop type="folio">F.152.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱང་ཆུབ་མ་ཐོབ་ཀྱི་བར་དུ་དེའི་ཆོས་ཀྱི་ཚུལ་དེ་འཇིག་པར་མི་འགྱུར། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Until they reach awakening they will not lose this Dharma way.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-271">
            <prop type="folio">F.152.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལས་དང་པོ་པའི་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་ནས་བཟུང་ནས་བསྐལ་པ་ལྔ་བརྒྱར་འཁོར་བ་ལས་ཕྱིར་ཕྱོགས་པར་བྱས་ནས་བླ་ན་མེད་པ་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་བྱང་ཆུབ་ལ་རེག་པར་འགྱུར་རོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Having worked to turn away from cyclic existence for five hundred eons starting from the time they began as bodhisattvas, they will reach unsurpassed and perfect awakening.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-272">
            <prop type="folio">F.152.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་དེའི་ཚེ་ཚིགས་སུ་བཅད་པ་འདི་དག་བཀའ་སྩལ་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-146"/>The Blessed One then expressed this in verse:</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-273">
            <prop type="folio">F.152.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མི་ཡི་དབང་པོ་འཇིག་རྟེན་མགོན། །སྐྱོབ་པ་ཡི་ནི་མཚན་ཐོས་པ། །བསྐལ་པ་ལྔ་བརྒྱ་ཐམ་པ་ཡི། །འཁོར་བ་དག་ནི་བཟློག་པར་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Hearing the name of this protector, The lord of humans, the world protector, They will eliminate five hundred eons Of cyclic existence.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-274">
            <prop type="folio">F.152.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཆི་བདག་གི་དུས་ཚེ་ཡང་། །སངས་རྒྱས་བྱེ་བ་སྟོན་པར་མཛད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-148"/>“When death comes to those noble sons and daughters, Millions of buddhas will appear to them.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-275">
            <prop type="folio">F.152.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མཐོང་ནས་དབང་པོས་ཕྱག་འཚལ་ཏེ། །ཆོས་ཀྱང་ཉན་ཅིང་འཛིན་པར་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Having seen them, paying homage with their faculties, They will listen to the Dharma and retain it.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-276">
            <prop type="folio">F.152.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པའི་མཚན་ཐོས་པ། །སྤྱད་པ་དམ་པ་སྤྱོད་པ་ན། །དེ་ཡིས་བསྟན་པའི་ཆོས་གང་དག །བསྐལ་པ་བྱེ་བར་ཆུད་མི་གསོན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-149"/>“When they hear that thus-gone one’s name And engage in sacred practice, They will not waste the Dharma taught by them— Even for millions of eons.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-277">
            <prop type="folio">F.152.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱི་ནི་མཚན་བསྒྲགས་པས། །རིན་ཆེན་ཞེས་བྱའི་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན། །སྟོང་ཕྲག་བདུན་ཅུ་དེ་ཚེ་འཐོབ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-150"/>“By proclaiming the name of this buddha, They will attain seventy thousand Absorptions known as precious,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-278">
            <prop type="folio">F.152.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡོན་ཏན་བྱེ་བར་སྒྲོགས་པར་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>And they will proclaim millions of virtues.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-279">
            <prop type="folio">F.152.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་ཞིག་ཐུབ་པའི་མཚན་འཛིན་པ། །ཏིང་འཛིན་གྲངས་མེད་བྱེ་བ་དང་། །དེ་བཞིན་ས་ཡ་དྲུག་ཅུ་དག །དེ་ལ་ཉེ་བར་གནས་པར་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-151"/>“Those who apprehend the name of this sage Will come to abide In countless millions Plus sixty million absorptions.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-280">
            <prop type="folio">F.152.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་བས་མཉམ་བཞག་དཔའ་བོ་ཡིས། །བྱང་ཆུབ་སྤྱད་པ་སྤྱོད་པའི་ཚེ། །སེམས་ཅན་མང་པོ་སྟོང་རྣམས་དག །བྱང་ཆུབ་མཆོག་ལ་འཇོག་པར་བྱེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-152"/>“Thus, when heroes of equilibrium Engage in bodhisattva conduct, They establish many thousands of beings In supreme awakening.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-281">
            <prop type="folio">F.152.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱང་ཆུབ་མ་རྫོགས་བར་དུ་ནི། །ནམ་ཡང་འདོད་ལ་མི་བསྟེན་ཏེ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-153"/>“Until reaching perfect awakening, They will not engage in desirous conduct.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-282">
            <prop type="folio">F.152.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སེམས་ཅན་གཞན་ཡང་སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱི། །མཚན་བསྟན་རྣམས་ནི་ཟློག་པར་བྱེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The beings to whom they teach the name of this buddha Will also turn away from desire.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-283">
            <prop type="folio">F.152.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་ཞིག་སངས་རྒྱས་མཚན་<tei:ref folio="F.152.b"/>ཐོས་ནས། །སྲོག་ཆགས་ཀུན་ལ་འདི་སྟོན་པ། །ནམས་ཀྱང་མི་ཁོམ་མི་འགྱུར་ཞིང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-154"/>“Those who hear the name of this buddha And teach it to all beings Will never again enter unfree states;</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-284">
            <prop type="folio">F.152.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ཡི་དལ་བ་རྙེད་མི་དཀའ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>It will not be hard for them to find leisure.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-285">
            <prop type="folio">F.152.b</prop>
            <prop type="alternative-source"/>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཤིན་དུ་བཟུང་བ་སངས་རྒྱས་དག །འབྱུང་བ་མཉེས་པར་བྱས་པས་ནི། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-155"/>“By pleasing the excellent<tei:note xml:id="UT22084-059-006-156"/> buddhas That appear,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-286">
            <prop type="folio">F.152.b</prop>
            <prop type="alternative-source"/>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ང་ཡི་མི་ཁོམ་གང་བསྟེན་པ། །དེ་དག་ཐམས་ཅད་སྤང་བར་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They will abandon all the unfree states<tei:note xml:id="UT22084-059-006-157"/> That I have described.<tei:note xml:id="UT22084-059-006-158"/>
                </seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-287">
            <prop type="folio">F.152.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཇི་ལྟར་འདྲེན་པ་མཁྱེན་པ་བཞིན། །གཞོན་ནུ་གལ་ཏེ་ཁྱོད་ཤེས་ན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-159"/>“Young man, if you were to understand What the guide knows,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-288">
            <prop type="folio">F.152.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྟོན་པའི་མཚན་ནི་བཟུང་ནས་སུ། །ཕྱོགས་ཀུན་ཏུ་ནི་རབ་ཏུ་སྒྲོགས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Once you knew the name of this teacher, You would spread it throughout the ten directions.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-289">
            <prop type="folio">F.152.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་བས་གཞོན་ནུ་གཞན་དག་ལ། །མཚན་འདི་རབ་ཏུ་བསྟན་བྱས་ན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-160"/>“Thus, young man, If you share this name with others,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-290">
            <prop type="folio">F.152.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡང་དག་བྱང་ཆུབ་འདི་བཟུང་ཞིང་། །འཇིག་རྟེན་གྱི་ནི་མགོན་དུ་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>You will acquire genuine awakening And become a protector of the world.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-291">
            <prop type="folio">F.152.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་ཞིག་སངས་རྒྱས་མཚན་ཐོས་ནས། །གཡེང་བ་མེད་པར་འདི་བཟུང་སྟེ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-161"/>“Those who hear this buddha’s name, Remember it without distraction,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-292">
            <prop type="folio">F.152.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སོང་ནས་གཞན་དག་ལ་སྟོན་པ། །དེ་ནི་བྱང་ཆུབ་མངོན་དུ་བསྲུང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>And share it with others, Will guard their awakening.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-293">
            <prop type="folio">F.152.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་ཞིག་མདོ་སྡེ་འདི་ཐོས་ནས། །གཞན་དག་ལ་ནི་རབ་སྟོན་ན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-162"/>“Those who hear this discourse And teach it to others</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-294">
            <prop type="folio">F.152.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལེགས་པར་གསུངས་པའི་ཆོས་ཀྱི་ཚུལ། །བསྟན་པ་འདི་དག་སྲུང་བར་བྱེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Will guard these teachings Of the well-spoken Dharma way.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-295">
            <prop type="folio">F.152.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཞོན་ནུ་ནུབ་ཕྱོགས་ལོགས་ན་གཞོན་ནུ་དཔེ་སྔ་མ་ལྟ་བུ་དེ་ལས་སུམ་འགྱུར་གྱི་རྡུལ་ཕྲ་མོའི་རྡུལ་བགྲངས་པའི་ཚུལ་གྱིས་དེ་སྙེད་ཀྱི་འཇིག་རྟེན་གྱི་ཁམས་དག་འདས་པ་ན། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-163"/>“Young man, located in the west, past worlds numbering three times the number of smallest particles in the previous analogy,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-296">
            <prop type="folio">F.152.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇིག་རྟེན་གྱི་ཁམས་རིན་ཆེན་བཀྲ་བ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་ཞིག་ཡོད་དེ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>there is a world called Citraratna.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-297">
            <prop type="folio">F.152.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ན་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་དགྲ་བཅོམ་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་སངས་རྒྱས་མེ་ཏོག་རྒྱས་པ་སཱ་ལའི་རྒྱལ་པོ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་ཞིག་བཞུགས་ཏེ་འཚོ་ཞིང་གཞེས་ལ་ཆོས་ཀྱང་སྟོན་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>There the thus-gone, worthy, perfect Buddha King of Blossoming Sal Tree Flowers lives. He is alive and well and teaches the Dharma.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-298">
            <prop type="folio">F.152.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཞོན་ནུ་ཐེག་པ་ཆེན་པོ་ལ་ཡང་དག་པར་གནས་པའི་རིགས་ཀྱི་བུའམ། རིགས་ཀྱི་བུ་མོ་གང་ལ་ལ་ཞིག་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་མེ་ཏོག་རྒྱས་པ་སཱ་ལའི་རྒྱལ་པོ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་དེའི་མཚན་ཐོས་ནས་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Young man, when those noble sons or daughters who abide in the Great Vehicle hear the name of the thus-gone one King of Blossoming Sal Tree Flowers—</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-299">
            <prop type="folio">F.152.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སོམ་ཉི་མི་ཟ་ལ་ངས་མཐོང་བ་ལ་ཡང་ཡིད་ཆེས་ན་དེ་ཚེ་འདས་པའི་དུས་འོག་དུ་ཆོས་ལྔ་འཛིན་པར་འགྱུར་ཏེ</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>as long as they do not doubt this but trust in my vision—they will acquire five qualities once they have passed away.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-300">
            <prop type="folio">F.152.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལྔ་གང་ཞེ་ན། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>What are these five?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-301">
            <prop type="folio">F.152.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལུས་ཞིག་ནས་སངས་རྒྱས་འབྱུང་བ་དང་། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>When their bodies are destroyed, buddhas will appear and</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-302">
            <prop type="folio">F.152.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེར་འཁོར་ལོས་སྒྱུར་བའི་རྒྱལ་པོ་ཉིད་དང་། མངོན་པར་ཤེས་པ་ལྔ་དང་། ཆོས་ཀྱི་རྣམ་གྲངས་ཀྱི་གཟུངས་ཏེ། དེ་ཡང་སྟོང་འཁྱིལ་བའི་གཟུངས་དང་། བྱང་ཆུབ་ཐོབ་ཀྱི་བར་དུ་སྐྱེས་བུ་ཆེན་པོའི་མཚན་སུམ་ཅུ་རྩ་གཉིས་པོ་དེ་དག་འཐོབ་པ་སྟེ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>they will attain the position of a universal monarch, the five forms of miraculous abilities, the recall of Dharma teachings, the thousand-swirled dhāraṇī, and the thirty-two marks of a great being until they attain awakening.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-303">
            <prop type="folio">F.152.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཆོས་ལྔ་པོ་དེ་དག་འཐོབ་པར་འགྱུར་རོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They will achieve these five qualities.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-304">
            <prop type="folio">F.153.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་དོན་འདི་<tei:ref folio="F.153.a"/>ཉིད་ཚིགས་སུ་བཅད་པས་བཀའ་སྩལ་པ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-164"/>The Blessed One then expressed the meaning of this in verse: </seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-305">
            <prop type="folio">F.153.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་ཞིག་མི་ཡི་ཁྱུ་མཆོག་སྐྱོབ་པའི་མཚན། །ཐོས་ནས་སོམ་ཉི་མེད་ཅིང་དད་བསྐྱེད་ནས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Those who hear the name of this leader of men, this protector, And are faithful, without hesitation,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-306">
            <prop type="folio">F.153.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ཡི་ཆོས་ལྔ་དེ་དག་འཛིན་འགྱུར་ཞིང་། །བྱང་ཆུབ་ཐོབ་པའི་བར་དུ་འཇིག་མི་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Will acquire these five qualities, Which shall not be lost until they attain awakening.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-307">
            <prop type="folio">F.153.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གསེར་གྱི་མདོག་འདྲའི་གཟུགས་དང་ལྡན་འགྱུར་ཞིང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-166"/>“They will gain a golden-colored appearance,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-308">
            <prop type="folio">F.153.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཁོར་ལོས་སྒྱུར་བའི་རྒྱལ་པོ་དམ་མཆོག་མཁས། །བསོད་ནམས་ལྡན་པ་སྲེད་མེད་བུ་འདྲ་ཞིང་། །དམ་ཆོས་འཁོར་ལོ་བར་ཆད་མེད་པར་བསྐོར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The supreme knowledge of a universal monarch, Merit rivaling that of Nārāyaṇa, And the unceasing turning of the wheel of the sacred Dharma.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-309">
            <prop type="folio">F.153.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བསོད་ནམས་ལྡན་པ་བུ་སྟོང་ཡོད་འགྱུར་ཏེ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-167"/>“They will be fortunate and have a thousand sons</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-310">
            <prop type="folio">F.153.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དཔའ་ཞིང་རྟུལ་ཕོད་ཕ་རོལ་ཚོགས་འཇོམས་ལ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Who are heroic and courageous, capable of defeating their opponents.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-311">
            <prop type="folio">F.153.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡན་ལག་མཆོག་གི་གཟུགས་ལྡན་མཚན་གྱིས་བརྒྱན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Adorned with marks, their bodies will have perfect limbs.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-312">
            <prop type="folio">F.153.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མཐུ་སྟོབས་ཆེ་བ་རྒྱལ་པོ་གཙོ་ཉིད་འདྲ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Therefore, their power will resemble that of a supreme ruler.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-313">
            <prop type="folio">F.153.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྒྱལ་པོའི་ཆུང་མ་གཟུགས་བཟང་གཟུགས་མཛེས་པ། །གསེར་གྱི་མདོག་འདྲ་མང་པོ་སྟོང་ཡོད་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-168"/>“They will have many thousands of queens Who are fine and beautiful, with golden complexions.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-314">
            <prop type="folio">F.153.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཕྱི་ནས་ཉལ་ཞིང་སྔར་ནི་ལྡང་བྱེད་དེ། །རྒྱལ་པོ་གཙོ་ལ་ནམས་ཀྱང་སྐྱོ་མི་བྱེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Going late to bed and rising early, They will never cause their supreme rulers any sorrow.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-315">
            <prop type="folio">F.153.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྒྱལ་ཕྲན་གང་དག་དེ་ཡི་ཡུལ་གནས་ཤིང་། །གང་དག་བློན་པོ་ཁྱིམ་བདག་གཙོ་བོ་ཀུན། །རྒྱལ་པོ་དེ་མཐོང་ནམས་ཀྱང་སྐྱོ་མི་བྱེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-169"/>“The vassals, ministers, and major householders Living in his realm Will never cause the king any grief when they meet.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-316">
            <prop type="folio">F.153.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་བས་དེ་ནི་བསོད་ནམས་དམ་མཆོག་ལྡན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Their merit will even be greater than that.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-317">
            <prop type="folio">F.153.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མཁས་མཆོག་ལྷ་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་ཀྱང་ཐུབ་པར་དཀའ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-170"/>“Even the crafty gods will find them difficult to match.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-318">
            <prop type="folio">F.153.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མི་ཡི་འཇིག་རྟེན་དག་ན་གནོད་སྦྱིན་ཀླུ། །དེ་ཡི་ཡུལ་ན་སེམས་ཅན་གང་གནས་པ། །དེ་ཡིས་ཐམས་ཅད་བྱང་ཆུབ་སྙིང་པོར་འཇོག །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>All the yakṣas and nāgas living in the human world And all the other beings living in his realm They will establish at the seat of awakening.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-319">
            <prop type="folio">F.153.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྒྱལ་སྲིད་རྒྱས་ཤིང་ཤིན་ཏུ་ལོ་ལེགས་དང་། །དེ་ཡི་རྒྱལ་སྲིད་བདེ་ཞིང་སངས་རྒྱས་འབྱུང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-171"/>“Their dominion will expand and the harvests grow bountiful. Their realm will be happy and buddhas will appear.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-320">
            <prop type="folio">F.153.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་དག་ལ་ནི་མཆོད་པ་དམ་པ་བྱེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They will perform sacred worship of them.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-321">
            <prop type="folio">F.153.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྒྱལ་པོ་བདག་ཡུལ་ནམས་ཀྱང་སྡང་སེམས་མེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The land of the king will be free from malice.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-322">
            <prop type="folio">F.153.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སངས་རྒྱས་མཚན་མཆོག་ཐོས་ནས་མཁས་པ་གང་། །སོམ་ཉི་ཟ་ཞིང་མི་དགའ་སུ་ཞིག་ཡོད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-172"/>“Even those scholars who hear the perfect name of this buddha, Yet doubt it or become displeased with it,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-323">
            <prop type="folio">F.153.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མདོ་སྡེ་དམ་པ་དེ་རིང་ངས་བཤད་པའི། །ཆོས་མཆོག་འདི་ཡིས་དེ་ལ་ཕན་འདོགས་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Will benefit from the perfect Dharma In the sublime discourse that I have spoken today.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-324">
            <prop type="folio">F.153.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཞན་དུ་གང་གིས་སྔོན་གྱི་རྒྱལ་རྣམས་ཀྱིས། །ཆོས་སྤངས་གྱུར་པའམ་བདུད་ཀྱིས་ཟིན་པའམ། །སེམས་ཅན་སྙིང་པོ་རྒྱལ་བ་མཆོག་དག་ནི། །སྔོན་ཆད་སྤྱོད་ཚེ་ཁྱད་དུ་བསད་མ་གཏོགས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-173"/>“However, this is not the case for those who abandoned the Dharma Of previous victors, or those in the grip of demons, Or those who in the past despised The essential beings, the perfect victors.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-325">
            <prop type="folio">F.153.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཞོན་ནུ་གང་ཞིག་རྒྱལ་པོའི་ཕོ་བྲང་དང་། །ལིཙྪ་བཱི་བཀོད་དགའ་བ་འདི་དག་དང་། །ཤཱཀྱ་སེང་གེ་ང་ནི་མ་མཐོང་བ། །དེ་དག་<tei:ref folio="F.153.b"/>སངས་རྒྱས་མཚན་ཐོས་སོམ་ཉི་ཟ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-174"/>“Young man, those who haven’t witnessed the delights Of the royal palace and this realm of the Licchavis And who haven’t seen me Will harbor doubts when they hear the name of this buddha.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-326">
            <prop type="folio">F.153.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཞོན་ནུ་བྱང་ཕྱོགས་ལོགས་ན་སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱི་ཞིང་འདི་ནས་གཞོན་ནུ་དཔེ་སྔ་མ་ལྟ་བུ་དེ་ལས་སུམ་འགྱུར་གྱིས་སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱི་ཞིང་དྲུག་ཅུ་འདས་པ་ན་འཇིག་རྟེན་གྱི་ཁམས་རིན་ཆེན་དྲ་བས་གཡོགས་པ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་ཡོད་དེ</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-175"/>“Young man, located in the north, past sixty buddha realms reckoned as thrice the number of smallest particles in the previous analogy, there is a world called Covered with a Jewel Net.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-327">
            <prop type="folio">F.153.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ན་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་དགྲ་བཅོམ་པ་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་སངས་རྒྱས་ཟླ་བའི་དཀྱིལ་འཁོར་རྣམ་དག་ཅེས་བྱ་བ་བཞུགས་ཏེ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>There the thus-gone, worthy, perfect Buddha Pure Moon Disk lives.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-328">
            <prop type="folio">F.153.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཚོ་ཞིང་གཞེས་ལ་ཆོས་ཀྱང་སྟོན་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He is alive and well and teaches the Dharma.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-329">
            <prop type="folio">F.153.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཞོན་ནུ་ཐེག་པ་ཆེན་པོ་ལ་ཡང་དག་པར་གནས་པའི་རིགས་ཀྱི་བུའམ། རིགས་ཀྱི་བུ་མོ་གང་ལ་ལ་ཞིག་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་ཟླ་བའི་དཀྱིལ་འཁོར་རྣམ་དག་དེའི་མཚན་ཐོས་ནས་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Young man, when those noble sons or daughters who abide in the Great Vehicle hear the name of the thus-gone one Pure Moon Disk</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-330">
            <prop type="folio">F.153.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སོམ་ཉི་མི་ཟ་ཞིང་ངས་མཐོང་བ་ལ་ཡང་ཡིད་ཆེས་ན་དེའི་ཚེ་འདས་པའི་འོག་ཏུ་རིན་ཆེན་འབྱུང་གནས་ཞེས་བྱ་བའི་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་ཐོབ་པར་འགྱུར། གང་གཱའི་ཀླུང་གི་བྱེ་མ་སྙེད་ཀྱི་སངས་རྒྱས་མཐོང་བར་འགྱུར། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>—as long as they do not doubt this but trust in my vision—they will obtain the absorption called source of jewels and behold as many buddhas as there are grains of sand in the Ganges once they have passed away.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-331">
            <prop type="folio">F.153.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་སྙེད་ཀྱི་བསྐལ་པ་བྱེ་བར་འཁོར་བ་ལས་ཕྱིར་ཕྱོགས་པར་འགྱུར། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>For as many millions of eons, they will turn away from cyclic existence.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-332">
            <prop type="folio">F.153.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལས་དང་པོ་པའི་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་དེ་བླ་ན་མེད་པ་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་བྱང་ཆུབ་ལ་རེག་པར་འགྱུར། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Such beginning bodhisattvas will reach unsurpassed and perfect awakening.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-333">
            <prop type="folio">F.153.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དབྱངས་སྙན་ལྡན་ཞེས་བྱ་བའི་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་ཀྱང་ཐོབ་པར་འགྱུར། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They will also attain the absorption called pleasant melody .</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-334">
            <prop type="folio">F.153.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བླ་ན་མེད་པ་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་བྱང་ཆུབ་ལས་ཕྱིར་མི་ལྡོག་པར་ཡང་འགྱུར་རོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They will not turn away from unsurpassed and perfect awakening.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-335">
            <prop type="folio">F.153.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བུད་མེད་གང་ལ་ལ་ཞིག་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་ཟླ་བའི་དཀྱིལ་འཁོར་རྣམ་དག་དེའི་མཚན་ཐོས་ནས་སོམ་ཉི་མི་ཟ་ཞིང་ཐེ་ཚོམ་མི་སྐྱེ་ལ་ངས་མཐོང་བ་ལ་ཡང་ཡིད་ཆེས་ན། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-176"/>“Should women hear the name of the blessed thus-gone one Pure Moon Disk without feeling any hesitation or doubt and with trust in my vision,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-336">
            <prop type="folio">F.153.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ཚེ་འདས་པའི་འོག་ཏུ་བུད་མེད་ཀྱི་དབང་པོ་རྣམ་པར་སྤངས་པར་འགྱུར་ཞིང་སྐྱེས་པའི་དབང་པོ་འཐོབ་པར་འགྱུར། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>they will abandon their female faculties and gain male faculties once they have passed away.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-337">
            <prop type="folio">F.153.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སེམས་ཅན་མང་པོ་བླ་ན་མེད་པ་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་བྱང་ཆུབ་ཏུ་ཡང་དག་པར་འཇོག་པར་འགྱུར། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They will establish many beings in unsurpassed and perfect awakening.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-338">
            <prop type="folio">F.153.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དབྱངས་སྙན་ལྡན་ཞེས་བྱ་བའི་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་ཀྱང་ཐོབ་པར་འགྱུར། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They will achieve the absorption called pleasant melody .</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-339">
            <prop type="folio">F.153.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བླ་ན་མེད་པ་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་བྱང་ཆུབ་ལས་ཕྱིར་མི་ལྡོག་པར་ཡང་འགྱུར་རོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They will not turn back from unsurpassed and perfect awakening.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-340">
            <prop type="folio">F.153.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་དེའི་ཚེ་ཚིགས་སུ་བཅད་པ་འདི་དག་བཀའ་སྩལ་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-177"/>The Blessed One then expressed this in verse:</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-341">
            <prop type="folio">F.154.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་ཞིག་རྐང་གཉིས་དམ་པ་དེ་ཡི་མཚན། །ཐོས་ནས་ནམས་ཀྱང་སོམ་ཉི་མི་ཟ་བ། །བསྐལ་པ་བྱེ་བ་གང་གཱའི་བྱེ་མ་<tei:ref folio="F.154.a"/>སྙེད། །དེས་སྤངས་མྱ་ངན་མེད་པའི་སྐྱེས་པར་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Those who hear the name of this sublime human And do not doubt it Will, after as many eons as there are grains of sand in the Ganges, Abandon rebirth and change to a state free from anguish.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-342">
            <prop type="folio">F.154.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་གཱའི་བྱེ་སྙེད་སངས་རྒྱས་དུ་མ་དག །མཐོང་ནས་དེ་དག་ལ་ནི་མཆོད་པར་བྱེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-179"/>“They will behold and venerate Buddhas as numerous as the sands of the Ganges.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-343">
            <prop type="folio">F.154.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་སྙེད་སངས་རྒྱས་དེ་ཡི་ཚེ་གཅིག་གིས། །སངས་རྒྱས་མཆོད་ནས་རྒྱལ་བ་མྱ་ངན་འདའ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>All those buddhas they will venerate In a single life, as the victors pass beyond anguish.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-344">
            <prop type="folio">F.154.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱང་ཆུབ་དམ་པ་སྤྱོད་མཆོག་སྤྱོད་པ་ན། །གང་གིས་སྐྱེས་བུ་ཁྱུ་མཆོག་མཚན་ཐོས་ནས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-180"/>“Those who hear the name of this leader of men As they engage in the perfect actions of sacred awakening</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-345">
            <prop type="folio">F.154.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ནམས་ཀྱང་སོམ་ཉི་མེད་ཅིང་འཛིན་བྱེད་ན། །དེ་འདྲའི་ཁྱད་པར་དེ་ཡིས་འཐོབ་པར་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>And remember it without ever doubting it Will achieve a similar exalted state.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-346">
            <prop type="folio">F.154.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་གིས་རྐང་གཉིས་མཚན་མཆོག་གཙོ་བོ་འདི། །ཐོས་ནས་ནམས་ཀྱང་སོམ་ཉི་མི་ཟ་བ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-181"/>“Those who hear the name of this supreme human And do not doubt it at all</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-347">
            <prop type="folio">F.154.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རང་བྱུང་ཡེ་ཤེས་སངས་རྒྱས་ཉིད་འགྱུར་ཞིང་། །མཁས་པས་དབྱངས་སྙན་ཏིང་འཛིན་ཐོབ་པར་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Shall obtain self-existing wisdom, buddhahood itself, And skillfully attain the absorption called pleasant voice.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-348">
            <prop type="folio">F.154.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱང་ཆུབ་དམ་པ་སྤྱད་མཆོག་སྤྱོད་པ་ན། །དག་པའི་བདག་ཉིད་སྐྱེས་པའི་དབང་པོ་ཐོབ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-182"/>“As they engage in the perfect actions of sacred awakening, They will achieve the faculties of a pure individual.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-349">
            <prop type="folio">F.154.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡོན་ཏན་ཀུན་དང་ལྡན་ཞིང་མཛེས་པ་སྟེ། །དེ་འདྲའི་ཁྱད་པར་དེ་ཡིས་ཐོབ་པར་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They will be beautiful and endowed with all qualities— Such distinctions they will attain.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-350">
            <prop type="folio">F.154.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཕྱོགས་རྣམས་ཀུན་ནི་རབ་ཏུ་སྣང་བྱེད་ཅིང་། །ས་ཡ་མཐའ་ཡས་ཞིང་དུ་སོང་ནས་སུ། །འཇིག་རྟེན་སྤྱོད་པ་ཐུབ་པ་ཆེ་མཐོང་ནས། །མྱ་ངན་བྲལ་ཏེ་བྱང་ཆུབ་ཕྱིས་རིག་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-183"/>“They will shine in all directions And proceed to countless millions of realms. As they behold the great sage engaging with the world,<tei:note xml:id="UT22084-059-006-184"/> They will escape anguish and later discover awakening.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-351">
            <prop type="folio">F.154.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཐུབ་དབང་ཆེན་པོ་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་ནི། །དེ་ཡི་མཚན་འདིར་ཐོས་ནས་རྫུ་འཕྲུལ་མཆོག །དེ་འདྲའི་ཁྱད་པར་དག་ནི་ཐོབ་པར་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-185"/>“Having heard the name Of that great lord, that thus-gone one, They will attain such distinctions as perfect miraculous powers,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-352">
            <prop type="folio">F.154.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱང་ཆུབ་འདོད་པ་གཞན་ཡང་ཐོབ་པ་ནི། །དྲི་བྲལ་བྱང་ཆུབ་འདུན་པ་བསྐྱེད་ནས་སུ། །རྒྱལ་བའི་མཚན་འདི་གཞན་ལའང་སྒྲོགས་པར་བྱེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>And also the desire to attain awakening. <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-186"/>“Having developed interest in immaculate awakening, They will share the name of the victor with others.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-353">
            <prop type="folio">F.154.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཟླ་བའི་དཀྱིལ་འཁོར་རབ་ཏུ་གསལ་བ་ལྟར། །དེ་ཡི་ཡོན་ཏན་དག་ཀྱང་དེ་འདྲར་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They will obtain virtues similar to his— As brilliant as the full moon.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-354">
            <prop type="folio">F.154.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སེམས་ཅན་མང་པོ་དུ་མ་བསམ་མི་ཁྱབ། །བྱང་ཆུབ་མཆོག་ལ་མཁས་པ་དེ་ཡིས་འཇོག །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-187"/>“Such learned persons will establish Fathomless multitudes of beings in supreme awakening.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-355">
            <prop type="folio">F.154.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཟླ་བ་མཁའ་ལ་གནས་པའི་གཞལ་མེད་ཁང་། །འོད་ཟེར་མང་པོ་བསགས་པས་མཛེས་པ་ལྟར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Like the chariot of the moon in the sky, They will be beautiful and shine brightly.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-356">
            <prop type="folio">F.154.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་ཞིག་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པའི་མཚན་འཛིན་པ། །དེ་ཡི་ལུས་ཀྱང་དེ་འདྲའི་རྣམ་པས་མཛེས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-188"/>“Those who remember the name of this victor Will have bodies that are just as beautiful.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-357">
            <prop type="folio">F.154.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མཁས་པ་གང་ཞིག་རྒྱལ་བའི་མཚན་ཐོས་ནས། །སོམ་ཉི་ཟ་ཞིང་མི་དགའ་སུ་ཞིག་ཡོད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Yet some scholars who hear the name of this victor Might doubt it, finding displeasure in it.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-358">
            <prop type="folio">F.154.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱང་ཆུབ་སྤྱད་མཆོག་དམ་པ་སྤྱོད་པ་ན། །ཆོས་འདི་དག་གིས་དེ་ལ་ཕན་འདོགས་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-189"/>“As they engage in the perfect actions of sacred awakening, These teachings will be helpful for them.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-359">
            <prop type="folio">F.154.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཐུབ་པ་ཆེན་པོ་འཇིག་རྟེན་སྤྱོད་མཆོག་པས། །མཁས་པ་དེ་ནི་ཕོངས་པ་མྱོང་མི་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Due to the supreme great sage who engages with the world, Such scholars will not come to ruin. </seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-360">
            <prop type="folio">F.154.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>
                    <tei:ref folio="F.154.b"/>གཞོན་ནུ་འོག་གི་ཕྱོགས་ན་གཞོན་ནུ་དཔེ་སྔ་མ་ལྟ་བུའི་རྣམ་པ་དེ་བཞིན་དུ་དགུ་བཅུ་རྩ་དགུར་བསྒྱུར་བ་འདས་ནས་འཇིག་རྟེན་གྱི་ཁམས་རྒྱལ་མཚན་མཆོག་གི་བདག་པོ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་ཡོད་དེ</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-190"/>“Young man, located below us, past ninety-nine times the number of particles in the previous analogy, there is a world called Lord of the Supreme Banner.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-361">
            <prop type="folio">F.154.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ན་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་དགྲ་བཅོམ་པ་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་སངས་རྒྱས་རབ་ཏུ་ཞི་བ་མཁས་པའི་གཟི་བརྗིད་དབྱངས་ཀྱི་དབང་ཕྱུག་གི་རྒྱལ་པོ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་བཞུགས་ཏེ་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>There resides the thus-gone, worthy, perfect Buddha King Who Is Peaceful and Splendorous in His Learning and Rich in Melody.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-362">
            <prop type="folio">F.154.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཚོ་ཞིང་གཞེས་ལ་ཆོས་ཀྱང་སྟོན་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He is alive and well and teaches the Dharma.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-363">
            <prop type="folio">F.154.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཞོན་ནུ་ཐེག་པ་ཆེན་པོ་ལ་ཡང་དག་པར་གནས་པའི་རིགས་ཀྱི་བུའམ། རིགས་ཀྱི་བུ་མོ་གང་ལ་ལ་ཞིག་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་རབ་ཏུ་ཞི་བ་མཁས་པའི་གཟི་བརྗིད་དབྱངས་ཀྱི་དབང་ཕྱུག་གི་རྒྱལ་པོ་དེའི་མཚན་ཐོས་ནས་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Young man, when those noble sons or daughters who abide in the Great Vehicle hear the name of the thus-gone one King Who is Peaceful and Splendorous in His Learning and Rich in Melody</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-364">
            <prop type="folio">F.154.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སོམ་ཉི་མི་ཟ་ལ་ངས་མཐོང་བ་ལ་ཡང་ཡིད་ཆེས་ན་དེ་ཚེ་འདས་པའི་འོག་ཏུ་ཀུན་ནས་འོད་ཟེར་ཞེས་བྱ་བའི་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་ཐོབ་པར་འགྱུར། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>—as long as they do not doubt this but trust in my vision—they will achieve the absorption called utterly illuminating once they have passed away.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-365">
            <prop type="folio">F.154.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཆི་བའི་དུས་ཀྱི་ཚེ་ཡང་སངས་རྒྱས་བྱེ་བ་ཁྲག་ཁྲིག་ཕྲག་འབུམ་དུ་ཚང་བ་དག་མཐོང་བར་འགྱུར། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>At the time of death, they will see trillions of buddhas.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-366">
            <prop type="folio">F.154.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཤར་ཕྱོགས་སུ་ཇི་ལྟ་བ་བཞིན་ཕྱོགས་ཐམས་ཅད་དུ་ཡང་དེ་བཞིན་དུ་སངས་རྒྱས་བྱེ་བ་ཁྲག་ཁྲིག་ཕྲག་འབུམ་དུ་ཚང་བ་དག་མཐོང་བར་འགྱུར། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>In all directions, as in the east, they will see trillions of buddhas.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-367">
            <prop type="folio">F.154.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སངས་རྒྱས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་དེ་དག་གིས་གང་ཆོས་བསྟན་པ་དེ་དག་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀུན་དུ་འཛིན་པར་འགྱུར། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They will retain all the Dharma teachings given by these blessed buddhas.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-368">
            <prop type="folio">F.154.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱང་ཆུབ་ལ་ཐུག་གི་བར་དུ་སངས་རྒྱས་གྲངས་མེད་པ་བྱེ་བ་ཁྲག་ཁྲིག་ཕྲག་འབུམ་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་བྱིན་གྱིས་བརླབས་པར་འགྱུར། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Until reaching awakening, they will be blessed by trillions of buddhas.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-369">
            <prop type="folio">F.154.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལས་དང་པོ་པའི་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་དེ། བསྐལ་པ་བྱེ་བ་ཁྲག་ཁྲིག་འབུམ་ཕྲག་དགུ་བཅུར་འཁོར་བ་ལས་ཕྱིར་ཕྱོགས་ནས་བླ་ན་མེད་པ་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་བྱང་ཆུབ་ཏུ་འགྱུར་རོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Such beginning bodhisattvas, having turned from cyclic existence for ninety-nine trillion eons, will reach unsurpassed and perfect awakening.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-370">
            <prop type="folio">F.154.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་དོན་འདི་ཉིད་ཚིགས་སུ་བཅད་པས་བཀའ་སྩལ་པ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-191"/>The Blessed One then expressed the meaning of this in verse:</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-371">
            <prop type="folio">F.154.b</prop>
            <prop type="alternative-source"/>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་ཞིག་འཇིག་རྟེན་འདི་ན་སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱི། །ཡོན་ཏན་རྒྱ་མཚོའི་མཚན་མཆོག་ཐོབ་གྱུར་པ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Those in this world who hear<tei:note xml:id="UT22084-059-006-193"/> the supreme name Of this buddha with an ocean of virtues</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-372">
            <prop type="folio">F.154.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེས་ནི་སངས་རྒྱས་བྱེ་བ་ཁྲི་རྣམས་ལ། །མྱུར་དུ་མཆོད་པ་བླ་མེད་རབ་ཏུ་བྱེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Will swiftly perform unsurpassed veneration Of one hundred billion buddhas.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-373">
            <prop type="folio">F.154.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མཐའ་ཡས་དྲི་མེད་ཁྱད་པར་མཆོད་བྱས་ཤིང་། །སྲིད་པ་ཀུན་ཏུ་སངས་རྒྱས་ཆེ་རྣམས་ཀྱི། །ཉི་མ་མཛད་པའི་སྤྱད་པ་སྤྱོད་ནས་སུ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-194"/>“Once they have venerated these limitless beings free from stains, They will engage in the splendorous activity Of the magnificent buddhas in all existences.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-374">
            <prop type="folio">F.154.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཕྱིས་ནི་བྱང་ཆུབ་དྲན་དབང་དེས་རེག་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Later, they will also reach the perfect insight of awakening.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-375">
            <prop type="folio">F.154.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཇི་ལྟར་གང་གཱའི་བྱེ་སྙེད་རྣམ་པར་འདྲེན། །མང་པོ་དག་ནི་ཚེ་གཅིག་གིས་མཆོད་དེ། །ཀུན་ནས་འོད་ཟེར་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་ཐོབ་ནས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-195"/>“Those who, in a single life, venerate as many guides As there are grains of sand in the Ganges Attain the utterly illuminating absorption </seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-376">
            <prop type="folio">F.155.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>
                    <tei:ref folio="F.155.a"/>ཕྱིས་ནི་བྱང་ཆུབ་མྱ་ངན་མེད་རེག་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>And subsequently reach awakening beyond anguish.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-377">
            <prop type="folio">F.155.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱང་ཆུབ་དྲི་མེད་བྱང་ཆུབ་ཆེ་ཐོབ་ནས། །ཆོས་ཀྱི་འཁོར་ལོ་དམ་པ་རབ་ཏུ་བསྐོར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-196"/>“Having obtained immaculate awakening, great awakening, They will turn the sublime wheel of Dharma,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-378">
            <prop type="folio">F.155.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སེམས་ཅན་སངས་རྒྱས་བྱང་ཆུབ་མཆོག་བཞག་ནས། །ཆར་ཆུས་མེ་བསད་ལྟར་ནི་མྱ་ངན་འདའ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Whereby they will establish beings in the supreme awakening of buddhahood, Transcending anguish just as rainfall quenches flames.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-379">
            <prop type="folio">F.155.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྐང་གཉིས་འདྲེན་པ་མི་འདུལ་ཁ་ལོ་སྒྱུར། །བསོད་ནམས་ཞིང་སྟེ་བསོད་ནམས་ཕུང་པོ་གཅིག །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-197"/>“The guide of humans, the charioteer of humans, Is the single field of merit, the single mount of merit.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-380">
            <prop type="folio">F.155.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ལ་མི་ཡིས་དད་པ་ཙམ་བསྐྱེད་ན། །སྐད་ཅིག་གིས་ནི་མི་ཁོམ་ཐམས་ཅད་སྤོང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>If people simply develop faith toward that buddha, They will instantly discard all unfree states.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-381">
            <prop type="folio">F.155.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་ཞིག་བདེ་བར་གཤེགས་ཀྱི་མཚན་འདོན་པ། །མི་ལུས་རྙེད་པ་དལ་བ་གཅིག་ཐོབ་ནས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-198"/>“Those who recite the name of this blissful one Will obtain human bodies and gain leisure.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-382">
            <prop type="folio">F.155.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མཐའ་ཡས་རྒྱ་མཚོ་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་བཞུགས་ལ། །མི་ཡི་མཁས་པ་བསོད་ནམས་རབ་ཏུ་བྱེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Then these wise persons will create merit In the limitless ocean wherein the thus-gone ones dwell.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-383">
            <prop type="folio">F.155.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སངས་རྒྱས་མཚན་ནི་སྟོང་ཕྲག་བརྒྱ་ཙམ་དུ། །གོམས་བྱེད་དེ་ནི་རྗེས་འཐུན་བཟོད་པ་ཐོབ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-199"/>“Those who chant the name of this buddha A mere one hundred thousand times will attain concordant acceptance</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-384">
            <prop type="folio">F.155.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལྷ་ཡི་མིག་ཐོབ་ཇི་ལྟར་ང་ཡིས་ནི། །སངས་རྒྱས་མར་མེ་མཛད་མཐོང་མེ་ཏོག་གིས། །གཏོར་བ་བྱས་ནས་བཟོད་པ་ཐོབ་གྱུར་པ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>And the attainment of the divine eye, just as I did.<tei:note xml:id="UT22084-059-006-200"/> <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-201"/>“When I saw the Buddha Dīpaṃkara I scattered flowers And thereby attained acceptance.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-385">
            <prop type="folio">F.155.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་འདྲའི་བཟོད་པ་དག་ནི་ཐོབ་པར་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They will acquire that sort of acceptance.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-386">
            <prop type="folio">F.155.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇིག་རྟེན་མགོན་པོ་འོད་མཛད་ཐུབ་པ་ཡི། །མཚན་ནི་ཐོས་ནས་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Upon hearing the name of this illuminating sage who protects the world.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-387">
            <prop type="folio">F.155.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སུ་ཞིག་ལུང་མི་ནོད། །གཞན་དུ་གང་ཞིག་མུ་སྟེགས་ཅན་གྱུར་པའམ། །ཕྲག་དོག་དག་གིས་ཉམས་པའི་མི་མ་གཏོགས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-202"/>“Only those who are extremists, Or who suffer from jealousy Would not want teachings</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-388">
            <prop type="folio">F.155.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདྲེན་པ་སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱི་ནི་མངོན་སུམ་དུ། །འདི་འདྲའི་མདོ་སྡེ་བཤད་པ་སུས་ཐོས་པ། །དེ་ནི་ཕྱི་དུས་དག་ཏུ་འདི་འཛིན་ཅིང་། །གཞན་དག་ལ་ཡང་རབ་ཏུ་སྟོན་པར་བྱེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-203"/>“Those who hear such a discourse taught Directly from the guide, the Buddha, Will remember it in the future And teach it to others.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-389">
            <prop type="folio">F.155.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཞོན་ནུ་སྟེང་གི་ཕྱོགས་ན་སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱི་ཞིང་འདི་ནས་གཞོན་ནུ་དཔེ་སྔ་མ་ལྟ་བུ་དེ་ལས་གང་གཱའི་ཀླུང་གི་བྱེ་མ་སྙེད་འདས་ནས་འཇིག་རྟེན་གྱི་ཁམས་ཤིན་ཏུ་རྣམ་པར་ཕྱེ་བ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་ཞིག་ཡོད་དེ</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-204"/>“Young man, located above this buddha realm, as in the previous analogy, past as many realms as there are grains of sand in the Ganges, there is a world called Wide Open.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-390">
            <prop type="folio">F.155.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ན་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་དགྲ་བཅོམ་པ་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་སངས་རྒྱས་བརྩོན་འགྲུས་གྲངས་མེད་པས་ཡང་དག་པར་རབ་ཏུ་གནས་པ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་ཞིག་བཞུགས་ཏེ་འཚོ་ཞིང་གཞེས་ལ་ཆོས་ཀྱང་སྟོན་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>There the thus-gone, worthy, perfect Buddha Stable in Immeasurable Diligence lives. He is alive and well and teaches the Dharma.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-391">
            <prop type="folio">F.155.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཞོན་ནུ་ཐེག་པ་ཆེན་པོ་ལ་ཡང་དག་པར་གནས་པའི་རིགས་ཀྱི་བུའམ། རིགས་ཀྱི་བུ་མོ་གང་ལ་ལ་ཞིག་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་བརྩོན་འགྲུས་གྲངས་མེད་པས་ཡང་དག་པར་རབ་ཏུ་གནས་པ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་དེའི་མཚན་ཐོས་ནས་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Young man, when those noble sons or daughters who abide in the Great Vehicle hear the name of the thus-gone one Stable in Immeasurable Diligence—</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-392">
            <prop type="folio">F.155.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སོམ་ཉི་མི་ཟ་<tei:ref folio="F.155.b"/>ལ་ངས་མཐོང་བ་ལ་ཡང་ཡིད་ཆེས་ན། དེ་ཚེ་འདས་པའི་འོག་ཏུ་ནམས་ཀྱང་བརྩོན་འགྲུས་དམན་པར་མི་འགྱུར། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>as long as they do not doubt this but trust in my vision—their diligence will never decrease once they have passed away.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-393">
            <prop type="folio">F.155.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ནམས་ཀྱང་འདོད་པ་ལ་སྟེན་པར་མི་འགྱུར། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Never again will they indulge in desire.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-394">
            <prop type="folio">F.155.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ནམས་ཀྱང་མའི་སྡུག་བསྔལ་གྱིས་གོས་པར་མི་འགྱུར། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Never again will they be stained by the suffering of a mother.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-395">
            <prop type="folio">F.155.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཕའི་སྡུག་བསྔལ་དང་། གཉེན་གྱི་སྡུག་བསྔལ་དང་། སྤུན་གྱི་སྡུག་བསྔལ་གྱིས་གོས་པར་མི་འགྱུར། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Never again will they be stained by the suffering of a father, relative, and friend.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-396">
            <prop type="folio">F.155.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྲིང་མོའི་སྡུག་བསྔལ་གྱིས་གོས་པར་མི་འགྱུར། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Never will they be stained by the suffering of a sister.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-397">
            <prop type="folio">F.155.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ནམས་ཀྱང་མཛའ་བོ་དང་། བཤེས་གཉེན་དང་། བློན་པོ་དང་། སྣག་གི་གཉེན་མཚམས་ཀྱི་སྡུག་བསྔལ་གྱིས་གོས་པར་མི་འགྱུར། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Never again will they be stained by the suffering of a companion, ally, clansman, or kinsman.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-398">
            <prop type="folio">F.155.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ནམས་ཀྱང་སྐྱེས་བུ་ཆེན་པོའི་མཚན་སུམ་ཅུ་རྩ་གཉིས་ཀྱིས་ལུས་མ་བརྒྱན་པར་མི་འགྱུར། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Never will their bodies not be adorned by the thirty-two marks of a great being.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-399">
            <prop type="folio">F.155.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ནམས་ཀྱང་འདོད་ཆགས་དང་ཞེ་སྡང་དང་གཏི་མུག་མང་བར་མི་འགྱུར། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Never again will their attachment, aggression, and ignorance increase.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-400">
            <prop type="folio">F.155.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ནམས་ཀྱང་ནད་མང་བར་མི་འགྱུར། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Never again will any diseases proliferate.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-401">
            <prop type="folio">F.155.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ནམས་ཀྱང་མྱ་ངན་མང་བར་མི་འགྱུར། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Never again will any anguish grow.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-402">
            <prop type="folio">F.155.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བདེ་བ་མཐའ་ཡས་པ་ཡོངས་སུ་བཟུང་བར་འགྱུར། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Instead, they will gain limitless happiness.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-403">
            <prop type="folio">F.155.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱང་ཆུབ་ལ་ཐུག་གི་བར་དུ་ཡོན་ཏན་མཐའ་ཡས་པ་བྱེ་བ་ཁྲག་ཁྲིག་འབུམ་ཕྲག་གྲངས་མེད་པས་ཡོངས་སུ་བཟུང་བར་འགྱུར་རོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>On the way to awakening, they will gain countless trillions of limitless virtues.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-404">
            <prop type="folio">F.155.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་དོན་འདི་ཉིད་ཚིགས་སུ་བཅད་པས་བཀའ་སྩལ་པ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-205"/>The Blessed One then expressed the meaning of this in verse:</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-405">
            <prop type="folio">F.155.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་ཞིག་འཇིག་རྟེན་མགོན་པོའི་མཚན། །ཐོས་ནས་སོམ་ཉི་མི་ཟ་བ། །ནམས་ཀྱང་ཕ་མ་གཉེན་འདུན་གྱི། །ཚོགས་ཀྱི་སྡུག་བསྔལ་མི་མཐོང་ངོ་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Those who hear the name of this world protector And do not doubt it Will never have to witness The suffering of parents and many relatives.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-406">
            <prop type="folio">F.155.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྟེང་གི་ཕྱོགས་ན་རྐང་གཉིས་མཆོག །འཇིག་རྟེན་སྣང་བར་མཛད་པ་བཞུགས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-207"/>“Above us abides the supreme human, Who illuminates the world.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-407">
            <prop type="folio">F.155.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྲིད་གསུམ་གསལ་བར་མཛད་ནས་སུ། །སྲོག་ཆགས་རྣམས་ལ་ཆོས་སྟོན་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He illuminates the three realms of existence And teaches beings the Dharma.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-408">
            <prop type="folio">F.155.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྫོགས་སངས་རྒྱས་པའི་མཚན་ཐོས་ནས། །དེ་ནི་གཞན་རྣམས་རབ་བསྟན་ན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-208"/>“Those who hear the name of this perfect buddha And teach it to others</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-409">
            <prop type="folio">F.155.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྟག་ཏུ་སུམ་ཅུ་རྩ་གཉིས་ཀྱི། །མཚན་དག་གིས་ནི་བརྒྱན་པར་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Will be perennially adorned With the thirty-two marks.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-410">
            <prop type="folio">F.155.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་ཞིག་ཐུབ་པའི་མཚན་འཛིན་ན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-209"/>“Those who remember the name of this sage</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-411">
            <prop type="folio">F.155.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནི་ཤེས་རབ་མི་ཉམས་ཤིང་། །བྱང་ཆུབ་སྤྱད་པ་སྤྱོད་པའི་ཚེ། །བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་ལ་ཡང་མཆོད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Will not have their insight impaired. When they are engaged in the practices of awakening, They will venerate the bodhisattvas as well.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-412">
            <prop type="folio">F.155.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱི་ནི་མཚན་བསྟན་པས། །ཕྱིས་ནི་བྱང་ཆུབ་སྤྱོད་པ་ན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-210"/>“By teaching this buddha’s name, When later they practice for awakening,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-413">
            <prop type="folio">F.155.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སངས་རྒྱས་བྱེ་བ་བསམ་མི་ཁྱབ། །ཤེས་རབ་ཅན་གྱིས་རྟག་མཆོད་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>These insightful ones shall constantly venerate Inconceivable millions of buddhas.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-414">
            <prop type="folio">F.155.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སངས་རྒྱས་མཚན་དེ་གང་ཐོས་ནས། །གཞན་རྣམས་ལ་ཡང་རབ་སྟོན་ན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-211"/>“Those who hear the name of this perfect buddha And then reveal it to others</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-415">
            <prop type="folio">F.156.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་འདྲའི་བསོད་ནམས་ཕུང་པོ་ཡི། །ཚད་ནི་<tei:ref folio="F.156.a"/>བཤད་པར་མི་ནུས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Will obtain a mass of merit The measure of which is impossible to describe.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-416">
            <prop type="folio">F.156.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ལྟར་མཚན་འདི་ཐོས་པ་ནི། །ཕྱི་དུས་དག་ནི་མང་པོར་ཡང་། །བླ་མེད་སངས་རྒྱས་ཡེ་ཤེས་ལ། །དེར་ནི་སོམ་ཉི་ཟ་མི་བྱེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-212"/>“Those who hear this name Shall never come to doubt— Even for the longest time in the future— The unsurpassed wisdom of buddhahood.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-417">
            <prop type="folio">F.156.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་གིས་རྫོགས་སངས་རྒྱས་མཐོང་ནས། །བཀུར་སྟི་རིམ་གྲོ་བྱས་པ་ནི། །ཕྱི་མའི་དུས་སུ་མདོ་སྡེ་འདི། །དེ་ཡི་ལག་ཏུ་འཐོབ་པར་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-213"/>“Those who see this perfect buddha And render service and honor unto him Shall receive this discourse In their hands at a future time.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-418">
            <prop type="folio">F.156.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ང་ནི་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཡིས། །བསྐོར་དང་དྲ་བ་ཅན་སུས་མཐོང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-214"/>“Those who see me surrounded by bodhisattvas, As well as Ratnajālin,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-419">
            <prop type="folio">F.156.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེས་ནི་མདོ་སྡེ་འདི་ཐོས་ནས། །དེ་ལ་སོམ་ཉི་ཟ་མི་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>And hear this discourse Will not come to doubt it.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-420">
            <prop type="folio">F.156.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་དཔག་མེད་དེ། །སངས་རྒྱས་ཆོས་ལ་ཐེ་ཙོམ་སྤངས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-215"/>“They will abandon any doubt In the boundless thus-gone ones and their buddha qualities.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-421">
            <prop type="folio">F.156.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདི་ལྟར་སྔོན་གྱི་སྤྱོད་པ་ནི། །བསྐལ་པ་བྱེ་བ་མང་བརྒྱར་སྤྱད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They will continue their earlier practices For many billions of eons.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-422">
            <prop type="folio">F.156.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལག་པ་རྐང་པ་གཏོང་བ་དང་། །རྣ་བ་སྣ་དང་མགོ་བོ་དང་། །བུ་ཕོ་བུ་མོ་ཡུལ་འཁོར་དག །བྱིན་ལ་ཡིད་ནི་མི་དགའ་མེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-216"/>“They will give up their hands and legs And give away their ears, noses, heads, Sons, daughters, and subjects Without any displeasure.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-423">
            <prop type="folio">F.156.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་ཞིག་མདོ་སྡེ་འདི་ཐོས་པ། །ཕྱི་མའི་དུས་ན་རྙེད་ནས་ནི། །གཞན་དག་ལ་ཡང་སྟོན་བྱེད་ན། །དེ་ནི་མཆོད་པའི་འོས་སུ་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-217"/>“When those who hear this discourse Come in contact with it in the future, They shall teach it to others, And so become worthy of veneration.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-424">
            <prop type="folio">F.156.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སངས་རྒྱས་ཀུན་གྱི་སྤྱོད་ཡུལ་བ། །མངོན་རྫོགས་བྱང་ཆུབ་འདོད་གང་གིས། །ནམ་ཡང་འཇིག་རྟེན་མགོན་པོ་ཡི། །བསྟན་ལ་སོམ་ཉི་མ་ཟ་ཅིག །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-218"/>“Let those who desire complete awakening, Which is the domain of all the buddhas, Never doubt the teachings Of the world protector!</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-425">
            <prop type="folio">F.156.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ལྟར་མདོ་སྡེ་འདི་ཐོས་ནས། །གཡོ་སྒྱུ་མེད་པའི་མིས་ཟུང་ལ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-219"/>“Those who have heard this discourse Must uphold it free from deceit.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-426">
            <prop type="folio">F.156.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཆག་པ་དག་ཏུའང་ཡང་དང་ཡང་། །མདོ་སྡེ་འདི་ནི་བརྗོད་པར་བགྱི། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They should preach this discourse again and again, Wherever they may go.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-427">
            <prop type="folio">F.156.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བརྗོད་བྱས་ཟླ་བ་གསུམ་དག་ཏུ། །ཚང་བར་ཤིན་ཏུ་ཡང་བརྗོད་ན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-220"/>“If they can perfect the meaning of this discourse, Entirely within three months,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-428">
            <prop type="folio">F.156.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཆོས་རྣམས་ཐམས་ཅད་འཛིན་བྱེད་པའི། །གཟུངས་ཀྱི་ཡེ་ཤེས་ཐོབ་པར་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They shall attain the wisdom of recall That recollects all teachings.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-429">
            <prop type="folio">F.156.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་ལིཙྪ་བཱི་གཞོན་ནུ་རིན་ཆེན་དྲ་བ་ཅན་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་ལེགས་པར་གསུངས་པར་རིག་ནས་རིན་ཐང་མེད་པའི་རས་བཅོས་བུ་གསེར་གྱིས་བརྒྱན་པ་ཟུང་གཅིག་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ལ་མངོན་པར་གསོལ་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-221"/>Once the Young Licchavi Ratnajālin had heard these well-spoken teachings of the Blessed One, he draped the Blessed One in priceless fabrics ornamented with gold.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-430">
            <prop type="folio">F.156.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་དེའི་ཚེ་རྫུ་འཕྲུལ་མངོན་པར་འདུ་མཛད་པ་ཇི་ལྟ་བུས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱི་སྐུ་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱི། བ་སྤུའི་ཁུང་བུ་ཐམས་ཅད་ནས་འོད་ཟེར་དག་བྱུང་སྟེ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Then the Blessed One performed a miracle such that from every pore of the Blessed One’s body, light streamed forth,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-431">
            <prop type="folio">F.156.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཤར་ཕྱོགས་ཀྱི་འཇིག་རྟེན་གྱི་ཁམས་དཔག་ཏུ་མེད་གྲངས་མེད་པ་ཇི་སྙེད་པ་དེ་དག་ཐམས་ཅད་སྣང་བར་གྱུར་པ་དང་། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>illuminating all the countless, infinite worlds in the east.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-432">
            <prop type="folio">F.156.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱི་ཞིང་དེ་དག་ན་སེམས་ཅན་གང་དག་སྐྱེས་པ་དེ་དག་གིས་སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱི་ཞིང་མཐོང་བ་དང་། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>All the beings born in those buddha realms beheld this buddha realm, and</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-433">
            <prop type="folio">F.156.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱི་ཞིང་འདི་ན་དེ་བཞིན་<tei:ref folio="F.156.b"/>གཤེགས་པའི་འཁོར་གྱི་དཀྱིལ་འཁོར་དུ་སེམས་ཅན་གང་དག་འདུས་པ་དེ་དག་གིས་ཀྱང་སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱི་ཞིང་དེ་མཐོང་བ་དང་། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>all the beings gathered in the Thus-Gone One’s assembly in this buddha realm also beheld this buddha realm.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-434">
            <prop type="folio">F.156.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེའི་ཚེ་གང་གཱའི་ཀླུང་གི་བྱེ་མ་སྙེད་དགུ་བཅུ་རྩ་དགུ་སྙེད་ཀྱི་སངས་རྒྱས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་རྣམས་འཁོར་བཞི་པོ་ལ་སྣང་བར་གྱུར་པ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>At that moment as many blessed buddhas, including their fourfold assemblies, were illuminated as ninety-nine times the number of grains of sand in the Ganges.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-435">
            <prop type="folio">F.156.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ལྟ་བུའི་རྫུ་འཕྲུལ་མངོན་པར་འདུ་མཛད་པས་མངོན་པར་འདུ་མཛད་དོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Such was the miracle that he performed.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-436">
            <prop type="folio">F.156.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་ལིཙྪ་བཱི་གཞོན་ནུ་རིན་ཆེན་དྲ་བ་ཅན་ལ་བཀའ་སྩལ་པ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-222"/>The Blessed One then asked the young Licchavi Ratnajālin,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-437">
            <prop type="folio">F.156.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཞོན་ནུ་ཁྱོད་ཀྱིས་སྟེང་གི་ཕྱོགས་ལོགས་ན་སངས་རྒྱས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་འདི་ལྟར་བསམ་གྱིས་མི་ཁྱབ་པ། འདི་ལྟར་གཞལ་གྱིས་མི་ལང་བ། འདི་ལྟར་ཐུག་པ་མེད་པ། འདི་ལྟར་ཚད་མེད་པ། འདི་ལྟར་བརྗོད་ཀྱིས་མི་ལང་བ་དེ་དག་མཐོང་ངམ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Young man, when you look above, do you see all the blessed buddhas, who are so unfathomably, innumerably, limitlessly, immeasurably, and indescribably many?”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-438">
            <prop type="folio">F.156.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གསོལ་པ། བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་མཐོང་ལགས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Blessed One, I see them.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-439">
            <prop type="folio">F.156.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བདེ་བར་གཤེགས་པ་མཐོང་ལགས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Blissful One, I see them.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-440">
            <prop type="folio">F.156.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རིགས་ཀྱི་བུ་འདི་ལྟ་སྟེ། སྟོང་གསུམ་གྱི་སྟོང་ཆེན་པོའི་འཇིག་རྟེན་གྱི་ཁམས་ན་ལྷ་དང་མི་རྣམས་ཀྱི་མིང་གི་ཚོགས་པས་ནི་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་རྣམས་ཀྱི་མཚན་ཆེས་མང་སྟེ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-224"/>“Noble son, the names of these thus-gone ones vastly outnumber the names of the gods and humans gathered in the worlds of the great trichiliocosm.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-441">
            <prop type="folio">F.156.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རེ་རེ་ལ་ཡང་མཚན་གྱི་ཚོགས་གྲངས་མེད་བསམ་གྱིས་མི་ཁྱབ་པ་ཡོད་དེ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Each of them has an inconceivable and boundless agglomeration of names.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-442">
            <prop type="folio">F.156.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདི་ལྟར་ཤར་ཕྱོགས་ན་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་ལེགས་པར་རབ་ཏུ་ཞི་བའི་དཔལ་དབྱངས་ཀྱི་དབང་ཕྱུག་གི་རྒྱལ་པོ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་རྣམས་དང་། དེ་བཞིན་དུ་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་ཟླ་བའི་དཀྱིལ་འཁོར་རྣམ་དག་ཅེས་བྱ་བ་རྣམས་དང་། དེ་བཞིན་དུ་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་མེ་ཏོག་གི་འོད་ཀྱིས་རྣམ་པར་རོལ་པ་མངོན་པར་མཁྱེན་པའི་རྒྱལ་པོ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་རྣམས་དང་། དེ་བཞིན་དུ་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་མེ་ཏོག་རྒྱས་པ་སཱ་ལའི་རྒྱལ་པོ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་རྣམས་དང་། དེ་བཞིན་དུ་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་རིན་ཆེན་འོད་ཟེར་ཟླ་བས་བརྒྱན་པ་མཁས་པའི་གཟི་བརྗིད་དབྱངས་ཀྱི་དབང་ཕྱུག་གི་རྒྱལ་པོ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་རྣམས་ཏེ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>This also applies to the thus-gone one Majestic King with the Elegant Peaceful Voice in the east, and likewise to the thus-gone one Pure Moon Disk, the thus-gone one King of Knowledge of Floral Light Displays, the thus-gone one King of Blossoming Sal Tree Flowers, and the thus-gone one Majestic King with the Splendorous Voice of Learning Adorned by Precious Moonlight.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-443">
            <prop type="folio">F.156.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་གཅིག་གི་མཚན་ཇི་ལྟ་བར་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་སོ་སོའི་མཚན་ཡང་དེ་དང་འདྲ་བར་མཐོང་ངམ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Just as it is with the name of a single thus-gone one, so it is with that of any thus-gone one. Do you see that?”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-444">
            <prop type="folio">F.156.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གསོལ་པ། བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་མཐོང་ལགས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-225"/>“Blessed One, I see it.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-445">
            <prop type="folio">F.156.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བདེ་བར་གཤེགས་པ་མཐོང་ལགས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Blissful One, I see it.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-446">
            <prop type="folio">F.157.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་བཞིན་དུ་ལྷོ་ཕྱོགས་དང་། ནུབ་ཕྱོགས་དང་། བྱང་ཕྱོགས་དང་། དེ་བཞིན་དུ་འོག་གི་ཕྱོགས་<tei:ref folio="F.157.a"/>དང་། དེ་བཞིན་དུ་སྟེང་གི་ཕྱོགས་ཏེདེ་ལྟར་ཕྱོགས་བཅུ་ཀུན་གྱི་ཕྱོགས་རེ་རེ་ན་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པའི་མཚན་གཅིག་པ་ཡང་གྲངས་མ་མཆིས་ལ། དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པའི་མཚན་ཐ་དད་པ་ཡང་བཞུགས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>So it is in the south, in the west, in the north, below, and above—in each of the ten directions there are countless names of the individual thus-gone ones and myriad different names of the thus-gone ones.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-447">
            <prop type="folio">F.157.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཞོན་ནུ་ཁྱོད་ཀྱིས་འཁོར་ལོས་སྒྱུར་བའི་རྒྱལ་སྲིད་ལ་གནས་པ་དེ་བས་ཀྱང་ཆེས་ལྷག་པའི་སངས་རྒྱས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་དག་མཐོང་ངམ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-226"/>“Young man, do you see how the blessed buddhas vastly exceed those who abide in the realm of a universal monarch?”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-448">
            <prop type="folio">F.157.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གསོལ་པ། བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་མཐོང་ལགས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Blessed One, I see it.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-449">
            <prop type="folio">F.157.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བདེ་བར་གཤེགས་པ་མཐོང་ལགས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Blissful One, I see it.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-450">
            <prop type="folio">F.157.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་ལིཙྪ་བཱི་གཞོན་ནུ་རིན་ཆེན་དྲ་བ་ཅན་མགུ་ཞིང་དགའ་ལ་ཡི་རངས། རབ་ཏུ་དགའ་ཞིང་དགའ་བ་དང་ཡིད་བདེ་བ་སྐྱེས་ནས་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-228"/>The young Licchavi Ratnajālin became pleased, delighted, joyful, and happy.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-451">
            <prop type="folio">F.157.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེའི་ཚེ་ས་ཆེན་པོ་གཡོས་པར་གྱུར་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>At that moment when he was happy and delighted the earth quaked.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-452">
            <prop type="folio">F.157.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སེམས་ཅན་ཐམས་ཅད་ལ་ཕན་པ་དང་། བདེ་བ་སྐྱེད་པ་དང་། སེམས་ཅན་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱི་སེམས་རབ་ཏུ་དགའ་བ་དང་། དགེ་བའི་རྩ་བ་སྐྱེད་པའི་སྣང་བ་ཆེན་པོ་བྱུང་བར་གྱུར་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>A great burst of light appeared that benefitted all beings, brought them happiness, pleased their minds, and aroused roots of virtue in them.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-453">
            <prop type="folio">F.157.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལྷ་བྱེ་བ་ཁྲག་ཁྲིག་འབུམ་ཕྲག་དུ་མ་དག་ནམ་མཁའ་ལ་འཁོད་ནས། ལྷའི་འཛམ་བུ་ཆུ་བོའི་གསེར་གྱི་ཕྱེ་མ་རྣམས་གཏོར་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Trillions of gods stationed in the sky cast down powdered gold from the divine Jambu River.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-454">
            <prop type="folio">F.157.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཚངས་པ་བྱེ་བ་ཁྲག་ཁྲིག་འབུམ་ཕྲག་དུ་མ་དག་གིས་ཀྱང་ལྷའི་ཙན་དན་དམར་པོའི་ཕྱེ་མ་རྣམས་ཀྱིས། བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ལ་གཏོར། མངོན་པར་གཏོར། མངོན་པར་རབ་ཏུ་གཏོར་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Trillions of brahmā gods tossed, scattered, and sprinkled divine red sandalwood powder upon the Blessed One.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-455">
            <prop type="folio">F.157.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལྷ་བྱེ་བ་ཁྲག་ཁྲིག་འབུམ་ཕྲག་དུ་མ་དག་གིས་ཀྱང་ལྷའི་མེ་ཏོག་ཨུད་པ་ལ་དང་། པད་མ་དང་། ཀུ་མུ་ད་དང་། པད་མ་དཀར་པོ་དང་། མན་དཱ་ར་བ་དང་། མན་དཱ་ར་བ་ཆེན་པོས་གཏོར། མངོན་པར་གཏོར། མངོན་པར་རབ་ཏུ་གཏོར་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Trillions of gods tossed, scattered, and sprinkled divine blue, pink, red, and white lotuses, as well as smaller and larger māndārava flowers.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-456">
            <prop type="folio">F.157.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལྷ་བྱེ་བ་ཁྲག་ཁྲིག་འབུམ་ཕྲག་དུ་མ་དག་གིས་ཀྱང་རིན་པོ་ཆེའི་གདུགས་སྟོང་ཕུལ་ལོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Trillions of gods offered thousands of jeweled parasols.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-457">
            <prop type="folio">F.157.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལྷ་བྱེ་བ་ཁྲག་ཁྲིག་འབུམ་ཕྲག་དུ་མ་དག་གིས་ཀྱང་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱི་ཞབས་ལ་མགོ་བོས་ཕྱག་འཚལ་ནས་ངུས་ཏེ། གནས་བྱེ་བ་ཁྲག་ཁྲིག་འབུམ་ཕྲག་དུ་མ་དག་རྗེས་སུ་དྲན་ནོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Trillions of gods wept as they bowed their heads to the Blessed One’s feet, recalling trillions of their past lives.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-458">
            <prop type="folio">F.157.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདི་ལྟ་སྟེ། སངས་རྒྱས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱི་བྱིན་གྱི་རླབས་ཀྱིས་ཀྱང་ཆོ་འཕྲུལ་བྱེ་བ་ཁྲག་ཁྲིག་འབུམ་ཕྲག་དུ་མ་དག་རབ་ཏུ་བསྟན་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>It was the blessings of the Blessed Buddha that allowed these trillions of miracles to occur.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-459">
            <prop type="folio">F.157.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ལ་འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་བྱ་སྟེ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-229"/>About this, it was said,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-460">
            <prop type="folio">F.157.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱེ་བ་བརྒྱ་ཕྲག་དུ་མ་ཡི། །ལྷ་རྣམས་ཁོ་ར་ཁོར་ཡུག་ནས། །ཙན་དན་དམར་པོ་ཞིབ་མོ་ཡིས། །རྫོགས་སངས་<tei:ref folio="F.157.b"/>རྒྱས་ལ་འཐོར་བར་བྱེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Billions of gods Stationed in the periphery Tossed fine red sandalwood powder Upon the perfect Buddha. </seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-461">
            <prop type="folio">F.157.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བརྒྱ་བྱིན་བྱེ་བ་ཕྲག་སྟོང་དག །མཁའ་ལ་གནས་ནས་འཛམ་བུ་ཡི། །ཆུ་བོའི་གསེར་ཕྱེ་མང་པོ་ཡིས། །དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་ལ་འཐོར་བར་བྱེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-231"/>Tens of billions of śakra gods Stationed in the sky Tossed much powdered gold from the Jambu River Upon the Thus-Gone One.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-462">
            <prop type="folio">F.157.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཚངས་པ་བྱེ་བ་ཉེར་ལྷགས་ནས། །ཙན་དན་དམར་པོའི་ཕྱེ་མ་ཡིས། །རྫོགས་སངས་རྒྱས་ལ་འཐོར་བྱེད་ཅིང་། །སྒྲ་དབྱངས་སྙན་པ་ཀུན་དུ་སྒྲོགས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-232"/>Ten million brahmā gods arrived And tossed powdered red sandalwood Upon the perfect Buddha And sang melodious songs.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-463">
            <prop type="folio">F.157.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དྲི་མ་མེད་པའི་འོད་རིག་ནས། །ནམ་མཁའ་ལ་ནི་ལྷ་འཁོད་དོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-233"/>Seeing the immaculate light, The gods arrayed themselves in the sky.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-464">
            <prop type="folio">F.157.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གླུ་དབྱངས་དཔག་ཏུ་མེད་པ་ལེན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They sang countless songs And</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-465">
            <prop type="folio">F.157.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མཁའ་ལ་རས་ཀྱིས་གཡོབ་པར་བྱེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>waved fabrics in the sky.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-466">
            <prop type="folio">F.157.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ནམ་མཁའ་ལ་ནི་ལྷ་འཁོད་དེ། །པད་མ་བརྒྱ་ཕྲག་སྟོང་བླངས་ནས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-234"/>The gods arrayed in the sky, Holding thousands of lotus flowers,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-467">
            <prop type="folio">F.157.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇིག་རྟེན་གསལ་ལ་སྟོན་བྱེད་ཅིང་། །རྒྱལ་མཚན་ལ་སོགས་མཆོད་པ་བྱེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Displayed them to the World Illuminator And venerated him with banners and so forth.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-468">
            <prop type="folio">F.157.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཟླ་མེད་རྒྱལ་མཆོག་ཐུབ་དབང་ལ། །རབ་ཏུ་ཡིད་དགས་ཕྱག་འཚལ་ཞིང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-235"/>With minds filled with joy, They honored the unparalleled supreme Victor, the Lord of Sages.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-469">
            <prop type="folio">F.157.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བསྟོད་བྱེད་ནོར་བུ་རིན་ཆེན་དང་། །མུ་ཏིག་རྒྱན་ཕྲེང་འཐོར་བར་བྱེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They praised him and scattered upon him Garlands of precious jewels and pearls.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-470">
            <prop type="folio">F.157.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མི་ནི་བྱེ་བ་འབུམ་ཐམ་པ། །རྒྱལ་མཆོག་ཟླ་མེད་པ་ལ་མཆོད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-236"/>A trillion people Venerated the unparalleled supreme Victor.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-471">
            <prop type="folio">F.157.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྔོན་གྱི་གནས་བརྒྱ་རྗེས་དྲན་ཞིང་། །ཐུབ་མཆོག་བླ་མེད་མགོས་ཕྱག་འཚལ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They remembered hundreds of their past lives And bowed their heads to the unparalleled Lord of Sages.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-472">
            <prop type="folio">F.157.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་འཇིག་རྟེན་སྣང་མཛད་པས། །ཆོས་ཀྱི་རྔ་ནི་རབ་བརྡུངས་ཏེ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-237"/>Then, the World Illuminator Beat the Dharma drum;</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-473">
            <prop type="folio">F.157.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ཡིས་སྒྲས་ནི་ཞིང་རབ་མང་། །བྱེ་བ་དག་ཏུ་གོ་བར་བྱས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Its sound was heard throughout many billions Of buddha realms.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-474">
            <prop type="folio">F.157.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ཡི་ཚེ་ན་སེམས་ཅན་ནི། །བྱེ་བ་གྲངས་མེད་ཀུན་ནས་ལྷགས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-238"/>At that moment, Countless millions of beings arrived from all directions.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-475">
            <prop type="folio">F.157.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་དག་རྫོགས་པའི་སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱིས། །སངས་རྒྱས་ཡེ་ཤེས་བླ་མེད་བཀོད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They were established in the wisdom of buddhahood By the perfect Buddha.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-476">
            <prop type="folio">F.157.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ཚེ་གཞོན་ནུ་དགའ་གྱུར་ནས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-239"/>The young man was delighted;</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-477">
            <prop type="folio">F.157.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཙན་དན་སྦྲུལ་གྱི་སྙིང་པོ་ཡི། །གདན་འབུལ་རིན་ཆེན་ཕྱེ་མ་ཡིས། །གཞོན་ནུ་སངས་རྒྱས་གཙོ་ལ་མཆོད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He offered a seat of uraga sandalwood And venerated the supreme Buddha With powdered gems.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-478">
            <prop type="folio">F.157.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ནོར་བུ་རིན་ཆེན་འོད་གཅིག་ནི། །འཇིག་རྟེན་སྟོང་དུ་གཏོང་བར་བྱེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-240"/>The light of one precious gem Shone throughout thousands of worlds.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-479">
            <prop type="folio">F.157.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རིན་ཆེན་གཅིག་ལས་འོད་ཟེར་ནི། །སྟོང་ཕྲག་བྱེ་བར་གཏོང་བར་བྱེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The light of that single gem Radiated throughout billions of worlds.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-480">
            <prop type="folio">F.157.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་བཞིན་རིན་ཆེན་མ་ལུས་ལས། །འོད་ཟེར་དག་ནི་བྱུང་བར་གྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-241"/>In the same way, light sprang forth From every gem without exception.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-481">
            <prop type="folio">F.157.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་དག་གིས་ནི་དེ་ཡི་ཚེ། །ཡངས་པ་ཅན་ཡང་སྣང་བར་བྱས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>At that moment, they also Illuminated Vaiśālī.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-482">
            <prop type="folio">F.157.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རིན་ཆེན་རྣམ་པ་དེ་སྙེད་ཀྱིས། །སངས་རྒྱས་གཙོ་ལ་མཆོད་བྱེད་ཅིང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-242"/>All of these gems were used To venerate the principle Buddha.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-483">
            <prop type="folio">F.157.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རིན་པོ་ཆེ་ཡི་ཕུང་པོ་ཡང་། །ཐུབ་པ་ཆེ་ལ་འབུལ་བར་བྱེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>A great pile of gems Also was offered to the Great Sage.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-484">
            <prop type="folio">F.157.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གདུགས་ནི་གང་དག་མུ་ཁྱུད་བྱས། །མུ་ཏིག་ཕྲེང་གིས་ཡོངས་བརྒྱན་པ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-243"/>Parasols adorned With pearl garlands surrounded him.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-485">
            <prop type="folio">F.157.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རེ་རེ་ལ་ཡང་མུ་ཁྱུད་ཅན། །སྟོང་ཕྲག་ཉི་ཤུ་རྩ་ལྔའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Each had twenty-five thousand Surrounding layers.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-486">
            <prop type="folio">F.158.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདི་འདྲའི་ལེགས་པ་དེ་ཡིས་ནི། །<tei:ref folio="F.158.a"/>ཐུབ་པ་ཆེ་ལ་མཆོད་པ་བྱས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-244"/>They venerated the Great Sage Through such excellent means. </seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-487">
            <prop type="folio">F.158.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཐམས་ཅད་ལ། །གསེང་ཐགས་ཀྱི་ནི་གོས་ཕུལ་ལོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Woven fabrics were offered To all the bodhisattvas.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-488">
            <prop type="folio">F.158.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱང་ཆུབ་ཤིང་དག་སྤྲུལ་ནས་སུ། །དེའི་དྲུང་སེང་གེའི་ཁྲི་བཤམས་ལ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-245"/>Lion thrones were placed Before emanated trees of awakening.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-489">
            <prop type="folio">F.158.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྟོང་ཕྲག་བྱེ་བ་ཉི་ཤུ་ལྔ། །དེ་རྣམས་ལ་ནི་འཁོད་གྱུར་པ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>All told, two hundred fifty million Were set out.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-490">
            <prop type="folio">F.158.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལོ་ནི་བྱེ་བ་གྲངས་སྙེད་པར། །བགྲང་བ་དག་ཏུ་མི་ཆོད་པའི། །བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཐམས་ཅད་ནི། །བྱེ་བ་བརྒྱ་ཕྲག་ལྷགས་པར་གྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-246"/>For millions of years, Countless bodhisattvas— Hundreds of millions in fact— Arrived there.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-491">
            <prop type="folio">F.158.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཤར་གྱི་ཕྱོགས་ནས་བཟུང་ནས་སུ། །ལྷོ་ཕྱོགས་ནུབ་ཕྱོགས་བྱང་ཕྱོགས་དང་། །འོག་དང་སྟེང་དང་དེ་བཞིན་དུ། །ཕྱོགས་དག་གི་ཡང་མཚམས་ནས་ལྷགས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-247"/>They arrived first from the east, And then from the south, west, and north, From above and below, And from the intermediate directions.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-492">
            <prop type="folio">F.158.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཇི་ཙམ་མིག་གིས་མཐོང་བའི་བར། །དེ་སྲིད་འཇིག་རྟེན་ཁམས་རྣམས་སུ། །སྐྱོབ་པ་འཇིག་རྟེན་མགོན་པོ་ཡི། །གསེར་གྱི་མདོག་འདྲའི་འོད་ཀྱིས་གང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-248"/>The golden-colored light Of the Refuge, the World Protector, Filled as many realms As the eye could see.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-493">
            <prop type="folio">F.158.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྟོན་པ་གང་ན་བཞུགས་པ་དང་། །ཆོས་ནི་གང་ན་འབར་བ་དེར། །འཇིག་རྟེན་ཁམས་ནི་ཐམས་ཅད་ནས། །བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཉེ་བར་ལྷགས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-249"/>Bodhisattvas arrived From all worlds To the place where the Teacher was sitting And the Dharma was shining.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-494">
            <prop type="folio">F.158.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ལྟར་མཐའ་ཡས་དཔག་ཏུ་མེད། །བསམ་གྱིས་མི་ཁྱབ་མཆོད་པ་ནི། །རིན་ཆེན་དྲ་བ་ལིཙྪ་བཱི། །གཞོན་ནུ་དེ་ཡི་ཚེ་ན་བྱས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-250"/>In this fashion, Ratnajālin, The young Licchavi, Performed boundless, Limitless, and inconceivable homage.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-495">
            <prop type="folio">F.158.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་བདག་ཉིད་ཆེན་པོ་པ། །ལྷ་དང་ཀླུ་དང་མི་རྣམས་ཀྱིས། །མདུན་དུ་མི་མཆོག་ཤཱཀྱ་ཡི། །སེང་གེས་དབུགས་ནི་འབྱིན་པར་མཛད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-251"/>Then the great person, The supreme human, the Lion of the Śākyas, Brought comfort to the assembled Gods, nāgas, and humans:</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-496">
            <prop type="folio">F.158.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ང་ཡི་མདུན་དུ་འདུག་ནས་སུ། །ཁྱོད་ཀྱིས་འདི་འདྲའི་མཆོད་བྱས་པ། །གང་གཱའི་བྱེ་མ་ཇི་སྙེད་པ། །དེ་སྙེད་མཆོད་པ་དག་གིས་མཆོད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-252"/>“Standing before me, You have performed such veneration. This veneration has been done with offerings As numerous as the grains of sand in the Ganges.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-497">
            <prop type="folio">F.158.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རིན་ཆེན་དྲ་བ་ཅན་གྱི་ཕྱིར། །མདོ་སྡེ་བཤད་པ་སུས་རིག་པ། །བྱང་ཆུབ་ལས་ནི་མི་ལྡོག་སྟེ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-253"/>“Those who hear this discourse, Which has been taught for the sake of Ratnajālin, Shall not turn back from awakening;</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-498">
            <prop type="folio">F.158.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སངས་རྒྱས་སྨྲ་བའི་མཆོག་ཏུ་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They will become supreme preachers of buddhahood.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-499">
            <prop type="folio">F.158.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་ཞིག་མདོ་སྡེ་འདི་འཛིན་པའི། །བསོད་ནམས་ཕུང་པོའི་ཚད་དག་ནི། །འདི་སྙེད་སོགས་པར་འགྱུར་རོ་ཞེས། །དེ་ལྟར་བཤད་པར་མི་ནུས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-254"/>“One cannot describe The measure of the mass of merit That ensues from remembering this discourse By saying, ‘It shall be this much.’</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-500">
            <prop type="folio">F.158.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཕྱོགས་བཅུའི་འཇིག་རྟེན་ས་དང་ཆུ། །མེ་དང་རླུང་གི་ཚད་དག་ནི། །འདི་ཙམ་ཞེས་ནི་བཤད་པར་ནུས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-255"/>“While one can describe the extent Of the earth, water, fire, and wind Throughout the ten directions,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-501">
            <prop type="folio">F.158.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བསོད་ནམས་ཕུང་པོ་བཤད་མི་ནུས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>It is impossible to describe this mass of merit.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-502">
            <prop type="folio">F.158.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དགེ་སློང་ངམ་ནི་དགེ་སློང་མ། །དགེ་བསྙེན་འམ་ནི་དགེ་བསྙེན་མ། །གང་གིས་མདོ་སྡེ་འདི་ཐོས་ནས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-256"/>“When a monk or nun, Or a novice monk or nun, Hears this discourse,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-503">
            <prop type="folio">F.158.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལྷ་དང་ཀླུ་དང་ལྟོ་འཕྱེ་ཆེ། །སེམས་ཅན་ཐམས་ཅད་ཉེར་ལྷགས་པས། །དེ་ཡི་གཟི་བརྗིད་མི་བཟོད་དེ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>All beings including gods, nāgas, and mahoragas <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-257"/>“Will arrive near them And find their splendor overwhelming.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-504">
            <prop type="folio">F.158.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མེ་ནི་བསིལ་བར་འགྱུར་སྲིད་ཀྱི། །དེ་ཡི་གཟི་<tei:ref folio="F.158.b"/>བརྗིད་ཉམས་པ་མེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>While it is possible that fire can turn cold, Their splendor will never diminish. </seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-505">
            <prop type="folio">F.158.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མདོ་སྡེ་འདི་ནི་གང་འཛིན་པ། །བྱང་ཆུབ་སྤྱད་པ་སྤྱོད་པའི་ཚེ། །སེམས་ཅན་ཀུན་གྱིས་བསྟེན་བྱ་ཞིང་། །བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་ལའང་མཆོད་པ་བྱེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-258"/>“When someone who remembers this discourse Engages in the conduct of awakening, All beings will attend to them And venerate the mind of awakening.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-506">
            <prop type="folio">F.158.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་ཞིག་སྟོབས་དང་ལྡན་པའི་མིས། །བྱེ་བ་སྟོང་དུ་བཤད་པ་ཡི། །སྐྲ་རྩེས་སྟོང་གི་འཇིག་རྟེན་ཁམས། །བསྐལ་པ་བྱེ་བ་བཟུང་བ་བས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-259"/>“A powerful person Might hold up a thousand worlds For millions of eons On the tip of a hair that has been split a billion times.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-507">
            <prop type="folio">F.158.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་ཞིག་ཕྱི་མའི་དུས་དག་ཏུ། །སངས་རྒྱས་བྱང་ཆུབ་གླེང་གཞི་ནི། །འདི་འདྲའི་རྣམ་པས་ཐོས་ནས་སུ། །གཞན་དག་ལ་ཡང་སྟོན་བྱེད་ན</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>during the latter days One may teach to others A discourse of the buddhas’ awakening That one has heard in this fashion.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-508">
            <prop type="folio">F.158.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་ཞིག་སྔར་ནི་རབ་བསྒྲགས་པ། །འདི་ཡི་ངོ་མཚར་ཆེན་པོ་ཡི། །བརྒྱ་དང་གྲངས་དང་བགྲང་བ་དང་། །དཔེར་ཡང་འགྱུར་བ་མ་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-261"/>“In that case the great wonder Of the former example Shall not measure even a hundredth of that— As no number, figure, or example could suffice.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-509">
            <prop type="folio">F.158.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཕྱི་མ་ཡི་ནི་དུས་དག་ཏུ། །འདི་འདྲའི་རྣམ་པ་སེང་གེའི་སྒྲ། །བསྟན་པ་བླ་མེད་ཐོས་གྱུར་ཀྱང་། །འགལ་མེད་དོན་མེད་འགྱུར་བར་འོང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-262"/>“In the latter days, When people hear the unsurpassed teachings Of the lion’s roar in this manner, It will not be contradicted or opposed.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-510">
            <prop type="folio">F.158.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇིག་རྟེན་མགོན་པོ་རྫོགས་སངས་རྒྱས། །འོད་མཛད་གང་གིས་འདིར་མཐོང་བ། །ཕྱི་མའི་དུས་སུ་དེས་ཐོས་ནས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-263"/>“In the future, when people hear Of those who have seen the World Protector— The shining perfect Buddha—</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-511">
            <prop type="folio">F.158.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཞེ་ས་གུས་པར་བྱེད་པར་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They will act with respect and reverence.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-512">
            <prop type="folio">F.158.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གལ་ཏེ་ཞིང་རྣམས་བྱེ་བ་ན། །སེམས་ཅན་གང་དག་འཁོད་དེ་དག །སངས་རྒྱས་ཡེ་ཤེས་ལྡན་གྱུར་ལ། །གང་གཱ་ཡི་ནི་བྱེ་མ་སྙེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-264"/>“If all beings In millions of buddha realms Were endowed with the wisdom of buddhahood— As many of them as there are grains of sand in the Ganges—</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-513">
            <prop type="folio">F.158.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བསྐལ་པ་དུ་མ་བརྒྱ་དག་ཏུ། །རིམ་གྲོ་དག་ནི་བྱེད་པ་དང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-265"/>“One might perform service to them For many hundreds of eons,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-514">
            <prop type="folio">F.158.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཇི་ལྟར་སྟོང་ཆེན་གྱི་ནི་འཇིག་རྟེན་ཁམས། །དེ་སྙེད་དག་གི་གཙུག་ལག་ཁང་མཆོག་ནི། །དབུལ་བྱ་ལྷ་ཡི་ཙན་དན་དག་ལས་བྱས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>And offer them as many fine temples As there are worlds in the great trichiliocosm. <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-266"/>“The temples could be made of sandalwood;</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-515">
            <prop type="folio">F.158.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལྷ་ཡི་གཙུག་ལག་ཁང་མཆོག་རེ་རེ་ལའང་། །བྱེ་བ་ཕྲག་སྟོང་དག་གི་ཁང་བཟངས་བྱས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>And each supreme and divine temple Would have ten billion assembly halls.<tei:note xml:id="UT22084-059-006-267"/>
                </seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-516">
            <prop type="folio">F.158.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱེ་བ་ཕྲག་སྟོང་དག་གི་ཁང་བཟངས་ཀྱང་། །དབུལ་བྱ་ལྷ་ཡི་རིན་ཆེན་དག་ལས་བྱས། །རེ་རེའི་ཁྲི་དག་བཤམས་ནས་རིམ་གྲོ་པ། །བྱེ་བ་ཕྲག་བརྒྱ་ཤིན་ཏུ་ཚང་བར་བཀོད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-268"/>“Each of the billion assembly halls Could be made from divine jewels as an offering. One could arrange thrones for everyone, Complete with a billion servants.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-517">
            <prop type="folio">F.158.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མཁས་པས་དེ་ནི་རིན་ཆེན་དྲ་བ་དག །བླངས་ནས་དེ་ཚེ་ཁྲི་དེ་བརྒྱན་པ་རྣམས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-269"/>“Skillfully, one could take nets of jewels And adorn the thrones.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-518">
            <prop type="folio">F.158.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་གཱའི་བྱེ་སྙེད་བསྐལ་པ་བྱེ་བ་བརྒྱར། །ཐུབ་ཆེན་འཇིག་རྟེན་སྤྱོད་པ་བཞུགས་པ་ཡི། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>For eons as numerous as the grains of sand in the Ganges, The great sages who wander through the world could then abide there.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-519">
            <prop type="folio">F.158.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སངས་རྒྱས་གཅིག་ལ་འབུལ་བྱ་དབུལ་བ་དང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-270"/>“One could offer all that is fit to be offered To each of those buddhas.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-520">
            <prop type="folio">F.158.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཇི་ལྟར་གང་གཱའི་ཀླུང་གི་བྱེ་མ་སྙེད། །ཡོངས་སུ་མྱ་ངན་འདས་ཀྱི་མཆོད་རྟེན་བྱས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>One could also create caityas for their parinirvāṇas As numerous as the grains of sand in the Ganges.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-521">
            <prop type="folio">F.159.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཇི་ལྟར་སྟོང་ཆེན་འཇིག་རྟེན་ཁམས་རྣམས་སུ། །སངས་རྒྱས་གཅིག་གི་མཆོད་རྟེན་བྱས་པ་ནི། །རིན་ཆེན་རང་བཞིན་ལྷ་ཡི་སྒོ་སྟོང་ལྡན། །ཤིན་ཏུ་<tei:ref folio="F.159.a"/>ལེགས་པར་སྲིད་པའི་རྩེ་སྲིད་མཐོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-271"/>“One could create a caitya to every single buddha In all the worlds of the great trichiliocosm— Composed of jewels, with thousands of divine doors, Reaching as high as the peak of existence.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-522">
            <prop type="folio">F.159.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཇི་ལྟར་གང་གཱའི་ཀླུང་གི་བྱེ་སྙེད་ཀྱི། །གདུགས་ནི་མཆོད་རྟེན་གཅིག་ལ་འབུལ་བར་བྱེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-272"/>“One could offer parasols as numerous as the grains of sand in the Ganges To each of these caityas.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-523">
            <prop type="folio">F.159.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ཚེ་རེ་རེ་གདུགས་ལ་མུ་ཏིག་གི། །རྒྱན་ཕྲེང་བྱེ་བ་རྣམས་ཀྱང་ཤིན་ཏུ་བཀྲམ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The parasols offered at that time would be Covered with ornamental garlands of pearl.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-524">
            <prop type="folio">F.159.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཇི་ལྟར་གང་གཱའི་ཀླུང་གི་བྱེ་མ་སྙེད། །བྱེ་བའི་འཕན་དང་རིན་ཆེན་སྣ་ཚོགས་ཀྱི། །རྒྱལ་མཚན་བྱེ་བ་ཕྲག་བརྒྱ་གང་གཱ་ཡི། །བྱེ་སྙེད་མཆོད་རྟེན་དག་ལ་འབུལ་བར་བྱེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-273"/>“One could also offer millions of streamers As numerous as the grains of sand in the Ganges And billions of banners made of various precious jewels To these caityas as numerous as the grains of sand in the Ganges.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-525">
            <prop type="folio">F.159.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྣང་བ་མཛད་པ་ཐམས་ཅད་མཁྱེན་གཅིག་གི། །མཆོད་རྟེན་གཅིག་ལ་སིལ་སྙན་བྱེ་བ་སྟོང་། །དཀྲོལ་ཅིང་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-274"/>“One could play billions of instruments At each caitya of the omniscient illuminators.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-526">
            <prop type="folio">F.159.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གུས་པའི་མི་ནི་ས་ཡ་དག །བྱེ་བ་ཕྲག་སྟོང་ཚང་བ་འབུལ་བར་བྱེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Trillions of respectful humans too Would join in making offerings.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-527">
            <prop type="folio">F.159.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མེ་ཏོག་གདུགས་བརྒྱ་དུ་མ་མཆོད་རྟེན་ལ་འབུལ་བ། །ཐུབ་པ་ཆེ་ལ་དེ་འདྲའི་མཆོད་པ་ཉིན་གཅིག་བཞིན། །གང་གཱའི་བྱེ་སྙེད་བསྐལ་པ་སྟོང་དུ་བྱེད་པ་བས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-275"/>“They would offer hundreds of flowers and parasols to the caitya And venerate the great sages in this manner every day For as many eons as there are grains of sand in the Ganges.<tei:note xml:id="UT22084-059-006-276"/>
                </seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-528">
            <prop type="folio">F.159.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་ཞིག་མདོ་སྡེ་འདི་ལས་ཚིགས་བཅད་གཅིག་ཐོས་ནསསོམ་ཉི་མེད་ཅིང་འདུན་པ་སྐྱེད་བྱེད་ལ། །རྒྱལ་བའི་མཚན་འདི་དག་ཀྱང་རྗོད་བྱེད་ན། །དེ་བས་བསོད་ནམས་འདི་ནི་བླ་མེད་མཆོག །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>hearing just one verse from this discourse While not doubting it, developing interest, And reciting these victors’ names Brings merit that is unsurpassed and supreme.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-529">
            <prop type="folio">F.159.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མཁས་པ་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་གྱི་མིང་ཐོས་ཤིང་། །ཚུལ་ཁྲིམས་སྐྱོན་མེད་མཚན་འདི་འཛིན་པ་དང་། །དེ་བཞིན་སངས་རྒྱས་ལ་ནི་མཆོད་བྱེད་པ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-278"/>“Wise ones should listen to the names of absorptions, Maintain flawless discipline, remember these names, And venerate the thus-gone buddhas.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-530">
            <prop type="folio">F.159.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེས་ནི་གང་གཱའི་བྱེ་སྙེད་སངས་རྒྱས་མཐོང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Thereby, they will behold as many buddhas as the grains of sand in the Ganges.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-531">
            <prop type="folio">F.159.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཐུབ་ཆེན་རྐང་གཉིས་མཆོག་གྱུར་དེ་དག་ལ། །མཆོད་པ་དམ་པའང་ཡིད་ཀྱིས་བྱས་ནས་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-279"/>“Having directed their minds to the sacred veneration Of the supreme humans, the great sages,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-532">
            <prop type="folio">F.159.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ནི། །རྟག་ཏུ་མྱོས་མེད་ཆོས་ཀྱང་སྟོན་བྱེད་ཅིང་། །བསྐལ་པ་བྱེ་བ་དེ་ནི་རྨོངས་མེད་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They will always be sane, they will teach the Dharma, And for millions of eons they will remain undeluded.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-533">
            <prop type="folio">F.159.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇིག་རྟེན་མགོན་པོས་མདོ་མཆོག་རྒྱལ་པོ་འདི། །སྟོན་པའི་ཚེ་ན་གང་གིས་སྔོན་མཐོང་བ། །རྒྱལ་བ་མཆོག་ལས་འདི་ནི་ཐོས་གྱུར་ནས། །ཕྱི་མའི་དུས་སུ་དེ་ནི་དགའ་བས་འཛིན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-280"/>“As the World Protector teaches This supreme king of discourses, Those who hear what the Supreme Victor has previously seen Will obtain happiness in the future.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-534">
            <prop type="folio">F.159.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དྲི་ང་ཕྱི་སའི་བུམ་པ་མིས་འདོར་ལྟར། །འདོད་པ་སྐྱོན་དུ་བགྲང་བ་སྤོང་བྱེད་ཅིང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-281"/>“They will discard desires, knowing them to have faults, Like a person tossing away a vessel filled with foul-smelling excrement.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-535">
            <prop type="folio">F.159.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མཁས་པ་ངེས་འབྱུང་ཞི་ལ་མངོན་དགའ་སྟེ། །རྟག་ཏུ་མྱོས་མེད་དགོན་པ་སྟེན་པར་བྱེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Such wise beings will delight in emancipation and peace, Be constantly sane, and rely on the protectors.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-536">
            <prop type="folio">F.159.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡངས་པའི་གྲོང་ཁྱེར་མཆོག་ཏུ་གནས་ནས་སུ། །དེར་ནི་བཤད་ཚེ་གང་གིས་ང་མཐོང་ཞིང་། །དྲ་བའང་ང་ལ་མཆོད་བྱེད་མཐོང་བ་ནི། །ཕྱི་མའི་དུས་སུ་མདོ་མཆོག་འདི་འཛིན་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-282"/>“Those who saw me teach this In the city of Vaiśālī, Including Ratnajālin, who beheld and venerated me, Shall remember this supreme discourse in the future.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-537">
            <prop type="folio">F.159.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ངའི་བུ་གང་ཞིག་རྟག་ཏུ་རྗེས་འབྲང་ཞིང་། །བྱང་ཆུབ་ཞི་བ་སྤྱོད་མཆོག་སྤྱོད་པ་ན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-283"/>“Those of my children who always follow me, Engage in the supreme acts of awakening and peace,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-538">
            <prop type="folio">F.159.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སེམས་ཅན་རྣམས་ནི་རྟག་ཏུ་འདུལ་བྱེད་པ། །<tei:ref folio="F.159.b"/>ཕྱི་མའི་དུས་སུ་མདོ་མཆོག་འདི་འཛིན་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>And constantly train beings Shall uphold this supreme discourse in the future.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-539">
            <prop type="folio">F.159.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སངས་རྒྱས་འདྲེན་པ་གཞལ་མེད་དཔག་མེད་ཀྱི། །སྤྱད་པ་སྤྱོད་ཚེ་གང་གིས་རིམ་གྲོ་དང་། །དེ་བཞིན་མཆོད་པ་མཆོག་དག་བྱེད་པ་ནི། །དེ་ནི་ཕྱི་དུས་རྒྱལ་མཆོག་ཆོས་འཛིན་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-284"/>“Those who serve the buddhas, the guides, As they engage in the fathomless and incalculable practices, And likewise engage in perfect worship, Shall uphold this teaching of the Supreme Victor in the future.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-540">
            <prop type="folio">F.159.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་ཞིག་བསྐལ་པ་བྱེ་བར་ཚངས་སྤྱོད་ཅིང་། །འཇིག་རྟེན་མཐའ་ཡས་དོན་ནི་སྔར་སྤྱད་པ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-285"/>“One could have engaged in pure conduct for a million eons Or previously worked for the benefit of infinite worlds;</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-541">
            <prop type="folio">F.159.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་ཞིག་ཕྱི་མའི་དུས་སུ་མདོ་སྡེ་འདི། །ཐོས་པའི་བསོད་ནམས་གྲངས་སུ་འགྱུར་མ་ཡིན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Yet the merit of hearing this discourse in the future Shall not be countable at all.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-542">
            <prop type="folio">F.159.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སངས་རྒྱས་འཁྲུགས་མེད་ཡང་ན་ཚེ་དཔག་མེད། །སངས་རྒྱས་གཞལ་མེད་དཔག་མེད་དེ་དག་འདིར། །སེམས་ཅན་སྙིང་པོ་གང་གིས་མཐོང་འདོད་པ། །མདོ་སྡེ་མཛེས་པ་དཔག་མེད་བཟུང་བར་གྱིས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-286"/>“Let those intelligent beings who desire to behold These peaceful and immortal buddhas— The unfathomable and limitless buddhas— Uphold the unfathomable greatness of this discourse!</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-543">
            <prop type="folio">F.159.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཚེ་དཔག་མེད་དང་མི་འཁྲུགས་དྲི་མེད་འོད། །སེང་གེ་དང་ནི་ཏོག་དང་དེ་བཞིན་དུ། །གང་ཞིག་སངས་རྒྱས་དེ་ཀུན་མཐོང་འདོད་པ། །ཕྱི་མའི་དུས་སུ་རྒྱལ་མཆོག་ཆོས་ཟུང་ཤིག །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-287"/>“Let those who wish to behold all these buddhas, Including Amitāyus, Akṣobhya, Vimalaprabhā, and Siṃhaketu, Uphold this teaching of the Supreme Victor in the future!</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-544">
            <prop type="folio">F.159.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སངས་རྒྱས་བྱམས་པ་དང་ནི་དྲི་མེད་འོད། །བདག་ཉིད་ཆེན་པོ་དང་ནི་སེང་གེ་ཏོག །རབ་སྣང་གཙོ་བོ་དེ་བཞིན་མཐོང་འདོད་པ། །དེ་ནི་ཕྱི་དུས་རྒྱལ་མཆོག་ཆོས་ཟུང་ཤིག །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-288"/>“Let those who wish to behold these principle illuminators, The buddhas Maitreya and Vimalaprabhā, Mahātman, and Siṃhaketu, Uphold this teaching of the Supreme Victor in the future!</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-545">
            <prop type="folio">F.159.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདི་འདྲའི་མདོ་སྡེ་ཁྱད་པར་འཕགས་མཆོག་དག །རིན་ཆེན་དྲ་བ་ཅན་ལ་ང་ཡིས་བཤད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-289"/>“I have taught this noble and supreme discourse to Ratnajālin.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-546">
            <prop type="folio">F.159.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཕྱི་མའི་དུས་སུ་དེ་ཚེ་ཁྱོད་ཀྱིས་ནི། །བག་མེད་གནས་ལ་འདུག་པར་མ་བྱེད་ཅིག །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>In the future, Do not stay in heedless places!</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-547">
            <prop type="folio">F.159.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཕྱི་མའི་དུས་ཀྱི་ཚེ་རུ་གྱུར་པ་ན། །ཚུལ་ཁྲིམས་སྐྱོན་མེད་རྟག་ཏུ་བག་བྱོས་དང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-290"/>“When the future times come, Be careful and always keep your discipline flawless.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-548">
            <prop type="folio">F.159.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་ཁྱོད་ནི་འཆི་བའི་དུས་བྱས་ནས། །རྒྱལ་བ་འོད་ཟེར་མཐའ་ཡས་ཅན་གྱི་ཞིང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Then, when your time comes to die, You will go to the realm of the victor Infinite Light.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-549">
            <prop type="folio">F.159.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རིན་ཆེན་ལྡན་ཞེས་བྱ་བའི་འཇིག་རྟེན་ཁམས། །སྟེང་གི་འཇིག་རྟེན་ཁམས་སུ་འགྲོ་བར་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-291"/>“His realm is known as Jeweled, And is located in a world above us.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-550">
            <prop type="folio">F.159.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་ཁྱོད་ནི་འཆི་བའི་དུས་བྱས་ནས། །མྱུར་བ་ཉིད་དུ་སངས་རྒྱས་བྱམས་པ་མཐོང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Following that, when your time comes to die, You will swiftly behold the Buddha Maitreya.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-551">
            <prop type="folio">F.159.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་དེ་སྐད་ཅེས་བཀའ་སྩལ་པ་དང་། ལིཙྪ་བཱི་གཞོན་ནུ་རིན་ཆེན་དྲ་བ་ཅན་དང་། བྱམས་པ་ལ་སོགས་པ་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་བྱེ་བ་ཕྲག་བཞི་བཅུ་དང་། དགྲ་བཅོམ་པ་བྱེ་བ་ཕྲག་དྲུག་ཅུ་དང་། ལྷ་བྱེ་བ་ཕྲག་དགུ་བཅུ་རྩ་དགུ་རྣམས་ཡི་རངས་ཏེ་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་གསུངས་པ་ལ་མངོན་པར་བསྟོད་དོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
  <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-292"/>Once the Blessed One gave this teaching, the young Licchavi Ratnajālin as well as four hundred million bodhisattvas such as Maitreya, and also six hundred million worthy ones and nine hundred ninety million gods rejoiced and praised what the Blessed One had said.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-552">
            <prop type="folio">F.159.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཕགས་པ་རིན་ཆེན་དྲ་བ་ཅན་གྱིས་ཞུས་པ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་ཐེག་པ་ཆེན་པོའི་མདོ་རྫོགས་སྷོ།། །།</seg>
            </tuv>
  <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>This completes the Great Vehicle sūtra “The Questions of Ratnajālin.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-006-TU-554">
            <prop type="folio">F.159.b</prop>
  <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྒྱ་གར་གྱི་མཁན་པོ་ཛྙཱ་ན་གར་བྷ་དང་། ལོཙྪ་བ་བནྡེ་ཡེ་ཤེས་སྙིང་པོས་བསྒྱུར། ཞུས་ཆེན་གྱི་ལོཙྪ་བ་བནྡེ་དཔལ་བརྩེགས་ཀྱིས་ཞུས་ཏེ་གཏན་ལ་ཕབ་པ།། །།</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-006-294"/>It was translated by the Indian scholar Jñānagarbha and the translator Venerable Yeshé Nyingpo.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
</body>
</tmx>