<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tmx xmlns="http://www.lisa.org/tmx14" xmlns:eft="http://read.84000.co/ns/1.0" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" version="1.4b">
<header creationtool="InterText" creationtoolversion="1.0" datatype="PlainText" segtype="block" adminlang="en-us" srclang="bo" o-tmf="TEI" eft:text-id="UT22084-061-004" eft:text-version="v-1.0.10-2020"/>
<body>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.96.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཕགས་པ་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའི་སྤྱོད་པ་བསྟན་པ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་ཐེག་པ་ཆེན་པོའི་མདོ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The Noble Great Vehicle Sūtra Teaching the Practice of a Bodhisattva</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.96.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སངས་རྒྱས་དང་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཐམས་ཅད་ལ་ཕྱག་འཚལ་ལོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-061-004-16"/>Homage to all buddhas and bodhisattvas.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.96.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདི་སྐད་བདག་གིས་ཐོས་པ་དུས་གཅིག་ན། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-061-004-17"/>Thus did I hear at one time.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.97.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཡངས་པ་ཅན་ན་ཚལ་ཆེན་པོའི་ཁང་པ་བརྩེགས་པའི་གནས་ན་དགེ་སློང་སྟོང་<tei:ref folio="F.97.a"/>ཐམ་པའི་དགེ་སློང་གི་དགེ་འདུན་ཆེན་པོ་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱང་དགྲ་བཅོམ་པ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The Blessed One was dwelling at the Kūṭāgāraśālā in the forest outside of Vaiśālī together with a great assembly of one thousand monks.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.97.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཟག་པ་ཟད་པ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>All of them were worthy ones whose defilements were exhausted.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.97.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཉོན་མོངས་པ་མེད་པ། དབང་དང་ལྡན་པར་གྱུར་པ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They were without afflictions and in control.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.97.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སེམས་ཤིན་ཏུ་རྣམ་པར་གྲོལ་བ། ཤེས་རབ་ཤིན་ཏུ་རྣམ་པར་གྲོལ་བ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Their minds were perfectly free, and their insight was perfectly liberated.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.97.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཅང་ཤེས་པ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They were of noble birth.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.97.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གླང་པོ་ཆེན་པོ། བྱ་བ་བྱས་པ། བྱེད་པ་བྱས་པ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They were great elephants who had completed their objectives and done what must be done.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.97.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཁུར་བོར་བ། བདག་གི་དོན་རྗེས་སུ་ཐོབ་པ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They had laid down their burdens and fulfilled their aims.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.97.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྲིད་པར་ཀུན་ཏུ་སྦྱོར་བ་ཡོངས་སུ་ཟད་པ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They had eliminated that which binds to existence.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.97.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡང་དག་པའི་ཤེས་པས་སེམས་ཤིན་ཏུ་རྣམ་པར་གྲོལ་བ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Their minds had been perfectly liberated by correct knowledge.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.97.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སེམས་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱི་དབང་གི་དམ་པའི་ཕ་རོལ་ཏུ་སོན་པ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They had obtained supreme perfection in mastering all mental states.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.97.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྤྱོད་ལམ་ཞི་བ་དང་། དུལ་བ་དང་། རྣམ་པར་གྲོལ་བ་དང་། མ་བརྟགས་པ་དང་ལྡན་པ་ཤ་སྟག་ལ་འདི་ལྟ་སྟེ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Their behavior was peaceful, disciplined, free, and natural.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.97.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཚེ་དང་ལྡན་པ་ཀུན་དགའ་བོ་གང་ཟག་གཅིག་ནི་མ་གཏོགས་ཏེ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The only exception was Venerable Ānanda,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.97.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ཡང་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་ཉམས་སུ་ལེན་པར་བཀའ་སྩལ་ཏེ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>but the Blessed One had instructed him in the practice as well, and</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.97.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཚེ་འདི་ཉིད་ལ་ལུང་བསྟན་པ་དང་། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>he had been prophesied to become a worthy one in this life.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.97.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སྟོང་ཐམ་པ་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱང་ཕྱིར་མི་ལྡོག་པ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-061-004-18"/>Also present were one thousand bodhisattvas. All of them had attained the stage free from regression.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.97.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱང་གཟུངས་ཐོབ་པ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>All of them had obtained retention.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.97.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱང་མཉམ་པ་ཉིད་ཀྱི་བཟོད་པ་དང་ལྡན་པ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>All of them possessed the patience of equanimity.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.97.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱང་ཇི་སྐད་སྨྲས་པ་དེ་བཞིན་དུ་བྱེད་པའི་ས་ཐོབ་པ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>All of them had reached the stage where one practices exactly what has been proclaimed.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.97.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མཁས་པ། དྲང་པོ། དད་པ་དང་ལྡན་པ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They were wise, honest, and faithful.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.97.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྟོག་པ་མང་བ། དང་བ་གཙོ་བོར་བྱེད་པ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They were extremely confident and exceedingly graceful.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.97.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཞིན་འཛུམ་པ། ཁྲོ་གཉེར་མེད་པ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They always smiled and never frowned angrily.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.97.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཡོ་མེད་པ། བསྒྲུབ་པ་དང་ལྡན་པ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They were steadfast and successful.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.97.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱི་རང་བཞིན་རྗེས་སུ་རྟོགས་པ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They had realized the nature of phenomena</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.97.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཆོས་བསྟན་པས་ཡོངས་སུ་མི་སྐྱོ་བ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>and never tired of teaching the Dharma.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.97.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱི་ཡེ་ཤེས་ཡང་དག་པར་སྐྱེས་པ་ཡོངས་སུ་སྨིན་པར་བྱེད་པ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They had encountered the wisdom of a buddha and were bringing it to full maturity.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.97.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལྡེམ་པོ་དག་ལ་ཕྱིན་ཅི་མ་ལོག་པའི་བཟོད་པ་དང་ལྡན་པ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They possessed unerring patience regarding allusive speech.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.97.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡུལ་ཐམས་ཅད་ཕྱིན་ཅི་མ་ལོག་པའི་ས་དང་ལྡན་པ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They had attained the stage of being unmistaken regarding all objects.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.97.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དུས་ཤེས་པ། ཚོད་ཤེས་པ། སྐབས་ཤེས་པ། རན་པ་ཤེས་པ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They knew the right time, season, occasion, and moment.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.97.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྒོད་པ་མེད་པ། ཁེངས་པ་མེད་པ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They were free from agitation and arrogance.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.97.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྤྱོད་ལམ་ཐ་མལ་པ་ཕུན་སུམ་ཚོགས་པ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Their behavior was natural and perfect.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.97.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྟོང་པ་ཉིད་ཀྱི་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་ལ་མཁས་པ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They were skilled in the meditative absorption on emptiness.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.97.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འབྱུང་བ་དང་འཇིག་པ་ཡོངས་སུ་སྤངས་པ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They had relinquished arising and disintegration.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.97.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྨོན་པ་མེད་པའི་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་དང་ལྡན་པ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They possessed the meditative absorption on wishlessness.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.97.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཁོར་བ་ལ་ཡུན་རིང་དུ་སྤྱོད་པ་ལ་ཞུགས་པ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They had practiced bodhisattva conduct in cyclic existence for a long time.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.97.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མཚན་མ་མེད་པའི་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་དང་ལྡན་པ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They possessed the meditative absorption on signlessness.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.97.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྤྲོས་པའི་རྣམ་པ་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱི་<tei:ref folio="F.97.b"/>མཚན་མ་ལེགས་པར་བཟུང་བ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They correctly understood the characteristics of all the content of mental constructs. </seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.97.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སེམས་ཅན་ཡོངས་སུ་སྨིན་པར་བྱ་བ་ལ་མཁས་པ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They were skilled in maturing beings.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.97.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདུ་ཤེས་ཐམས་ཅད་དང་བྲལ་བ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They were free from ideation.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.97.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཉན་ཐོས་ཀྱི་ཐེག་པ་རྣམ་པར་གཞག་པ་ལ་མཁས་པ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They were skilled in the presentation of the Hearer Vehicle.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.97.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཆོས་བསྟན་པ་ཡང་དག་པར་དབྱེ་བར་འཇུག་པར་བྱེད་པ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They engaged in properly distinguishing the teachings of the Dharma.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.97.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རང་སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱི་ཐེག་པ་སྟོན་པ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They taught the Solitary Buddha Vehicle.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.97.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཉེ་བར་ཞི་བའི་བསྔགས་པ་བརྗོད་པ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They praised tranquility.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.97.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཡང་དག་པར་སློང་བ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They inspired beings to become bodhisattvas.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.97.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྤྱོད་པ་ཇི་ལྟ་བ་བཞིན་དུ་ཞེ་འགྲས་པ་མེད་པར་ཆོས་སྟོན་པ་ཤ་སྟག་ལ་འདི་ལྟ་སྟེ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They behaved appropriately, teaching the Dharma without hatred or animosity.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.97.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོ་བྱམས་པ་དང་། འཇམ་དཔལ་གཞོན་ནུར་གྱུར་པ་དང་། སྤོབས་པ་བརྩེགས་པ་དང་། ལག་ན་རིན་ཆེན་ལྡན་དང་། སྤོས་འོད་དང་། མཐའ་ཡས་སྣང་བའི་བློ་གྲོས་དང་། ངན་སོང་སྤོང་དང་། དོན་གྲུབ་སེམས་པ་དང་། ཡོན་ཏན་རྒྱལ་པོ་སྣང་དང་། མྱ་ངན་གྱི་མུན་པ་ཐམས་ཅད་སེལ་བའི་བློ་གྲོས་དང་། མི་མཉམ་པ་ཐམས་ཅད་སྟོན་པ་དང་། དེའི་རང་བཞིན་དུ་མི་གནས་པ་དང་། བློ་མཐའ་ཡས་དང་། བརྩོན་འགྲུས་དང་། རྩལ་བརྟན་པོར་སེམས་པ་དང་། རིན་ཆེན་འབྱུང་གནས་དང་། བཀོད་པའི་རྒྱལ་པོ་དང་། རྣམ་པར་འཕྲུལ་པའི་རྒྱལ་པོ་དང་། འཁྲུལ་པ་མེད་པའི་མཐུ་རྩལ་དང་། ཁྱད་པར་བློ་གྲོས་དང་། ཀུན་ནས་མཛེས་དང་། སྒྲིབ་མེད་སྟོན་དང་། རྣམ་པར་རྩེ་དང་། གསེར་མཆོག་འོད་དཔལ་དང་། ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་ལ་རྟག་ཏུ་ལྟ་བའི་བློ་ལྡན་དང་། སྤོས་དྲི་མྱུར་སྦྱིན་མེ་ཏོག་ཀུན་ཏུ་རྒྱས་དང་། གཙོ་བོ་བརྩེགས་དང་། མྱ་ངན་མེད་པའི་དཔལ་དང་། ལྷུན་པོའི་ལྟོ་དང་། སྤྱན་རས་གཟིགས་དབང་ཕྱུག་དང་། སྤོས་ཀྱི་དབང་ཕྱུག་རྒྱལ་པོ་དང་། མཆོག་ཏུ་དགའ་བའི་རྒྱལ་པོ་དང་། བློ་མཐའ་ཡས་སྒྲུབ་པ་དང་། དམ་པའི་ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་མི་བརྗེད་པར་གནས་པ་དང་། བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོ་སེང་གེ་ལྟར་སྒྲ་མངོན་པར་སྒྲོགས་པ་དང་། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-061-004-19"/>Among them were the bodhisattva great being Maitreya, Mañjuśrī­kumāra­bhūta, Pratibhānakūṭa, Ratnapāṇi, Gandhaprabha, Ananta­prabhāsamati, Apāyajaha, Siddhārtha­cintin, Guṇa­rāja­prabhāsa, Sarva­śokāndha­kārāpoha­mati, Sarva­viṣamadarśin, Tat­svabhāvā­pratiṣṭhita, Anantamati, Vīrya, Vikrama­saṃdarśa­kacintin, Ratnākara, Vyūharāja, Vikurvāṇarāja, Avyabhicāra­prabhāva, Viśeṣamati, Samanta­prāsādika, Anāvaraṇa­darśin, Vikrīḍamāna, Suvarṇottama­prabhā­śrī, Sarva­dharma­nityadarśana­dhīmat, Āśugandhadāna­kusumita, Jyeṣṭhakūṭa, Aśokaśrī, Merudāra, Avalokiteśvara, Gandheśvara­rāja, Prāmodyarāja, Ananta­mati­pratipatti, Sarvasa­ddharmā­vismaraṇasthita,<tei:note xml:id="UT22084-061-004-20"/> and the bodhisattva great being Siṃha­nādābhinādin.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.97.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་དག་དང་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སྟོང་ཕྲག་མང་པོ་གཞན་དག་དང་ཡང་ཐབས་ཅིག་ཏུ་བཞུགས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Also dwelling with them were many thousands of other bodhisattvas.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.97.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་སྔ་དྲོའི་དུས་ཀྱི་ཚེ་ཤམ་ཐབས་དང་ཆོས་གོས་གསོལ་ཏེ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-061-004-21"/>One morning the Blessed One donned his lower and upper robes,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.98.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལྷུང་བཟེད་བསྣམས་<tei:ref folio="F.98.a"/>ནས་དགེ་སློང་ཉིས་སྟོང་གིས་བསྐོར་ཅིང་མདུན་དུ་བདར་ཏེ་ཡངས་པའི་གྲོང་ཁྱེར་ཆེན་པོར་བསོད་སྙོམས་ལ་གཤེགས་ནས། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>took up his alms bowl, and went to collect alms in the city of Vaiśālī accompanied and attended by two thousand monks.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.98.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་ཞབས་སྒོའི་ཐེམ་པ་ལ་བཞག་མ་ཐག་ཏུ་སངས་རྒྱས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་རྣམས་གྲོང་ཁྱེར་དུ་གཤེགས་པ་ན་ངོ་མཚར་རྨད་དུ་བྱུང་བའི་ཆོས་རྣམས་འབྱུང་བར་འགྱུར་བ་གང་དག་ཡིན་པ་དེ་དག་བྱུང་སྟེ</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>As soon as the Blessed One placed his foot at the threshold of the city gates, the following wondrous miracles occurred, miracles that occur whenever the blessed buddhas enter a city:</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.98.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལོང་བ་རྣམས་ནི་མཐོང་བར་གྱུར། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>blind people gained sight,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.98.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འོན་པ་རྣམས་ནི་ཐོས་པར་གྱུར། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>deaf people gained hearing,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.98.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྨྱོན་པ་རྣམས་ནི་དྲན་པ་རྙེད་པར་གྱུར་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>and the insane regained their senses.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.98.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལྷའི་མེ་ཏོག་གི་ཆར་ཡང་བབ་བོ། །སྣང་བ་ཆེན་པོ་ཡང་བྱུང་ངོ་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>A rain of divine flowers fell, a bright light shone,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.98.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྲང་ཡང་དྲི་མ་མེད་པར་གྱུར་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>and the roads became free of filth.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.98.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལྷའི་སིལ་སྙན་ཡིད་དུ་འོང་བ་དག་ཀྱང་མ་བརྡུངས་པར་གྲག་གོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The enchanting musical instruments of the gods resounded even without being played.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.98.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མནར་མེད་པའི་སེམས་ཅན་དམྱལ་བ་ལ་ཐུག་པ་ནས་འོག་མིན་གྱི་གནས་མན་ཆད་ཀྱི་སེམས་ཅན་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱང་གཅིག་ཏུ་ངེས་པར་བདེ་བ་དང་ལྡན་པར་གྱུར་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>All beings, from the Hell of Uninterrupted Torment up to the Highest Heaven, became completely happy.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.98.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེའི་ཚེ་ཡངས་པའི་གྲོང་ཁྱེར་ཆེན་པོ་ན་ལིཙྪ་བཱི་སེང་གེའི་བུ་རིན་ཆེན་བྱིན་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་སྐྱེས་ནས་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-061-004-22"/>At that time in the city of Vaiśālī there was a boy named Ratnadatta who had been born as the son of a Licchavi man named Siṃha.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.98.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལོ་གསུམ་ལོན་པ་མ་མའི་པང་པ་ན་འདུག་པ་ཁང་བཟངས་ཀྱིས་བརྒྱན་པའི་ཁང་བཟངས་ཀྱི་སྟེང་ན་འདུག་སྟེ</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The three-year-old was sitting on his mother’s lap on the top floor of their house, and</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.98.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཁྱེའུ་རིན་ཆེན་བྱིན་གྱིས་རྨད་དུ་བྱུང་བའི་མཚན་མ་དག་མཐོང་ངོ་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>when he witnessed these miraculous signs,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.98.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་ཁྱེའུ་རིན་ཆེན་བྱིན་གྱིས་རང་གི་མ་མ་ལ་ཚིགས་སུ་བཅད་དེ་སྨྲས་པ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>the boy Ratnadatta spoke the following verses to his mother:</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.98.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མ་མ་གང་གི་མཐུ་སྟོབས་ཀྱིས། །ཤིན་ཏུ་ཡ་མཚན་བྱུང་བ་སྣང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-061-004-23"/>“Mother, whose magical power Has manifested these extraordinary miracles?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.98.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཉི་མ་བྱེ་བ་རྣམས་ཀྱི་འོད། །ཟིལ་གནོན་སྣང་འདི་སུ་ཞིག་ཡིན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>This light outshines the radiance Of millions of suns. Whose is it?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.98.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྟོང་གསུམ་ས་གཞི་ཁྱབ་གྱུར་ནས། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-061-004-24"/>“It pervades the ground of the three-thousand-fold world</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.98.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ངན་འགྲོ་སྐེམས་པར་བྱེད་པ་ཡི། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>And dries up the lower realms.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.98.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྫུ་འཕྲུལ་སྣང་བ་གང་ཡིན་འདི། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>What is this magical light?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.98.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མ་མ་བདག་ལ་མྱུར་དུ་སྨྲོས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Quick, Mother, please tell me!</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.98.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དུས་མིན་མེ་ཏོག་ཆར་པ་ཡིས། །སངས་རྒྱས་ཞིང་མཚམས་མེད་པར་མཛེས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-061-004-25"/>“A rain of unseasonable flowers Continually beautifies this buddha realm,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.98.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཕྱོགས་རྣམས་བྱ་ཡི་ཚོགས་རྣམས་ཀྱིས། །སྐད་སྙན་པས་ནི་ཁྱབ་པར་གྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>And everywhere flocks of birds Fill the air with song.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.98.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྲང་ཡང་མེ་ཏོག་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་ཁེབས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-061-004-26"/>“The roads are covered with flowers,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.98.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མེ་ཏོག་གདུགས་ཀྱང་རྣམ་པར་བྲེས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The flower parasols unfurled,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.98.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྐྱེས་པ་བུད་མེད་དགའ་རྣམས་ཀྱིས། །ཀུན་ནས་རབ་ཏུ་མཛེས་པར་འདུག །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>And both sides are adorned With happy men and women.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.98.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལོང་བ་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་མིག་ཀྱང་ཐོབ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-061-004-27"/>“Blind people have gained sight,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.98.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྐྱེ་བོ་འོན་རྣམས་སྒྲ་ཡང་ཐོས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Deaf people can hear sounds,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.98.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱད་ངན་བྱད་གཟུགས་ཕུན་སུམ་ཚོགས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Those who were ugly are now handsome,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.98.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མདོག་ངན་ཁ་དོག་ཕུན་སུམ་ཚོགས། །<tei:ref folio="F.98.b"/>
                </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Those of poor complexion now have perfect skin, </seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.98.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཡེངས་པ་རྣམས་ཀྱང་དྲན་པ་རྙེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-061-004-28"/>“The bewildered have regained their senses,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.98.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལྕེ་མེད་ཚིག་ནི་རྣམ་པར་དག །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The mute can speak clearly,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.98.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སེམས་ཅན་བྱམས་པའི་སེམས་མེད་པ། །བྱམས་པའི་སེམས་དང་ལྡན་པར་གྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>And beings who had no love in their hearts Are now filled with love.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.98.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མ་མ་སེམས་ཅན་ཁྱད་པར་ཅན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-061-004-29"/>“Quick, Mother, tell me,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.98.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྫུ་འཕྲུལ་གྲུབ་པ་མཐུ་ལྡན་པ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Who is this extraordinary being</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.98.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇིག་རྟེན་དག་ན་རྒྱུ་བ་འདི། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Who moves throughout the worlds</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.98.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སུ་ཡིན་བདག་ལ་མྱུར་དུ་སྨྲོས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>With the power to perform such miracles?”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.98.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་ཁྱེའུ་རིན་ཆེན་བྱིན་གྱི་མ་མས་ཁྱེའུ་རིན་ཆེན་བྱིན་ལ་ཚིགས་སུ་བཅད་དེ་སྨྲས་པ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-061-004-30"/>Ratnadatta’s mother answered him in the following verses:</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.98.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྣམ་པར་དག་པ་སྤྱོད་མཆོག་ལྡན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-061-004-31"/>“He is a pure being with supreme conduct,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.98.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྒྱལ་བ་དྲི་མེད་བློ་མི་དམན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>A stainless victor without harmful intent</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.98.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བསམ་ཡས་མ་ལུས་ཡོངས་སུ་དག །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Who is beyond thought and utterly pure.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.98.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དབང་ལྡན་ཡོན་ཏན་རིན་ཆེན་འཕགས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He is powerful, exalted in precious virtues.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.98.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇིག་རྟེན་མགོན་པོ་འཁྲ་ས་མིག །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-061-004-32"/>“He is the world’s protector, refuge, and guide.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.98.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་རྩ་ལག་འདི། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>This is our kinsman, the Thus-Gone One,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.98.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བློ་ལྡན་བསོད་སྙོམས་དོན་དུ་གཤེགས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>A wise man come to beg alms</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.98.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇིག་རྟེན་ཆོས་ལ་རྟེན་པ་མེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Who does not adhere to worldly duty.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.98.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདི་ལ་སྡུག་དང་མི་སྡུག་སོགས། །འཇིག་རྟེན་པ་ཡི་རྟོག་མི་མངའ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-061-004-33"/>“He does not entertain mundane thoughts Such as pleasant or unpleasant.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.98.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>པད་མ་ཆུ་ལས་སྐྱེས་པ་ལྟར། །མངའ་བདག་མི་གོས་སྤྱོད་པར་མཛད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The lord engages in conduct without being stained, Like a lotus born from the water.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.98.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བློ་གྲོས་ལྡན་པ་ཐེ་ཙོམ་གཅོད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-061-004-34"/>“This intelligent one eliminates doubt.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.98.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཕན་མཛད་ཐུགས་རྗེར་ལྡན་པ་སྟེ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He benefits beings and is compassionate.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.98.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འགྲོ་བའི་སྡུག་བསྔལ་བསལ་བའི་ཕྱིར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>To dispel the suffering of beings.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.98.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྣམ་པར་འདྲེན་པ་འདིར་གཤེགས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Now this leader has come here</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.98.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བསྟོད་ཀྱང་དགྱེས་པར་མི་འགྱུར་ལ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-061-004-35"/>“Praise does not delight him,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.98.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྨད་ཀྱང་འཁྲུག་པར་མི་འགྱུར་ཏེ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>And blame does not upset him.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.98.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཁོང་ཁྲོ་རྗེས་སུ་ཆགས་པ་སྤངས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He has abandoned anger and attachment</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.98.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཆགས་མེད་རྒྱུ་བ་རླུང་དང་འདྲ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>And moves freely, like the wind.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.98.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདི་ནི་ཆོས་རྒྱལ་དམ་པ་སྟེ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-061-004-36"/>“He is a sublime dharma king</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.98.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡེ་ཤེས་ཟབ་མོ་ཕུན་སུམ་ཚོགས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Who has mastered profound wisdom</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.98.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དོན་དམ་དོན་ལ་མཁས་པ་པོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>And is learned in the ultimate meaning—</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.98.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འགྲོ་བའི་སློབ་དཔོན་གཤེགས་པ་ཡིན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The teacher of beings has come.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.98.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནི་དབུ་མ་སྟོན་པ་སྟེ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-061-004-37"/>“He teaches the middle way</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.98.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡོད་མེད་འཛིན་ལས་རྣམ་པར་གྲོལ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>That is free from grasping at existence or nonexistence.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.98.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཆོས་ལམ་ལྡན་ཞིང་ཞི་བ་སྟེ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He possesses the path of Dharma and is peaceful.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.98.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བརྟེན་པ་ཐམས་ཅད་ཡོངས་སུ་སྤངས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He has abandoned all types of dependence.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.98.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡེ་ཤེས་ཕུང་པོ་བདག་མེད་བདག །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-061-004-38"/>“The one for whom wisdom is the aggregates’ lack of self,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.98.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བསོད་ནམས་ཚོགས་རྣམས་བསྩགས་པ་ཡི། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Who has gathered the accumulation of merit,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.98.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བདེ་གཤེགས་འཇིག་རྟེན་འདྲེན་པ་པོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The blissful one, the guide of the world</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.98.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མཐའ་ཡས་གཟུགས་ཅན་དེང་གཤེགས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Whose form is boundless, has come today!</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.98.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དབུ་སྐྲ་གཡས་སུ་འཁྱིལ་པར་གནས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-061-004-39"/>“His hair is coiled to the right</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.98.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་ཞིང་མདོག་སྣུམ་ལྕང་ལོ་ཅན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>And is soft, shiny, and curly.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.98.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གནག་ཅིང་འཛིངས་པ་མེད་རྣམས་ཀྱིས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>It is black, not matted,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.98.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ཡི་དབུ་ནི་རྣམ་པར་མཛེས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>And perfectly adorns his head.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.98.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཙུག་ཏོར་གཡས་སུ་འཁྱིལ་པ་སྟེ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-061-004-40"/>“His crown protuberance circles to the right,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.98.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དབུ་སྐྲ་འཁྱིལ་ཞིང་ལེགས་པར་གནས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Its hair is coiled, and it is perfectly placed.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.98.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རི་རབ་རྩེ་མོ་འདྲ་བར་ནི། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>It resembles the peak of Mt. Meru—</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.99.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ཡི་དབྱིབས་ནི་མཛེས་<tei:ref folio="F.99.a"/>པ་ཡིན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>So beautiful is its shape. </seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.99.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ཡི་སྨིན་མཚམས་མཛོད་སྤུ་མཛེས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-061-004-41"/>“The middle of his brow is adorned with a curled hair</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.99.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་ཞིང་གཡས་སུ་འཁྱིལ་བ་སྟེ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>That is smooth and turns to the right.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.99.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འོད་ནི་ཤེལ་དང་ཟླ་བ་ཡི། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Its radiance is far brighter than a lattice</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.99.a</prop>
            <prop type="alternative-source"/>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འོད་ཟེར་དྲ་བ་མང་བས་ལྷག །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Of pure crystal lunar rays.<tei:note xml:id="UT22084-061-004-42"/>
                </seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.99.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ཡི་ཞལ་ནས་སྤྱན་མཛེས་པ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-061-004-43"/>“His eyes are beautiful</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.99.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མེ་ཏོག་ཨུཏ་པལ་སྔོན་པོ་འདྲ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Like blue lotus flowers.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.99.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བ་ཡི་རྫི་མ་ཡོངས་སུ་དག །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He has perfect eyelashes like a cow.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.99.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མི་དམར་མ་འཛིངས་ཞི་བར་གཟིགས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He has a peaceful gaze without redness or agitation.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.99.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དཔལ་ལྡན་སེང་གེའི་འགྲམ་པ་འདྲ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-061-004-44"/>“He has a jaw like a glorious lion,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.99.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནི་རྟག་ཏུ་ཞལ་ཡང་འཛུམ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>And he always has a smile on his face.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.99.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྒྲོས་ནི་བིམ་པ་བཞིན་དུ་དམར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>His lips are red like a bimba fruit,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.99.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཞལ་མཛེས་ལུས་ཅན་ཀུན་འདྲེན་པ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>His beautiful face attracts all embodied beings.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.99.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མཐུ་སྟོབས་ཆེན་པོ་ཕུན་སུམ་ཚོགས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-061-004-46"/>“He has an abundance of great power and strength,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.99.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བསོད་ནམས་བརྒྱ་ཡི་སྟོབས་མངའ་བ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The strength of hundreds of merits.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.99.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཚེམས་ཀྱི་ཕྲེང་བ་སྤ་བའི་འོད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The rows of his teeth have a beautiful shine,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.99.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྙོམས་ཤིང་ཐགས་བཟང་ཡོངས་སུ་དག །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>And they are even and perfectly spaced.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.99.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ཡི་ཚེམས་ནི་ཤིན་ཏུ་དཀར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-061-004-47"/>“His teeth are pure white.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.99.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལྗགས་ནི་ཤིན་ཏུ་རིང་ཞིང་སྲབ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>His tongue is very long and thin,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.99.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བདག་ཉིད་ཀྱི་ནི་ཞལ་གྱི་ངོས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>And with it he can completely cover</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.99.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ཡིས་ཀུན་ཏུ་ཁྱབ་པར་གནས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The surface of his own face.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.99.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དཔལ་ལྡན་དབུ་ནི་གདུགས་དང་འདྲ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-061-004-48"/>“The head of the glorious one is like a parasol.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.99.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་བཞིན་དེ་ནི་ཤངས་ཀྱང་མཐོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Likewise, his nose is prominent,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.99.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མདོག་ནི་བཙོ་མའི་གསེར་དང་འདྲ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>His complexion is like refined gold,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.99.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ཡི་ཞལ་གྱི་འཕྲལ་བ་མཛེས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>And he has a beautiful forehead.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.99.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ཡི་ཞལ་གྱི་སྨིན་ཚུགས་ནི། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-061-004-49"/>“His eyebrows are very pleasant</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.99.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཁ་དོག་མཐོན་མཐིང་ཤིན་ཏུ་སྡུག །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>And the color of blue sapphire.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.99.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཞི་བའི་སྤྱན་ནི་མཛེས་པ་སྟེ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>His peaceful eyes are beautiful</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.99.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྙན་གྱི་དྲུང་དུ་ཐུག་པར་གནས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>And extend toward his ears.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.99.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྙན་ཤལ་རིང་ལ་རབ་ཏུ་འཕྱང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-061-004-50"/>“His earlobes are long and dangling.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.99.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཞལ་མཛེས་སྟོན་གྱི་ཟླ་བས་ལྷག །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>His face is more beautiful than an autumn moon</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.99.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཞལ་རས་པད་མ་རྣམ་དག་འདྲ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>And resembles a perfectly pure lotus.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.99.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཞལ་མདངས་དཀར་ལ་དང་ཞིང་གསལ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>It is radiant, pure, and clear.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.99.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བརྟན་པོ་ཚངས་པའི་སྒྲ་སྐད་ལྡན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-061-004-51"/>“His speech is steady and eloquent,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.99.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་གསུང་ཀ་ལ་པིང་ཀའི་འདྲ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>And his voice is kind, pleasing,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.99.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ཡི་གསུང་བཟང་ཡིད་དུ་འོང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>And soft; it satisfies beings</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.99.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་ཞིང་སེམས་ཅན་ཚིམ་པར་བྱེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Like the call of a sparrow.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.99.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྨ་བྱ་ངང་པ་མིའམ་ཅི། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-061-004-52"/>“The sound of a peacock, A swan, a kinnara,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.99.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ནེ་ཙོ་རི་སྐེགས་ཁུ་བྱུག་དང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>A parrot, a myna, and a cuckoo,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.99.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འབྲུག་སྒྲ་ཁྲུང་ཁྲུང་ཀུ་ན་ལ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Of thunder, a crane,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.99.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཤང་ཤང་ཏེའུ་དང་གླིང་བུ་དང་། །རྫ་རྔའི་སྒྲ་དང་གཞན་དག་ཀྱང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-061-004-53"/>“A pheasant, a flute, the beat Of a clay drum; and anything else,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.99.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྒྲ་སྐད་སྙན་པ་ཅི་ཡང་རུང་། །དེ་དག་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་ཡི། །གསུང་གི་བཅུ་དྲུག་ཆར་མི་ཕོད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>However pleasant, does not match a sixteenth Of the voice of the Thus-Gone One.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.99.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྐུལ་མཛད་དེ་བཞིན་མཉེན་པ་སྟེ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-061-004-54"/>“It is inspiring, yet soft.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.99.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནི་སྙན་ཅིང་འཇམ་པ་དང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>It is sweet and gentle,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.99.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡིད་འོང་དགའ་བྱེད་གསལ་བ་སྟེ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Endearing, pleasing, and clear.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.99.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྐྱོན་དང་བྲལ་ཞིང་འཇིགས་པ་མེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>It is flawless and fearless.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.99.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རེ་བ་རྣམས་ལ་ཆར་རྒྱུན་ལྟར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-061-004-55"/>“Like a steady rain for the hopeful,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.99.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སེམས་རྒྱུན་ཚིམ་པར་བྱེད་ལ་ཞི། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>It satisfies and pacifies the mind.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.99.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མ་ཉམས་མ་འཁྲུལ་རབ་ཏུ་ཞི། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>It is uncorrupted, unmistaken, perfectly peaceful,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.99.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་བཞིན་དག་ཅིང་བརྡ་ཕྲད་སླ། །<tei:ref folio="F.99.b"/>
                </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Pure, and also easy to comprehend. </seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.99.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྐལ་དང་ལྡན་ཞིང་སྙན་པར་ལྡན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-061-004-56"/>“It is auspicious, sweet,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.99.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དོན་དང་ཡོན་ཏན་ཐམས་ཅད་ཚོགས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Meaningful, and possesses all good qualities.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.99.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གསུང་གི་རྒྱན་རྣམས་ཕུན་སུམ་ཚོགས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>His poetic embellishments are perfect.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.99.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ཡི་གསུང་ནི་དགེ་སྐྱེད་པ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>His speech inspires virtue.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.99.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སེམས་ཅན་མོས་པ་ཐ་དད་དང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-061-004-57"/>“Beings with different inclinations And</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.99.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་བཞིན་ངེས་ཚིག་ཐ་དད་རྣམས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>different interpretations</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.99.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ཡི་གསུང་ལ་ངེས་པར་དད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Have faith in what he says</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.99.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡིད་ཀྱང་རབ་ཏུ་དགའ་བར་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>And become exceedingly happy.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.99.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེས་ནི་ཕྱོགས་བཅུའི་འཇིག་རྟེན་ཁམས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>In the world systems of the ten directions,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.99.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གནས་པའི་སེམས་ཅན་གསུང་གིས་ཁྱབ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-061-004-58"/>“His voice reaches all beings who abide</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.99.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མགོན་པོ་དེ་ཡི་གསུང་ཚིག་ནི། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>And the words of the protector</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.99.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སེམས་ཅན་རྣམས་ལ་དོན་ཡོད་འཇུག །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Are rendered meaningful to all those beings.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.99.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཐུབ་པ་སྐྱེས་མཆོག་དེ་ཡི་ནི། །མགུར་ཡང་དུང་འདྲ་དཔུང་མགོ་ཟླུམ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-061-004-59"/>“That sage, supreme among beings, Has a neck like a conch and round shoulders.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.99.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ཡི་ཐལ་གོང་རྒྱས་པ་སྟེ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He is broad chested,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.99.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནི་བདུན་པོ་མཐོ་བ་མངའ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>And the seven parts<tei:note xml:id="UT22084-061-004-60"/> of his body are prominent.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.99.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ཡི་ཕྱག་ཀྱང་རབ་ཏུ་རིང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-061-004-61"/>“His arms are very long,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.99.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>པགས་པ་གསེར་མདོག་འདྲ་བ་སྟེ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>His skin the color of gold.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.99.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གསེར་གྱི་སྡོང་པོ་བཞིན་དུ་མཐོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He is as tall as the wish-fulfilling tree,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.99.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ནྱ་གྲོ་ད་ལྟར་ཆུ་ཞེང་གབ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>His girth like a banyan.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.99.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཐུགས་ཀ་དཔལ་གྱི་བེའུས་བརྒྱན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-061-004-62"/>“His chest is adorned with the endless knot.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.99.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཁོར་ལོའི་མཚན་ཅན་པད་མའི་ཕྱག །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>His lotus hands bear the imprints of a wheel.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.99.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཤིང་བལ་འདབ་ལྟར་རེག་ན་འཇམ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They are soft to the touch like cotton or flower petals,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.99.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ཡི་ཕྱག་གི་སོར་མོ་རིང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>And their fingers are long.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.99.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྤུ་རྣམས་རེ་རེར་སྐྱེས་ཤིང་ཡར་ཕྱོགས་སྟུག་ལ་འཇམ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-061-004-63"/>“Each body hair is present, upright, thick, and soft.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.99.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྲང་གི་ཕེལ་ཀ་ཆེ་ལ་རབ་རྒྱས་ལྟེ་བ་ཟབ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>His torso is broad and his navel is deep.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.99.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཕྱལ་དབྱིབས་གཞུ་འདྲ་གླང་ཆེན་བཞིན་དུ་སྦུབས་སུ་ནུབ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>His belly is the shape of a bow, and his genitals are retracted in a sheath like an elephant.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.99.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྗེ་ངར་ཨེ་ནེ་ཡ་འདྲ་མདངས་དཀར་འདམ་བུའི་སྦུབས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He has calves like an antelope and with a white hue like the inside of a reed.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.99.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལོང་བུ་མི་མངོན་དེ་ཡི་རྟིང་པ་ལེགས་པར་གྲུབ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-061-004-64"/>“His ankle bones do not protrude, and his heels are well shaped.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.99.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་བཞིན་དྲང་སྲོང་སོར་མོ་རིང་ཞིང་སེན་མོ་དམར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The sage’s fingers are long and his nails are red.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.99.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བདེ་བར་གཤེགས་ཀྱི་ཞབས་ཀྱི་ལོང་བུ་མི་མངོན་ཏེ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The soles of the Blissful One’s feet are not arched,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.99.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཁོར་ལོ་ལྕགས་ཀྱུ་བཀྲ་ཤིས་ལྡན་དང་དུང་གིས་སྤྲས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>And they are adorned with wheels, hooks, svastikas, and conches.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.99.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མགོན་པོ་དེ་ཡི་ཞབས་གཉིས་མཉམ་ཞིང་ལེགས་གནས་དང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-061-004-65"/>“The Lord’s feet are of equal proportion and steady.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.99.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཤིང་བལ་བཞིན་དུ་རེག་ན་འཇམ་ཞིང་བཟང་བ་དང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They are soft and pleasing to the touch like cotton.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.99.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མེ་ཏོག་ཨུཏ་པལ་དམར་པོ་ལེགས་པར་སྐྱེས་པ་ཡི། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Their color is like a blooming red lotus,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.99.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཁ་དོག་འདྲ་བས་ས་གཞི་དག་ལ་གཤེགས་པར་མཛད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>And with them he traverses the worlds.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.99.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་སེང་གེའི་སྒྲ་སྒྲོགས་བདེ་སྦྱིན་པ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-061-004-66"/>“The lion’s roar of the Thus-Gone One bestows happiness.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.99.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འགྲོ་བ་རྣམས་ཀྱི་གཙོ་བོ་དེ་ནི་འདིར་གཤེགས་ཏེ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>This chief among beings has now arrived here,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.99.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡོང་གིས་འཇིགས་པ་མེད་པར་སེང་གེའི་སྒྲ་སྐད་ཀྱིས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>And the lack of mental constructs with the fearless roar of a lion.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.99.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཉིས་སུ་མེད་ཅིང་སྤྲོས་པ་མེད་པའི་ཆོས་ཀྱང་སྟོན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>And when he comes, he teaches the Dharma of nonduality</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.99.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་ཁྱེའུ་རིན་ཆེན་བྱིན་གྱིས་བདག་གི་མ་མ་ལ་འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་སྨྲས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-061-004-67"/>Then the boy Ratnadatta said to his mother, </seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.100.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མ་མ་བདག་<tei:ref folio="F.100.a"/>སྐར་ཁུང་འདིར་ཞོག་ཤིག་དང་། དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་བལྟའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Mother, put me in the window so I can see the Thus-Gone One,”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.100.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་མ་མ་དེས་ཁྱེའུ་རིན་ཆེན་བྱིན་སྐར་ཁུང་དུ་བཞག་གོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>so his mother sat him in the window.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.100.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་ཁྱེའུ་རིན་ཆེན་བྱིན་གྱི་སེམས་ཀྱི་ཡོངས་སུ་རྟོག་པ་ཐུགས་ཀྱིས་མཁྱེན་ནས་སྲང་དེ་ཁོ་ནར་གཤེགས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The Blessed One knew what Ratnadatta was thinking, so he walked right down his street.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.100.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཁྱེའུ་རིན་ཆེན་བྱིན་གྱིས་ཀྱང་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་གཤེགས་པ་མཐོང་ངོ་། །མཐོང་ནས་ཀྱང་དེ་འདི་སྙམ་དུ་སེམས་ཏེ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>When the boy saw the Blessed One walking he thought,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.100.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་དག་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་ཡོན་ཏན་ཐམས་ཅད་དང་ལྡན་པ་འདི་ལྟ་བུ་མཐོང་ནས་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Whoever sees the Thus-Gone One, who possesses all good qualities, and</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.100.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱང་ཆུབ་ཀྱི་སེམས་སྐྱེད་པར་མི་བྱེད་པ་དེ་དག་ནི་རྙེད་པ་ཉེས་པར་རྙེད་པའོ་སྙམ་མོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>does not generate the mind of awakening is indeed unfortunate.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.100.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཁྱེའུ་རིན་ཆེན་བྱིན་གྱི་སྒོ་དྲུང་དུ་གཤེགས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The Blessed One proceeded right up to Ratnadatta’s door</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.100.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་ཁྱེའུ་རིན་ཆེན་བྱིན་འདི་སྙམ་དུ་སེམས་ཏེ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>and the boy thought,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.100.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སེམས་ཅན་ཁྱད་པར་ཅན་འདི་ལྟ་བུ་ནི་བསྐལ་པ་བྱེ་བ་ཕྲག་འབུམ་དུ་ཡང་རྙེད་པར་དཀའ་བས། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Since it is difficult to meet such an extraordinary being even in a trillion eons,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.100.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཁང་བཟངས་འདི་ལས་བདག་གིས་མཆོང་བར་བྱའོ་སྙམ་མོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>I should jump down from this house.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.100.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་དེའི་ཚེ་ཁྱེའུ་རིན་ཆེན་བྱིན་གྱིས་རིལ་གྱིས་གསེར་ལས་བྱས་པའི་པད་མ་འདབ་མ་འབུམ་དང་ལྡན་པ་བརྩེན་པ་ལག་མཐིལ་དུ་ཁྱེར་རོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-061-004-68"/>With that thought, Ratnadatta placed his toy, a golden lotus with a hundred thousand petals, in the palm of his hand</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.100.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་ཁྱེའུ་རིན་ཆེན་བྱིན་གྱིས་ཁང་བཟངས་དེ་ལས་བདག་ཉིད་ཀྱིས་མཆོངས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>and [With that thought, Ratnadatta placed his toy, a golden lotus with a hundred thousand petals, in the palm of his hand and] jumped off the house.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.100.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱི་མཐུས་ནམ་མཁའ་བར་སྣང་ལ་འདུག་གོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>However, due to the Buddha’s power, he remained floating in midair.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.100.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་ཁྱེའུ་རིན་ཆེན་བྱིན་གྱིས་རིལ་གྱིས་གསེར་ལས་བྱས་པའི་པད་མ་འདབ་མ་འབུམ་དང་ལྡན་པ་དེ་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ལ་ཕུལ་ལོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Ratnadatta then offered the golden lotus with a hundred thousand petals to the Blessed One.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.100.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ཁྱེའུ་རིན་ཆེན་བྱིན་གྱི་ལག་ནས་བཏང་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་དབུའི་དྲང་ཐད་ཀྱི་སྟེང་གི་ནམ་མཁའ་བར་སྣང་ལ་པད་མའི་གདུགས་སུ་བྱས་ཏེ་རིན་པོ་ཆེའི་དྲ་བ་ཡང་བྲེས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>As soon as Ratnadatta let go of the lotus, the Blessed One transformed it into a lotus parasol adorned with a net of jewels, and it hovered in the sky directly above the Blessed One’s head.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.100.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་དེའི་ཚེ་ཁྱེའུ་རིན་ཆེན་བྱིན་གྱིས་ཚིགས་སུ་བཅད་པ་འདི་དག་སྨྲས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>When that happened, the boy Ratnadatta recited the following verses:</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.100.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སངས་རྒྱས་པད་མ་འདི་ཕུལ་བ། །བདག་ནི་ཅི་ཡང་མི་འཚལ་ཏེ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-061-004-69"/>“I offer this lotus to the Buddha Seeking nothing in return—</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.100.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དོན་རྣམས་ཐམས་ཅད་བཅད་སླད་དུ། །བདག་ནི་བྱང་ཆུབ་མཆོག་འཚལ་ལོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>To eliminate all goals. I seek supreme awakening</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.100.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཇི་ལྟར་བྱང་ཆུབ་མ་སྐྱེས་ལ། །ཐོབ་པ་མ་མཆིས་བཤིག་མ་མཆིས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-061-004-70"/>“Since in unborn awakening There is nothing to gain or lose</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.100.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བླང་དུ་མ་མཆིས་དོར་མ་མཆིས། །དེ་ལྟར་བདག་གིས་མེ་ཏོག་དབུལ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>And nothing to accept or reject, I offer this flower.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.100.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱིས་པ་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་དོན་གང་བརྟགས། །བརྟགས་པ་དེ་ནི་དོན་མ་མཆིས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>That childish beings construct is pointless. <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-061-004-71"/>“The conception of value</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.100.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྟོག་པ་<tei:ref folio="F.100.b"/>ཐམས་ཅད་བཅད་སླད་དུ། །གང་ཟག་མཆོག་ལ་བདག་མཆོད་བགྱིད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>So that I may eliminate all conceptual thought. I make this offering to the supreme human being</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.100.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ཕྱིར་མེ་ཏོག་ཕུལ་བ་འདི། །བདག་ལ་རྣམ་སྨིན་འབྲས་མ་གྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-061-004-72"/>“I do not offer this flower So that a result will ripen for me.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.100.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དངོས་པོ་ཐམས་ཅད་བཅད་སླད་དུ། །པད་མ་འདི་ནི་བདག་གིས་ཕུལ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>To eliminate all existent things. I offer this lotus blossom</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.100.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བདག་གི་སངས་རྒྱས་ཞིང་དུ་ནི། །རྒྱལ་མཆོག་ཐེག་པས་འགྲོ་མ་གཏོགས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-061-004-73"/>“In my buddha realm One will follow only the vehicle of the supreme victor—</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.100.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཉན་ཐོས་ཀྱི་ནི་མིང་ཡང་རུང་། །རང་རྒྱལ་མིང་ཡང་འབྱུང་མ་གྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>May even the names hearer or solitary buddha Not arise there.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.100.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་ཚེ་དང་ལྡན་པ་མཽད་གལ་གྱི་བུ་ཆེན་པོས་ཁྱེའུ་རིན་ཆེན་བྱིན་ལ་ཚིགས་སུ་བཅད་དེ་སྨྲས་པ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-061-004-74"/>Then, Venerable Mahā­maudgalyā­yana recited the following verse to the boy Ratnadatta:</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.100.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཁྱོད་ནི་སྟོན་པ་འདི་འདྲ་ལ། །དད་པས་མཆོད་པ་བྱེད་མོད་ཀྱི། །བློ་གྲོས་ཕྱིན་ཅི་ལོག་གྱུར་ནསངས་རྒྱས་སུ་ནི་ཇི་ལྟར་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-061-004-75"/>“Although you make this offering Out of faith in such a teacher, Your understanding is mistaken. How, then, will you become a buddha?”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.100.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་ཁྱེའུ་རིན་ཆེན་བྱིན་གྱིས་ཚེ་དང་ལྡན་པ་མཽད་གལ་གྱི་བུ་ཆེན་པོ་ལ་ཚིགས་སུ་བཅད་དེ་སྨྲས་པ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-061-004-76"/>Ratnadatta replied to Venerable Mahā­maudgalyā­yana with the following verses:</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.100.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདི་དག་ཐམས་ཅད་མ་སྐྱེས་ཏེ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-061-004-77"/>“All these entities are unborn.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.100.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདུས་བྱས་དག་ནི་གསོབ་དང་གསོག །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Conditioned things are hollow and void.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.100.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་འདྲ་བ་ཡི་ཆོས་རྣམས་ལ། །དངོས་པོར་འགྱུར་བ་ག་ལ་ཡོད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>How could such phenomena Have any substance?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.100.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཁྱོད་ནི་ཆོས་གོས་ངུར་སྨྲིག་བགོས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-061-004-78"/>“You wear saffron monastic robes</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.100.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དགྲ་བཅོམ་ཉིད་དུ་འཛིན་པར་བྱེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>And grasp at the state of a worthy one,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.100.b</prop>
            <prop type="alternative-source"/>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྣམ་ཤེས་འདི་དག་སྤྱོད་ཡུལ་ཡང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>But aren’t consciousness and<tei:note xml:id="UT22084-061-004-79"/> its domain</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.100.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྟོང་པ་ཁོ་ན་མ་ཡིན་ནམ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Simply empty?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.100.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དམིགས་པ་ལ་ནི་གནས་བཅས་པས། །སངས་རྒྱས་བྱེ་བ་མ་མཉེས་བྱས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-061-004-80"/>“The millions of buddhas are not pleased By having recourse to apprehension.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.100.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱེ་བ་དེ་ཡང་ཞི་བར་མཐོང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Those millions perceive only quiescence,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.100.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སུ་ཡང་མ་མཉེས་བྱས་པ་མེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>And there is not one of them who does not find joy in that.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.100.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མཽད་གལ་བུ་ལ་ད་དུང་ཡང་། །དམིགས་པ་འཇུག་པ་ཡོད་དམ་ཅི། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-061-004-81"/>“Maudgalyā­yana, do you still Engage in apprehension?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.100.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཁྱོད་ཀྱི་སེམས་ནི་གང་ཞིག་གིས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Can someone who thinks as you do</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.100.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡོན་ཡང་ཡོངས་སུ་སྦྱོང་བར་བྱེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Even purify a gift?”<tei:note xml:id="UT22084-061-004-82"/>
                </seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.100.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་ཚེ་དང་ལྡན་པ་མཽད་གལ་གྱི་བུ་ཆེན་པོས་ཁྱེའུ་རིན་ཆེན་བྱིན་ལ་འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་སྨྲས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-061-004-83"/>Venerable Mahā­maudgalyā­yana replied to Ratnadatta, saying,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.100.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཁྱེའུ་ཅི་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པས་བླ་ན་མེད་པ་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་བྱང་ཆུབ་མངོན་པར་རྫོགས་པར་སངས་མ་རྒྱས་སམ། ཆོས་ཀྱང་མ་བསྟན་ཏམ། ཁྱེའུ་རིན་ཆེན་བྱིན་གྱིས་སྨྲས་པ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Child, tell me, has the Thus-Gone One not become a complete buddha who has manifested unsurpassed and perfect awakening? Furthermore, has he not taught the Dharma?”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.100.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མཽད་གལ་གྱི་བུ་མཁས་པས་ནི་བྱང་ཆུབ་སྤྲོས་པར་མི་བྱའོ། །དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་ཡང་རློམ་སེམས་སུ་མི་བྱའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-061-004-84"/>“Maudgalyā­yana,” Ratnadatta replied, “a wise person should not conceptualize awakening or formulate opinions about the Thus-Gone One.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.100.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཆོས་མི་སྐྱེའོ་སྙམ་དུ་བརྟག་པར་མི་བྱའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They should not impute concepts such as the thought that phenomena do not arise,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.100.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་འདུས་བྱས་སོ་སྙམ་དུ་བརྟག་པར་མི་བྱའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>the thought that all phenomena are conditioned, or</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.100.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་འདུས་མ་བྱས་སོ་སྙམ་དུ་བརྟག་པར་མི་བྱའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>the thought that all phenomena are unconditioned.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.101.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་བཞིན་དུ་སྦྱར་ཏེ་ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་སྐྱེ་བ་དང་། མི་སྐྱེ་བ་དང་། <tei:ref folio="F.101.a"/>དངོས་པོ་དང་། དངོས་པོ་མེད་པ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་དང་། འཛིན་པ་དང་། གཏོང་བ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་དང་། ཕྲད་པ་དང་བྲལ་བ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་དང་། འགྲོ་བ་དང་། འོང་བ་དང་། གནས་པ་དང་། འཕོ་བ་དང་། འདོད་ཆགས་ཀྱི་ཆོས་དང་། ཞེ་སྡང་གི་ཆོས་དང་། གཏི་མུག་གི་ཆོས་དང་། ཆོས་དང་། ཆོས་མ་ཡིན་པ་ཞེས་བརྟག་པར་མི་བྱའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They should not impute concepts such as ‘all phenomena arise, do not arise, are existent, or are nonexistent,’ ‘grasping and letting go,’ ‘meeting and separating,’ ‘going, coming, remaining, transmigrating, phenomena associated with attachment, hatred, and delusion, and right and wrong.’<tei:note xml:id="UT22084-061-004-85"/>
                </seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.101.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མ་རིག་པ་ལ་སོགས་པ་ནས་སོ་སོའི་སྐྱེ་བོའི་ཆོས་རྣམས་དང་། ཉན་ཐོས་ཀྱི་ཆོས་རྣམས་དང་། རང་སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱི་ཆོས་རྣམས་དང་། སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱི་ཆོས་རྣམས་དང་། ཀུན་ནས་ཉོན་མོངས་པའི་ཆོས་རྣམས་དང་། རྣམ་པར་བྱང་བའི་ཆོས་རྣམས་དང་། གཟུགས་ཅན་དང་། གཟུགས་ཅན་མ་ཡིན་པ་དང་། འདུ་ཤེས་དང་། འདུ་ཤེས་མེད་པ་དང་། མཚན་ཉིད་དང་། མཚན་ཉིད་མེད་པ་དང་། སྤྱོད་པ་ཡོངས་སུ་དག་པ་དང་། མཉམ་པ་ཉིད་དང་། མི་མཉམ་པ་ཉིད་དང་། ལུས་དང་། སེམས་དང་། ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་ཚུལ་བཞིན་དང་། ཚུལ་བཞིན་མ་ཡིན་པ་ཞེས་བྱ་བའི་བར་དུ་སྐྱེ་བར་འགྱུར་རོ། །ཞེས་བརྟག་པར་མི་བྱའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They should not impute the concept that ‘ignorance and the like<tei:note xml:id="UT22084-061-004-86"/> up to and including the qualities of hearers, the qualities of solitary buddhas, the qualities of the buddhas, the factors of pollution, the factors of purification, the physical and nonphysical, perception and lack of perception, marks and lack of marks, pure conduct, sameness, difference, body, mind, and all correct and incorrect qualities arise.’</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.101.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མཽད་གལ་གྱི་བུ་འདི་ཇི་སྙམ་དུ་སེམས། དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་བླ་ན་མེད་པ་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་བྱང་ཆུབ་མངོན་པར་རྫོགས་པར་འཚང་རྒྱའམ། སྨྲས་པ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>So you tell me, Maudgalyā­yana—do you think the thus-gone ones are complete buddhas who manifest unsurpassed and perfect awakening?”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.101.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནི་མ་ཡིན་ནོ། །སྨྲས་པ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Maudgalyā­yana replied, “That is not the case.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.101.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཅི་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་དེ་བཞིན་ཉིད་ལ་མ་གཏོགས་པ་དང་། བྱང་ཆུབ་དེ་བཞིན་ཉིད་ལ་མ་གཏོགས་པ་དང་། སོ་སོའི་སྐྱེ་བོ་དེ་བཞིན་ཉིད་ལ་མ་གཏོགས་པར་འདོད་མ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-061-004-88"/>The boy said, “Do you assert that the thus-gone ones are not included in suchness, that awakening is not included in suchness, or that ordinary beings are not included in suchness?”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.101.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མཽད་གལ་གྱི་བུས་སྨྲས་པ། དེ་ནི་མ་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Maudgalyā­yana said, “That is not the case.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.101.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཁྱེའུས་སྨྲས་པ། མཽད་གལ་གྱི་བུ་ཁྱོད་སྤྲོས་པ་མེད་པ་ལ་སྤྲོས་པར་བྱེད་མ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-061-004-90"/>“Maudgalyā­yana,” the boy responded, “do you conceptualize the lack of conceptualization?”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.101.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མཽད་གལ་གྱི་བུས་སྨྲས་པ། ཁོ་བོ་ནི་འཇིག་རྟེན་གྱི་ཀུན་རྫོབ་ཀྱི་སྒོ་ནས་སྟོན་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“I teach by means of the conventions of the world,” Maudgalyā­yana replied.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.101.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཁྱེའུས་སྨྲས་པ། མཽད་གལ་གྱི་བུ་འཇིག་རྟེན་ནི་བརྫུན་པ། སླུ་བ་སྒྱུ་མའི་རྣམ་པ། བྱིས་པ་འདྲིད་པར་བྱེད་པའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-061-004-92"/>The boy continued, “Maudgalyā­yana, the world is a fake, deceptive, and illusory appearance that tricks childish beings.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.101.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མཽད་གལ་གྱི་བུས་སྨྲས་པ། གལ་ཏེ་འཇིག་རྟེན་འདི་བརྫུན་པ་སླུ་བའི་ཆོས་ཅན་ཡིན་པ་དང་བསྟན་པ་འདི་ཡང་བརྫུན་པ། སླུ་བའི་ཆོས་ཅན་ཡིན་ན་ཁྱོད་ཅིའི་ཕྱིར་སྟོན་པར་བྱེད། སྨྲས་པ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Maudgalyā­yana,” answered the boy, [the world is a fake, deceptive, and illusory appearance] "phenomena cannot be demonstrated. </seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.101.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མཽད་གལ་གྱི་བུ་ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་ནི་བསྟན་དུ་མེད་པ་སྟེ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-061-004-93"/>“If the world is a fake and deceptive phenomenon,” said Maudgalyā­yana, “then this teaching is also a fake and deceptive phenomenon. Why, then, do you teach it?”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.101.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>
                    <tei:ref folio="F.101.b"/>དེ་དག་ནི་བསྟན་པར་བྱ་བ་མ་ཡིན། ཐོབ་པར་བྱ་བ་མ་ཡིན། མངོན་སུམ་དུ་བྱ་བ་མ་ཡིན། སྤང་བར་བྱ་བ་མ་ཡིན། ཡོངས་སུ་ཤེས་པར་བྱ་བ་མ་ཡིན། བསྒོམ་པར་བྱ་བ་མ་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They cannot be demonstrated, attained, actualized, abandoned, understood, or meditated upon.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.101.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མཽད་གལ་གྱི་བུས་སྨྲས་པ། འོ་ན་ཁྱོད་ཀྱིས་གང་གི་དོན་དུ་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་མཆོད། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-061-004-95"/>Maudgalyā­yana replied, “If that is the case, what is the point of you making an offering to the Thus-Gone One?”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.101.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཁྱེའུས་སྨྲས་པ། མཽད་གལ་གྱི་བུ་ཁྱོད་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པའམ། སྦྱིན་པ་པོའམ། སྦྱིན་པར་དམིགས་སམ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Maudgalyā­yana,” the boy asked, “do you apprehend a Thus-Gone One, someone who gives a gift, or an act of giving?”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.101.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་ཚེ་དང་ལྡན་པ་མཽད་གལ་གྱི་བུ་ཅང་མི་སྨྲ་བར་གྱུར་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-061-004-97"/>Venerable Maudgalyā­yana remained silent,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.101.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཁྱེའུ་རིན་ཆེན་བྱིན་གྱིས་སྨྲས་པ། མཽད་གལ་གྱི་བུ་བདག་གིས་དེ་ལས་བསམས་ནས་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པར་འགྱུར་བ་ཡོངས་སུ་སྤངས་ཏེ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>so the boy Ratnadatta continued, “Maudgalyā­yana, with this in mind, I have given up becoming a thus-gone one and</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.101.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཉན་ཐོས་ཀྱི་ཐེག་པ་ལ་སེམས་སྐྱེད་པར་བྱེད་པ་གང་དག་ཡིན་པ་དེ་དག་ནི་རྙེད་པ་ཉེས་པར་རྙེད་པའོ་ཞེས་དེ་སྐད་ཀྱི་ཚིག་སྨྲས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>say those who form the resolve set on the vehicle of the hearers ‘are indeed unfortunate.’ ”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.101.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མཽད་གལ་གྱི་བུས་སྨྲས་པ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-061-004-98"/>Maudgalyā­yana replied,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.101.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཁྱོད་ནི་ན་ཚོད་ཤིན་ཏུ་གཞོན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-061-004-99"/>“You are very young,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.101.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཤེས་རབ་ཀྱིས་ནི་རྒྱ་མཚོ་བཞིན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Yet your insight is vast as the ocean.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.101.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཁྱོད་ཀྱིས་ཇི་སྲིད་ཙམ་ཞིག་ནས། །ཆོས་འདི་དག་ལ་བསླབས་པར་གྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>How long have you been Trained in these teachings?”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.101.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཁྱེའུ་རིན་ཆེན་བྱིན་གྱིས་སྨྲས་པ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-061-004-100"/>Ratnadatta replied with the following verses:</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.101.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བསླབ་པ་ཐམས་ཅད་རྣམ་འཇིག་པ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-061-004-101"/>“All training perishes.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.101.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བསླབ་པ་གང་ཡིན་དེ་བསླབ་མིན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Training is not training.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.101.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་ལ་བསླབ་པ་མེད་པ་དེ། །མཁས་པ་རྣམས་ཀྱི་བསླབ་པ་ཡིན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Consists in being one who lacks training. The training of the wise ones</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.101.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དོན་གང་ཁྱོད་ཀྱིས་བདག་དྲིས་པ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-061-004-102"/>“The question ‘what is the point?’ that you asked me</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.101.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སེམས་ཅན་འདུ་ཤེས་གནས་པ་སྟེ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Is based upon the perceptions of beings,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.101.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདིར་ནི་ཆོས་རྣམས་ཐམས་ཅད་ལ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Any phenomena arising anywhere.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.101.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་ལའང་སྐྱེ་བ་མི་རྙེད་དོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>And to this I say one does not find</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.101.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱིས་པ་རྣམས་ནི་བྱང་ཆུབ་དང་། །འཁོར་བ་ཉིད་དུ་རྟོག་པར་བྱེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-061-004-103"/>“Childish beings conceptualize Both awakening and cyclic existence.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.101.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདིར་ནི་ད་དུང་བཙུན་པ་ཁྱོད། །བྱིས་པའི་ཆོས་ལ་འབྲང་ངམ་ཅི། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>So do you, Venerable One, Still follow the way of childish beings?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.101.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རིང་པོའམ་ཡང་ན་ཐུང་ངུ་ཞེས། །མཁས་པ་དག་ནི་རྟོག་མི་བྱེད། །ཆོས་ཀུན་སྙིང་པོ་མེད་པར་ནི། །དེ་བཞིན་དེ་དག་ཁོང་དུ་ཆུད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-061-004-104"/>“Since they understand That all phenomena lack essence, The wise do not generate Concepts such as ‘near’ and ‘far.’</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.101.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱིས་པའམ་བྱིས་པའི་ཆོས་རྣམས་སམ། །སངས་རྒྱས་ཆོས་སམ་རྒྱལ་བའང་རུང་། །བློ་ལྡན་ཐ་དད་མི་འབྱེད་ཀྱིས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-061-004-105"/>“Intelligent ones do not differentiate Between childish beings and their qualities, Or the buddhas’ qualities and the victors,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.101.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྟོང་པ་ཉིད་ལ་དེ་ལྟར་ལྟོས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>So you too should see these as merely empty.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.101.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དྲང་སྲོང་ཆེན་པོས་བྱང་ཆུབ་ཐོབ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-061-004-106"/>“That the great sage attained awakening</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.101.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནི་མི་རིགས་བརྟགས་པ་ཡིན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Is an illogical imputation.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.101.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཆོས་འདི་ལ་ནི་སྐྱེ་མེད་ན། །མྱ་ངན་འདས་པ་ཇི་ལྟར་ཐོབ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>If the phenomenon of awakening does not arise, How can one attain nirvāṇa?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.101.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཆོས་རྣམས་མཐའ་ཡས་རབ་ཏུ་གསུངས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-061-004-107"/>“An infinite number of teachings are proclaimed,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.101.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སེམས་ཅན་གྲོལ་བའང་དངོས་པོ་མེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Yet there is no such thing as the liberation of beings.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.102.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མྱ་ངན་འདས་དང་འཁོར་བ་ལ། <tei:ref folio="F.102.a"/>ཐ་དད་དབྱེར་མེད་གཟུང་བར་གྱིས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Between nirvāṇa and saṃsāra. Understand this: there is no distinction </seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.102.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདི་ལ་རྣམ་པ་ཐམས་ཅད་དུ། །བསྣན་དང་དབྲི་བ་ཅི་ཡང་མེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-061-004-108"/>“Thus, in all cases, There is never any increase or decrease.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.102.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཐ་དད་མེད་པའི་ཆོས་རྣམས་ལ། །མཁས་པ་རྣམས་ནི་རྨོངས་མི་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>About the fact that phenomena are indistinct. The wise harbor no delusions</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.102.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱིས་པ་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་ཐོབ་ཅིང་རྙེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-061-004-109"/>“Childish beings obtain and attain.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.102.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱིས་པས་མྱ་ངན་འདས་པ་ཐོབ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>A childish being who attains nirvāṇa</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.102.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཁོར་བ་ལ་ནི་དེ་ཀུན་ཆགས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Is thoroughly attached to saṃsāra.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.102.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རློམ་སེམས་བདུད་ཀྱི་འཆིང་བ་ཡིན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Such conceited thinking is Māra’s trap.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.102.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་གིས་བློ་ལ་ངས་ཐོབ་སྙམ། །དེས་ནི་ཅི་ཡང་ཐོབ་པ་མེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-061-004-110"/>“Someone who thinks ‘I have attained’ Has not attained anything at all.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.102.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ཡི་ཡང་སྲིད་འགྲོ་བ་ཡི། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They will proceed to their next birth</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.102.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མ་རིག་པ་ཡང་འཇུག་པར་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>And start all over again in ignorance.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.102.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱང་ཆུབ་སྙིང་པོར་འདུག་ནས་ནི། །མཐོང་བ་མེད་ཅིང་སྤངས་པའང་མེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-061-004-111"/>“Abiding at the seat of awakening, There is nothing to see and nothing to abandon.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.102.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སངས་རྒྱས་རྣམས་ཀྱི་བྱང་ཆུབ་འདི། །ཐ་སྙད་ཡིན་ཏེ་དོན་དུ་མིན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The awakening of all the buddhas Is a conventional term but nothing in actuality.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.102.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱང་ཆུབ་དང་ནི་མྱ་ངན་འདས། །ཐ་སྙད་དག་གིས་བརྗོད་མི་ནུས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-061-004-112"/>“Awakening and nirvāṇa Cannot be expressed by conventional terms.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.102.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་དག་དེ་ལྟར་ཡང་དག་མཐོང་། །དེ་དག་ཆོས་ཉིད་རྣམ་པར་ཤེས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Those who see correctly in that way Fully understand the nature of reality.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.102.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ལ་ཚེ་དང་ལྡན་པ་ཤཱ་རིའི་བུས་འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་གསོལ་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-061-004-113"/>Venerable Śāriputra then asked the Blessed One,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.102.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཁྱེའུ་རིན་ཆེན་བྱིན་གྱིས་ཡུན་ཇི་སྲིད་ཅིག་ནས་ཆོས་འདི་ལ་སྤྱད་ལགས། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Blessed One, how long has this boy Ratnadatta practiced this teaching?”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.102.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་བཀའ་སྩལ་པ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-061-004-114"/>The Blessed One replied,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.102.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་གི་ཚེ་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་མར་མེ་མཛད་ཀྱིས་ང་མི་སྐྱེ་བའི་ཆོས་ལ་བཟོད་པ་ཐོབ་པར་འགྱུར་བ་ལུང་བསྟན་པ་དེའི་ཚེ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“When the thus-gone one Dīpaṁkara gave his prophecy that I would attain acceptance of the nonarising of phenomena,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.102.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདི་མར་མེ་མཛད་ཀྱི་གསུང་རབ་ལ་སྟོང་པ་ཉིད་ལ་གནས་པའི་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་རྣམས་ཀྱི་མཆོག་ཏུ་གྱུར་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>at that point he was foremost among those bodhisattvas who abided in emptiness according to Dīpaṁkara’s teachings.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.102.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་གི་ཚེ་ངས་བླ་ན་མེད་པ་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་བྱང་ཆུབ་ཏུ་དང་པོ་སེམས་བསྐྱེད་པ་དེའི་ཚེ་འདིས་བཟོད་པ་ཐོབ་ནས་བསྐལ་པ་སུམ་འབུམ་ལོན་ནོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>At the moment when I first generated the mind set on unsurpassed and perfect awakening, three hundred thousand eons had passed since he attained acceptance.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.102.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཤཱ་རིའི་བུས་གསོལ་པ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-061-004-115"/>“Blessed One,” asked Śāriputra,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.102.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཁྱེའུ་རིན་ཆེན་བྱིན་བླ་ན་མེད་པ་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་བྱང་ཆུབ་མངོན་པར་རྫོགས་པར་སངས་མ་རྒྱས་པའི་རྒྱུ་ནི་གང་ལགས། རྐྱེན་ནི་གང་ལགས། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“what cause and what conditions are responsible for the boy Ratnadatta not becoming a complete buddha who has manifested unsurpassed and perfect awakening?”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.102.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཁྱོད་ཀྱིས་ཁྱེའུ་རིན་ཆེན་བྱིན་འདི་ཉིད་ལ་དྲིས་ཤིག་དང་འདི་ཉིད་ཀྱིས་ཁྱོད་ལ་སྟོན་པར་འགྱུར་རོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-061-004-116"/>“You should ask Ratnadatta himself this question. He will tell you,” the Blessed One responded.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.102.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་ཚེ་དང་ལྡན་པ་ཤཱ་རིའི་བུས་ཁྱེའུ་རིན་ཆེན་བྱིན་ལ་འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་སྨྲས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-061-004-117"/>So Venerable Śāriputra asked the boy Ratnadatta,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.102.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཅིའི་ཕྱིར་ཁྱོད་བླ་ན་མེད་པ་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་བྱང་ཆུབ་མངོན་པར་རྫོགས་པར་སངས་མ་རྒྱས། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Why have you not become a complete buddha who has manifested unsurpassed and perfect awakening?” </seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.102.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རིན་ཆེན་བྱིན་གྱིས་སྨྲས་པ། བླ་ན་མེད་པ་ཡང་དག་པར་<tei:ref folio="F.102.b"/>རྫོགས་པའི་བྱང་ཆུབ་མ་དམིགས་པས་ན་དེའི་ཕྱིར་བདག་མངོན་པར་རྫོགས་པར་འཚང་མི་རྒྱའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-061-004-118"/>“The reason I do not become a complete manifest buddha,” Ratnadatta replied, “is that I do not apprehend unsurpassed and perfect awakening.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.102.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཤཱ་རིའི་བུས་སྨྲས་པ། འོ་ན་ཅི་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་འདི་མངོན་པར་རྫོགས་པར་སངས་རྒྱས་པ་ལས་ན་དམིགས་པ་ལ་སྤྱོད་དམ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-061-004-119"/>“If that is so,” Śāriputra asked, “since this thus-gone one is a complete manifest buddha, do you apprehend him?”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.102.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རིན་ཆེན་བྱིན་གྱིས་སྨྲས་པ། གལ་ཏེ་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་མངོན་པར་རྫོགས་པར་སངས་རྒྱས་པར་འཛིན་ན་ནི། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-061-004-120"/>Ratnadatta replied, “If someone grasps at the Thus-Gone One as a complete manifest buddha, and</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.102.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེའི་དམིགས་པར་འགྱུར་བ་ཞིག་ན། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>if he becomes the referent object of that grasping, then</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.102.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཆོས་གསུང་བ་ནི་མངོན་པར་རྫོགས་པར་འཚང་རྒྱ་བར་ཡང་མི་མཛད་ལ་སྤོང་བར་ཡང་མི་མཛད་དོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>the Dharma he teaches will not cause that person to become a complete manifest buddha, and it will not even bring about renunciation.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.102.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཤཱ་རིའི་བུས་སྨྲས་པ། ཁྱོད་ཆོས་བཞི་སྒྲུབ་པ་དང་ཡོངས་སུ་སྨིན་པ་མཉམ་པས་བཟོད་པ་གང་ལ་གནས། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-061-004-121"/>“Since you equate complete maturation with accomplishing the four factors,<tei:note xml:id="UT22084-061-004-122"/> what is your acceptance based on?” Śāriputra asked.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.102.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཁྱེའུ་རིན་ཆེན་བྱིན་གྱིས་སྨྲས་པ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-061-004-123"/>The boy Ratnadatta replied,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.102.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བདག་གིས་ནི་ཆོས་གཅིག་ཀྱང་ཡོངས་སུ་གྲུབ་པར་ཡང་དག་པར་མ་མཐོང་ན་བཞི་ལྟ་ཅི་སྨོས། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“I do not perceive even a single phenomenon that is truly established, much less four.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.102.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདི་ལ་ཡང་དག་པར་གྲུབ་པ་གང་ཞིག་ཡོད་དེ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>What is there truly established in them?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.102.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཆོས་རྣམ་པར་རིག་པ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་འདི་ནི་དམིགས་པའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>‘Knowing the Dharma’ is apprehension.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.102.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱང་ཆུབ་ཅེས་བྱ་བ་འདི་ནི་དམིགས་པའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>‘Awakening’ is apprehension.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.102.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་འདི་ནི་འཛིན་པའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>‘The Thus-Gone One’ is grasping.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.102.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གྲོལ་བ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་འདི་ནི་སྤྲོས་པའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>‘Liberation’ is a mental construct.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.102.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཤཱ་རིའི་བུས་སྨྲས་པ། རིགས་ཀྱི་བུ་ཁྱོད་འདི་ལྟ་བུའི་ཆོས་རྣམས་ལ་སྤྱོད་ལ་རྫུས་ཏེ་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-061-004-124"/>“Son of the lineage,” Śāriputra replied, “what a wonder that you experience things in this way and</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.102.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྐྱེ་བས་སངས་རྒྱས་རྣམས་མངོན་སུམ་དུ་གྱུར་པར་སྐྱེ་ཞིང་རྟག་ཏུ་རབ་ཏུ་འབྱུང་བ་འདི་ནི་ངོ་མཚར་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>that you have attained such a miraculous birth whereby you were born in the presence of the buddhas and will always go forth!”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.102.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་དེའི་ཚེ་ཁྱེའུ་རིན་ཆེན་བྱིན་གྱིས་ཚིགས་སུ་བཅད་པ་འདི་དག་སྨྲས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-061-004-125"/>Ratnadatta then replied with the following verses:</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.102.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྐྱེ་དང་དེ་བཞིན་སྐྱེ་མེད་གཉིས་ནི་སྤྲོས་པ་སྟེ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-061-004-126"/>“Born and not born are both mental constructs.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.102.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཀུན་ཏུ་རྟོགས་པའི་ས་དང་བདུད་ཀྱི་སྤྱོད་ཡུལ་ཡིན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They are the level of conceptual imputation and the domain of Māra.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.102.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལུས་ལ་སོགས་པའི་ཆོས་འཛིན་རློམ་སེམས་འདོད་པ་ཡི། །ལྷ་དང་ལྷ་མིན་འགྲོ་བ་རྣམས་ནི་འདིར་བརླག་གོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Desire realm beings such as the gods and asuras who grasp at And harbor conceit about phenomena such as the body are destroyed in this domain.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.102.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྒྱལ་བས་བདུད་རྩི་འདུས་མ་བྱས་པ་བརྙེས་སྙམ་དུ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-061-004-127"/>“Thinking, ‘The Victor attained the unconditioned, deathless state,’</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.102.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ལྟར་གང་དག་བསམ་པ་རབ་ཏུ་འཇུག་བྱེད་པ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Some set out with the same intention</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.102.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་དག་སངས་རྒྱས་ལ་ནི་སྐུ་ངས་གསོལ་བར་བྱེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>And insult the buddhas.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.102.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བརྙེས་ཀྱང་འདི་ལ་འདྲེན་པ་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་བརྙེས་པ་མེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Though they attain it, there is nothing in it that the guides attain.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.102.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདིར་ནི་སྐྱེ་བོ་མང་པོ་དག །རབ་ཏུ་བྱུང་ནས་རང་བྱུང་རློམ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-061-004-128"/>“There are many people who, Having gone forth for this, presume they have gone forth.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.102.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སེམས་ཀྱི་དམིགས་པས་རྣམ་འཁྲུལ་ནས། །བསྟན་པ་ལ་ནི་སུན་འབྱིན་རྣམས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They are confused by mental apprehension And they corrupt the teachings.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.102.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བདུད་རྩི་བདག་གིས་ཐོབ་བོ་ཞེས། །ཐོབ་པའི་ང་རྒྱལ་ཅན་དག་སྨྲ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-061-004-129"/>“Those who are proud of their attainment say, ‘I have attained deathlessness.’</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.102.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྐྱོབ་པ་ཤཱཀྱ་སེང་གེ་ཡི། །བསྟན་པ་ལ་ནི་སྤྲོས་མེད་པ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>But the teaching of the protector, the lion of the Śākya clan, Lacks mental constructs. </seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.103.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སེམས་<tei:ref folio="F.103.a"/>ཀྱིས་རྣམ་པ་ཐམས་ཅད་དུ། །སེམས་ཀྱིས་ངོ་བོ་ཉིད་མི་རྟོགས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-061-004-130"/>“Among all mental content One does not find the nature of mind.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.103.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་བཞིན་རྣམ་འདྲེན་གསུངས་པ་ཡི། །ལྟ་བ་དེ་ནི་རང་བཞིན་མེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Thus, the view taught by the guide Has no inherent nature.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.103.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྤྱན་དག་རྒྱལ་བས་གསུངས་པ་ཡི། །ལྟ་བ་ལ་ནི་ལྟ་བ་མེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-061-004-131"/>“In the view taught by the Victor with pure vision There is no viewing.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.103.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ཕྱིར་ཤེས་རབ་ལྡན་པ་ནི། །བདག་ཉིད་གྲོལ་སྙམ་འཛིན་པ་མེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>That is why those who have insight Do not grasp at the thought, ‘I am free.’</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.103.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མཚན་མར་འཛིན་པ་སྒོམ་པ་རྣམས། །བདག་ཏུ་དམིགས་པས་རྨོངས་པར་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-061-004-132"/>“Those accustomed to apprehending marks Apprehend a self and are deluded.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.103.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མཁས་པ་མ་ཡིན་ཁ་ཅིག་ནི། །ཡང་དག་མ་ཡིན་སྟོང་པ་སྤོང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Such unwise people Reject emptiness as incorrect.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.103.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དངོས་པོ་རྨི་ལམ་སྒྱུ་མ་འདྲ། །རང་གི་བློས་ནི་བརྟགས་ནས་ཀྱང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-061-004-133"/>“The unwise impute things With their own minds,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.103.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མི་མཁས་དེ་དག་དངོས་པོ་རྣམས། །གཞིག་ཕྱིར་མྱ་ངན་འདས་པ་སྨྲ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Like a dream and an illusion. Then, when things cease, they call it nirvāṇa.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.103.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལུས་ལ་ཡང་ནི་རྟེན་བཅས་ནས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-061-004-134"/>“They take the body as a support</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.103.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཚུལ་ཁྲིམས་འདུ་ཤེས་རྣམ་པར་འཇིག །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>And do away with the notion of discipline.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.103.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སེམས་ཀྱི་དམིགས་པ་དག་ལ་ཡང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They take mental apprehention as a support</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.103.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བསམ་གཏན་འདུ་ཤེས་རྣམ་པར་འཇིག །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>And do away with the notion of meditative absorption.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.103.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་བཞིན་ཤེས་རབ་དམིགས་ནས་ཀྱང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-061-004-135"/>“Likewise, they apprehend insight</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.103.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ས་བོན་འདུ་ཤེས་རྣམ་པར་རྨོངས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>And have a deluded notion of it as a seed.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.103.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇིག་རྟེན་འཇིག་རྟེན་མཁས་རྣམས་ཀྱིས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The wise people of the world</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.103.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་དག་ཆོས་ཀྱི་རྐུན་པོར་བརྗོད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Proclaim them thieves of the Dharma.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.103.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདི་འདྲ་བ་ཡི་ཆོས་རྣམས་ལ། །ཆོས་དབྱིངས་འོད་གསལ་ཉོན་མོངས་མེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-061-004-136"/>“The luminous expanse of phenomena, Free of afflictions, is in all such phenomena.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.103.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འོ་ན་རབ་ཏུ་བྱུང་བའི་དོན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The point of going forth?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.103.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཁྱོད་ཀྱིས་བདག་ལ་ཇི་སྐད་བརྗོད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>So, will you please tell me</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.103.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཆོས་རྣམས་ཐམས་ཅད་ཐ་དད་མེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-061-004-137"/>“All phenomena are indistinct.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.103.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདི་དག་བྲག་ཅ་འདྲ་བ་ཡིན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They are like an echo.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.103.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མཁས་པ་དེ་དག་ནམ་དུ་ཡང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The sphere of the noble ones.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.103.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཕགས་པའི་སྤྱོད་ཡུལ་རྟོག་མི་བྱེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The wise never conceptualize</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.103.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཞན་མིན་མཚན་ཉིད་དེ་བཞིན་ཉིད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-061-004-138"/>“Their characteristic is suchness and nothing else.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.103.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཞན་དག་ཏུ་ནི་ཡོང་མི་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They never transform into other things.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.103.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཆོས་རྣམས་འགྱུར་བ་མེད་པ་ལ། །རབ་བྱུང་བརྟགས་པས་ཅི་ཞིག་བྱ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Since phenomena are unchanging, What use is the concept of going forth?”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.103.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་འཇམ་དཔལ་གཞོན་ནུར་གྱུར་པས་ཁྱེའུ་རིན་ཆེན་བྱིན་ལ་འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་སྨྲས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-061-004-139"/>Then Mañjuśrī­kumāra­bhūta asked Ratnadatta,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.103.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཁྱེའུ་བྱང་ཆུབ་ཅེས་བྱ་བ་དེ་གང་གི་ཚིག་བླ་དགས་ཡིན། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Child, what is ‘awakening’ a verbal designation for?”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.103.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རིན་ཆེན་བྱིན་གྱིས་སྨྲས་པ། འཇམ་དཔལ་བྱང་ཆུབ་ནི་ཚིག་གི་བླ་དགས་མེད་པའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Mañjuśrī,” Ratnadatta replied, “awakening is devoid of verbal designations.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.103.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་གྱིས་སྨྲས་པ། ཁྱོད་ཅི་ལས་བསམས་ཏེ་དེ་སྐད་སྨྲ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-061-004-141"/>“How do you consider and verbally express it?” Mañjuśrī asked.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.103.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རིན་ཆེན་བྱིན་གྱིས་སྨྲས་པ། འཇམ་དཔལ་ཆོས་ཉིད་ནི་བསམ་དུ་མེད་པ་ཡིན་ན། དེ་བདག་གིས་འདི་ལྟར་བསམས་ཏེ་བསྟན་པར་བྱ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Ratnadatta replied, “Mañjuśrī, since reality is inconceivable, I consider it as such and then express it.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.103.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་གྱིས་སྨྲས་པ། འདི་ལ་ལས་དང་པོ་པའི་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་ལ་<tei:ref folio="F.103.b"/>ཇི་ལྟར་གདམས་ངག་བསྟན་པར་བྱ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-061-004-143"/>Mañjuśrī asked, “How should beginner bodhisattvas be given instructions on this?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.103.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཇི་ལྟར་རྗེས་སུ་བསྟན་པར་བྱ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>How should they be taught about it?” </seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.103.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རིན་ཆེན་བྱིན་གྱིས་སྨྲས་པ། འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་སྨྲ་བར་བྱ་སྟེ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-061-004-144"/>Ratnadatta replied, “One should say the following:</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.103.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདོད་ཆགས་མ་སྤངས་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>‘Do not abandon desire.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.103.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཤིག་ཞེ་སྡང་མ་གཞིལ་ཅིག །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Do not get rid of anger.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.103.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཏི་མུག་མ་བསལ་ཅིག །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Do not clear away delusion.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.103.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རང་གི་ལུས་ལས་གྱེན་དུ་མ་བསྐྱོད་ཅིག །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Do not rise above the body.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.103.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མི་དགེ་བ་སྤྱོད་ཅིག །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Practice nonvirtue.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.103.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལྟ་བ་ཚར་མ་གཅོད་ཅིག །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Do not vanquish views.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.103.b</prop>
            <prop type="alternative-source"/>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཀུན་ཏུ་སྦྱོར་བ་རྣམས་མ་སྟོན་ཅིག །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Do not remove<tei:note xml:id="UT22084-061-004-145"/> fetters.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.103.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཕུང་པོ་རྣམས་ཡོངས་སུ་ཟུང་ཤིག །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Grasp at the aggregates.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.103.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཁམས་རྣམས་རིལ་པོར་གྱིས་ཤིག །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Make the elements into a single mass.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.103.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྐྱེ་མཆེད་རྣམས་ལ་སྤྱོད་ཅིག །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Engage the sense spheres.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.103.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱིས་པའི་ས་ལས་འདའ་བར་མ་བྱེད་ཅིག །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Do not go beyond the level of childish beings.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.103.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མི་དགེ་བ་ལ་རྟོགས་ཤིག །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Realize nonvirtue.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.103.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དགེ་བ་སྤོངས་ཤིག །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Abandon virtue.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.103.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སངས་རྒྱས་ཡིད་ལ་མ་བྱེད་ཅིག །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Do not contemplate the Buddha.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.103.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཆོས་མ་སེམས་ཤིག །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Do not think about the Dharma.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.103.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དགེ་འདུན་ལ་ནི་མཆོད་པ་མ་བྱེད་ཅིག །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Do not make offerings to the Saṅgha.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.103.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བསླབ་པ་དག་ཡང་དག་པར་མ་ལེན་ཅིག །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Do not take up the trainings.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.103.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྲིད་པ་ཉེ་བར་ཞི་བ་དོན་དུ་མ་གཉེར་ཅིག །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Do not strive to pacify existence.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.103.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཆུ་བོ་ལས་མ་རྒལ་ཅིག །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Do not cross over the river.’</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.103.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཅེས་གདམས་ངག་འདི་ལྟ་བུས་ལས་དང་པོ་པའི་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་ལ་གདམས་པར་བྱའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-061-004-146"/>“It is with such instructions that one should instruct [and teach] beginner bodhisattvas.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.103.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྗེས་སུ་བསྟན་པར་བྱའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>[“It is with such instructions that one should instruct and] teach beginner bodhisattvas.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.103.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ཅིའི་ཕྱིར་ཞེ་ན། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Why is that?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.103.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཆོས་རྣམས་ཀྱི་ཆོས་གནས་པ་འདི་ནི་གནས་པ་ཁོ་ན་ཡིན་པའི་ཕྱིར་རོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Because only this state is the state of phenomena.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.103.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱིས་པ་དེ་དག་ནི་སྐྱེ་བའི་ཆོས་སུ་ལུང་སྟོན་པར་བྱེད་དོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Childish beings declare that phenomena arise and</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.103.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འགག་པའི་ཆོས་སུ་ལུང་སྟོན་པར་བྱེད་དོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>declare that phenomena cease.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.103.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཆོས་ཀྱི་དབྱིངས་འདི་ནི་རྣམ་པར་མི་རྟོག་པས་རབ་ཏུ་ཕྱེ་བ་ཡིན་ཏེ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The realm of phenomena is discerned through nonconceptuality.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.103.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཆོས་འདི་རྣམས་ཀྱི་རང་བཞིན་དེ་ལྟར་རྗེས་སུ་རྟོགས་པ་གང་ཡིན་པ་དེ་ནི་བྱང་ཆུབ་བོ་ཞེས་དེ་ལྟར་གདམས་ན། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>If someone receives the instruction that understanding the nature of phenomena in this way is awakening, and</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.103.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གལ་ཏེ་མི་སྐྲག་མི་དངང་ཞིང་དངང་བར་མི་འགྱུར་ན། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>if they are not afraid, scared, or frightened by it, then</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.103.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཀྱེ་མ་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་འདི་ནི་ཕྱིར་མི་ལྡོག་པ་སྟེ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>that person is a bodhisattva who will truly never regress.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.103.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཕྱིར་མི་ལྡོག་པའི་སའི་སྐལ་བ་ཅན་ཡིན་ནོ་སྙམ་དུ་ཤེས་པར་བྱ་སྟེ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>That bodhisattva who has reached the stage free from regression should be considered a fortunate one.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.103.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གདམས་ངག་འདིས་ཡང་དང་ཡང་དུ་ཡང་དག་པར་དགའ་བ་བསྐྱེད་པར་བྱའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Through these instructions, one should give rise to true joy again and again.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.103.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེའི་ཚེ་དམིགས་པ་ཅན་གྱི་དགེ་སློང་བརྒྱད་ཀྱིས་ཆོས་ཀྱི་རྣམ་གྲངས་འདི་མ་བསྟེན་པར་སྤངས་ནས་འཁོར་དེ་ནས་སོང་སྟེ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-061-004-147"/>At that point, eight monks who maintained the view of apprehension refused to follow this Dharma teaching, rejected it, and left the assembly.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.103.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཁ་ནས་ཁྲག་དྲོན་མོ་བྱུང་ནས་ཤིའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They all vomited warm blood and died, and</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.103.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཤི་ནས་སེམས་ཅན་དམྱལ་བ་ཆེན་པོ་ངུ་འབོད་དུ་སྐྱེས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>after they died they were reborn in the Great Wailing Hell.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.103.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ལ་འཇམ་དཔལ་གཞོན་ནུར་གྱུར་པས་འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་གསོལ་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>At that point Mañjuśrī­kumāra­bhūta alerted the Blessed One saying,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.104.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་དགེ་སློང་དེ་དག་གིས་ཆོས་ཀྱི་རྣམ་གྲངས་<tei:ref folio="F.104.a"/>འདི་ཐོས་པས་གནོད་པ་ཆེན་པོ་ཇི་ཙམ་དུ་གྱུར་པ་ལ་གཟིགས། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Blessed One, see how those monks have suffered such great harm by listening to this Dharma teaching!” </seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.104.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་ཁྱོད་དེ་སྐད་མ་ཟེར་ཅིག །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-061-004-148"/>“Do not say such things, Mañjuśrī,” the Blessed One replied.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.104.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གལ་ཏེ་དགེ་སློང་འདི་དག་གིས་ཆོས་ཀྱི་རྣམ་གྲངས་འདི་མ་ཐོས་སུ་ཟིན་ན། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“If these monks had not heard this Dharma teaching,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.104.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བསྐལ་པ་ས་ཡའི་བར་དུ་ནམས་ཀྱང་བཟང་འགྲོར་སྐྱེ་བར་ཡང་མི་འགྱུར་ན་སངས་རྒྱས་དང་ཕྲད་ཅིང་མཉེས་པར་བྱེད་པ་ལྟ་ཅི་སྨོས། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>they would not have secured higher births for millions of eons, let alone meeting and serving any buddhas.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.104.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ད་ནི་དེ་དག་གིས་ཆོས་ཀྱི་རྣམ་གྲངས་འདི་སོམ་ཉི་དང་བཅས་པས་ཐོས་ནས་ད་གཟོད་ཁོ་ནར་སེམས་ཅན་དམྱལ་བ་ཆེན་པོ་ངུ་འབོད་ནས་ཤི་འཕོས་ཏེ་དགའ་ལྡན་གྱི་ལྷའི་རིས་སུ་སྐྱེའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Since they just listened to this Dharma teaching with doubt, they are right now dying and transmigrating from the Great Wailing Hell and being reborn among the gods in the Heaven of Joy.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.104.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་དག་བསྐལ་པ་དྲུག་ཅུ་རྩ་བརྒྱད་ཀྱི་བར་དུ་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་ཁྲག་ཁྲིག་ཕྲག་བཅུ་མཉེས་པར་བྱེད་པར་འགྱུར་ཏེ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>For sixty-eight eons, they will serve billions of thus-gone ones.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.104.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཐམས་ཅད་དུ་རྫུས་ཏེ་སྐྱེ་ཞིང་འཁོར་ལོས་སྒྱུར་བའི་རྒྱལ་པོ་ཤ་སྟག་ཏུ་འགྱུར་ལ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>In all these lives they will only take miraculous birth and become universal monarchs.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.104.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བསྐལ་པ་གཅིག་ལ་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་དགྲ་བཅོམ་པ་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་སངས་རྒྱས་དྲི་མ་མེད་པའི་འོད་ཅེས་བྱ་བ་དག་ཏུ་འགྱུར་རོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>In a later eon they will become thus-gone ones, worthy ones, perfect complete buddhas known as Vimalaprabhāsa.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.104.a</prop>
            <prop type="alternative-source"/>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་ལྷའི་བུ་དེ་དག་གིས་བདག་ཅག་ལུང་བསྟན་པ་ལྷའི་རྣ་བའི་ཁམས་ཀྱིས་ཐོས་ནས། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-061-004-149"/>Then, having heard the prophecy<tei:note xml:id="UT22084-061-004-150"/> with their divine hearing,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.104.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་དག་ལྷའི་བུ་བརྒྱད་ཁྲི་དང་ལྷན་ཅིག་ཏུ་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ག་ལ་བ་དེར་དོང་སྟེ་ལྷགས་ནས་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>those gods, together with eighty thousand gods, traveled to where the Blessed One was.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.104.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལྷའི་མེ་ཏོག་གིས་ཡངས་པའི་གྲོང་ཁྱེར་ཐམས་ཅད་དུ་གཏོར་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>When they arrived, they scattered divine flowers all over Vaiśālī.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.104.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཆོས་ཀྱི་རྣམ་གྲངས་འདི་ལ་ཡང་རྗེས་སུ་ཡི་རང་སྟེ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They rejoiced in this Dharma teaching, saying,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.104.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་བདག་ཅག་རྗེས་སུ་ཡི་རང་ལགས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Blessed One, we rejoice!</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.104.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་རྣམས་ཀྱི་བྱང་ཆུབ་ཀྱི་ཚུལ་འཕེལ་བར་མཛད་དུ་གསོལ་ཞེས་ཀྱང་གསོལ་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Please cause the system of the awakening of the thus-gone ones to flourish!”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.104.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་དག་རྗེས་སུ་ཡི་རང་བའི་མོད་ལ་བླ་ན་མེད་པ་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་བྱང་ཆུབ་ལས་ཕྱིར་མི་ལྡོག་པར་གྱུར་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The moment that they rejoiced in this way, they became irreversible from unsurpassed and perfect awakening.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.104.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡངས་པའི་གྲོང་ཁྱེར་ཆེན་པོའི་སྲོག་ཆགས་བརྒྱད་ཁྲི་བཞི་སྟོང་ཡང་བླ་ན་མེད་པ་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་བྱང་ཆུབ་ལས་ཕྱིར་མི་ལྡོག་པར་གྱུར་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Eighty-four thousand beings of the great city of Vaiśālī also became irreversible from unsurpassed and perfect awakening.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.104.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྲོག་ཆགས་ཁྲི་ཉིས་སྟོང་ནི་ཆོས་རྣམས་ལ་ཆོས་ཀྱི་མིག་རྡུལ་མེད་ཅིང་དྲི་མ་དང་བྲལ་བ་རྣམ་པར་དག་གོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Twelve thousand beings removed the dust from the Dharma eye that sees all phenomena, rendering it stainless and pure.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.104.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་འཇམ་དཔལ་གཞོན་ནུར་གྱུར་པ་ལ་བཀའ་སྩལ་པ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-061-004-151"/>The Blessed One continued to address Mañjuśrī­kumāra­bhūta, saying,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.104.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་གང་གིས་བསྐལ་པ་འབུམ་གྱི་<tei:ref folio="F.104.b"/>བར་དུ་ཐབས་ལ་མཁས་པ་མེད་པར་ཕ་རོལ་ཏུ་ཕྱིན་པ་དྲུག་ལ་སྤྱད་པ་བས། གང་གིས་ཆོས་ཀྱི་རྣམ་གྲངས་འདི་སོམ་ཉི་དང་བཅས་པས་ཐོས་ནའདི་ནི་དེ་བས་ཆེས་བསོད་ནམས་མང་དུ་སྐྱེད་ན་གང་གིས་སོམ་ཉི་མེད་པར་ཐོས་པ་ལྟ་ཅི་སྨོས། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Mañjuśrī, since someone who listens to this Dharma teaching with doubt generates far greater merit than a bodhisattva who practices the six perfections without skillful means for one hundred thousand eons , why mention someone who has no doubt when they hear it?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.104.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་གིས་ཡི་གེར་འདྲི་བ་དང་། ལུང་ནོད་པ་དང་། འཆང་བ་དང་། གཞན་དག་ལ་ཡང་རྒྱ་ཆེར་ཡང་དག་པར་སྟོན་པ་ལྟ་ཅི་སྨོས། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>And why mention those who write it down, explain it, hold it, and teach it extensively to others?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.104.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་དེ་ལྟ་བས་ན་དགྲ་བཅོམ་པ་ཉིད་ཐོབ་པར་འདོད་པས་ཀྱང་ཆོས་འདི་ལ་བསླབ་པར་བྱའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Therefore, Mañjuśrī, those who want to attain the state of a worthy one should train in this teaching,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.104.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རང་བྱང་ཆུབ་ཐོབ་པར་འདོད་པས་ཀྱང་ཆོས་འདི་ལ་བསླབ་པར་བྱའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>those who want to attain the state of a solitary buddha should train in this teaching, and</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.104.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བླ་ན་མེད་པ་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་བྱང་ཆུབ་མངོན་པར་རྫོགས་པར་འཚང་རྒྱ་བར་འདོད་པས་ཀྱང་ཆོས་འདི་ལ་བསླབ་པར་བྱའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>those who want to become a complete buddha who manifests unsurpassed and perfect awakening should train in this teaching.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.104.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་ཁྱེའུ་རིན་ཆེན་བྱིན་གྱིས་རང་གི་མ་མ་ལ་འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་སྨྲས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-061-004-152"/>The boy Ratnadatta then said to his mother,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.104.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མ་མ་ཁོ་བོ་ལ་ཁ་ཟས་བྱིན་ཅིག་དང་། བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱི་ཞལ་ཟས་དབུལ་བར་བྱའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Mother, please give me some food, and I will offer it to the Blessed One.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.104.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་ཁྱེའུ་རིན་ཆེན་བྱིན་གྱི་མ་མས་ཁར་བའི་སྣོད་ཟས་རོ་བརྒྱ་དང་ལྡན་པས་བཀང་སྟེ། ཁྱེའུ་རིན་ཆེན་བྱིན་ལ་བྱིན་ནོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Ratnadatta’s mother filled a metal bowl with delicious food and gave it to the child.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.104.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་ཁྱེའུ་རིན་ཆེན་བྱིན་གྱིས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ལ་འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་གསོལ་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Ratnadatta then addressed the Blessed One, saying,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.104.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་མི་ཟད་པའི་བདེན་པ་གང་ལགས་པའི་བདེན་པ་དེས་ན་དགེ་སློང་གི་དགེ་འདུན་ཐམས་ཅད་ཚིམ་པར་མ་གྱུར་གྱི་བར་དུ་ཁར་བའི་སྣོད་འདི་ཡོངས་སུ་འགྲིབ་པར་མ་གྱུར་ཅིག །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Blessed One, since it is true that all phenomena are inexhaustible, may the food in this metal bowl not diminish until the entire saṅgha of monks has been satisfied.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.104.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་ཁྱེའུ་རིན་ཆེན་བྱིན་གྱིས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱི་ལྷུང་བཟེད་བཀང་ནས་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Ratnadatta filled the Blessed One’s alms bowl first and then addressed the saṅgha of monks, saying,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.104.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དགེ་སློང་གི་དགེ་འདུན་ལ་སྨྲས་པ། བཙུན་པ་རྣམས་བདག་ལ་ཐུགས་བརྩེ་བའི་སླད་དུ་གང་གིས་བདག་ལ་འབྲས་བུ་ཆེན་པོར་འགྱུར་བའི་བསོད་སྙོམས་འདི་བཞེས་ཏེ</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Venerable Ones, may these alms be accepted out of compassion for me by someone who can ensure that I obtain a great result.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.104.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་ལུས་ཀྱིས་ཡོན་སྦྱོང་བར་མི་བྱེད་པ་དང་། སེམས་ཀྱིས་སྦྱོང་བར་མི་བྱེད་པ་དང་། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>May these alms be accepted by someone who does not purify the gift with the body, who does not purify it with the mind;</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.104.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་ལ་ཕུལ་ན་བསོད་ནམས་སུ་མི་འགྱུར་བ་དང་། རྣམ་པར་སྨིན་པར་མི་འགྱུར་བ་དང་། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>someone who will not generate merit or ripen karma when it is offered to them;</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.104.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་ལུས་ཀྱི་ལས་དང་། ངག་གི་ལས་དང་། ཡིད་ཀྱི་ལས་དང་མི་ལྡན་པ་དང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>someone who has no physical, verbal, or mental karma;</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.104.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་འདུས་བྱས་ལ་མི་གནས་པ་དང་། གང་འདུས་མ་བྱས་ལ་མི་གནས་པ་དང་། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>someone who abides neither in the conditioned nor in the unconditioned;</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.105.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་སོ་སོའི་སྐྱེ་བོའི་ཆོས་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་མ་གོས་པ་དང་། <tei:ref folio="F.105.a"/>
                </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>someone who is not stained by the qualities of ordinary beings;</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.105.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཉན་ཐོས་ཀྱི་ཆོས་རྣམས་ལ་མི་རྟེན་པ་དང་། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>someone who does not rely upon the teachings of the hearers;</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.105.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱི་ཐེག་པ་ལ་ངེས་པར་མི་འབྱུང་བ་དང་། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>someone who is not skilled in the vehicle of the buddhas;</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.105.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ངེས་པར་འབྱུང་བར་མི་འདོད་པ་དེས་བཞེས་ཤིག །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>and someone who has no wish to be skilled in it!”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.105.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་དགེ་སློང་གི་དགེ་འདུན་དེ་དག་གི་ནང་ནས་སུས་ཀྱང་སྣོད་དེ་མ་བླངས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-061-004-153"/>No one in the saṅgha of monks took up the bowl,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.105.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཁྱེའུ་རིན་ཆེན་བྱིན་གྱིས་སྨྲས་པ། བཙུན་པ་དག་བདག་ཀྱང་སྦྱིན་པར་འདོད་པ་ལགས། ཁྱེད་ཀྱང་གསོལ་བར་བཞེད་པ་ལགས་ཏེ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>so the child Ratnadatta continued, “Venerable Ones, I wish to make a gift, and you also wish to eat.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.105.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བདག་བཙུན་པ་རྣམས་ལས་ཅི་ཡང་རེ་བ་མ་མཆིས་ཀྱི་བཞེས་ཤིག །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>I do not expect anything in return from you venerable ones, so please eat!</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.105.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་གྱི་ཚད་དང་མཉམ་པའི་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་བྱེ་བ་ཕྲག་འབུམ་གྱི་སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱི་ཞིང་གི་ཡོན་ཏན་བཀོད་པ་དེ་བས་ཀྱང་ཆེས་བྱེ་བ་ཕྲག་འབུམ་ལས་ལྷག་པའི་སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱི་ཞིང་གི་ཡོན་ཏན་བཀོད་པ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>If it is true that my buddha realm will have a display of qualities that is a billion times greater than the display of qualities present in the buddha realms of billions of bodhisattvas who are of the same stature as Mañjuśrī, and</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.105.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བདག་གི་སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱི་ཞིང་དུ་འགྱུར་བའི་བདེན་པ་དང་བདེན་པའི་ཚིག་གང་ཡིན་པའི་བདེན་པ་དང་བདེན་པའི་ཚིག་དེས་ན་ཁར་བའི་སྣོད་འདི་ལས་ཁྱེད་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱི་ལྷུང་བཟེད་རྣམས་གང་བར་གྱུར་ཅིག །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>if it is true that what I have spoken is the truth, then by these true statements may all your bowls be filled from this metal bowl, and</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.105.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཁར་བའི་སྣོད་འདི་ཡང་ཡོངས་སུ་ཟད་པར་མ་གྱུར་ཅིག་ཅེས་བྱས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>may this bowl never be emptied!”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.105.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་དགེ་སློང་གི་དགེ་འདུན་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱི་ལྷུང་བཟེད་དེ་དག་གང་བར་གྱུར་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>All the alms bowls of the saṅgha of monks were then filled.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.105.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་ཁྱེའུ་རིན་ཆེན་བྱིན་གྱིས་ཡངས་པའི་གྲོང་ཁྱེར་གྱི་སྐྱེ་བོའི་ཚོགས་ཇི་སྙེད་ཡོད་པ་ཐམས་ཅད་ཁ་ཟས་རོ་བརྒྱ་དང་ལྡན་པ་དེས་ཚིམ་པར་བྱས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The child Ratnadatta fed the entire population of Vaiśālī with delicious food, and</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.105.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བསོད་སྙོམས་དེ་ཡང་ཟད་པར་མ་གྱུར་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>even then the alms did not run out.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.105.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་ཁྱེའུ་རིན་ཆེན་བྱིན་ལ་འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་བཀའ་སྩལ་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-061-004-154"/>Then the Blessed One addressed the child Ratnadatta, saying,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.105.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རིན་ཆེན་བྱིན་ལྔ་པོ་འདི་དག་ནི་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའི་ཡོན་ཡོངས་སུ་སྦྱོང་བ་སྟེ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Ratnadatta, these five are a bodhisattva’s purification of a gift:</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.105.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལུས་མི་དམིགས་པ་དང་། སེམས་མི་དམིགས་པ་དང་། སྦྱིན་པ་ལ་མངོན་པར་ཞེན་པ་མེད་པ་དང་། རྣམ་པར་སྨིན་པ་མི་འདོད་པ་དང་། ལེན་པ་པོ་རྣམས་ལ་རྣམ་པར་སྨིན་པ་མེད་པའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>not apprehending a body, not apprehending a mind, having no attachment to the gift, not desiring any ripening, and no ripening for the recipients.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.105.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རིན་ཆེན་བྱིན་བཞི་པོ་འདི་དག་ནི་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔས་རྟག་ཏུ་མངོན་དུ་བྱ་བ་སྟེ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Moreover, Ratnadatta, a bodhisattva should always manifest the following four things:</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.105.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྟོང་པ་ཉིད་ཀྱི་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་དང་། སངས་རྒྱས་རྗེས་སུ་དྲན་པ་དང་། སྙིང་རྗེ་ཆེན་པོ་དང་། བདག་གི་ལས་ཀྱི་རྣམ་པར་སྨིན་པའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>the meditative concentration of emptiness, recollecting the Buddha, great compassion, and the ripening of one’s own karma.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.105.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་<tei:ref folio="F.105.b"/>འཇམ་དཔལ་གཞོན་ནུར་གྱུར་པ་ལ་འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་བཀའ་སྩལ་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-061-004-155"/>The Blessed One addressed Mañjuśrī­kumāra­bhūta, saying,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.105.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་ཁྱེའུ་རིན་ཆེན་བྱིན་འདི་བསྐལ་པ་སུམ་ཅུ་ན་བླ་ན་མེད་པ་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་བྱང་ཆུབ་མངོན་པར་རྫོགས་པར་འཚང་རྒྱ་བར་འགྱུར་ཏེ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Mañjuśrī, in thirty eons, this child Ratnadatta will become a complete buddha who has manifested unsurpassed and perfect awakening.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.105.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་དགྲ་བཅོམ་པ་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་སངས་རྒྱས་རིག་པ་དང་ཞབས་སུ་ལྡན་པ། བདེ་བར་གཤེགས་པ། འཇིག་རྟེན་མཁྱེན་པ། སྐྱེས་བུ་འདུལ་བའི་ཁ་ལོ་སྒྱུར་བ་བླ་ན་མེད་པ། ལྷ་དང་མི་རྣམས་ཀྱི་སྟོན་པ། སངས་རྒྱས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་སྟོབས་དང་གྲགས་པ་དོན་ཡོད་པ་ཞེས་བྱ་བར་འཇིག་རྟེན་དུ་འབྱུང་བར་འགྱུར་རོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He will appear in the world as a thus-gone one, a worthy one, a perfect buddha, learned and virtuous, a blissful one, a knower of the world, an unsurpassed charioteer who tames beings, a teacher of gods and humans, a blessed buddha called Amogha­bala­kīrti.<tei:note xml:id="UT22084-061-004-156"/>
                </seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.105.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེའི་འཁོར་དུ་འདུས་པ་ཡང་མཐའ་ཡས་པར་འགྱུར་ཏེ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Those who gather in his retinue will be infinite in number, and</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.105.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱང་ཕྱིར་མི་ལྡོག་པའི་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཤ་སྟག་གོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>all of them will be bodhisattvas who do not regress.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.105.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་དག་ཀྱང་འོད་མཐའ་ཡས་པ་དང་། ཚེ་དཔག་ཏུ་མེད་པར་འགྱུར་རོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They will be infinitely radiant and have immeasurable lifespans.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.105.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ལ་འཇམ་དཔལ་གཞོན་ནུར་གྱུར་པས་འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་གསོལ་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-061-004-157"/>Mañjuśrī then asked the Blessed One,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.105.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཆོས་ཀྱི་རྣམ་གྲངས་འདིའི་མིང་ཅི་ལགས། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Blessed One, what is the name of this Dharma teaching?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.105.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདི་ཇི་ལྟར་གཟུང་བར་བགྱི། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>How should it be remembered?”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.105.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་བཀའ་སྩལ་པ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-061-004-158"/>The Blessed One replied,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.105.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའི་སྤྱོད་པ་བསྟན་པ་ཞེས་བྱ་བར་ཟུང་ཤིག །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“You should remember it as Teaching the Practice of a Bodhisattva, or</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.105.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཆོས་ཉིད་ཀྱི་སྐྱེ་བོ་ཞེས་བྱ་བར་ཡང་ཟུང་ཤིག །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>you can also remember it as A Being Born from Reality.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.105.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་དགེ་སློང་གི་དགེ་འདུན་དང་ཐབས་ཅིག་ཏུ་བསོད་སྙོམས་བཞེས་ནས་གཤེགས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-061-004-159"/>After the Blessed One and the saṅgha of monks had eaten their alms they went on their way, and</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.105.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་དེ་སྐད་ཅེས་བཀའ་སྩལ་ནས། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>after the Blessed One had said this,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.105.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་རིན་ཆེན་བྱིན་དང་། ཐམས་ཅད་དང་ལྡན་པའི་འཁོར་དེ་དང་། ལྷ་དང་། མི་དང་། ལྷ་མ་ཡིན་དང་། དྲི་ཟར་བཅས་པའི་འཇིག་རྟེན་ཡི་རངས་ཏེ། བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་གསུངས་པ་ལ་མངོན་པར་བསྟོད་དོ།། །།</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>the bodhisattva Ratnadatta, the entire retinue, and the world with its gods, humans, asuras, and gandharvas rejoiced and praised the Blessed One’s words.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.105.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཕགས་པ་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའི་སྤྱོད་པ་བསྟན་པ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་ཐེག་པ་ཆེན་པོའི་མདོ་རྫོགས་སོ།། །།</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>This concludes the noble Great Vehicle sūtra “Teaching the Practice of a Bodhisattva.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.105.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྒྱ་གར་གྱི་མཁན་པོ་ཛི་ན་མི་ཏྲ་དང་། པྲཛྙཱ་ཝརྨ་དང་། ཞུ་ཆེན་གྱི་ལོ་ཙྪ་བ་བན་དེ་ཡེ་ཤེས་སྡེ་ལ་སོགས་པས་བསྒྱུར་ཅིང་ཞུས་ཏེ་གཏན་ལ་ཕབ་པ།། །།</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-061-004-160"/>It was translated, edited, and finalized by the Indian scholars Jinamitra and Prajñāvarman and the chief editor-translator Bandé Yeshé Dé and others.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
</body>
</tmx>