<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tmx xmlns="http://www.lisa.org/tmx14" xmlns:eft="http://read.84000.co/ns/1.0" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" version="1.4b">
    <header creationtool="linguae-dharmae/84000" creationtoolversion="2.16.12a" datatype="PlainText" segtype="block" adminlang="en-us" srclang="bo" o-tmf="TEI" eft:text-id="UT22084-051-006" eft:text-version="v-1.0.4-2022" eft:source-ref="/db/apps/84000-data/uploads/linguae-dharmae/aligned/31-10-2022/complete/toh118-bo_aligned.txt" eft:seconds-to-revise="1.272"/>
    <body>
        <!--<tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-1">
            <tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>༄༅༅། །རྒྱ་གར་སྐད་དུ། ཨཱརྱ་རཏྣ་ཀོ་ཊི་ནཱ་མ་མ་ཧཱ་ཡཱ་ན་སཱུ་ཏྲ། བོད་སྐད་དུ།</seg></tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en"><seg/></tuv>
        </tu>-->
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-1">
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">translation</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཕགས་པ་རིན་པོ་ཆེའི་མཐའ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་ཐེག་པ་ཆེན་པོའི་མདོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The Noble Great Vehicle Sūtra Infinite Jewels</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-2">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-19</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སངས་རྒྱས་དང་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཐམས་ཅད་ལ་ཕྱག་འཚལ་ལོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Homage to all buddhas and bodhisattvas!</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-3">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-21</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།འདི་སྐད་བདག་གིས་ཐོས་པ་དུས་གཅིག་ན།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Thus did I hear at one time.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-4">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-21</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་རྒྱལ་པོའི་ཁབ་ན་བྱ་རྒོད་ཀྱི་ཕུང་པོའི་རི་ལ་དགེ་སློང་ལྔ་བརྒྱ་ཐམ་པའི་དགེ་སློང་གི་དགེ་འདུན་ཆེན་པོ་དང་ཐབས་ཅིག་ཏུ་བཞུགས་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The Blessed One was dwelling on Vulture Peak Mountain near Rājagṛha, together with a great saṅgha of five hundred monks.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-5">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-21</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་འཇམ་དཔལ་གཞོན་ནུར་གྱུར་པ་མཚན་མོ་སྲོད་ལ་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱི་བཞུགས་ཁང་ག་ལ་བ་དེར་སོང་སྟེ་ཕྱིན་ནས་བཞུགས་ཁང་གི་སྒོ་དྲུང་ན་འགྲེང་སྟེ་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ལ་སྡོད་དོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>At dusk Youthful Mañjuśrī went to the Blessed One’s residence, stood at the door, and praised the Blessed One.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-6">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-21</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེའི་ཚེ་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་རིན་པོ་ཆེའི་མཐའ་ཞེས་བྱ་བའི་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་ལ་སྙོམས་པར་ཞུགས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>At that time, the Blessed One was resting in equipoise in the absorption known as infinite jewels</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-7">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-21</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་དྲན་པ་དང་མཁྱེན་བཞིན་དུ་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་དེ་ལས་བཞེངས་ནས་འཇམ་དཔལ་གཞོན་ནུར་གྱུར་པ་སྒོ་ན་འདུག་པ་གཟིགས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Mindful and alert, the Blessed One then arose from that absorption.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-8">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-21</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།གཟིགས་ནས་ཀྱང་འཇམ་དཔལ་ཁྱོད་ནང་དུ་ཤོག་ཅེས་དེ་སྐད་ཅེས་བཀའ་སྩལ་ཏོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He saw that Youthful Mañjuśrī was at the door and said, “Please come inside, Mañjuśrī.”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-9">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-23</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ལེགས་སོ་ལེགས་སོ་ཞེས་གསོལ་ཏེ། འཇམ་དཔལ་གཞོན་ནུར་གྱུར་པས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱི་ལྟར་མཉན་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ག་ལ་བ་དེར་སོང་སྟེ་ཕྱིན་ནས།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Very well, Blessed One, very well,” replied Youthful Mañjuśrī, and, heeding the Blessed One’s words, he went before the Blessed One.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-10">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-23</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱི་ཞབས་ལ་མགོ་བོས་ཕྱག་འཚལ་ཏེ་ཕྱོགས་གཅིག་ཏུ་འགྲེང་ངོ་།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He prostrated, placing his head at the Blessed One’s feet, and stood to one side.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-11">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-23</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།འཇམ་དཔལ་གཞོན་ནུར་གྱུར་པ་ཕྱོགས་གཅིག་ཏུ་འགྲེང་བ་དང་། བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་སྟན་ལ་འདུག་ཅེས་གནང་བ་མཛད་དོ། །བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་གནང་བས་དེ་ནས་འཇམ་དཔལ་གཞོན་ནུར་གྱུར་པ། བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ག་ལ་བ་དེ་ལོགས་སུ་ཐལ་མོ་སྦྱར་བ་བཏུད་དེ་ཕྱོགས་གཅིག་ཏུ་འདུག་གོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The Blessed One gave Youthful Mañjuśrī permission to sit, and, with the Blessed One’s permission, Youthful Mañjuśrī bowed with palms joined and then sat to one side of the Blessed One.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-12">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-24</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཕྱོགས་གཅིག་ཏུ་འདུག་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ལ་འཇམ་དཔལ་གཞོན་ནུར་གྱུར་པས་འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་གསོལ་ཏོ། །བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ད་གདོད་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་གང་གིས་བཞུགས་བཞུགས་པ་ལས་བཞེངས་ལགས།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Sitting to one side, Youthful Mañjuśrī asked the Blessed One, “What was the absorption from which you just arose, Blessed One?”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-13">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-25</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་སྐད་ཅེས་གསོལ་པ་དང་། བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་འཇམ་དཔལ་གཞོན་ནུར་གྱུར་པ་ལ་འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་བཀའ་སྩལ་ཏོ། །འཇམ་དཔལ་རིན་པོ་ཆེའི་མཐའ་ཞེས་བྱ་བའི་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་ཡོད་དོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Mañjuśrī, there is an absorption called infinite jewels ,” replied the Blessed One to Youthful Mañjuśrī.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-14">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-25</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་དེས་ང་ད་གདོད་གནས་གནས་པ་ལས་ལངས་སོ། །གསོལ་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“That is the absorption from which I just arose.”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-15">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-26</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཅིའི་སླད་དུ་དེ་ལ་རིན་པོ་ཆེའི་མཐའ་ཞེས་བགྱི་ལགས།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Blessed One, why is it called infinite jewels</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-16">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-26</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་བཀའ་སྩལ་པ། འཇམ་དཔལ་འདི་ལྟ་སྟེ། དཔེར་ན་ནོར་བུ་རིན་པོ་ཆེ་ཤིན་ཏུ་དག་ཅིང་ཤིན་ཏུ་བྱི་དོར་བྱས་པ་ས་ཕྱོགས་མཉམ་པ་ལ་བཞག་ན་དེ་གང་དང་གང་ཁོ་ནར་བཞག་པ་དེ་དང་དེར་རིན་པོ་ཆེ་བྱེ་བ་གནས་པར་འགྱུར་རོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The Blessed One responded, “Mañjuśrī, take as an analogy an exceedingly pure and well-polished precious jewel. If it is placed on level ground, then wherever it is placed, there will be untold millions of jewels.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-17">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-26</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།འཇམ་དཔལ་དེ་བཞིན་དུ་ང་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་དེ་ལ་གནས་ནས་ཤར་ཕྱོགས་སུ་བལྟས་ཏེ། ཤར་ཕྱོགས་སུ་བལྟས་ན་ངས་འཇིག་རྟེན་གྱི་ཁམས་དཔག་ཏུ་མེད་གྲངས་མེད་པ་དག་ན་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་དགྲ་བཅོམ་པ་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་སངས་རྒྱས་ཆོས་སྟོན་ཅིང་བཞུགས་པ་དག་མཐོང་ངོ་།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>In the same way, Mañjuśrī, when I remain in this absorption and look to the east, I see thus-gone ones, worthy ones, perfect buddhas abiding and teaching the Dharma in countless, innumerable world systems.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-18">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-26</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་བཞིན་དུ་ལྷོ་ཕྱོགས་དང་། ནུབ་ཕྱོགས་དང་། བྱང་ཕྱོགས་དང་། འོག་དང་། སྟེང་ནས་ཕྱོགས་བཅུའི་བར་དུ་བལྟས་ན་ངས་འཇིག་རྟེན་གྱི་ཁམས་དཔག་ཏུ་མེད་པ་དག་ན་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་དགྲ་བཅོམ་པ་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་སངས་རྒྱས་ཆོས་སྟོན་ཅིང་བཞུགས་པ་དག་མཐོང་ངོ་།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>It is the same to the south, west, north, below, and above. When I look in the ten directions, I see thus-gone ones, worthy ones, perfect buddhas abiding and teaching the Dharma in boundless world systems.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-19">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-26</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།འཇམ་དཔལ་ངས་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་འདི་ལ་གནས་ནས་གང་ཡང་དག་པའི་མཐའ་མ་ཡིན་པའི་ཆོས་དེ་གང་ཡང་ཡང་དག་པར་རྗེས་སུ་མ་མཐོང་ངོ་།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Remaining in this absorption, Mañjuśrī, I do not actually see any phenomenon whatsoever that is not the limit of reality.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-20">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-26</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།འཇམ་དཔལ་ཡང་དག་པའི་མཐའི་ཕྱག་རྒྱ་འདི་ངས་ཕྱག་རྒྱར་བཞག་སྟེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Mañjuśrī, I posit this seal of the limit of reality as my seal.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-21">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-26</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དད་པ་ཅན་གྱི་རིགས་ཀྱི་བུ་རྣམས་དང་། རིགས་ཀྱི་བུ་མོ་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་ཕྱག་རྒྱ་འདི་ལ་སྤྱད་ན་སྤོབས་པ་མི་ཆོད་པ་འཛིན་པར་འགྱུར་རོ། །གསོལ་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Faithful noble sons and daughters who engage in this seal will gain uninterrupted eloquence.”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-22">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-28</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་བདག་སྤོབས་ལགས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Blessed One, I have something to say.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-23">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-28</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།བདེ་བར་གཤེགས་པ་སྤོབས་ལགས་སོ། །བཀའ་སྩལ་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Well-Gone One, I have something to say.”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-24">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-28</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་ཁྱོད་སྤོབས་པར་གྱིས་ཤིག །གསོལ་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Then speak, Mañjuśrī.”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-25">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-30</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་དཔེར་བགྱི་ན་ནོར་བུ་རིན་པོ་ཆེ་དེ་ཉིད་ངོས་གང་དང་གང་ཁོ་ནས་ཕབ་སྟེ་གཞག་པའི་རིན་པོ་ཆེའི་ངོས་དེ་དང་དེ་ཁོ་ན་འབབ་ཅིང་གནས་པར་འགྱུར་ལགས་སོ། །བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་དེ་བཞིན་དུ་ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་ནི་ཡང་དག་པའི་མཐའ་ཁོ་ནས་གནས་ལགས་སོ། །བཀའ་སྩལ་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Blessed One, take as an analogy that very same precious jewel. Whatever facet it is set down upon, it will rest on precisely that facet of the precious jewel. Blessed One, in the same way, all phenomena abide only as the limit of reality.”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-26">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-32</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་ཁྱོད་ཀྱིས་ཡང་དག་པའི་མཐའ་ཤེས་སམ། གསོལ་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Mañjuśrī, do you know the limit of reality?”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-27">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-32</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་འཚལ་ལགས་སོ། །བཀའ་སྩལ་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“I do, Blessed One.”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-28">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-34</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་འོ་ན་ཡང་དག་པའི་མཐའ་གང་ན་འདུག །གསོལ་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Well then, Mañjuśrī, where is the limit of reality?”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-29">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-34</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཡང་དག་པའི་མཐའ་ནི་བདག་གི་མཐའ་གང་ན་མཆིས་པ་དེ་ན་མཆིས་ལགས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Blessed One, the limit of reality is wherever my limit is.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-30">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-34</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཡང་དག་པའི་མཐའ་ནི་སོ་སོའི་སྐྱེ་བོའི་ཆོས་རྣམས་གང་ན་མ་མཆིས་པ་དེ་ན་མཆིས་ལགས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The limit of reality is wherever the phenomena of ordinary beings are not.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-31">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-34</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཡང་དག་པའི་མཐའ་ནི་ལས་སམ། རྣམ་པར་སྨིན་པ་ཡང་མ་ལགས་ལ་ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱི་མཐའ་ཡང་དེ་ཁོ་ན་ལགས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The limit of reality is not karma or ripening but only the limit of all phenomena.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-32">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-34</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་གང་དག་དེ་ལྟར་མོས་པ་དེ་དག་ནི་གང་ལས་ཀྱང་རྣམ་པར་གྲོལ་བ་མ་མཆིས་ལགས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Blessed One, those who have such conviction are not liberated from anything at all.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-33">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-34</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།གང་དག་གང་ལས་ཀྱང་གྲོལ་བ་མ་མཆིས་པ་དེ་དག་ནི་ལོག་པ་ལས་རྣམ་པར་གྲོལ་བ་ལགས་སོ། །གང་དག་ལོག་པ་ལས་རྣམ་པར་གྲོལ་བ་དེ་དག་ནི་ཡང་དག་པར་རྣམ་པར་གྲོལ་བ་ལགས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Those who are not liberated from anything at all are liberated from being mistaken. Those who are liberated from being mistaken are truly liberated.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-34">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-34</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།གང་དག་ཡང་དག་པར་རྣམ་པར་གྲོལ་བ་དེ་དག་ནི་སྤྱོད་ཡུལ་མ་ལགས་པ་ལ་ཞུགས་པ་ལགས་སོ། །གང་དག་སྤྱོད་ཡུལ་མ་ལགས་པ་ལ་ཞུགས་པ་དེ་དག་ནི་ཡང་དག་པར་ཞུགས་པ་ལགས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Those who are truly liberated have entered what is not an objective world. Those who have entered what is not an objective world have entered into reality.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-35">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-34</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ཅིའི་སླད་དུ་ཞེ་ན།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>And why?</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-36">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-34</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་སྤྱོད་ཡུལ་མ་ལགས་པ་ཞེས་བགྱི་བ་ནི་སྤྱོད་ཡུལ་དེས་བགྱིས་ལགས་པ་སྟེ། དེའི་སླད་དུ་སྤྱོད་ཡུལ་མ་ལགས་པ་ཞེས་འདོགས་ལགས་སོ། །བཀའ་སྩལ་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Blessed One, when one thinks, ‘It is not an objective world,’ then one has already made it an objective world. It is on account of that that we label it not an objective world</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-37">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-38</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་སྤྱོད་ཡུལ་མ་ཡིན་པ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་དེ་གང་གི་ཚིག་བླ་དགས་ཡིན། གསོལ་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Mañjuśrī, what does not an objective world refer to?”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-38">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-38</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་སྤྱོད་ཡུལ་མ་ལགས་པ་ཞེས་བགྱི་བ་དེ་ནི་ཡང་དག་པའི་མཐའི་ཚིག་བླ་དགས་ལགས་སོ། །བཀའ་སྩལ་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Blessed One, not an objective world refers to the limit of reality.”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-39">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-40</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་ལམ་སྒོམ་པ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་དེ་གང་གི་ཚིག་བླ་དགས་ཡིན། གསོལ་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Mañjuśrī, what does cultivating the path refer to?”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-40">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-40</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ལམ་བསྒོམ་པ་ཞེས་བགྱི་བ་དེ་ནི་ལམ་སྒོམ་པ་མ་མཆིས་པའི་ཚིག་བླ་དགས་ལགས་སོ། །བཀའ་སྩལ་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Blessed One, cultivating the path refers to not cultivating the path.”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-41">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-42</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་ཁྱོད་ལས་དང་པོ་པའི་རིགས་ཀྱི་བུ་རྣམས་དང་། རིགས་ཀྱི་བུ་མོ་རྣམས་ལ་ཆོས་ཇི་ལྟར་སྟོན། གསོལ་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Mañjuśrī,  how do you teach the Dharma to noble sons and daughters who are beginners?”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-42">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-42</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་བདག་ནི་ལས་དང་པོ་པའི་རིགས་ཀྱི་བུ་རྣམས་དང་། རིགས་ཀྱི་བུ་མོ་རྣམས་ལ་འཇིག་ཚོགས་དོར་དུ་མ་མཆིས་པར་ཆོས་སྟོན་ལགས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Blessed One, I teach the Dharma to noble sons and daughters who are beginners by teaching that the composite person should not be discarded.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-43">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-42</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།བདག་ནི་འདོད་ཆགས་དང་། ཞེ་སྡང་དང་། གཏི་མུག་རྣམས་སྤང་དུ་མ་མཆིས་པར་ཆོས་སྟོན་པ་ལགས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>When I teach the Dharma, I teach that attachment, aversion, and delusion are not to be abandoned.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-44">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-42</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ཅིའི་སླད་དུ་ཞེ་ན།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Why is this?</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-45">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-42</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཆོས་འདི་རྣམས་ཀྱི་རང་བཞིན་གང་ལགས་པ་དེ་ནི་སྤང་བར་རྔོ་མི་ཐོགས་པའི་སླད་དུ་ལགས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Because, Blessed One, it is impossible to abandon whatever is the nature of these phenomena.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-46">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-42</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་འཇིག་ཚོགས་སམ། འཇིག་ཚོགས་ཀུན་འབྱུང་བ་སྤོང་བར་འཚལ་བ་དེ་ནི་ཡང་དག་པའི་མཐའ་སྤོང་བར་བས་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Blessed One, to seek to abandon the composite person or the origin of the composite person would amount to abandoning the limit of reality.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-47">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-42</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་བདག་ནི་ལས་དང་པོ་པའི་རིགས་ཀྱི་བུ་རྣམས་དང་། རིགས་ཀྱི་བུ་མོ་རྣམས་ལ་མངོན་པར་ཞེན་པ་མ་མཆིས་པའི་ཚུལ་གྱིས་སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱི་ཆོས་རྣམས་གཟུང་བར་མི་བགྱི་བའམ། མངོན་སུམ་དུ་མི་བགྱི་བ་དང་། སོ་སོའི་སྐྱེ་བོའི་ཆོས་རྣམས་ལྷག་པར་མི་དམིགས་པའམ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Rather, Blessed One, to noble sons and daughters who are beginners I teach that, in a manner free from clinging, the Buddha’s attributes are not to be taken up or actualized, and the attributes of ordinary beings should not be grasped or abandoned.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-48">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-42</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྤང་བར་མི་བགྱི་བ་དེ་ལྟ་བུར་ཆོས་སྟོན་ལགས་ན་གདུལ་བ་ལས་དང་པོ་པ་རྣམས་ལ་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཇི་ལྟར་ཆོས་སྟོན་པར་མཛད་ལགས། བཀའ་སྩལ་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Blessed One, how do you teach the Dharma to those who are beginners?”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-49">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-45</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་ང་ནི་གཟུགས་རྣམ་པར་འཇིག་པ་མེད་པ་དང་། སྐྱེ་བ་མེད་པར་ཆོས་སྟོན་ཏོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Mañjuśrī, I teach the Dharma whereby form does not disintegrate and is unborn.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-50">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-45</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཚོར་བ་དང་། འདུ་ཤེས་དང་། འདུ་བྱེད་རྣམས་དང་། རྣམ་པར་ཤེས་པ་རྣམ་པར་འཇིག་པ་མེད་པ་དང་། སྐྱེ་བ་མེད་པར་ཆོས་སྟོན་ཏོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>I teach that feelings, perceptions, and formations, as well as consciousness, do not disintegrate and are unborn.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-51">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-45</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།འདོད་ཆགས་དང་། ཞེ་སྡང་དང་། གཏི་མུག་རྣམས་རྣམ་པར་འཇིག་པ་མེད་པ་དང་། སྐྱེ་བ་མེད་པ་དང་། བསམ་གྱིས་མི་ཁྱབ་པའི་ཆོས་རྣམས་ཀྱང་ཐོབ་པ་མེད་པར་ཆོས་སྟོན་ཏོ། །ངས་ནི་འདི་ལྟར་ཆོས་གང་ཡང་མ་བཤིག་མ་བསྐྱེད་པ་དེ་ལྟར་བླ་ན་མེད་པ་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་བྱང་ཆུབ་མངོན་པར་རྫོགས་པར་སངས་རྒྱས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>I teach the Dharma whereby attachment, aversion, and delusion do not disintegrate and are unborn, and I also teach that the inconceivable attributes are unattainable. It is in this way, without destroying or producing any attribute whatsoever, that I awakened to unsurpassed and perfect buddhahood.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-52">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-45</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།འཇམ་དཔལ་སངས་རྒྱས་ཉིད་ཅེས་བྱ་བ་དེ་ནི་ཆོས་ཀྱི་དབྱིངས་ཀྱི་ཚིག་བླ་དགས་ལགས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Mañjuśrī, buddhahood is a term for the realm of phenomena.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-53">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-45</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།སྟོབས་རྣམས་དང་། མི་འཇིགས་པ་རྣམས་དང་། མ་འདྲེས་པ་ལ་ཐུག་པའི་སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱི་ཆོས་གང་དག་ཡིན་པ་དེ་དག་ཀྱང་ཆོས་ཀྱི་དབྱིངས་ཁོ་ན་ཡིན་པར་ཁོང་དུ་ཆུད་པར་བྱའོ། །ངས་ནི་ཆོས་ཀྱི་དབྱིངས་ལ་འདི་ལྟ་སྟེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>One should understand that the attributes of a buddha, such as the powers, fearlessnesses,  and the unique attributes, are also nothing but the realm of phenomena.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-54">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-45</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སོ་སོའི་སྐྱེ་བོའི་ཆོས་རྣམས་སམ། དགྲ་བཅོམ་པའི་ཆོས་རྣམས་སམ། རང་སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱི་ཆོས་རྣམས་སམ། སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱི་ཆོས་རྣམས་ཀྱང་རུང་སྟེ། དེ་དག་ཐ་དད་པར་ཡང་དག་པར་རྗེས་སུ་མི་མཐོང་ངོ་།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>With regard to the realm of phenomena, I do not see any distinct attributes of ordinary beings, worthy ones, solitary buddhas, or buddhas.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-55">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-45</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ཅིའི་ཕྱིར་ཞེ་ན།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>How is this so?</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-56">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-45</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་དབྱིངས་དེ་ལ་ནི་བྱེ་བྲག་མེད་དེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Mañjuśrī, in that realm there are no distinctions;</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-57">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-45</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདི་ལྟ་སྟེ། ཆོས་ཀྱི་དབྱིངས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>such is the realm of phenomena.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-58">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-45</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཆོས་ཀྱི་དབྱིངས་ནི་མ་འདྲེས་པའི་དབྱིངས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The realm of phenomena is an unadulterated realm.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-59">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-46</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།འཇམ་དཔལ་འདི་ལྟ་སྟེ། དཔེར་ན་ཆུ་ཀླུང་མིང་ཐ་དད་པ་དང་། ཁ་དོག་ཐ་དད་པ་དང་། རོ་ཐ་དད་པ་རྒྱ་མཚོའི་ནང་དུ་བབ་པ་རྣམས་ལ་ནི་འདི་ལྟ་སྟེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“As an analogy, Mañjuśrī, consider rivers that have distinct names, colors, and waters.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-60">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-46</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདི་ནི་གང་གཱའོ་ཞེའམ་སི་ཏའོ་ཞེའམ། ཡ་མུ་ནའོ་ཞེས་བྱེ་བྲག་ཏུ་དབྱེ་བའམ་ཐ་དད་དུ་བྱར་མི་ནུས་སོ། །འཇམ་དཔལ་དེ་བཞིན་དུ་མིང་ཐ་དད་པའི་ཆོས་རྣམས་ཀྱང་ཆོས་ཀྱི་དབྱིངས་ལ་འདི་ནི་སོ་སོའི་སྐྱེ་བོའི་ཆོས་རྣམས་སོ་ཞེའམ། ཉན་ཐོས་དང་། རང་སངས་རྒྱས་དང་། བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་དང་། སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱི་ཆོས་རྣམས་སོ་ཞེས་ཐ་དད་པར་གདགས་པར་མི་ནུས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>When they flow into the ocean it becomes impossible to differentiate them or identify them, saying, ‘This is the Ganges,’ ‘This is the Sītā,’ or ‘This is the Yamunā.’ Similarly, Mañjuśrī, within the realm of phenomena, all those phenomena that have different names cannot be distinctly labeled, saying, ‘These are the attributes of ordinary beings, and here are those of the hearers, solitary buddhas, bodhisattvas, and buddhas.’</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-61">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-47</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།འཇམ་དཔལ་འདི་ལྟ་སྟེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Mañjuśrī, consider this analogy.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-62">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-47</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དཔེར་ན་འབྲུའི་ཕུང་པོ་སྣ་ཚོགས་ལ་ནི་འདི་ནི་འབྲུ་ཆེ་གེ་མོ་ཞིག་གི་ཕུང་པོའོ། །འདི་ནི་ཆེ་གེ་མོ་ཞིག་གོ་ཞེས་གདགས་སུ་ཡོད་པ་བཞིན་དུ་ཆོས་ཀྱི་དབྱིངས་ལ་ནི་འདི་དག་སོ་སོའི་སྐྱེ་བོའི་ཆོས་རྣམས་སོ་ཞེའམ། ཉན་ཐོས་དང་། རང་སངས་རྒྱས་དང་། བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་དང་། སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱི་ཆོས་རྣམས་སོ་ཞེས་ཐ་དད་པར་གདགས་པར་མི་ནུས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>If you have different heaps of grain, you can label them, saying, ‘This is a heap of such-and-such a grain, and this is such-and-such.’ However, within the realm of phenomena you cannot make such distinctions and point out the individual attributes of ordinary beings, hearers, solitary buddhas, bodhisattvas, and buddhas.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-63">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-48</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།འཇམ་དཔལ་འདི་ལྟ་སྟེ། དཔེར་ན་འབྲུའི་ཕུང་པོ་སྣ་ཚོགས་ལ་ནི་འདི་ནི་འབྲུ་ཆེ་གེ་མོ་ཞིག་གི་ཕུང་པོའོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Mañjuśrī, consider this analogy.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-64">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-48</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།འདི་ནི་ཆེ་གེ་མོ་ཞིག་གོ་ཞེས་གདགས་སུ་ཡོད་པ་བཞིན་དུ་ཆོས་ཀྱི་དབྱིངས་ལ་ནི་འདི་དག་ནི་སོ་སོའི་སྐྱེ་བོའི་ཆོས་རྣམས་སོ། །འདི་དག་ནི་དགྲ་བཅོམ་པའི་ཆོས་རྣམས་སོ། །འདི་དག་ནི་རང་སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱི་ཆོས་རྣམས་སོ། །འདི་དག་ནི་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའི་ཆོས་རྣམས་སོ། །འདི་དག་ནི་སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱི་ཆོས་རྣམས་སོ་ཞེས་ཐ་དད་པར་གདགས་པར་མི་ནུས་སོ། །འདི་ནི་ཆོས་ཀྱི་དབྱིངས་ཏེ་དེ་ནི་འདི་ན་འདུག་གོ་ཞེའམ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>If you have different heaps of grain, you can label them, saying, ‘This is a heap of such-and-such a grain, and this is such-and-such.’ However, within the realm of phenomena you cannot make such distinctions, saying, ‘These are the attributes of ordinary beings, these are the attributes of worthy ones, these are the attributes of solitary buddhas, these are the attributes of bodhisattvas,  and these are the attributes of buddhas.’ It cannot be pointed out or labeled, as by saying, ‘This is the realm of phenomena;</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-65">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-48</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ག་གེ་མོ་ཞིག་ན་འདུག་གོ་ཞེས་དེ་ལྟར་བསྟན་པའམ་གདགས་པར་མི་ནུས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>this is where it is’ or ‘It is in such-and-such a location.’ And why not?</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-66">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-48</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ཅིའི་ཕྱིར་ཞེ་ན། འདི་ལྟར་ཆོས་ཀྱི་དབྱིངས་ནི་བལྟར་མི་མཐོང་ཞིང་བསྟན་དུ་མེད་དེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Because the realm of phenomena cannot be seen and cannot be shown.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-67">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-48</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གདགས་པར་བྱ་བ་མ་ཡིན་ཞིང་གདགས་པ་ལས་ཡང་དག་པར་འདས་པའི་ཕྱིར་རོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>It is not something that can be labeled; it is beyond being labeled. “I have taught that beings are this realm.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-68">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-48</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།འགྲོ་བ་འདི་དེ་ལྟ་བུའི་དབྱིངས་ཡིན་པར་ངས་ཇི་སྐད་བསྟན་པ་ལ་གལ་ཏེ་མཚམས་མེད་པ་བྱེད་པ་དེ་ལྟར་མོས་ཏེ། མཚམས་མེད་པ་ཡང་དེ་ལྟ་བུའི་དབྱིངས་ཡིན་པར་ཤེས་ན། དེ་ཀུན་ནས་ཉོན་མོངས་པ་ཅན་དུ་མི་འགྱུར་རོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>If one commits an act of immediate retribution yet has conviction in this teaching and understands that acts of immediate retribution are also this realm, then one will not become defiled.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-69">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-48</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ཅིའི་ཕྱིར་ཞེ་ན།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>And why not?</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-70">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-48</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་མཚམས་མེད་པ་ནི་ཆོས་ཀྱི་དབྱིངས་དང་མཚུངས་པར་མཉམ་པའི་ཕྱིར་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Because, Mañjuśrī, the acts of immediate retribution are equivalent to the realm of phenomena.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-71">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-48</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདི་ལྟར་མཚམས་མེད་པའི་དབྱིངས་དང་། ཆོས་ཀྱི་དབྱིངས་འདི་ནི་གཉིས་སུ་མེད་ཅིང་གཉིས་སུ་དབྱེར་མེད་དེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>In this way, the realm of the acts of immediate retribution and the realm of phenomena are nondual and inseparable.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-72">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-48</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདི་ལ་ནི་འོང་བའམ། འགྲོ་བའམ། ཀུན་ནས་ལྡང་བ་མི་དམིགས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Here, coming, going, or appearing are not apprehended.”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-73">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-50</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་དེ་སྐད་ཅེས་བཀའ་སྩལ་པ་དང་། འཇམ་དཔལ་གཞོན་ནུར་གྱུར་པས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ལ་འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་གསོལ་ཏོ། །བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་བདག་གིས་ཀྱང་ཆོས་ཀྱི་དབྱིངས་ངན་སོང་དུ་མཆི་བའམ། མཐོ་རིས་སུ་མཆི་བའམ། མྱ་ངན་ལས་འདས་པར་མཆི་བར་མ་མཐོང་ལགས་སོ། །བཀའ་སྩལ་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Then Youthful Mañjuśrī said to the Blessed One, “Blessed One, I also do not see the realm of phenomena going to the lower realms, the higher realms, or nirvāṇa.”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-74">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-51</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་གལ་ཏེ། ལ་ལ་ཞིག་ཁྱོད་ལ་འདི་སྐད་དུ་འདྲི་སྟེ། ཁྱོད་ཀྱི་སྟོན་པ་འགྲོ་བ་དྲུག་དང་ལྡན་པའི་འཁོར་བ་ཇི་ལྟར་འདོགས་ཞེས་དེ་སྐད་དྲིས་ན་འཇམ་དཔལ་ཁྱོད་ཀྱིས་ཇི་སྐད་ལན་གདབ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Mañjuśrī, suppose someone were to ask how your teacher designates saṃsāra with its six classes of beings. What would you answer?”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-75">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-52</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གསོལ་པ། བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་དེ་སྐད་དུ་སྨྲས་ན་བདག་གིས་འདི་སྐད་དུ་ལན་གདབ་པར་བགྱི་སྟེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Blessed One, if I were asked such a question this would be my reply:</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-76">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-52</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དཔེར་ན་མི་གཉིད་ཀྱིས་ལོག་པའི་རྨི་ལམ་དུ་སེམས་ཅན་དམྱལ་བའམ། དུད་འགྲོའི་སྐྱེ་གནས་སམ། ཡི་དགས་ཀྱི་ཡུལ་ལམ། ལྷ་མ་ཡིན་གྱི་རིས་སམ། ལྷ་རྣམས་སམ། མི་རྣམས་མཐོང་ན།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Consider the analogy of a sleeping person who in dreams sees hell beings, animal realms, lands of hungry ghosts, classes of asuras, gods, or people.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-77">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-52</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཇི་ལྟར་གཡར་ལམ་རྨི་བའི་མིས་སྣ་ཚོགས་མཐོང་ཡང་གཡར་ལམ་སྣ་ཚོགས་མ་མཆིས་པ་དེ་བཞིན་དུ་བདག་གིས་འགྲོ་བ་ཐ་དད་པ་བསྟན་ཀྱང་ཆོས་ཀྱི་དབྱིངས་ཀྱི་ངོ་བོ་ཉིད་ཐ་དད་པ་གདགས་པར་རྔོ་མི་ཐོགས་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Blessed One, although the dreaming person sees myriad things, all the myriad things dreamed are not there. In the same way, although I teach distinct types of beings, it is impossible to designate distinct essences within the realm of phenomena.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-78">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-52</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ལྟ་ལགས་པས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་བདག་གིས་ནི་དེ་སྐད་འདྲི་བ་ལ་དེ་སྐད་ཅེས་ལན་གདབ་པར་བགྱི་ལགས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>That being so, Blessed One, that is how I would answer such a question.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-79">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-53</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་དེ་བཞིན་དུ་སངས་རྒྱས་རྣམས་དང་། བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་རྣམས་དང་། རང་སངས་རྒྱས་རྣམས་དང་། ཉན་ཐོས་ཀྱི་ཡོངས་སུ་མྱ་ངན་ལས་འདས་པ་ཡང་ཐ་དད་པར་གདགས་པར་རྔོ་མི་ཐོགས་ལགས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Similarly, Blessed One, the parinirvāṇa of the buddhas, bodhisattvas, solitary buddhas, and hearers cannot be distinctly labeled.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-80">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-53</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་དེ་དག་གིས་གནས་པ་དག་ཀྱང་ཐ་དད་པར་གདགས་པར་རྔོ་མི་ཐོགས་ལགས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Blessed One, their ways of abiding also cannot be distinctly labeled.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-81">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-53</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ཅིའི་སླད་དུ་ཞེ་ན།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>And why not?</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-82">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-53</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདི་ལྟར་ཆོས་ཀྱི་དབྱིངས་ལས་ཐ་མི་དད་པའི་སླད་དུ་ལགས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Because they are not distinct from the realm of phenomena.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-83">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-53</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་དཔེར་བགྱི་ན་རྒྱ་མཚོ་ཆེན་པོའི་རིན་པོ་ཆེ་སྣ་ཚོགས་དུང་དང་། མན་ཤེལ་དང་། བྱི་རུ་ལ་སོགས་པ་ཐ་མ་དང་། འབྲིང་དང་། མཆོག་རྣམས་ལ་འདི་ནི་རིན་པོ་ཆེ་ཆེ་གེ་མོ་ཞིག་གོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>To give an analogy, Blessed One, there are various precious substances in the sea—conch shells, crystal, coral, and the like—of lesser, middling, or superior quality.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-84">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-53</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།འདི་ནི་རིན་པོ་ཆེ་ཆེ་གེ་མོ་ཞིག་གོ་ཞེས་ཐ་དད་པར་གདགས་སུ་མཆིས་ལགས་ཀྱི།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>These can all be distinctly labeled, saying, ‘This is such-and-such precious substance;</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-85">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-53</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཆོས་ཀྱི་དབྱིངས་ལ་ནི་དེ་ལྟར་ཐ་དད་པར་གདགས་པའི་རྔོ་མི་ཐོགས་ལ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>this is such-and-such precious substance.’ However, such distinct labeling cannot be applied to the realm of phenomena, where such labeled distinctions cannot be differentiated.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-86">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-53</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གདགས་པ་དེ་ལ་ཡང་ཐ་དད་པར་དབྱེར་མ་མཆིས་ལགས་སོ། །དེ་ལ་ནི་འཆི་འཕོ་བ་དང་། སྐྱེ་བ་ཐ་དད་པར་གདགས་པའི་རྔོ་མི་ཐོགས་ལགས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Therein, death, transmigration, and birth cannot be distinctly labeled.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-87">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-53</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ཅིའི་སླད་དུ་ཞེ་ན།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Why is that?</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-88">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-53</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཆོས་ཀྱི་དབྱིངས་ལ་ནི་འཆི་འཕོའམ། སྐྱེ་བའམ། ཀུན་ནས་ཉོན་མོངས་པའམ། རྣམ་པར་བྱང་བ་མ་མཆིས་པའི་སླད་དུ་ལགས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Because the realm of phenomena is without death, transmigration, birth, pollution, and purification.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-89">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-53</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཆོས་ཀྱི་དབྱིངས་ནི་ཀུན་ནས་ཉོན་མོངས་པ་ཅན་མ་ལགས།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The realm of phenomena is not polluted.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-90">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-53</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཆོས་ཀྱི་དབྱིངས་ནི་འདྲེས་པ་མ་ལགས་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The realm of phenomena is not adulterated.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-91">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-53</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཆོས་ཀྱི་དབྱིངས་ལ་ནི་གང་དག་སྤང་བར་བགྱི་བའམ། བསྐྱེད་པར་བགྱི་བའི་ཆོས་དེ་དག་མ་མཆིས་ལགས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Within the realm of phenomena there are no attributes to be relinquished or generated.”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-92">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-54</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་མཁྱེན་བཞིན་དུ་འཇམ་དཔལ་གཞོན་ནུར་གྱུར་པ་ལ་འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་བཀའ་སྩལ་ཏོ། །འཇམ་དཔལ་ཁྱོད་ཀྱིས་ཆོས་ཀྱི་དབྱིངས་ཤེས་སམ། གསོལ་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Then the Blessed One, though he already knew, asked Youthful Mañjuśrī, “Mañjuśrī, do you know the realm of phenomena?”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-93">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-54</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གལ་ཏེ་དམིགས་ན་བདག་གིས་འཚལ་ལགས་སོ། །བཀའ་སྩལ་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“If I were to apprehend it, I would know it.”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-94">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-56</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་འཇིག་རྟེན་གང་ལ་སྤྱོད་ཤེས་སམ། གསོལ་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Mañjuśrī, do you know the world that is experienced?”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-95">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-56</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་འཇིག་རྟེན་ནི་སྒྱུ་མ་སྤྲུལ་པའི་མི་གང་ཁོ་ན་ལ་སྤྱོད་པ་དེ་ལ་སྤྱོད་ལགས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Blessed One, the world is merely that which is experienced by people who are illusory apparitions.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-96">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-56</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་འཇིག་རྟེན་ཞེས་བགྱི་བ་དེ་ནི་མིང་ཙམ་དུ་བས་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Blessed One, what is called world is no more than a mere name.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-97">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-56</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བདག་གིས་ནི་གང་བསྟན་པར་བགྱི་བའི་འཇིག་རྟེན་གྱི་དངོས་པོ་དང་། འཇིག་རྟེན་གང་ལ་སྤྱོད་པ་ཡང་ཡང་དག་པར་རྗེས་སུ་མ་མཐོང་ལགས་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Apart from that I do not see any world that can be pointed out, or a world to experience.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-98">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-56</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བདག་གིས་ནི་འཇིག་རྟེན་གྱི་ཆོས་ཀྱི་དབྱིངས་ལས་ཐ་དད་པར་ཡང་དག་པར་རྗེས་སུ་མ་མཐོང་ལགས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>I do not see anything distinct from the world’s realm of phenomena.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-99">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-56</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ཅིའི་སླད་དུ་ཞེ་ན།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>And why not?</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-100">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-56</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མ་མཆིས་པའི་སླད་དུ་ལགས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Because there isn’t any.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-101">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-56</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་འཇིག་རྟེན་གང་ལ་སྤྱོད་ཅེས་བཀའ་སྩལ་པ་དེ་ཡང་། གཟུགས་ཀྱི་ངོ་བོ་ཉིད་གང་ལགས་པ་དེ་ལ་ནི་འཆི་འཕོ་དང་། སྐྱེ་བ་ཡང་མ་མཆིས།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Regarding the Blessed One’s statement about ‘the world that is experienced,’ the essence of form is without death, transmigration, or birth; it does not disintegrate or perish.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-102">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-56</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ལ་ནི་འཇིག་པའམ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>This being the case, what is there to experience?</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-103">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-56</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རབ་ཏུ་འཇིག་པ་ཡང་མ་མཆིས་ན་གང་ལ་སྤྱོད་པར་འགྱུར་ལགས། དེ་བཞིན་དུ་ཚོར་བ་དང་། འདུ་ཤེས་དང་། འདུ་བྱེད་དང་། རྣམ་པར་ཤེས་པ་རྣམས་ཀྱི་ངོ་བོ་ཉིད་གང་ལགས་པ་དེ་ནི་གཏན་མ་མཆིས་པའི་སླད་དུ་སྐྱེ་བའམ་འགག་པ་མ་མཆིས་ལ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Likewise, since the essence of feeling, perception, formation, and consciousness does not exist, there is no arising or ceasing.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-104">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-56</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མཚན་ཉིད་གཅིག་ལས་མི་འདའ་སྟེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>These things do not go beyond the single characteristic;</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-105">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-56</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདི་ལྟ་སྟེ་མཚན་ཉིད་གཅིག་པ་ལགས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>indeed, their characteristic is identical.”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-106">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-58</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།བཀའ་སྩལ་པ། འཇམ་དཔལ་འདི་ཇི་སྙམ་དུ་སེམས། ང་ད་ལྟར་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་དགྲ་བཅོམ་པ་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་སངས་རྒྱས་སུ་འགྱུར་བ་འདི་ལ་ཁྱོད་འདི་སྙམ་དུ་འདི་ཡོངས་སུ་མྱ་ངན་ལས་འདས་པར་འགྱུར་བའམ། མི་སྣང་བར་འགྱུར་རོ་སྙམ་དུ་སེམས་སམ། གསོལ་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Mañjuśrī, tell me, do you think that I, the Thus-Gone One, the Worthy One, the Perfect Buddha, will pass into parinirvāṇa or disappear?”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-107">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-59</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་དེ་ནི་མ་ལགས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“No, Blessed One, I do not.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-108">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-59</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ཅིའི་སླད་དུ་ཞེ་ན།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>And why not?</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-109">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-59</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཆོས་ཀྱི་དབྱིངས་ནི་ཡང་དག་པར་གྲུབ་པ་མ་ལགས་པའི་སླད་དུ་ལགས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Because the realm of phenomena is not truly established.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-110">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-59</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་གལ་ཏེ་ཆོས་ཀྱི་དབྱིངས་ཡང་དག་པར་གྲུབ་པ་ཞིག་ལགས་ན་ནི་དེའི་སླད་དུ་དེ་མི་འདའ་བར་ཡང་འགྱུར་བ་ཞིག་ན།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Blessed One, if the realm of phenomena were truly established, then it would not be something to pass beyond.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-111">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-59</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ལ་ནི་ཡང་དག་པར་གྲུབ་པ་མི་དམིགས་པ་སྟེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>However, it is not apprehended as something truly established.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-112">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-59</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་མི་གདའ་བའམ། ཡོངས་སུ་མྱ་ངན་ལས་འདའ་བར་ལྟ་ག་ལ་འགྱུར་ལགས།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Thus, how can one speak of not passing beyond or passing into parinirvāṇa?</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-113">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-59</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་ནི་དེ་ལྟ་བུའི་དབྱིངས་ལགས་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The Thus-Gone One is the realm of phenomena.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-114">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-59</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེའི་སླད་དུ་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ནི་སྐྱེས་པ་ཡང་མ་ལགས། ཡོངས་སུ་མྱ་ངན་ལས་འདའ་བར་མི་འགྱུར་ལགས་སོ། །བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་བཀའ་སྩལ་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>For that reason, the Blessed One is not born and does not pass into parinirvāṇa.”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-115">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-61</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་འོ་ན་ཁྱོད་འདས་པའི་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་གང་གཱའི་ཀླུང་གི་བྱེ་མ་སྙེད་པོ་དེ་དག་ཡོངས་སུ་མྱ་ངན་ལས་འདས་སོ་ཞེས་དེ་ལ་ཁྱོད་ཇི་ལྟར་མོས། གསོལ་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Well then, Mañjuśrī,” said the Blessed One, “how can you have conviction in the statement that the thus-gone ones of the past, equal in number to the grains of sand in the River Ganges, have passed into parinirvāṇa?”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-116">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-61</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གལ་ཏེ་དེ་དག་གི་སྐྱེ་བ་ཡང་དག་པར་རྗེས་སུ་མཐོང་ན་ནི་བདག་མོས་ལགས་སོ། །བཀའ་སྩལ་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“If I had beheld their birth, I would have conviction.”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-117">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-63</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཁྱོད་སོ་སོའི་སྐྱེ་བོ་ཤི་བ་རྣམས་ཉིད་མཚམས་སྦྱོར་བར་འདོད་དམ། གསོལ་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Do you maintain that ordinary beings are reborn after they die?”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-118">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-63</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་སོ་སོའི་སྐྱེ་བོ་ཉིད་ཀྱང་བདག་གིས་ཡང་དག་པར་རྗེས་སུ་མ་མཐོང་མི་དམིགས་ན་དེའི་ཉིང་མཚམས་སྦྱོར་བ་ལྟ་ག་ལ་དམིགས་ལགས། བཀའ་སྩལ་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Blessed One, since I do not see or apprehend ordinary beings, how could I possibly apprehend their rebirth?”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-119">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-63</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་ཆོས་གནས་པར་བཞེད་ཀྱིས་ཁྱོད་སྤོབས་པར་གྱིས་ཤིག །གསོལ་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Mañjuśrī, please expound on the Thus-Gone One’s assertion that phenomena abide.”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-120">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-66</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཅི་ཞིག་ལས་བརྩམས་ཏེ་སྤོབས་པར་བགྱི་ལགས། བཀའ་སྩལ་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Where should I begin my discourse?”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-121">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-66</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཆོས་ཀྱི་དབྱིངས་ལས་རྩོམས་ཤིག །གསོལ་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Start with the realm of phenomena.”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-122">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-68</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་གང་ཆོས་ཀྱི་དབྱིངས་མ་ལགས་པའི་ཆོས་དེ་བདག་གིས་ཡང་དག་པར་རྗེས་སུ་མ་མཐོང་ལགས་སོ། །བཀའ་སྩལ་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Blessed One, I do not actually see any phenomena that are not the realm of phenomena.”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-123">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-68</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་མངོན་པའི་ང་རྒྱལ་ཅན་རྣམས་སྐྲག་པར་འགྱུར་རོ། །གསོལ་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Mañjuśrī, those who are presumptuously arrogant will be frightened.”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-124">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-70</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་གལ་ཏེ་ཡང་དག་པའི་མཐའ་སྐྲག་པར་འགྱུར་ན་ནི་དེའི་སླད་དུ་མངོན་པའི་ང་རྒྱལ་ཅན་ཡང་སྐྲག་པར་འགྱུར་ལགས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Blessed One, if the limit of reality were to be frightened, then, based on that, those who are presumptuously arrogant would also be frightened.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-125">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-70</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ཅིའི་སླད་དུ་ཞེ་ན།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Why is this?</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-126">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-70</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཡང་དག་པའི་མཐའ་ཡང་གཞན་ལ་མངོན་པའི་ང་རྒྱལ་ཅན་ཡང་གཞན་པ་ནི་མ་ལགས་ཀྱི།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Blessed One, those who are presumptuously arrogant are not something other than the limit of reality.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-127">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-70</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མངོན་པའི་ང་རྒྱལ་ཅན་རྣམས་ཀྱི་མཐའ་གང་ལགས་པའི་མཐའ་དེ་ཉིད་ཡང་དག་པའི་མཐའ་ལགས་ལ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Whatever is the limit of those who are presumptuously arrogant, that very limit is the limit of reality.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-128">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-70</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡང་དག་པའི་མཐའ་གང་ལགས་པ་དེ་ཡང་ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱི་མཐའ་ལགས་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Moreover, that which is the limit of reality is also the limit of all phenomena.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-129">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-70</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེའི་སླད་དུ་མི་སྐྲག་ལགས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>For that reason, they are not frightened.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-130">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-70</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་ཡང་དག་པར་མ་བསྒྲུབས་པ་ཞེས་བགྱི་བ་འདི་ནི་རྡོ་རྗེའི་གཞི་ལགས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The statement ‘no phenomenon is truly established’ is a vajra basis.”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-131">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-71</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་བཀའ་སྩལ་པ། འཇམ་དཔལ་ཅིའི་ཕྱིར་ན་འདི་རྡོ་རྗེའི་གཞི་ཞེས་བྱ། གསོལ་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Mañjuśrī,” asked the Blessed One, “Why is this called a vajra basis</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-132">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-71</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་ནི་མི་ཕྱེད་པ་ལགས་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Blessed One, all phenomena are indestructible.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-133">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-71</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེའི་སླད་དུ་འདི་རྡོ་རྗེའི་གཞི་ལགས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>It is for this reason that it is called a vajra basis</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-134">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-71</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་བསམ་གྱིས་མི་ཁྱབ་པའི་སླད་དུ་ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་བསམ་གྱིས་མི་ཁྱབ་པ་འདི་ནི་རྡོ་རྗེའི་གཞི་ལགས་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Since the thus-gone ones are inconceivable, all phenomena are inconceivable. This is a vajra basis.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-135">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-71</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཅིའི་སླད་དུ་རྡོ་རྗེའི་གཞི་ཞེས་བགྱི་ཞེ་ན།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Why is this referred to as a vajra basis</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-136">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-71</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་སེམས་མ་མཆིས་པའི་སླད་དུ་ལགས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>It is because all phenomena are not mind.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-137">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-71</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་བྱང་ཆུབ་ཅེས་བགྱི་བ་འདི་ནི་རྡོ་རྗེའི་གཞི་ལགས་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>To say that all phenomena are awakening is a vajra basis.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-138">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-71</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ཅིའི་སླད་དུ་ཞེ་ན།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Why is this?</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-139">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-71</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་བརྗོད་པ་མ་མཆིས་པའི་སླད་དུ་སྟེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Because all phenomena are inexpressible.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-140">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-71</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདི་ན་མིང་གང་དང་གང་གིས་ཆོས་གང་དང་གང་བརྗོད་པའི་ཆོས་དེ་དང་དེ་ཆོས་དེ་དང་དེ་ལ་མ་མཆིས་ལགས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Phenomena expressed by means of various names are not actually present in those very phenomena.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-141">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-71</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།གང་མ་མཆིས་པ་དེ་ནི་སྟོང་པ་ལགས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Whatever is not present is empty.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-142">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-71</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།གང་སྟོང་པ་དེ་ནི་མེད་པ་ལགས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>That which is empty does not exist.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-143">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-71</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།གང་མེད་པ་དེ་ནི་བརྗོད་པའི་རྔོ་མི་ཐོགས་པ་ལགས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>What does not exist  cannot be expressed.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-144">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-71</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།བརྗོད་དུ་མ་མཆིས་པ་དེ་ནི་བྱང་ཆུབ་ལགས་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The inexpressible is awakening.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-145">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-71</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེའི་སླད་དུ། འདི་ནི་རྡོ་རྗེའི་གཞི་ལགས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>It is for that reason that this is a vajra basis.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-146">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-71</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་ནི་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པའི་ཡུལ་ལགས་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>All phenomena are the object of the thus-gone ones.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-147">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-71</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདི་ནི་རྡོ་རྗེའི་གཞི་ལགས་སོ། །བཀའ་སྩལ་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>This is a vajra basis.”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-148">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-73</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཅིའི་ཕྱིར་རྡོ་རྗེའི་གཞི་ཞེས་བྱ། གསོལ་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Why is it called a vajra basis</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-149">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-73</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་ནི་རང་གི་ཡུལ་ལས་དབེན་པ་ལགས་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Blessed One, all phenomena are devoid of their own objects.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-150">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-73</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེའི་སླད་དུ་འདི་རྡོ་རྗེའི་གཞི་ལགས་སོ། །བཀའ་སྩལ་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>For that reason, this is a vajra basis.”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-151">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-75</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་དགེ་སློང་ཀུན་དགའ་བོ་དེ་ཡང་ཆོས་ཀྱི་རྣམ་གྲངས་འདི་ཀུན་འཛིན་པར་འགྱུར་ན།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Mañjuśrī, the monk Ānanda will also comprehend this Dharma exposition.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-152">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-75</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདིར་འོངས་པའི་མཚན་མ་ངས་བྱའམ། གསོལ་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Shall I motion him to come here?”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-153">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-75</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་འདི་ནི་ཆོས་བརྗོད་པའམ། བསྟན་པ་མཆིས་ལགས་སམ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Blessed One, is there any Dharma that has been taught or expressed here?</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-154">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-75</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བདག་གིས་ནི་ཡི་གེ་གཅིག་ཀྱང་བསྟན་པར་ཡང་དག་པར་རྗེས་སུ་མ་མཐོང་ལགས་ན།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>I myself have not actually witnessed even a single syllable that has been taught.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-155">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-75</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མང་པོ་ལྟ་ག་ལ་མཐོང་ལགས། བཀའ་སྩལ་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>That being so, how could I possibly have perceived many of them?”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-156">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-77</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་ལེགས་སོ་ལེགས་སོ། །འཇམ་དཔལ་ཁྱོད་འདི་སྐད་དུ་འཆད་པ་ནི་ཁྱོད་ཀྱི་ཚིག་འདི་ལེགས་པར་སྨྲས་པ་ཡིན་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Excellent, Mañjuśrī, excellent. These words of yours, which you present in this way, are well spoken.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-157">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-77</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་ཁྱོད་ལེགས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Well done, Mañjuśrī.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-158">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-77</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།འཇམ་དཔལ་ངས་ནི་ཕྱོགས་བཅུའི་འཇིག་རྟེན་གྱི་ཁམས་དཔག་ཏུ་མེད་གྲངས་མེད་པ་དག་ན་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་དགྲ་བཅོམ་པ་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་སངས་རྒྱས་རྣམས་ཆོས་ཉིད་འདི་ཁོ་ན་སྟོན་ཅིང་བཞུགས་པ་དག་མཐོང་ངོ་།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>In the countless, innumerable world systems of the ten directions, I see thus-gone ones, worthy ones, perfect buddhas abiding and teaching this reality.”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-159">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-78</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ནས་ཚེ་དང་ལྡན་པ་ཤཱ་རིའི་བུ་རང་གི་གནས་ཁང་ནས་བྱུང་ནས།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>At this point Venerable Śāriputra left his dwelling and went to the dwelling of Youthful Mañjuśrī.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-160">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-78</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་གཞོན་ནུར་གྱུར་པའི་གནས་ཁང་ག་ལ་བ་དེར་སོང་སྟེ་ཕྱིན་ནས་འཇམ་དཔལ་གཞོན་ནུར་གྱུར་པ་མ་མཐོང་སྟེ། བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱི་བཞུགས་ཁང་ག་ལ་བ་དེར་སོང་ནས།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He did not see Mañjuśrī there, and so he went to the Blessed One’s dwelling.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-161">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-78</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཞུགས་ཁང་གི་ཕྱི་སྒོ་ན་འགྲེང་བ་དང་། གསུང་བའི་གསུང་ཐོས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He stood outside the door and heard the teachings being given.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-162">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-79</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་འཇམ་དཔལ་གཞོན་ནུར་གྱུར་པ་ལ་འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་བཀའ་སྩལ་ཏོ། །འཇམ་དཔལ་དགེ་སློང་ཤཱ་རིའི་བུ་འདི་གནས་ཁང་གི་ཕྱི་སྒོ་ན་འགྲེང་སྟེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The Blessed One said to Youthful Mañjuśrī, “Mañjuśrī, the monk Śāriputra is standing outside the door of this dwelling.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-163">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-79</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཆོས་ཉན་པར་འདོད་ན་འཇམ་དཔལ་ཤཱ་རིའི་བུ་ཆོས་ཉན་པར་ནང་དུ་འོང་བར་གྱིས་ཤིག །གསོལ་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>As he wishes to listen to the Dharma, Mañjuśrī, bring Śāriputra inside so he can listen.”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-164">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-80</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མཐའ་འདི་ནི་ཡང་དག་པའི་མཐའ་ལགས་ན། གང་གི་སླད་རོལ་དང་། ནང་དང་གཉིས་ཀ་མ་མཆིས་པར་གདའ་ལགས་སམ། བཀའ་སྩལ་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“If this limit is the limit of reality, is it present outside, inside, or neither?”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-165">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-80</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་དེ་ནི་མ་ཡིན་ནོ། །གསོལ་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Mañjuśrī, it is none of these.”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-166">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-82</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་དེ་ལྟ་ལགས་པས་ཡང་དག་པའི་མཐའ་ནི་མཐའ་མ་མཆིས་པ་ལགས་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Therefore, Blessed One, the limit of reality is not a limit.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-167">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-82</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ལྟ་བུའི་མཐའ་གང་ལགས་པ་དེ་ལ་ནི་ཚུར་མཆི་བའམ། ཕར་མཆི་བ་མ་མཆིས་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Regarding a limit such as this, one does not come here or go there.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-168">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-82</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་དེ་ལྟ་བུའི་མཐའ་ཅན་གྱི་བཙུན་པ་ཤཱ་རིའི་བུ་དེ་ནི་ཚུར་མཆི་བའམ། ནང་དུ་མཆི་བའི་མི་རིགས་ལགས་སོ། །བཀའ་སྩལ་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Thus, Blessed One, it is not appropriate for the honorable Śāriputra, who is limited in this way, to come here or come inside.”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-169">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-84</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་གལ་ཏེ་ང་གནས་ཁང་གི་ནང་ན་ཉན་ཐོས་དག་དང་ལྷན་ཅིག་ཏུ་གཏམ་ཟེར་ཞིང་འདུག་ལ། ཁྱོད་ནི་ཕྱི་རོལ་ན་འདུག་སྟེ། ནང་དུ་འོང་དུ་ཡང་མི་དབང་ན་ཅི་ཁྱོད་སྡུག་བསྔལ་བར་མི་འགྱུར་རམ། གསོལ་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Mañjuśrī, if I were in this dwelling speaking with the hearers while you were outside, powerless to enter, would you not suffer?”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-170">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-85</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་དེ་ནི་མ་ལགས་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Blessed One, it is not so.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-171">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-85</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ཅིའི་སླད་དུ་ཞེ་ན།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>And why not?</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-172">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-85</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་ནི་ཆོས་ཀྱི་དབྱིངས་སུ་ཡང་དག་པར་འདུ་བའི་སླད་དུ་སྟེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Because all phenomena are included within the realm of phenomena.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-173">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-85</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདི་ནི་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་ཞེས་བརྗོད་པ་གང་ལགས་པ་འདི་ཡང་ཆོས་ཀྱི་དབྱིངས་ལགས་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>In this regard, the expression thus-gone one means the realm of phenomena.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-174">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-85</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མཚན་ཉིད་གཅིག་པའི་སླད་དུ་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་ཡང་གཞན་ལ་ཆོས་ཀྱི་དབྱིངས་ཀྱང་གཞན་མ་ལགས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Since they are of a single characteristic, the Thus-Gone One and the realm of phenomena are not any different.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-175">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-85</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཆོས་སམ་ཆོས་བསྟན་པ་ཞེས་བགྱི་བའམ། ཆོས་ཉན་པ་ཞེས་བགྱི་བའི་ཆོས་འདི་དག་ཀྱང་གཉིས་སུ་མ་མཆིས་པའི་སླད་དུ་ཐ་དད་པ་མ་མཆིས་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Phenomena such as ‘Dharma,’ ‘Dharma teachings,’ or ‘listening to the Dharma’ are nondual and thus are not distinct.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-176">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-85</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེའི་སླད་དུ་ཡང་ཆོས་ཀྱི་དབྱིངས་ལས་ཐ་དད་པ་མ་ལགས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>And it is for that reason, too, that they are not distinct from the realm of phenomena.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-177">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-85</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།འཇམ་དཔལ་ཞེས་བགྱི་བའི་ཡི་གེ་གང་ལགས་པ་འདི་དག་ཀྱང་ཆོས་ཀྱི་དབྱིངས་སུ་གཏོགས་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The syllables that make up the name Mañjuśrī also belong to the realm of phenomena.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-178">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-85</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་རྣམ་གྲངས་དེས་ན་བདག་ཆུང་ཟད་ཀྱང་གདུང་བ་མ་མཆིས་ལགས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Thus, Blessed One, for this reason I would not be distressed in the slightest.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-179">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-85</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་བསྐལ་པ་གང་གཱའི་ཀླུང་གི་བྱེ་མ་སྙེད་དུ་ཆོས་སྟོན་དུ་ལགས་ཀྱང་བདག་དེར་མཆི་ཡང་མི་མཆི། དེར་མཆིར་དགའ་བའམ། ཡོངས་སུ་གདུང་བ་ཡང་མི་སྐྱེད་ལགས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Even if the Blessed One were to teach the Dharma for eons equal in number to the grains of sand in the River Ganges, whether I were there or not, I would experience neither joy at being there nor anguish otherwise.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-180">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-85</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ཅིའི་སླད་དུ་ཞེ་ན།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>And why not?</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-181">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-85</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་གཉིས་ཤིག་མཆིས་ན་ནི་དགའ་བའམ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Blessed One, if duality existed then I would experience joy or anguish.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-182">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-85</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡོངས་སུ་གདུང་བ་སྐྱེད་པར་འགྱུར་ན་ཆོས་ཀྱི་དབྱིངས་དེ་ནི་གཉིས་སུ་མ་མཆིས་ཏེ། དེའི་སླད་དུ་བདག་དགའ་བའམ། ཡོངས་སུ་གདུང་བར་མི་འགྱུར་ལགས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>However, the realm of phenomena is nondual, and it is for that reason that I would not become joyful or anguished.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-183">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-85</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཆོས་སྟོན་པ་མཛད་པའི་ཆོས་བསྟན་པ་དེས་ཀྱང་ཆོས་གང་ཡང་སོགས་པའམ། འབྲི་བའམ། འཕེལ་བའམ། འགྲིབ་པར་མི་བགྱིད་དེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Blessed One, the teachings by which you share the Dharma do not cause any phenomena to accumulate, diminish, increase, or decrease.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-184">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-85</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདི་ལྟར་ཆོས་བསྟན་པ་དེ་ནི་ཆོས་གང་ཡང་དམིགས་པས་ཉེ་བར་གནས་པ་མ་ལགས་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Such a teaching is not founded on apprehending any phenomenon whatsoever.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-185">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-85</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་དེའི་སླད་དུ་ཡང་བདག་དགའ་བར་མི་འགྱུར་ཞིང་ཡོངས་སུ་གདུང་བར་མི་འགྱུར་ལགས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>It is for that reason as well, Blessed One, that I would not become joyous or anguished.”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-186">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-86</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་ཚེ་དང་ལྡན་པ་ཤཱ་རིའི་བུ་ལ་བཀའ་སྩལ་པ། ཤཱ་རིའི་བུ་ཁྱོད་ཀྱིས་འཇམ་དཔལ་གཞོན་ནུར་གྱུར་པའི་སྤོབས་པ་ཐོས་སམ། གསོལ་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>At this point, the Blessed One asked Venerable Śāriputra, “Did you hear Youthful Mañjuśrī’s eloquence, Śāriputra?”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-187">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-87</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཐོས་ལགས་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Blessed One, I heard.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-188">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-87</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་བདག་ནི་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་དང་འཇམ་དཔལ་གཞོན་ནུར་གྱུར་པའི་སྤོབས་པ་ཐོས་ཀྱང་ཅི་མ་རུང་སྙམ་སྟེ། དེའི་སླད་དུ་བདག་འདི་ན་མཆིས་ལགས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>I came here, Blessed One, thinking how wonderful it would be to hear the eloquent words of the Blessed One and of Youthful Mañjuśrī.”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-189">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-88</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ལ་འཇམ་དཔལ་གཞོན་ནུར་གྱུར་པས་འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་གསོལ་ཏོ། །བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཚེ་དང་ལྡན་པ་ཤཱ་རིའི་བུ་ནང་དུ་མཆི་བར་མཛད་དུ་གསོལ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Youthful Mañjuśrī then said to the Blessed One, “Blessed One, please invite Venerable Śāriputra to come inside.”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-190">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-88</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་ཚེ་དང་ལྡན་པ་ཤཱ་རིའི་བུ་ལ་འདི་སྐད་དུ་ཤཱ་རིའི་བུ་ཁྱོད་གནས་ཁང་གི་ནང་དུ་ཤོག་ཅེས་བཀའ་སྩལ་ཏོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Enter, Śāriputra,” said the Blessed One to Venerable Śāriputra.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-191">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-90</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ནས་ཚེ་དང་ལྡན་པ་ཤཱ་རིའི་བུ་གནས་ཁང་དུ་འོངས་ནས། བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱི་ཞབས་ལ་ཕྱག་འཚལ་ཏེ་ཕྱོགས་གཅིག་ཏུ་འདུག་གོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Venerable Śāriputra entered, prostrated at the Blessed One’s feet, and sat to one side.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-192">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-90</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཕྱོགས་གཅིག་ཏུ་འདུག་པ་དང་། ཚེ་དང་ལྡན་པ་ཤཱ་རིའི་བུ་ལ་འཇམ་དཔལ་གཞོན་ནུར་གྱུར་པས་འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་སྨྲས་སོ། །བཙུན་པ་ཤཱ་རིའི་བུ་ཁྱོད་དོན་གྱི་དབང་གང་མཐོང་བས་འདིར་འོངས།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Honorable Śāriputra,” said Youthful Mañjuśrī to Venerable Śāriputra, who was seated to the side, “what purpose did you envision for coming here?”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-193">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-91</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྨྲས་པ། འཇམ་དཔལ་ཁོ་བོ་ནི་ཆོས་ཉན་པར་འདོད་པའི་ཕྱིར་འདིར་འོངས་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“I came here, Mañjuśrī, with a longing to hear the Dharma.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-194">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-91</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདི་ལྟར་གང་ན་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་དང་། སྐྱེས་བུ་དམ་པ་ཁྱོད་ལྟ་བུ་གནས་པ་དེ་ན་བསྟན་པ་ཟབ་མོ་ཡང་དག་པར་ཕུལ་དུ་བྱུང་བ་ཡོད་དེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Where the Blessed One and sublime beings such as yourself are dwelling, there are profound and exquisite teachings.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-195">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-91</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེའི་ཕྱིར་ཁོ་བོ་འོངས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>It is because of this that I came.”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-196">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-91</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྨྲས་པ། བཙུན་པ་ཤཱ་རིའི་བུ་དེ་ནི་དེ་བཞིན་ཏེ་བསྟན་པ་འདི་ནི་ཟབ་བོ། །སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“So it is, Honorable Śāriputra. This teaching is profound.”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-197">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-93</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཉིད་དང་ཐབས་ཅིག་ཏུ་བརྩམས་པའི་ཆོས་བསྟན་པ་དེ་ཇི་ཙམ་དུ་ཟབ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“How profound is this Dharma exposition that you commenced together with the Blessed One?”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-198">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-93</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྨྲས་པ། དེ་ནི་བཙུན་པ་ཤཱ་རིའི་བུས་རྟོགས་པར་མི་འགྱུར་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“It will not be comprehended by Honorable Śāriputra.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-199">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-93</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དགྲ་བཅོམ་པ་ཟག་པ་ཟད་པ་ནི་ཆོས་བསྟན་པ་འདིའི་སྣོད་མ་ཡིན་ནོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>A worthy one whose contaminants have been exhausted is not a vessel for this Dharma teaching.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-200">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-93</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ཅིའི་ཕྱིར་ཞེ་ན།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Why is this?</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-201">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-93</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདི་ལྟར་ཆོས་བསྟན་པ་འདི་ནི་སོ་སོའི་སྐྱེ་བོའི་ཆོས་ལ་ཞུགས་པ་མ་ཡིན། དགྲ་བཅོམ་པ་ཉིད་ཀྱི་ཆོས་ལ་ཞུགས་པ་མ་ཡིན། རང་སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱི་ཆོས་ལ་ཞུགས་པ་མ་ཡིན། དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པའི་ཆོས་ལ་ཞུགས་པ་མ་ཡིན་པའི་ཕྱིར་རོ། །འདི་ནི་ཆོས་གང་དམིགས་པའི་ཕྱིར་ཡང་ཞུགས་པ་མ་ཡིན་ནོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Because this Dharma teaching is not engaged with the properties of ordinary beings, is not engaged with the properties of worthy ones, is not engaged with the properties of solitary buddhas, and is not engaged with the properties of thus-gone ones.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-202">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-93</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།འདི་ནི་གང་དུ་ཞུགས་པའམ་ལྡོག་པ་ཡང་མེད་དེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>It is not engaged with the apprehending any property.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-203">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-93</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་ཤིན་ཏུ་དབེན་པའི་ཕྱིར་རོ། །སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Since all attributes are completely void, it is not engaged with, or disengaged from, anything at all.”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-204">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-95</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་ཁྱོད་ཀྱིས་ཅི་ལས་བསམས་ཏེ། དགྲ་བཅོམ་པ་ཟག་པ་ཟད་པ་ཆོས་བསྟན་པ་འདིའི་སྣོད་མ་ཡིན་ཞེས་དེ་སྐད་སྨྲ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Mañjuśrī, what is your rationale for saying that worthy ones whose contaminants are exhausted are not vessels for this teaching?”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-205">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-96</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྨྲས་པ། བཙུན་པ་ཤཱ་རིའི་བུ་དགྲ་བཅོམ་པ་ཉིད་ནི། འདོད་ཆགས་དང་། ཞེ་སྡང་དང་། གཏི་མུག་ཟད་པ་ཡིན་ན་དེ་གང་གི་སྣོད་ཡིན་ཞིང་།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Honorable Śāriputra, I thought, ‘If the worthy one’s attachment,  aversion, and delusion are exhausted, what kind of vessel is he?</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-206">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-96</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་གང་ཇི་ལྟ་བུ་ཞིག་གི་སྣོད་དུ་འགྱུར་སྙམ་སྟེ། དེ་ལས་བསམས་ནས་དགྲ་བཅོམ་པ་ཟག་པ་ཟད་པ། ཆོས་བསྟན་པ་འདིའི་སྣོད་མ་ཡིན་ནོ་ཞེས་ཁོ་བོ་དེ་སྐད་སྨྲའོ། །སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>What kind of vessel will he become?’ Having considered these questions, I reply that worthy ones whose contaminants are exhausted are not vessels for this teaching.”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-207">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-97</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་ཁོ་བོ་ནི་ཆོས་བསྟན་པ་འདིའི་དོན་དུ་གཙུག་ལག་ཁང་ནས་གཙུག་ལག་ཁང་དང་། གནས་ཁང་ནས་གནས་ཁང་དང་། ཕུག་ནས་ཕུག་ཏུ་ཁྱོད་ཚོལ་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Mañjuśrī, for the sake of this teaching I went from monastery to monastery, from dwelling to dwelling, and from hermitage to hermitage in search of you.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-208">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-97</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བདག་གིས་ཁྱོད་ལས་ཟབ་པ་ཟབ་པ་ཡང་དག་པའི་སྤོབས་པ་འདི་ལྟ་བུ་འདི་དག་ཐོས་ཀྱང་ཅི་མ་རུང་སྙམ་སྟེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>I thought of how wonderful it would be to hear such profound and eloquent expositions from you.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-209">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-97</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་ཁོ་བོ་ནི་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་དང་། ཁྱོད་ཀྱི་ཆོས་བསྟན་པ་ལ་ཆོག་མི་ཤེས་སོ། །སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Mañjuśrī, I am insatiable when it comes to the Blessed One’s teachings or your own.”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-210">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-98</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཙུན་པ་ཤཱ་རིའི་བུ་ཁྱོད་ཆོས་བསྟན་པས་ཆོག་མི་ཤེས་སམ། སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Honorable Śāriputra, you are not sated by Dharma teachings?”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-211">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-98</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཁོ་བོ་ཆོག་མི་ཤེས་སོ། །སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“I am not.”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-212">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-100</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཙུན་པ་ཤཱ་རིའི་བུ་ཅི་ཆོས་ཀྱི་དབྱིངས་ཆོས་ཚོལ་བར་བྱེད་དམ། སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Honorable Śāriputra, does the realm of phenomena seek out the Dharma?”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-213">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-100</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་མི་བྱེད་དོ། །སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“It does not, Mañjuśrī.”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-214">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-102</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཆོས་ཀྱི་དབྱིངས་ཀྱང་གཞན་ལ། ཚེ་དང་ལྡན་པ་ཤཱ་རིའི་བུ་ནི་གཞན་པ་ནི་མ་ཡིན་ན་ཅིའི་ཕྱིར་ཚེ་དང་ལྡན་པ་ཤཱ་རིའི་བུ་ཆོས་མཉན་པ་ལ་ཆོག་མི་ཤེས།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Since it is not the case that the realm of phenomena is one distinct thing while Venerable Śāriputra is something other, why is it that Venerable Śāriputra is insatiable in listening to the Dharma?</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-215">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-102</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ཅིའི་ཕྱིར་ཞེ་ན།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Why do I say this?</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-216">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-102</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཙུན་པ་ཤཱ་རིའི་བུ་ཆོས་ཀྱི་དབྱིངས་ནི་ཆོས་ཚོལ་བར་མི་བྱེད་པའི་ཕྱིར་རོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Honorable Śāriputra, it is because the realm of phenomena does not seek the Dharma.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-217">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-102</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།གལ་ཏེ་དེ་ཚོལ་བར་བྱེད་ན་ནི་དེའི་ཕྱིར་དེ་ཆོག་ཤེས་པར་འགྱུར་བ་ཞིག་ན་གང་གི་ཕྱིར་ཚོལ་བར་མི་བྱེད་པ་དེའི་ཕྱིར་ཆོག་མི་ཤེས་སོ། །སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>If it did seek, then it would be something that could be sated. However, since it does not seek, it is not sated.”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-218">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-103</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་མ་གཏོགས་པར་ཁོ་བོ་ལྟ་བུ་ཆོས་ཉན་པ་དེ་ལྟ་བུ་ཁྱོད་ཀྱིས་ག་ལ་རྙེད། སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Mañjuśrī, apart from the Thus-Gone One, where else will you find someone like me to listen to the Dharma?”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-219">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-103</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཙུན་པ་ཤཱ་རིའི་བུ་ཁྱོད་ཤཱ་རིའི་བུ་ཡོངས་སུ་མྱ་ངན་ལས་མི་འདའ་བའི་ཆོས་ཅན་ཡིན་པར་མོས་སམ། སྨྲས་པ། མོས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Honorable Śāriputra, do you believe that you, Śāriputra, will not enter parinirvāṇa?”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-220">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-103</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Yes, I do.”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-221">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-106</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཇི་ལྟར་མོས། སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Why do you believe this?”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-222">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-106</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་ཡོངས་སུ་མ་གྲུབ་པས་ན་ཁོ་བོ་ཡང་ཡོངས་སུ་མྱ་ངན་ལས་མི་འདའ་བའི་ཆོས་ཅན་ཡིན་ནོ་སྙམ་དུ་དེ་ལྟར་མོས་སོ། །སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“I believe this thinking that, since no phenomenon is established, I too will not enter parinirvāṇa.”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-223">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-108</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཙུན་པ་ཤཱ་རིའི་བུ་ཁྱོད་ཤི་འཕོ་མེད་པ་དང་། སྐྱེ་བ་མེད་པའི་ཆོས་ཅན་ཡིན་པར་མོས་སམ། སྨྲས་པ། མོས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Honorable Śāriputra, do you believe that for you there is no death, transmigration, and rebirth?”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-224">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-108</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Yes, I do.”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-225">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-110</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཇི་ལྟར་མོས།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Why do you believe this?”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-226">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-110</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྨྲས་པ། ཆོས་ཀྱི་དབྱིངས་སུ་གཏོགས་པའི་ཕྱིར་ཏེ། ཆོས་ཀྱི་དབྱིངས་ལ་འཆི་འཕོའམ་སྐྱེ་བ་མེད་པ་དེ་ལྟར་མོས་སོ། །སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“I believe this because I am included within the realm of phenomena, and in the realm of phenomena death, transmigration, and birth do not exist.”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-227">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-112</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཙུན་པ་ཤཱ་རིའི་བུ་ཁྱོད་དགྲ་བཅོམ་པ་ཟག་པ་ཟད་པ་མི་ཤེས་པ་དང་ལྡན་པར་མོས་སམ། སྨྲས་པ། མོས་སོ། །སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Honorable Śāriputra, do you believe that a worthy one whose contaminants have been exhausted is ignorant?”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-228">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-114</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཇི་ལྟར་མོས། སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Why do you believe this?”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-229">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-114</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཤེས་པ་དང་། མི་ཤེས་པ་མཉམ་པ་ཉིད་ཀྱི་ཕྱིར་དགྲ་བཅོམ་པ་ཟག་པ་ཟད་པ་མི་ཤེས་པ་དང་ལྡན་ཏེ་འདི་ལྟར་མི་ཤེས་པ་དང་། ཤེས་པ་ནི་མི་ཟད་པའི་ཆོས་ཅན་ཡིན་པའི་ཕྱིར་དབེན་པ་སྟེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Since knowledge and ignorance are equivalent, a worthy one whose contaminants have been exhausted is ignorant. In this way, ignorance and knowledge are inexhaustible, and therefore they are void.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-230">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-114</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་བས་ན་མི་ཤེས་པ་དང་། ཤེས་པར་རྣམ་པར་མི་རྟོགས་པའི་ཕྱིར་དགྲ་བཅོམ་པ་ཟག་པ་ཟད་པ་མི་ཤེས་པ་དང་ལྡན་པར་མོས་སོ། །སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>That being the case, it is because of not conceptualizing ignorance and consciousness that I believe that a worthy one whose contaminants have been exhausted is ignorant.”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-231">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-116</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཙུན་པ་ཤཱ་རིའི་བུ་ཁྱོད་དགྲ་བཅོམ་པ་ཟག་པ་ཟད་པ། ཤེས་པ་དང་བྲལ་བར་མོས་སམ། སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Honorable Śāriputra, do you believe that worthy ones whose contaminants have been exhausted are devoid of knowledge?”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-232">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-116</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མོས་སོ། །སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Yes, I do.”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-233">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-118</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཇི་ལྟར་མོས།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Why do you believe this?”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-234">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-118</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྨྲས་པ། འདི་ལྟར་ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་ནི་ངོ་བོ་ཉིད་དང་བྲལ་བ་སྟེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“All phenomena are devoid of any essence.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-235">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-118</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་བས་ན་དགྲ་བཅོམ་པ་ཟག་པ་ཟད་པ་ཤེས་པ་དང་བྲལ་བར་མོས་སོ། །སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Because of this I believe that worthy ones whose contaminants have been exhausted are devoid of knowledge.”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-236">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-120</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཙུན་པ་ཤཱ་རིའི་བུ་ཁྱོད་དགྲ་བཅོམ་པ་ཟག་པ་ཟད་པ། རྣམ་པར་མ་གྲོལ་བའི་ཆོས་ཅན་དུ་མོས་སམ། སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Honorable Śāriputra, do you believe that worthy ones whose contaminants are exhausted are not liberated?”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-237">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-120</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མོས་སོ། །སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Yes, I do.”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-238">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-122</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཇི་ལྟར་མོས།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Why do you believe that?”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-239">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-122</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྨྲས་པ། ཉོན་མོངས་པ་མེད་པའི་ཕྱིར་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“I believe this because defilements do not exist.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-240">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-122</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདི་ལྟར་ཉོན་མོངས་པ་མེད་ན་གང་དག་ལས་རྣམ་པར་གྲོལ་བར་འགྱུར་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>From what is one liberated if defilements do not exist?”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-241">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-124</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ལྟར་མོས་སོ། །སྨྲས་པ། བཙུན་པ་ཤཱ་རིའི་བུ་ཁྱོད་སྔོན་གྱི་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་རྣམས་མ་བྱུང་ཞིང་ཡོངས་སུ་མྱ་ངན་ལས་མ་འདས་པར་མོས་སམ། སྨྲས་པ། མོས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Honorable Śāriputra, do you believe that the prior thus-gone ones did not appear and did not enter parinirvāṇa?”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-242">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-124</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Yes, I do.”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-243">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-126</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཇི་ལྟར་མོས།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Why do you believe this?”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-244">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-126</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྨྲས་པ། འཇམ་དཔལ་བསམ་གྱིས་མི་ཁྱབ་པའི་དབྱིངས་ལ་ནི་སྐྱེ་བ་མེད་དེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“In the inconceivable realm, Mañjuśrī, there is no birth.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-245">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-126</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་མི་སྐྱེ་བ་དེ་ལ་མི་སྣང་བར་འགྱུར་བའམ། ཡོངས་སུ་མྱ་ངན་ལས་འདའ་བར་འགྱུར་བ་ག་ལ་ཡོད་དེ་དེ་ལྟར་མོས་སོ། །སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Thus, how could what is unborn disappear or pass into parinirvāṇa? That is why I believe it.”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-246">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-128</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཙུན་པ་ཤཱ་རིའི་བུ་ཁྱོད་སངས་རྒྱས་ཐམས་ཅད་གཅིག་ཡིན་པར་མོས་སམ། སྨྲས་པ། མོས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Honorable Śāriputra, do you believe that all buddhas are one?”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-247">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-128</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Yes, I do.”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-248">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-130</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཇི་ལྟར་མོས།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Why do you believe this?”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-249">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-130</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྨྲས་པ། འཇམ་དཔལ་ཆོས་ཀྱི་དབྱིངས་ལ་ནི་ཐ་དད་པ་མེད་པ་དེ་དེ་ལྟར་མོས་སོ། །སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Mañjuśrī, it is because there are no distinctions in the realm of phenomena that I believe this.”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-250">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-132</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཙུན་པ་ཤཱ་རིའི་བུ་ཁྱོད་སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱི་ཞིང་ཐམས་ཅད་སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱི་ཞིང་གཅིག་ཡིན་པར་མོས་སམ། སྨྲས་པ། མོས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Honorable Śāriputra, do you believe that all buddha fields are a single buddha field?”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-251">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-132</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Yes, I do.”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-252">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-134</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཇི་ལྟར་མོས།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Why do you believe this?”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-253">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-134</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྨྲས་པ། འཇམ་དཔལ་སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱི་ཞིང་ཐམས་ཅད་ནི་མི་ཟད་པ་ཉིད་ཀྱི་ཞིང་ཡིན་ཏེ་དེ་ལྟར་མོས་སོ། །སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Mañjuśrī, since all buddha fields are the field of the inexhaustible, I believe in this way.”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-254">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-136</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཙུན་པ་ཤཱ་རིའི་བུ་ཁྱོད་ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་ཡོངས་སུ་ཤེས་པར་བྱ་བ་མ་ཡིན་པ་དང་། སྤང་བར་བྱ་བ་མ་ཡིན་པ་དང་། མངོན་སུམ་དུ་བྱ་བ་མ་ཡིན་པ་དང་། བསྒོམ་པར་བྱ་བ་མ་ཡིན་པར་མོས་སམ། སྨྲས་པ། མོས་སོ། །སྨྲས་པ། ཇི་ལྟར་མོས།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Honorable Śāriputra, do you believe that no phenomenon can be known, abandoned, actualized,  and cultivated?”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-255">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-136</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Yes, I do.” “Why do you believe this?”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-256">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-136</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་ངོ་བོ་ཉིད་ཀྱིས་ངོ་བོ་ཉིད་ཡོངས་སུ་མི་ཤེས་པ་དང་། རང་བཞིན་གྱིས་རང་བཞིན་སྤོང་བ་དང་། མངོན་སུམ་དུ་མི་བྱེད་པ་དང་། སྒོམ་པར་མི་བྱེད་པ་དང་། སྐྱེད་པར་མི་བྱེད་པ་དང་། འགག་པར་མི་བྱེད་པ་དང་། ལེན་པར་མི་བྱེད་པ་དང་། འདོར་བར་མི་བྱེད་པ་དང་། མཐའ་དེ་ནི་མི་གནས་པ་ཉིད་དེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Essentially, Mañjuśrī, no essence is known. Naturally, no nature is abandoned, actualized, cultivated, produced, ended, adopted, or rejected. That limit is nonabiding.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-257">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-136</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ལྟར་མོས་སོ། །སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>That is what I believe.”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-258">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-140</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཙུན་པ་ཤཱ་རིའི་བུ་ཁྱོད་ཆོས་ཀྱི་དབྱིངས་ནི་ཕུང་པོར་མི་འདུག་པའི་དབྱིངས་ཡིན་པ་དང་། ཆོས་གང་ཡང་སྐྱེ་བའམ། འགག་པ་མེད་པ་དང་། ཆོས་གང་ཡང་ཕུང་པོར་འདུག་པ་མེད་པར་མོས་སམ། སྨྲས་པ། མོས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Honorable Śāriputra, do you believe that the realm of phenomena is a realm without aggregates, that there is no arising or ceasing of any phenomena, and that there are no phenomena whatsoever that are present as aggregates?”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-259">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-140</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Yes, I do.”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-260">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-142</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཇི་ལྟར་མོས། སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Why do you believe this?”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-261">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-142</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་ཆོས་གང་ཡང་སྐྱེ་བའམ། འགག་པའམ། ཕུང་པོར་འདུག་པ་དེ་མི་དམིགས་ཏེ་དེ་ལྟར་མོས་སོ། །སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Mañjuśrī, I do not apprehend any phenomena arising, ceasing, or present as aggregates, and so I believe in this way.”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-262">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-144</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཙུན་པ་ཤཱ་རིའི་བུ་ཁྱོད་ཤེས་རབ་གང་ཡིན་པ་དེ་ཆོས་ཀྱི་དབྱིངས་ཡིན་ལ། ཆོས་ཀྱི་དབྱིངས་གང་ཡིན་པ་དེ་ཤེས་རབ་ཡིན་ཏེ། ཆོས་ཀྱི་དབྱིངས་ཞེས་བྱ་བའི་མིང་ཡང་ཐོབ་པ་དང་། དེའི་ཕྱིར་ཡང་དགྲ་བཅོམ་པ་ཞེས་བྱ་བར་མོས་སམ། སྨྲས་པ། མོས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Honorable Śāriputra, do you believe that insight is the realm of phenomena, and that the realm of phenomena is insight, and that therefore the so-called realm of phenomena is also called a worthy one</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-263">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-144</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Yes, I do.”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-264">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-146</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཇི་ལྟར་མོས། སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Why do you believe this?” “Mañjuśrī, the state of a worthy one comes about through the insight that leads to realization.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-265">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-146</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་རྟོགས་པར་འགྱུར་བའི་ཤེས་རབ་ཀྱིས་དགྲ་བཅོམ་པ་ཉིད་དུ་འགྱུར་བ་དེ་བཞིན་དུ་ཆོས་ཀྱི་དབྱིངས་ཡོངས་སུ་ཤེས་པར་ཟད་ཀྱི་ཆོས་ཀྱི་དབྱིངས་ཡོངས་སུ་ཤེས་པ་ནི་འདོད་ཆགས་ཀྱི་བདག་ཉིད་དམ། ཞེ་སྡང་གི་བདག་ཉིད་དམ། གཏི་མུག་གི་བདག་ཉིད་ཀྱང་མ་ཡིན་ལ། ཆོས་ཀྱི་དབྱིངས་ལས་ཀྱང་དགྲ་བཅོམ་པ་གུད་ན་མེད་དེ་དེ་ལྟར་མོས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Accordingly, as this amounts to knowledge of the realm of phenomena, that knowledge is not epitomized by attachment, aversion, or delusion, and a worthy one is therefore not other than the realm of phenomena.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-266">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-146</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Thus, I believe in this way.”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-267">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-149</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཙུན་པ་ཤཱ་རིའི་བུ་ཁྱོད་ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱི་ཁྱུ་མཆོག་དང་མཉམ་པར་མོས་སམ། སྨྲས་པ། མོས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Honorable Śāriputra, do you believe all phenomena are equal to the Buddha, the great leader?”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-268">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-149</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Yes, I do.”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-269">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-151</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཇི་ལྟར་མོས།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Why do you believe this?”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-270">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-151</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྨྲས་པ། འཇམ་དཔལ་འདི་ལྟར་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་ནི་ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་རང་བཞིན་གྱིས་དབེན་པར་མངོན་པར་རྫོགས་པར་སངས་རྒྱས་ཏེ། དེ་ལྟར་མོས་སོ། །སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Mañjuśrī, I believe this because the Blessed One has fully understood that all phenomena are devoid of an inherent nature.”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-271">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-153</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཙུན་པ་ཤཱ་རིའི་བུ་ཁྱོད་ཀྱི་ཡུལ་ཇི་ཙམ་པ་དེ་ཙམ་དུ་ཁྱོད་ཀྱིས་ལན་བཏབ་པ་ལེགས་སོ་ལེགས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Honorable Śāriputra, it is excellent that you have given answers according to the extent of your purview. Well done.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-272">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-153</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ཙམ་ཞིག་ཁྱོད་ལ་དྲིས་ཀྱིས་ད་ནི་རང་གི་གནས་སུ་སོང་ཤིག །ཤཱ་རིའི་བུས་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>That is as far as I will question you. Now, return to your place.”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-273">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-153</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་འདི་ལྟར་འདི་ཉིད་ནི་བདག་གི་ཇི་སྲིད་འཚོའི་བར་གྱི་གནས་ཡིན་ནོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Śāriputra responded, “Mañjuśrī, this is my place, for as long as I live.”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-274">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-155</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་ཚེ་དང་ལྡན་པ་ཤཱ་རིའི་བུ་ལ་བཀའ་སྩལ་པ། ཤཱ་རིའི་བུ་རིགས་ཀྱི་བུའམ་རིགས་ཀྱི་བུ་མོ་གང་ལ་ལ་ཆོས་ཀྱི་རྣམ་གྲངས་འདི་འཛིན་པའམ། འཆང་བའམ། ཀློག་པའམ། ཀུན་ཆུབ་པར་བྱེད་པ་དེས་ནི་སྤོབས་པ་མྱུར་དུ་ཐོབ་པར་འགྱུར་རོ། །གསོལ་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>At this point, the Blessed One said to Venerable Śāriputra,  “Śāriputra, noble sons or daughters who remember, keep, read, or learn this teaching will swiftly become eloquent.”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-275">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-156</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་དེ་ནི་དེ་ལྟ་ལགས་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“So it is, Blessed One.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-276">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-156</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཇི་སྐད་བཀའ་སྩལ་པ་བཞིན་དུ་རིགས་ཀྱི་བུའམ་རིགས་ཀྱི་བུ་མོ་གང་དག་གི་སླད་དུ་ཆོས་ཀྱི་ཕྱག་རྒྱ་འདི་བཞག་པ་དེ་དག་ནི་སྔོན་གྱི་རྒྱལ་བ་རྣམས་ལ་བགྱི་བ་བགྱིས་པ་ལགས་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Those who, for the sake of noble sons or daughters, present this Dharma seal exactly as it has been taught will be paying service to the victors of the past;</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-277">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-156</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་དག་དེ་ལྟར་རིག་པར་བྱའོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>they should be seen in this way.”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-278">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-157</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ལ་ཚེ་དང་ལྡན་པ་ཤཱ་རིའི་བུས་འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་གསོལ་ཏོ། །བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཆོས་ཀྱི་རྣམ་གྲངས་འདིའི་མིང་ཅི་ལགས། འདི་ཇི་ལྟར་གཟུང་བར་བགྱི། དེ་སྐད་ཅེས་གསོལ་པ་དང་། བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་ཚེ་དང་ལྡན་པ་ཤཱ་རིའི་བུ་ལ་འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་བཀའ་སྩལ་ཏོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Then Venerable Śāriputra asked the Blessed One, “What is the name of this Dharma teaching, Blessed One? How should it be known?”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-279">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-158</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཤཱ་རིའི་བུ་དེའི་ཕྱིར་ཁྱོད་ཀྱིས་ཆོས་ཀྱི་རྣམ་གྲངས་འདི་འཇམ་དཔལ་གཞོན་ནུར་གྱུར་པས་ཞུས་ནས་ངས་ལན་བཏབ་པ་ཞེས་བྱ་བར་ཟུང་ཤིག །ཆོས་ཀྱི་དབྱིངས་ཞེས་བྱ་བར་ཡང་ཟུང་ཤིག །ཡང་དག་པའི་མཐའ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་དང་། རིན་པོ་ཆེའི་མཐའ་ཞེས་བྱ་བར་ཡང་ཟུང་ཤིག །ཤཱ་རིའི་བུ་རིགས་ཀྱི་བུའམ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“To that end, Śāriputra,” said the Blessed One to Venerable Śāriputra, “you may identify this Dharma teaching as My Response to Youthful Mañjuśrī’s Question . Identify it also as The Realm of Phenomena . You can also identify it as The Limit of Reality and Infinite Jewels</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-280">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-158</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རིགས་ཀྱི་བུ་མོ་གང་དག་ཆོས་ཀྱི་རྣམ་གྲངས་འདི་འཛིན་པ་དང་། འཆང་བ་དང་། ཀློག་པ་དང་། ཀུན་ཆུབ་པར་བྱེད་པ་དང་། སྒོམ་པ་དང་། སྦྱོར་བ་ལ་བརྩོན་པར་གནས་པ་དེ་དག་ནི་རིན་པོ་ཆེ་དང་འདྲ་བ་ཡིན་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Śāriputra, noble sons and daughters who exert themselves in remembering, keeping, reading, learning, cultivating, and applying this Dharma teaching are like jewels.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-281">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-158</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མི་སྐྱེ་བའི་ཆོས་རྣམས་ལ་ཡང་བཟོད་པ་མྱུར་དུ་ཐོབ་པར་འགྱུར་རོ། །གཞན་དག་ལ་ཡང་དགེ་བའི་རྩ་བ་རྣམས་ཡང་དག་པར་བསྐྱེད་པར་འགྱུར་རོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They will swiftly attain acceptance that phenomena are unborn and generate roots of virtue in others.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-282">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-158</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཆོས་ཉུང་ངུ་ཀུན་ཆུབ་པར་བྱས་པས་ཀྱང་ཆོས་མང་པོ་སྟོན་པར་འགྱུར་རོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Even if they master just a small portion of the Dharma, they will be able to teach the Dharma elaborately.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-283">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-158</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།སྤོབས་པ་མི་ཆོད་པར་ཡང་འགྱུར་རོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Their eloquence will be uninterrupted.”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-284">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-159</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་དེ་སྐད་ཅེས་བཀའ་སྩལ་ནས། འཇམ་དཔལ་གཞོན་ནུར་གྱུར་པ་དང་། ཚེ་དང་ལྡན་པ་ཤཱ་རིའི་བུ་དང་། ལྷ་དང་མི་དང་། ལྷ་མ་ཡིན་དང་། དྲི་ཟར་བཅས་པའི་འཇིག་རྟེན་ཡི་རངས་ཏེ། བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་གསུངས་པ་ལ་མངོན་པར་བསྟོད་དོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>When the Blessed One had said this, Youthful Mañjuśrī, Venerable Śāriputra, and the world with its gods, humans, asuras, and gandharvas rejoiced and praised what the Blessed One had said.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-285">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-160</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།འཕགས་པ་རིན་པོ་ཆེའི་མཐའ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་ཐེག་པ་ཆེན་པོའི་མདོ་རྫོགས་སོ།།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>This completes the noble Great Vehicle sūtra “Infinite Jewels.”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-286">
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-051-006-161</prop>
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།།རྒྱ་གར་གྱི་མཁན་པོ་པྲཛྙཱ་བརྨ་དང་། ཞུ་ཆེན་གྱི་ལོཙྪ་བ་བན་དེ་ཡེ་ཤེས་སྡེ་ལ་སོགས་པས་བསྒྱུར་ཅིང་ཞུས་ཏེ་གཏན་ལ་ཕབ་པ།།</seg>
            </tuv>
          <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>This was translated, proofed, and finalized by the Indian preceptor Prajñāvarman, the translator-editor Bandé Yeshé Dé, and others.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
    
        <tu id="UT22084-051-006-TU-287">
            <prop type="revision">v-1.0.4-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The Noble Great Vehicle Sūtra Infinite Jewels {{milestone:UT22084-051-006-112}} “Yes.” milestone:UT</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        </body>
</tmx>