<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tmx xmlns="http://www.lisa.org/tmx14" xmlns:eft="http://read.84000.co/ns/1.0" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<header creationtool="monlam-ai/84000" datatype="PlainText" segtype="block" adminlang="en-us" srclang="bo" o-tmf="TEI" eft:text-id="UT22084-059-009" eft:text-version="v-1.0.3-2023"/>
<body>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-1">
    <prop type="location-id">translation</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>
                    <tei:ref folio="F.171.b"/>༄༅༅། །རྒྱ་གར་སྐད་དུ། ཨཱརྱ་རཱཥྚ་པཱ་ལ་པ་རི་པྲྀཙྪཱ་ནཱ་མ་མ་ཧཱ་ཡཱ་ན་སཱུ་ཏྲ། བོད་སྐད་དུ། འཕགས་པ་ཡུལ་འཁོར་སྐྱོང་གིས་ཞུས་པ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་ཐེག་པ་ཆེན་པོའི་མདོ། སངས་རྒྱས་དང་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཐམས་ཅད་ལ་ཕྱག་འཚལ་ལོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The Noble Great Vehicle Sūtra The Questions of Rāṣṭrapāla<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-009-22"/> Homage to all buddhas and bodhisattvas.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-2">
    <prop type="location-id">translation</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།འདི་སྐད་བདག་གིས་ཐོས་པ་དུས་གཅིག་ན།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Thus did I hear at one time.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-3">
    <prop type="location-id">translation</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་རྒྱལ་པོའི་ཁབ་ན། བྱ་རྒོད་ཕུང་པོའི་རི་ལ་དགེ་སློང་སྟོང་ཉིས་བརྒྱ་ལྔ་བཅུའི་དགེ་སློང་གི་དགེ་འདུན་ཆེན་པོ་དང་ཐབས་ཅིག་ཏུ་བཞུགས་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The Blessed One was residing at Vulture Peak in Rājagṛha, together with a great saṅgha of 1,250 monks.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-4">
    <prop type="location-id">translation</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་ཚེ་དང་ལྡན་པ་ཡུལ་འཁོར་སྐྱོང་སྟན་ལས་ལངས་ཏེ། བླ་གོས་ཕྲག་པ་གཅིག་ཏུ་གཟར་ནས། པུས་མོ་གཡས་པའི་ལྷ་ང་ས་ལ་བཙུགས་ཏེ། བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱི་ཞབས་ལ་མགོ་བོས་ཕྱག་འཚལ་ནས། བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ག་ལ་བ་དེ་ལོགས་སུ་ཐལ་མོ་སྦྱར་བ་བཏུད་ནས། བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ལ་འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་གསོལ་ཏོ། །བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པའི་བསྟན་པ་འདི་ནུབ་པར་བགྱིད་པའི་སེམས་ཅན་གང་ལགས་པ་དེ་དག་ཇི་ལྟ་བུ་དག་ཅིག་ལགས།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Then, the venerable Rāṣṭrapāla arose from his seat, draped his upper robe over one shoulder, knelt down on his right knee, bowed before the Blessed One, and with folded hands asked, “Blessed One, what are the qualities of the beings who will bring about the decline of the Thus-Gone One’s teaching?”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-5">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-25</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་སྐད་ཅེས་གསོལ་པ་དང་། བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་ཚེ་དང་ལྡན་པ་ཡུལ་འཁོར་སྐྱོང་ལ་འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་བཀའ་སྩལ་ཏོ། །ཡུལ་འཁོར་སྐྱོང་གནས་འདི་གཉིས་ནི་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་གསུངས་པ་སྟེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-009-25"/>The Blessed One replied, “Rāṣṭrapāla, there are two conditions.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-6">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-25</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཉིས་གང་ཞེ་ན།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>What are they?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-7">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-25</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དགེ་སློང་གི་གནས་དང་། ལྷོད་པའི་གནས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They are the condition of the monk and the condition of laxity.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-8">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-25</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ལ་<tei:ref folio="F.172.a"/>དགེ་སློང་གི་གནས་ནི། ཚུལ་ཁྲིམས་དང་ལྡན་པའི་ཕྱོགས་གང་ཡིན་པའོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Now, the condition of the monk is that which pertains to having moral discipline.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-9">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-25</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ལྷོད་པའི་གནས་ནི། ཚུལ་ཁྲིམས་འཆལ་པའི་ཕྱོགས་གང་ཡིན་པའོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>And the condition of laxity is that which pertains to lacking moral discipline. “</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-10">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-26</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཡུལ་འཁོར་སྐྱོང་དེ་ལ་ཡོངས་སུ་མྱ་ངན་ལས་འདའ་བར་འདོད་པའི་དགེ་སློང་གིས་ནི། གནས་འདི་གཉིས་ལ་བསླབ་པར་བྱའོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-009-26"/>Rāṣṭrapāla, monks who seek complete nirvāṇa should train in these two conditions.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-11">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-26</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།གཉིས་གང་ཞེ་ན།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>What are the two?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-12">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-26</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཚུལ་ཁྲིམས་ཀྱི་ཕུང་པོས་ཀྱང་ཤིན་ཏུ་བསྲུང་བར་བྱ་བ་དང་། བདག་ཉིད་ལ་ངེས་པར་བསམ་པར་བྱའི། ཕ་རོལ་ལ་ངེས་པར་བསམ་པར་མི་བྱའོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Through the component of moral discipline, they should fully guard themselves and they should contemplate themselves and nothing else.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-13">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-26</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ལ་ཇི་ལྟར་བདག་ཉིད་ལ་ངེས་པར་བསམ་པར་བྱའི། ཕ་རོལ་ལ་ངེས་པར་བསམ་པར་མི་བྱ་ཞེ་ན།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Now, what is it to contemplate oneself and nothing else?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-14">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-26</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེས་འདི་ལྟར་བརྟག་པར་བྱ་སྟེ། ཅི་བདག་རང་གི་སྡུག་བསྔལ་གྱི་ཕུང་པོ་ཟད་པར་བྱེད་འདོད་པ་ཡིན་ནམ། འོན་ཏེ་བླ་ན་མེད་པ་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་བྱང་ཆུབ་མངོན་པར་རྫོགས་པར་འཚང་རྒྱ་བར་འདོད་པ་ཡིན་སྙམ་དུ་བརྟག་པར་བྱའོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>It is to analyze by thinking, ‘Do I want to want to eliminate my own suffering, or do I want to awaken to unexcelled perfect awakening?’ “</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-15">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-27</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།གལ་ཏེ་ཉན་ཐོས་ཀྱི་ཐེག་པས་ཡོངས་སུ་མྱ་ངན་ལས་འདའ་བར་འདོད་པ་ཞིག་ཡིན་ན་ནི། དེས་ཉན་ཐོས་ཀྱི་བསླབ་པ་ཁོ་ན་ལ་བསླབ་པར་བྱ་སྟེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-009-27"/>Those who seek complete nirvāṇa through the vehicle of the śrāvakas should train only in the precepts of the śrāvakas.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-16">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-27</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སོ་སོར་ཐར་པའི་སྡོམ་པས་བསྡམ་པར་བྱའོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They are to be bound by the prātimokṣa vows.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-17">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-27</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཆོ་ག་དང་སྤྱོད་ཡུལ་ཕུན་སུམ་ཚོགས་པར་བྱའོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Their conduct and personal associations should be perfect.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-18">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-27</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཁ་ན་མ་ཐོ་བ་ཕྲ་རབ་ཙམ་དག་ལ་ཡང་འཇིགས་པར་ལྟ་བས་ཡང་དག་པར་བླངས་ཏེ་བསླབ་པར་བྱའོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They should train having genuinely accepted that even the slightest fault is to be viewed with apprehension.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-19">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-27</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།བསླབ་པའི་གཞི་རྣམས་ལ་ཡང་ལུས་ཀྱི་ལས་དང་། ངག་གི་ལས་དང་། ཡིད་ཀྱི་ལས་ཡོངས་སུ་དག་པར་བྱའོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They should purify their actions of body, speech, and mind in accordance with the precepts.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-20">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-27</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།འཚོ་བ་ཡོངས་སུ་དག་པ་དང་། སྨད་དུ་མེད་པར་ཡང་བྱའོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They should have pure livelihoods and be irreproachable.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-21">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-27</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།བརྐམ་པ་མེད་ཅིང་རོ་རྣམས་ལ་འཆུམས་པ་མེད་པ་དང་། ཆོས་གོས་ལ་ཚོད་ཟིན་པར་ཡང་བྱའོ། །ལྷུང་བཟེད་ལ་ཚོད་ཟིན་པར་ཡང་བྱའོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Without greed and without longing for flavorful foods, they should have suitable robes and suitable begging bowls. “</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-22">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-28</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེས་ཁ་ཟས་ཡོག་དྲོད་ཀྱིས་བཟའ་བར་ཡང་མི་བྱ་སྟེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-009-28"/>Also, they should not eat just any mixture of food.<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="UT22084-059-009-29"/>
                </seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-23">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-28</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལྟོ་མ་བཀྲེས་ཙམ་དུ་ཁ་ཟས་བསྙུངས་པ་དེས་བསླབ་པར་བྱའོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They should train by eating a little bit of food until just sated.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-24">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-28</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེས་ཁ་ཟས་ལ་རྟག་ཏུ་རྒྱུན་མི་ཆད་པར་མི་གཙང་བའི་འདུ་ཤེས་བསྐྱེད་པར་བྱའོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>In this way, they should always and continuously consider food as filth.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-25">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-28</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།འདི་ལྟ་སྟེ། ཕྱི་ས་དང་། གཅིན་གྱི་འདུ་ཤེས་དང་། རྣག་གི་འདུ་ཤེས་དང་། སྐྱུགས་པའི་འདུ་ཤེས་དང་། མི་གཙང་བའི་འདུ་ཤེས་དང་། རྨ་བསྐུ་བ་ལྟ་བུའི་འདུ་ཤེས་དང་། <tei:ref folio="F.172.b"/>དམན་པའི་འདུ་ཤེས་དང་། མི་འཐུན་པའི་འདུ་ཤེས་དང་། བུའི་ཤ་ལྟ་བུའི་འདུ་ཤེས་དང་། དོར་བའི་འདུ་ཤེས་དང་། སྤང་བའི་འདུ་ཤེས་དང་། དྲི་མི་ཞིམ་པའི་འདུ་ཤེས་བསྐྱེད་པར་བྱ་སྟེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>In other words, they should perceive food as excrement and urine, as pus, as vomit, as rubbish, as like a crusted wound, as base, as unpleasant, as like the flesh of children, as trash, as refuse, as fetid.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-26">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-28</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེས་དེ་ལྟ་བུའི་ཚུལ་དུ་བཟའ་ཞིང་ཚོད་རིག་པར་བྱའོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>In this manner they should think about what and how much they eat. “</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-27">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-30</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེས་ཆགས་པ་མེད་པ་དང་། སྡང་བ་མེད་པ་དང་། རྨོངས་པ་མེད་པ་དང་། རྟག་ཏུ་དབེན་པ་ལ་མངོན་པར་དགའ་བར་བྱ་སྟེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-009-30"/>Without attachment,<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="UT22084-059-009-31"/> aversion, and confusion, they should always delight in solitude.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-28">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-30</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྲེ་མོའི་གཏམ་ལ་མངོན་པར་དགའ་བར་མི་བྱའོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They should never delight in idle chatter.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-29">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-30</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།རི་དགས་འཆི་བ་ལྟ་བུར་དང་དུ་བླང་བར་བྱའོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They should readily accept solitude like a dying deer.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-30">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-30</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དབེན་པར་བྱའོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They should be isolated.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-31">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-30</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དབེན་པ་ལ་མངོན་པར་དགའ་བར་བྱའོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They should delight in solitude.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-32">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-30</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དབེན་པ་ལ་མངོན་པར་དགའ་ཞིང་མོས་པ་དང་། བཟོད་པ་དང་ལྡན་པར་བྱའོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Delighting in solitude, they should be resolute and patient.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-33">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-30</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེས་པ་དང་འགྲོགས་ན་བདེ་བར་བྱའོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>If associating with noble people, they should be pleasant.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-34">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-30</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།འཇིག་རྟེན་གྱི་གཏམ་ལ་མི་རྟེན་པར་བྱའོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They should not be given to worldly talk.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-35">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-30</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཉོ་ཚོང་སྤྱོད་པ་སྤང་བར་བྱའོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They should abandon commercial activity.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-36">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-30</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།སྨན་དཔྱད་ལ་དགའ་བ་དང་། ཕྲིན་པ་ལ་དགའ་བ་དང་། ཁྱིམ་གྱི་བྱ་བ་དང་འབྲེལ་པར་མི་བྱའོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Delight in medicinal cures, delight in gossip, and association with household activities should be avoided.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-37">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-30</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།འདུག་པ་དང་། འགྲེང་བ་དང་། འཆག་པ་དང་། ཉལ་བ་ལ་མཁས་པར་བྱའོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They should be discerning while sitting, standing, walking, and sleeping.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-38">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-30</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།རབ་ཏུ་དབེན་པ་དང་། དགོན་པར་དགའ་བ་དང་། ཞི་བའི་གནས་མལ་སྒྲ་ཆུང་བ། སྐད་ཆུང་བ། འཇིགས་པའི་ཡིད་ལ་བྱེད་པ་མེད་པ། སྡིག་སྦྲུལ་མེད་པ། མི་མང་པོ་མེད་པ། མིས་དབེན་པ། ནང་དུ་ཡང་དག་འཇོག་དང་འཚམ་པ་བསྟེན་པར་བྱའོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They should rely on total solitude, delightful retreats, and peaceful places<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="UT22084-059-009-32"/> that are quiet and silent, not frightening, without any slithering snakes, without many people, devoid of people, and suitable for inner absorption. “</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-39">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-33</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།བདག་བསྟོད་པར་ཡང་མི་བྱ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-009-33"/>They should refrain from self-exaltation.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-40">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-33</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཞན་སྨད་པར་ཡང་མི་བྱའོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They should refrain from belittling others.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-41">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-33</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཚུལ་འཆོས་པ་དང་ཁ་གསག་མི་བྱའོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They should refrain from pretension and flattery.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-42">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-33</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།རྟག་ཏུ་རྒྱུན་མི་ཆད་པར་སྐྱོ་བའི་སེམས་བསྐྱེད་པར་བྱའོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They should always and continuously cultivate an attitude of dissatisfaction.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-43">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-33</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེས་ཁྱིམ་པ་དང་། རབ་ཏུ་བྱུང་བ་རྣམས་དང་འདུ་ཞིང་འདྲིས་པར་མི་བྱའོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They should not associate with and get to know householders and monastics.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-44">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-33</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།སྟོང་པའི་ཆོས་རྣམས་ཀུན་ཏུ་བསྟེན་པར་བྱ། བསྒོམ་པར་བྱ། མང་དུ་བྱའོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They should rely on all empty dharmas, meditate on them, and expand on them.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-45">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-33</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེས་རིག་པ་དང་མི་ལྡན་པའི་དགེ་སློང་དང་ལྷན་ཅིག་ཕྲད་པ་སྤང་བར་བྱའོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They should avoid congregating with ignorant monks.<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="UT22084-059-009-34"/>
                </seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-46">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-33</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དགེ་སློང་མ་དང་འདྲིས་པར་མི་བྱའོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They should not associate with nuns.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-47">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-33</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།འདོད་པ་ཆུང་བར་ཡང་བྱའོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They should have few desires.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-48">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-33</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།རྟག་ཏུ་བདག་ཉིད་ཀྱི་འཁྲུལ་པ་རྣམས་ལ་སོ་སོར་བརྟག་པར་བྱའོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They should always examine themselves for personal faults.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-49">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-33</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།གཞན་གྱི་འཁྲུལ་པ་རྣམས་ལ་བརྟག་པར་མི་བྱའོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>And they should not look for the faults of others.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-50">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-33</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཕ་མ་ལ་ཡང་ཡིད་བརྟན་པར་མི་བྱ་ན། རིགས་གཞན་ལྟ་ལ་ཅི་སྨོས།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They should not rely on their parents, let alone other families.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-51">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-33</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཤིན་ཏུ་ཡང་དག་པར་བསྡམ་<tei:ref folio="F.173.a"/>པ་ཅན་དུ་བྱའོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They should be properly and thoroughly restrained.<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="UT22084-059-009-35"/>
                </seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-52">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-33</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཉེ་བར་ཞི་བའི་ཆོས་ཀྱི་སྦྱིན་བདག་བྱའོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They should be givers of the appeasing Dharma.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-53">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-33</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དམིགས་པ་ལ་མཁས་པར་བྱའོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They should be discriminating in their focus.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-54">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-33</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དབེན་པའི་གནས་མལ་དུ་གནས་པར་བྱའོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They should dwell in isolated places.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-55">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-33</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།འཐུན་པ་ཡང་གཞན་དག་ལ་སྨྲ་བར་མི་བྱ་ན་མི་འཐུན་པ་ལྟ་ཅི་སྨོས།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They should not speak to others even in an agreeable manner, let alone in an unagreeable manner. “</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-56">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-36</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེས་ཆོས་དེ་དག་ལ་སེམས་ཉེ་བར་གནས་པར་བྱས་ནས། ཆོས་ཟབ་མོ་རྣམས་ལ་སོ་སོར་བརྟག་པར་བྱའོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-009-36"/>They should establish their minds firmly in the teachings and analyze the profound dharmas.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-57">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-36</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཆོས་ཟབ་མོ་རྣམས་ལ་བརྟག་པར་བྱ་བ་དེ་དག་ཀྱང་གང་ཞེ་ན།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>What is it to analyze the profound dharmas?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-58">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-36</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མིག་མི་རྟག་གོ་སྙམ་དུ་སོ་སོར་བརྟག་པར་བྱའོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>It is to analyze by thinking, for example, that ‘the eye is impermanent.’</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-59">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-36</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེའི་སྐྱེ་བ་དང་འཇིག་པ་ལ་ཡང་སོ་སོར་བརྟག་པར་བྱའོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>It is to analyze its arising and dissolution.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-60">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-36</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ལ་སྐྱེ་བ་དང་། འཇིག་པ་ལ་སོ་སོར་བརྟག་པ་གང་ཡིན་པ་དེ་ནི་མེད་པ་ལ་སོ་སོར་རྟོག་པའོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>And that with respect to which arising and dissolution should be analyzed is itself analyzed as nonexistent.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-61">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-36</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ཅིའི་ཕྱིར་ཞེ་ན།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Why?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-62">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-36</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མིག་ཅེས་བྱ་བ་ནི་མེད་པའི་ཕྱིར་རོ། །མིག་དང་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>That which is called ‘eye’ does not exist.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-63">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-36</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཟུགས་དང་། མིག་གི་རྣམ་པར་ཤེས་པ་ནི་དམིགས་པ་མ་ཡིན་གྱི་མེད་པ་དམིགས་པ་ཡིན་ནོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Though the eye, form, and eye consciousness are not objects of perception, they are perceived as nonexistent.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-64">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-36</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ཅིའི་ཕྱིར་ཞེ་ན།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Why?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-65">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-36</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་དམིགས་པ་མེད་པའི་ཕྱིར་རོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>There are no dharmas that are objects of perception.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-66">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-36</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེས་རྣ་བའི་རྟེན་བསམ་པར་མི་བྱའོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Therefore, the support of the ear should not be imagined.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-67">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-36</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།སྣ་དང་། ལྕེ་དང་། ལུས་དང་། ཡིད་ཀྱི་རྟེན་བསམ་པར་མི་བྱའོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The supports of the nose, tongue, body, and mind should not be imagined.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-68">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-36</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཅི་ཡང་རུང་བའི་རྟེན་བསམ་པར་མི་བྱའོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>No support whatsoever should be imagined.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-69">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-36</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ལྟར་བྱས་ན་ཅི་ཞིག་བསམ་པ་ཡིན།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>What would be imagined when doing so?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-70">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-36</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་བཞིན་དུ་ཆོས་རྣམས་སྟོང་པར་ཡང་བརྩོན་པར་བྱའོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>All dharmas should be apprehended as empty in this way.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-71">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-36</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ལྟར་བརྩོན་པ་དེ་ནི་ཚུལ་ཁྲིམས་ཀྱི་ཕུང་པོ་ཡོངས་སུ་དག་པར་བྱེད་དོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Apprehending the dharmas in this way purifies the component of moral discipline.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-72">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-36</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་གྱི་ཕུང་པོ་དང་། ཤེས་རབ་ཀྱི་ཕུང་པོ་ཡོངས་སུ་དག་པར་བྱེད་དོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>It purifies the components of concentration and of wisdom.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-73">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-36</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།རྒྱུན་དུ་ཞུགས་པའི་འབྲས་བུ་འཐོབ་པར་འགྱུར་རོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>It gives rise to the result of stream-entry.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-74">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-36</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ལན་ཅིག་ཕྱིར་འོང་བའི་འབྲས་བུ་དང་། ཕྱིར་མི་འོང་བའི་འབྲས་བུ་དང་། དགྲ་བཅོམ་པ་ཉིད་ཐོབ་པར་འགྱུར་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>And it gives rise to the result of the once-returner, the result of the non-returner, and arhathood.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-75">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-36</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ལྟ་བུའི་འདུ་འཛི་མེད་པ་ནི་དང་པོའི་ཉན་ཐོས་ཀྱི་ས་ཡིན་ཏེ། དེ་དག་གིས་ཟག་པ་ཟད་པ་ཐོབ་པར་འགྱུར་རོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Detached in this way, the initial śrāvakas eliminated their defilements. “</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-76">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-37</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ལ་དགེ་སློང་ལྟར་བཅོས་པ་གང་ཞེ་ན།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-009-37"/>Now, what are imposter monks?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-77">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-37</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡུལ་འཁོར་སྐྱོང་འདི་ན་དགེ་སློང་བདག་ཉིད་ལ་ངའོ་སྙམ་དུ་འཛིན་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Rāṣṭrapāla, such monks cling to the conception that they are themselves monks.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-78">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-37</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནི་ཚུལ་ཁྲིམས་ཀྱི་ཕུང་པོ་ཡོངས་སུ་མ་རྫོགས་པ་དང་ལྡན་པ་ཡིན།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Their component of moral discipline is incomplete.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-79">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-37</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཆོས་གོས་གཅེས་པར་འཛིན་པ་དང་། ལྷུང་བཟེད་གཅེས་པར་འཛིན་པ་ཡིན།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They cherish their robes and begging bowls.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-80">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-37</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཟང་ཟིང་གཅེས་པར་འཛིན་པ་ཡིན་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They cherish material things.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-81">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-37</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནི་མི་སྨྲ་བ་སྤངས་<tei:ref folio="F.173.b"/>ནས་ངན་སོང་དུ་འགྱུར་བའི་མལ་ཆ་དང་། སྟན་དང་། མགྲོན་དུ་གཉེར་བ་ཆེན་པོ་རྣམས་བདག་གིར་བྱེད།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Abandoning silence, they claim for themselves bedding, seats, and great invitations that lead to unfortunate rebirths.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-82">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-37</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བུད་མེད་དང་འདྲིས་པར་བྱེད།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They associate with women.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-83">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-37</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དགེ་སློང་མ་དང་འདྲིས་པར་བྱེད།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They associate with nuns.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-84">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-37</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྒྱལ་པོས་བཀྲབས་པ་དང་འདྲིས་པར་བྱེད་དེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They associate with those favored by the king.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-85">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-37</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་འདྲིས་པར་གྱུར་ནས་རྒྱུན་མི་འཆད་པར་མིག་གིས་གཟུགས་རྣམས་ལ་ངེས་པར་སེམས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>And through associating with them, their eyes are always intent on forms.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-86">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-37</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེས་དེ་ལྟར་སེམས་བསྐྱེད་ནས་ཀུན་ནས་ཉོན་མོངས་པར་འགྱུར་རོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>By cultivating such a mind, they are thoroughly afflicted.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-87">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-37</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཀུན་ནས་ཉོན་མོངས་པའི་སེམས་དང་ལྡན་ན་གནས་འདི་ལྟ་བུ་ཡོད་དོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>If their mind is afflicted, so will be their condition.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-88">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-37</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཉེས་པ་ལྕི་བ་དེ་བྱེད་པའམ། ཡང་ན་ཆུང་ངུ་བྱེད་ཅིང་འདུག་པར་འགྱུར་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They will consistently make serious mistakes or small ones.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-89">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-37</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡུལ་འཁོར་སྐྱོང་འདི་ནི་དགེ་སློང་ལྟར་བཅོས་པ་ཡིན་ནོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>These, Rāṣṭrapāla, are imposter monks. “</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-90">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-38</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཡུལ་འཁོར་སྐྱོང་ཅིའི་ཕྱིར་དགེ་སློང་ལྟར་བཅོས་པ་ཡིན་ཞེ་ན།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-009-38"/>Why are they imposter monks?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-91">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-38</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དགེ་སློང་ལྟར་བཅོས་པ་དེ་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པས་མལ་ཆ་དང་། སྟན་གནང་བ་ཐ་མལ་པ་གང་ལ་དགེ་སྦྱོང་གནས་པའི་མལ་ཆ་དང་སྟན་གང་ཡིན་པ་མི་བླུན་པོ་དེས་སྤངས་ན་ཆོས་གོས་ལ་ཞེན་ཅིང་ཟང་ཟིང་ལ་ཞེན་ནས་བུད་མེད་དང་འདྲིས་པར་བྱེད་ཅིང་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Imposter monks are those fools who reject the plain bedding and seats approved by the Thus-Gone One, which are the bedding and seats proper to ascetics, who yearn for robes, who yearn for material things, and who associate with women and householders.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-92">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-38</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཁྱིམ་པ་དང་འདྲིས་པར་བྱེད་ན་འདྲིས་པར་འགྱུར་བའི་མི་བླུན་པོ་དེ་ལ་དགེ་སྦྱོང་གི་ཚུལ་ལྟ་ག་ལ་ཡོད་དེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>How could ascetic conduct be found in fools with such associations?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-93">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-38</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེའི་སྟེང་དུ་ཆོས་ཟབ་མོ་རྣམས་ལ་ཡང་སུན་འབྱིན་ཅིང་གཤེ་བར་བྱས།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Moreover, they criticize and revile the profound dharmas.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-94">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-38</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལས་དེས་ཐོས་སུ་ཟིན་ཀྱང་བསྔགས་པ་མ་ཡིན་པ་རྗོད་པར་བྱེད་དོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Although they have heard of karma, they speak ill of others.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-95">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-38</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དགོན་པའི་བསྔགས་པ་མ་ཡིན་པ་རྗོད་པར་བྱེད་དོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They speak ill of the wilderness.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-96">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-38</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།གང་ལ་དེའི་སེམས་མངོན་པར་དགའ་བའི་འདོད་པ་རྣམས་འབའ་ཞིག་གི་བསྔགས་པ་རྗོད་པར་བྱེད་ཅིང་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They praise those who are solely focused on desire for pleasure.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-97">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-38</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་ལ་དེའི་སེམས་མངོན་པར་དགའ་བའི་བྲེ་མོའི་གཏམ་འབའ་ཞིག་གི་བསྔགས་པ་རྗོད་པར་བྱེད་ལ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They praise those who are solely absorbed in pleasurable idle chatter.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-98">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-38</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དགེ་སློང་གི་གནས་གང་ཡང་རུང་བ་དེ་དག་གི་བསྔགས་པ་མ་ཡིན་པ་རྗོད་པར་བྱེད་དོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They speak ill of those possessing any of the conditions of monks. “</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-99">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-39</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།གང་ལ་ལས་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པས་མདོའི་ཚིག་ཁྱིམ་ན་གནས་པ་དང་། རབ་ཏུ་བྱུང་བ་རྣམས་དང་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-009-39"/>The Thus-Gone One said in a sūtra, ‘There is no occasion to associate with householders and monastics.’</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-100">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-39</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདུ་འཛིར་མི་འབྱུང་བར་བྱའོ་ཞེས་གསུངས་པའི་མདོའི་ཚིག་དེ་བོར་ནས་དགེ་སྦྱོང་གི་ཚུལ་མི་འདོད་ཅིང་དགེ་སློང་གི་དངོས་པོ་མི་འདོད་དེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Those who reject this have no desire for ascetic conduct. They have no desire to be a monk.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-101">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-39</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཅིག་པུར་འདུག་ཅིང་བུད་མེད་ལ་ཆོས་འཆད་པར་བྱེད་ལ་གཞན་དག་ལ་ཡང་དེ་ལྟ་བུའི་གཞི་རྣམས་སུ་ལུང་འབོག་པར་བྱེད་པའོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Sitting apart, they teach the Dharma to women and instruct others still in the foundations of such behavior.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-102">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-39</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ཅིའི་ཕྱིར་<tei:ref folio="F.174.a"/>ཞེ་ན།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Why?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-103">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-39</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་དག་ནི་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པས་ཆོས་ཀྱི་ཆོམ་རྐུན་པར་གསུངས་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The Thus-Gone One describes them as the robbers of the Dharma.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-104">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-39</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སོ་སོར་ཐར་པ་སྤངས་ནས་གཅིག་པུར་འདུག་ཅིང་བུད་མེད་ལ་ཆོས་འཆད་པའི་ཕྱིར་རོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Abandoning the prātimokṣa vows, they sit apart and teach the Dharma to women.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-105">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-39</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།མི་བླུན་པོ་དེ་དག་ནི་བཅོས་མ་སྟེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>These fools are imposter monks.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-106">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-39</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མགོ་བྲེགས་པས་བཅོས་པ་དང་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>With their shaven heads, they are imposters.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-107">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-39</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གོས་ངུར་སྨྲིག་གྱོན་པས་བཅོས་པའོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>With their saffron robes, they are imposters. “</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-108">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-40</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།རྒྱུ་གང་གིས་བཅོས་མ་ཡིན་པར་ཤེས་པར་བྱ་ཞེ་ན།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-009-40"/>How can an imposter be known?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-109">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-40</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སངས་རྒྱས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་སྨད་པ་གང་ཡིན་པ་དེ་ནི་མི་བླུན་པོ་དེ་དག་གིས་གནང་བར་བྱེད་དེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Those fools approve of that which the blessed buddhas condemn.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-110">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-40</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལོ་ཉི་ཤུ་མ་ལོན་པར་རྫོགས་པར་བསྙེན་པར་བྱེད།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They ordain people before they reach twenty years of age.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-111">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-40</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རང་གི་ལག་གིས་ལེན་པར་བྱེད།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They take with their own hands.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-112">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-40</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མ་བརྟགས་པ་ལ་ལོངས་སྤྱོད་པར་བྱེད།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They enjoy things without thinking.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-113">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-40</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རང་ཉིད་གཡོས་དང་འཚེད་པའི་ལས་བྱེད།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They prepare and cook food for themselves.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-114">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-40</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གསེར་དང་དངུལ་བདག་གིར་བྱེད།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They handle gold and silver.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-115">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-40</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཁྲེ་རྒོད་དང་། འབྲུ་ལ་སོགས་པ་བསོགས་པར་བྱེད།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They accumulate millet, barley, and other grains.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-116">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-40</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཁྱིམ་གྱི་གཞི་དང་། ཞིང་གི་གཞི་དང་། ཀུན་དགའ་ར་བའི་གཞི་ཉོ་ཚོང་བྱེད་ཅིང་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They engage in commercial activity related to houses, fields, and parks.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-117">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-40</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཚལ་ཟའི་འཚོ་བ་སྦྱོར་བར་བྱེད།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They employ servants.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-118">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-40</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཁྱིམ་གྱི་གཞི་དང་། ཞིང་གི་གཞི་དང་། ཀུན་དགའ་ར་བའི་གཞི་ལེན་པར་བྱེད་དེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They appropriate objects related to houses, fields, and parks.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-119">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-40</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལས་ཀྱི་རྣམ་པར་སྨིན་པ་ལ་ཡང་ཡིད་མི་ཆེས་ཤིང་སོ་སོར་ཐར་པ་ལ་ཡང་མ་དད་ནས་དེ་ལ་འབབ་དེ་ལ་བབ་དེ་ལ་བདེན་པར་འཛིན་དེའི་སྤྱོད་ལམ་བྱེད།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Not believing in the fruition of karma, not having confidence in the prātimokṣa, toward that lifestyle are they inclined, toward that lifestyle do they fall, toward that lifestyle do they sink—they act as if that is all there is.<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="UT22084-059-009-41"/>
                </seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-120">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-40</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དགེ་སྦྱོང་དུ་འདྲ་བར་འཛིན་ཅིང་གང་ན་སྐྱེ་བོ་མང་པོ་ཡོད་པ་དེར་གཅེར་བུ་པ་དང་མཚུངས་པར་སྟོན་པར་བྱེད།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Regarding themselves as ascetics, where there are many people, they teach in a way that resembles the naked ascetics.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-121">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-40</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་ཟག་ཏུ་ལྟ་བ་བསྔགས་པར་བྱེད།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They champion the view of personal identity.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-122">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-40</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་ཟག་ཏུ་ལྟ་བ་དང་། གཅེར་བུ་པ་དང་མཚུངས་པར་སྟོན་པས། སྐྱེ་བོ་མང་པོ་འཛུད་པར་བྱེད་ཅིང་འགོད་པར་བྱེད།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>By teaching personal identity, and like the naked ascetics, they draw many people in and transfix them.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-123">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-40</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱི་སྤྱོད་ཡུལ་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པའི་གནས་པ་སྟོང་པ་ཉིད་ལ་དམིགས་ནས་སུན་འབྱིན་པར་བྱེད།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Apprehending the domain of buddhas, the condition of thus-gone ones, as empty, they disparage it.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-124">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-40</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཤེ་བར་བྱེད་པར་ཤེས་པར་བྱའོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They are known to revile it. “</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-125">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-42</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཡུལ་འཁོར་སྐྱོང་དེ་ལྟ་བུའི་སེམས་ཅན་དག་འབྱུང་བར་འགྱུར་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-009-42"/>Rāṣṭrapāla, sentient beings such as these will arise.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-126">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-42</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་དག་ནི་ཁྱིམ་པ་ཡང་མ་ཡིན། དགེ་སྦྱོང་ཡང་མ་ཡིན་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They are not householders, nor are they ascetics.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-127">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-42</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་དག་གིས་ནི་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པའི་བསྟན་པ་འདི་ནུབ་པར་བྱེད་དོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They will bring about the decline of the Thus-Gone One’s teaching.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-128">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-43</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་དེའི་ཚེ་ཚིགས་སུ་བཅད་པ་འདི་དག་བཀའ་སྩལ་ཏོ། །དགེ་སློང་ཚུལ་ཁྲིམས་རྣམས་ལ་བསྡམ། །ཞི་ཞིང་ཞི་བའི་གནས་ལ་དགའ། །སོ་སོར་ཐར་པ་སློབ་བྱེད་པ། །དེ་དག་དགེ་<tei:ref folio="F.174.b"/>སློང་བྲམ་ཟེ་ཡིན།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-009-43"/>Then, the Lord at that time spoke the following verses: <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-009-44"/>“Monks<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="UT22084-059-009-45"/> who are restrained in moral discipline, Who, at peace, delight in calm places, Who train in the prātimokṣa— They are brahmin monks. “</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-129">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-46</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཆོས་རྣམས་གཙོ་བོ་བླངས་ནས་ནི། །ཅི་ཡང་མེད་པའི་དགེ་སློང་བ། །བས་མཐའ་དགོན་པ་རྣམས་སུ་དགའ། །དེ་དག་དགེ་སློང་བྲམ་ཟེ་ཡིན།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-009-46"/>Taking up the most important dharmas, Monks who have nothing, Who delight in the remote wilderness— They are brahmin monks. “</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-130">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-47</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་དག་བྲེ་མོ་གཏམ་མི་དགའ། །སོ་སོར་ཐར་རྣམས་ལེགས་པར་བསླབས། །གང་ཟག་མཆོག་ལ་ཉིན་མཚན་དུ། །བཀུར་སྟི་ཆེན་པོ་བྱེད་པ་ཡིན།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-009-47"/>Those who do not delight in idle chatter, Who train well in the prātimokṣa, Pay great veneration, day and night, To the superior person. “</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-131">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-48</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཞིང་ཡང་མི་རྨེད་ཚོང་མི་བྱེད། །ལྷུང་བཟེད་ཆོས་གོས་རྙེད་མི་ཚོལ། །ལེན་པ་མེད་པར་བརྩོན་པ་གང་། །དེ་དག་སངས་རྒྱས་ཉན་ཐོས་ཡིན།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-009-48"/>Those who neither till the fields nor buy and sell, Who do not pine for begging bowls and robes, And who make effort without appropriation Are the Buddha’s śrāvakas. “</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-132">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-49</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་དག་བུད་མེད་སྟོན་མི་བྱེད། །བུད་མེད་རྣམས་དང་འདུ་བ་མེད། །ཤིང་དྲུང་རྣམས་ནི་བསྔགས་པར་བྱེད། །དེ་དག་སངས་རྒྱས་ཉན་ཐོས་ཡིན།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-009-49"/>Those who do not teach women,<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="UT22084-059-009-50"/> Who do not associate with women, Who praise those who sit under trees— They are the Buddha’s śrāvakas. “</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-133">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-51</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཟས་དང་སྐོམ་གྱི་དོན་གྱི་ཕྱིར། །གཅམ་གསག་དག་ཀྱང་ཡང་མི་བྱེད། །དེ་འདྲར་གྱུར་པ་དེ་དག་ནི། །དགེ་སློང་མོ་ལ་སྟེན་མི་བྱེད།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-009-51"/>Do not offer flattery, For the sake of food and drink; Monks who become like that Do not spend time around women. “</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-134">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-52</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།མཚོན་རྣོ་ཇི་ལྟར་བདར་བ་བཞིན། །བུད་མེད་རྣམས་ནི་དེ་འདྲར་ཤེས།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-009-52"/>Women are known to be Like sharp swords polished.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-135">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-52</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།སོ་སོར་ཐར་ལས་བྱུང་བ་བཞིན། །བུད་མེད་འདུ་ཤེས་སྤོང་བར་བྱེད།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>From the prātimokṣa it follows That the idea of women is abandoned. “</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-136">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-53</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེས་པ་དེ་དག་ཟས་ཕྱིར་དང་། །སྐོམ་གྱི་ཕྱིར་དང་གོས་ཀྱི་ཕྱིར། །ཁྱིམ་ཁྱིམ་དག་ཏུ་འགྲོ་བྱེད་ཅིང་། །ཆོས་རྣམས་སྟོན་པར་མི་བྱེད་དོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-009-53"/>Those gentle ones, for the sake of food, For drink, and for robes, Go from house to house But do not teach the dharmas. “</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-137">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-54</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དགེ་སློང་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་བུད་མེད་རྣམས། །བལྟ་བར་མི་བྱ་རྫོགས་སངས་རྒྱས།།དེ་ལ་ཤེས་ལྡན་སུ་ཞིག་རྟོན།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-009-54"/>‘Monks should not look at women,’ The Perfectly Awakened One has said. Rely on those who know that.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-138">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-54</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ནི་བདུད་ཀྱི་སྤྱོད་ཡུལ་ཡིན།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Looking at women is the sphere of Māra. “</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-139">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-55</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་དག་གིས་ནི་མེད་པར་སྨྲས། །རོ་དང་ཉལ་བ་བཞིན་དུ་ཉལ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-009-55"/>They teach that women are nonexistent, That to lie down with a woman is like lying with a corpse.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-140">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-55</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ཕྱིར་སངས་རྒྱས་ཐམས་ཅད་མཁྱེན། །འདུ་འཛི་བསྔགས་པར་མི་མཛད་དོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>For that reason, the all-knowing buddhas Do not commend distractions. “</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-141">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-56</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཆོས་རྣམས་སྲོག་མེད་གསོ་བ་མེད། །གསོབ་དང་གསོག་དང་སྙིང་པོ་མེད།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-009-56"/>The dharmas are without life force, without personality, Hollow, insignificant, and insubstantial.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-142">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-56</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།སྟོང་པ་ཉིད་ལ་མོས་བྱེད་པ། །དེ་ནི་དགེ་སློང་ཆོས་ཉིད་དོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Those who affirm emptiness<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="UT22084-059-009-57"/>— They are true monks. “</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-143">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-58</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།རྟག་ཏུ་བརྩོན་འགྲུས་ཕུན་སུམ་ཚོགས། །གཅིག་པུ་དགོན་པར་གནས་བྱེད་དང་། །འཇིག་རྟེན་ན་ནི་རྟེན་མེད་སེམས། །དེ་ནི་དགེ་སློང་ཆོས་ཉིད་དོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-009-58"/>Those who always abound in strong effort, Who dwell in the wilderness alone, Whose minds do not rely on the world— They are true monks. “</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-144">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-59</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།སེང་གེ་བཞིན་དུ་འཇིགས་པ་མེད། །ཚངས་པར་སྤྱོད་ལ་གཞོལ་བར་བྱེད།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-009-59"/>Fearless like lions, They dedicate themselves to pure conduct.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-145">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-59</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།སྡུག་བསྔལ་ཀུན་ལས་ཐར་བྱའི་ཕྱིར། །ཤེས་རབ་ལྡན་པས་ལམ་ལ་སྒོམ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>For the sake of liberation from all suffering, Those endowed with wisdom cultivate the path. “</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-146">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-60</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།མིག་དང་གཟུགས་ནི་ཚོལ་བ་ན། །དེ་དག་གིས་ནི་རྣམ་ཤེས་རྙེད།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-009-60"/>When examining the eye and form, They find consciousness.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-147">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-60</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དངོས་པོ་དེ་ཡང་ཚོལ་བ་ན། །བཙལ་བ་གང་ཡིན་མི་<tei:ref folio="F.175.a"/>རྙེད་དོ། །སྔོན་ཡང་མ་བྱུང་ཕྱིས་མི་འབྱུང་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They do not find what they are looking for When examining objects— Those did not arise before, and they will not arise later.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-148">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-60</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དབུས་ནའང་ཡོད་པ་མ་ཡིན་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>In the middle, too, there is nothing. “</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-149">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-61</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ལྟ་བུ་ཡི་དོན་གྱིས་ན། །ཆོས་ཀུན་མཉམ་པ་ཉིད་ཀྱི་ཕྱིར། །དེས་པ་དེ་དག་ཟས་ཕྱིར་དང་། །སྐོམ་གྱི་ཕྱིར་དང་གོས་ཀྱི་ཕྱིར། །ཁྱིམ་ཁྱིམ་དག་དུ་འགྲོ་བྱེད་ཅིང་། །ཆོས་རྣམས་སྟོན་པར་མི་བྱེད་དོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-009-61"/>This being the case, On account of the sameness of all dharmas, Those gentle ones, for the sake of food, For drink, and for robes Go from house to house, But they do not teach the dharmas. “</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-150">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-62</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།རྒྱུ་མེད་དེས་པ་བཟང་པོ་ཡིན།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-009-62"/>Without cause, the gentle are virtuous.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-151">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-62</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་དག་སངས་རྒྱས་བསླབས་པ་རྣམས། །འདའ་ཞིང་འཇིག་པར་མི་བྱེད་དེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They do not violate or destroy The precepts of the Buddha.<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="UT22084-059-009-63"/>
                </seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-152">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-62</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།བརྟུལ་བཟང་སྟོང་ཉིད་སྐྲག་པ་མེད།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Disciplined and virtuous, they do not fear emptiness.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-153">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-62</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།འཇིགས་པ་མེད་པར་འཇུག་པར་བྱེད།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They enter into fearlessness.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-154">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-62</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ལྟ་བ་མི་བཟད་འཇིག་མི་བྱེད།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They do not eliminate the frightening view. “</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-155">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-64</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།སེམས་ཅན་གང་ཟག་དངོས་མི་འཇིག །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-009-64"/>They do not eliminate actual sentient persons.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-156">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-64</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དཀར་པོའི་ཆོས་རྣམས་ཐམས་ཅད་ལ། །ཤིན་ཏུ་བརྟན་པར་གནས་པ་ཡིན།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>In all wholesome dharmas, They remain well established.<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="UT22084-059-009-65"/>
                </seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-157">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-64</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།བརྟན་པོ་དེ་དག་འཇིག་རྟེན་ན། །མྱ་ངན་འདས་པའང་རེག་གྱུར་ནས། །མཆོད་པའི་གནས་སུ་འོས་པར་འགྱུར།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Steadfast, those who in the world Reach nirvāṇa Will become worthy of veneration. “</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-158">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-66</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།གང་དག་ཤེས་རབ་འཆལ་པ་དང་། །ལེ་ལོ་ཅན་དང་དམན་ལ་བརྩོན། །ཐོས་པ་ཉུང་དང་སྡིག་པ་འདོད། །ང་རྒྱལ་ཐ་བ་ཁྲོ་འགྱུར་གནས། །མགོ་ལ་སྤུ་གྲི་སྟེན་བྱེད་ཅིང་། །ཤིང་གིས་ཁ་བསྒྱུར་ཆོས་གོས་གྱོན། །སྟོང་པ་ཉིད་ནི་དོན་མེད་པ། །དེ་ནི་མཁས་པ་སྒོམ་མི་བྱེད།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-009-66"/>Those who are lacking in wisdom, Who are lazy, who make little effort, Who have learned little, who desire wickedness, Who are arrogant, harsh, and quick to anger,<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="UT22084-059-009-67"/> Who take a razor to their heads, Who wear wood-dyed Dharma robes, Who do not understand the meaning of emptiness— They do not cultivate discernment. “</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-159">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-68</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཆོས་ལ་སུན་འབྱིན་ཐེག་ཆེན་གྱི། །བསྔགས་པ་མ་ཡིན་རྗོད་པར་བྱེད།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-009-68"/>They disparage the Dharma And speak ill of the Great Vehicle.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-160">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-68</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།གང་ཞིག་ཆོས་འདི་བསྟན་པ་རྣམས། །ཇི་ལྟར་བསྟན་པ་དེ་བཞིན་དུ། །ནག་པོའི་ཕྱོགས་ལ་ཀུན་ཏུ་ཆགས།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Those who have taught this Dharma In accordance with what they have been taught Are attached to the dark faction.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-161">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-68</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེས་ནི་ངན་འགྲོར་འགྲོ་བར་འགྱུར།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They are bound for unfortunate rebirth.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-162">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-69</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་དེ་སྐད་ཅེས་བཀའ་སྩལ་ནས། ཚེ་དང་ལྡན་པ་ཡུལ་འཁོར་སྐྱོང་དང་། དགེ་སློང་དེ་དག་དང་། ལྷ་དང་། མི་དང་། ལྷ་མ་ཡིན་དང་། དྲི་ཟར་བཅས་པའི་འཇིག་རྟེན་ཡི་རངས་ཏེ། བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་གསུངས་པ་ལ་མངོན་པར་བསྟོད་དོ།། །།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-009-69"/>When the Blessed One had spoken, the venerable Rāṣṭrapāla and the world with its monks, gods, humans, asuras, and gandharvas rejoiced and praised what the Blessed One had said.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-163">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-70</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཕགས་པ་ཡུལ་འཁོར་སྐྱོང་གིས་ཞུས་པ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་ཐེག་པ་ཆེན་པོའི་མདོ་རྫོགས་སྷོ།། །།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-009-70"/>The Great Vehicle sūtra “The Questions of Rāṣṭrapāla (2)” is complete.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-059-009-TU-164">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-059-009-71</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྒྱ་གར་གྱི་མཁན་པོ་ཛི་ན་མི་ཏྲ་ལ་སོགས་པ་དང་། ཞུ་ཆེན་གྱི་ལོཙྪ་བ་བནྡེ་ཡེ་ཤེས་སྡེས་བསྒྱུར་ཅིང་ཞུས་ཏེ་གཏན་ལ་ཕབ་པ།། །།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-059-009-71"/>The Indian scholar Jinamitra and others, along with the chief editor-translator Bandé Yeshé Dé, translated, edited, and finalized the text.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
</body>
</tmx>