<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tmx xmlns="http://www.lisa.org/tmx14" xmlns:eft="http://read.84000.co/ns/1.0" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" version="1.4b">
<header creationtool="InterText" creationtoolversion="1.0" datatype="PlainText" segtype="block" adminlang="en-us" srclang="bo" o-tmf="TEI" eft:text-id="UT22084-057-008" eft:text-version="v-1.0.8-2021"/>
<body>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.330.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཕགས་པ་བྱམས་པས་ཞུས་པ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་ཐེག་པ་ཆེན་པོའི་མདོ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The Noble Mahāyāna Sūtra The Question of Maitreya (3)</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.330.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སངས་རྒྱས་དང་། བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཐམས་ཅད་ལ་ཕྱག་འཚལ་ལོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-057-008-24"/>Homage to all buddhas and bodhisattvas!</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.330.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདི་སྐད་བདག་གིས་ཐོས་པ་དུས་གཅིག་ན། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Thus did I hear at one time.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.330.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་རྒྱལ་པོའི་ཁབ་ན་བྱ་རྒོད་ཀྱི་ཕུང་པོའི་རི་ལ་དགེ་སློང་གི་དགེ་འདུན་ཆེན་པོ་དང་ཐབས་ཅིག་ཏུ་བཞུགས་ཏེ། བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའི་དགེ་འདུན་ཆེན་པོ་དང་ཡང་ཐབས་ཅིག་གོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The Blessed One was dwelling in Rājagṛha, on Vulture Peak Mountain, together with a great saṅgha of monks and a great saṅgha of bodhisattvas.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.330.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོ་བྱམས་པ་སྟན་ལས་ལངས་ཏེ། བླ་གོས་ཕྲག་པ་གཅིག་ཏུ་གཟར་ནས། པུས་མོ་གཡས་པའི་ལྷ་ང་ས་ལ་བཙུགས་ཏེ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-057-008-27"/>On that occasion the bodhisattva mahāsattva Maitreya<tei:note xml:id="UT22084-057-008-28"/> rose from his seat, draped his shawl over one shoulder, and knelt on his right knee.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.330.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ག་ལ་བ་དེ་ལོགས་སུ་ཐལ་མོ་སྦྱར་བ་བཏུད་ནས། བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ལ་འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་གསོལ་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Joining his palms and bowing to the Blessed One, he spoke these words:</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.330.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་འདི་ལ་ཆོས་སྦྱིན་པའི་རྣམ་པར་སྨིན་པ་གང་ལགས། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Blessed One, what are the karmic results of bestowing the Dharma?”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.330.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོ་བྱམས་པ་ལ་འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་བཀའ་སྩལ་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-057-008-29"/>The Blessed One replied to the bodhisattva mahāsattva Maitreya,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.330.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱམས་པ་སུས་སྟོང་གསུམ་གྱི་སྟོང་ཆེན་པོའི་འཇིག་རྟེན་གྱི་ཁམས་གང་གཱའི་ཀླུང་གི་བྱེ་མ་སྙེད་རིན་པོ་ཆེ་སྣ་བདུན་གྱིས་ཡོངས་སུ་བཀང་སྟེ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Maitreya, suppose one person filled as many great trichiliocosms as there are grains of sand in the river Ganges with the seven precious substances and</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.330.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་དགྲ་བཅོམ་པ་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་སངས་རྒྱས་རྣམས་ལ་དབུལ་བ་ཕུལ་བ་བས། གང་གིས་སྙིང་རྗེ་བས་ཚིགས་སུ་བཅད་པ་གཅིག་གཞན་གྱི་རྒྱུད་ལ་བཞག་ན་བྱམས་པ་བསོད་ནམས་ཀྱི་ཕུང་པོ་འདི་ལ་བསོད་ནམས་ཀྱི་ཕུང་པོ་སྔ་མ་དེས་བརྒྱའི་ཆར་ཡང་ཉེ་བར་མི་འགྲོ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>offered them to the tathāgata, arhat, truly perfect buddhas, and another person, out of compassion, established a single verse of the Dharma in the mindstream of another. Maitreya, the former mass of merit would not even come close to a hundredth of this latter mass of merit.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.330.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྟོང་གི་ཆ་དང་། བརྒྱ་སྟོང་གི་ཆ་དང་། བྱེ་བའི་ཆ་དང་། བྱེ་བ་ཁྲག་ཁྲིག་བརྒྱ་སྟོང་གི་ཆ་དང་། གྲངས་དང་། ཆ་དང་། བགྲང་བ་དང་། དཔེ་དང་རྒྱུར་ཡང་མི་བཟོད་དོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Nor could it be compared to even a thousandth, a hundred-thousandth, a ten-millionth, a hundred-sextillionth,<tei:note xml:id="UT22084-057-008-30"/> or any other portion, fraction, enumeration, or example.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.330.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བདེ་བར་གཤེགས་པས་དེ་སྐད་གསུངས་ནས། སྟོན་པས་གཞན་ཡང་འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་བཀའ་སྩལ་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-057-008-31"/>After the Sugata had said this, the Teacher furthermore declared:</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.330.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་གིས་གང་གཱའི་བྱེ་སྙེད་འཇིག་རྟེན་ཁམས། །དེ་དག་རིན་ཆེན་བྱུར་བུར་བཀང་བྱས་ཏེ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Consider one who has caused as many world realms as there are sand grains in the Ganges To be filled to the brim with an abundance of riches<tei:note xml:id="UT22084-057-008-33"/>
                </seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.330.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དགའ་རབ་སེམས་ཀྱིས་རྒྱལ་ལ་ཕུལ་བ་བས། །གང་གིས་ཚིགས་བཅད་གཅིག་ཅིག་སེམས་ཅན་བྱིན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>And offered these to the victors with a joyful mind, And another who has bestowed a single verse to a sentient being—</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.331.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རིན་ཆེན་སྦྱིན་པ་ཤིན་ཏུ་རྒྱ་ཆེན་དེ། །སྙིང་རྗེ་བསྐྱེད་ནས་ཚིགས་བཅད་སྦྱིན་པ་ལ། །གང་གཱའི་ཆ་དང་གྲངས་སུའང་མི་ཕོད་<tei:ref folio="F.331.a"/>ན། །ལན་གཉིས་ལན་གསུམ་སེམས་ལ་ག་ལ་ཞིག །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-057-008-34"/>“If that exceedingly vast gift of riches Does not equal any fraction or portion<tei:note xml:id="UT22084-057-008-35"/> Of cultivating compassion and then bestowing a single verse, How could one fathom the ripening of giving a verse twice, or three times?”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.331.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་དེ་སྐད་ཅེས་བཀའ་སྩལ་ནས། བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོ་བྱམས་པ་དང་། བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་དེ་དག་དང་། དགེ་སློང་དེ་དག་དང་། ལྷ་དང་། མི་དང་། ལྷ་མ་ཡིན་དང་། དྲི་ཟར་བཅས་པའི་འཇིག་རྟེན་ཡི་རངས་ཏེ། བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་གསུངས་པ་ལ་མངོན་པར་བསྟོད་དོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-057-008-37"/>When the Blessed One had spoken, the bodhisattva mahāsattva Maitreya, the other bodhisattvas and the monks,<tei:note xml:id="UT22084-057-008-38"/> and the world with its gods, humans, asuras, and gandharvas rejoiced and praised the words of the Blessed One.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.331.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཕགས་པ་བྱམས་པས་ཞུས་པ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་ཐེག་པ་ཆེན་པོའི་མདོ་རྫོགས་སོ།།</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-057-008-39"/>This completes the noble Mahāyāna sūtra “The Question of Maitreya.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
</body>
</tmx>