<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tmx xmlns="http://www.lisa.org/tmx14" xmlns:eft="http://read.84000.co/ns/1.0" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" version="1.4b">
    <header creationtool="InterText" creationtoolversion="1.0" datatype="PlainText" segtype="block" adminlang="en-us" srclang="bo" o-tmf="TEI" eft:text-id="UT22084-066-007" eft:text-version="v-1.5.2-2019"/>
    <body>
        <tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.59.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">translation</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཕགས་པ་ཆོས་བཞི་བསྟན་པ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་ཐེག་པ་ཆེན་པོའི་མདོ། </seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The Noble Mahāyāna Sūtra Entitled Teaching the Four Factors</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.59.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-066-007-16</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སངས་རྒྱས་དང་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཐམས་ཅད་ལ་ཕྱག་འཚལ་ལོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-066-007-16"/>Homage to all the buddhas and bodhisattvas!</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.59.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-066-007-55</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདི་སྐད་བདག་གིས་ཐོས་པ་དུས་གཅིག་ན། </seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-066-007-55"/>Thus did I hear at one time.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.59.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-066-007-55</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་སུམ་ཅུ་རྩ་གསུམ་ལྷའི་ནང་ན་ལྷའི་འདུན་ས་ཆོས་བཟང་ན་དགེ་སློང་ལྔ་བརྒྱ་ཐམ་པའི་དགེ་སློང་གི་དགེ་འདུན་ཆེན་པོ་དང་། བྱམས་པ་དང་། འཇམ་དཔལ་ལ་སོགས་པ་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོ་རབ་ཏུ་མང་པོ་དང་ཐབས་ཅིག་ཏུ་བཞུགས་ཏེ</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The Blessed One was dwelling in the Sudharmā assembly hall in the Heaven of the Thirty-Three, together with a great gathering of five hundred monks,<tei:note xml:id="UT22084-066-007-17"/> and very many bodhisattva mahāsattvas, including Maitreya and Mañjuśrī.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.59.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-066-007-18</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོ་བྱམས་པ་ལ་བཀའ་སྩལ་པ། </seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-066-007-18"/>At that time the Blessed One said to the bodhisattva mahāsattva Maitreya,</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.59.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-066-007-18</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>
                    <tei:ref folio="F.59.b"/>བྱམས་པ་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོ་ཆོས་བཞི་དང་ལྡན་ན་སྡིག་པ་བྱས་ཤིང་བསགས་པ་ཟིལ་གྱིས་ནོན་པར་འགྱུར་རོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“O Maitreya, bodhisattva mahāsattva, if you possess four factors, the misdeeds you have committed and accumulated will be overcome.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.59.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-066-007-19</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཞི་གང་ཞེ་ན། </seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-066-007-19"/>“What are these four?</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.59.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-066-007-19</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྣམ་པར་སུན་འབྱིན་པ་ཀུན་ཏུ་སྤྱོད་པ་དང་། གཉེན་པོ་ཀུན་ཏུ་སྤྱོད་པ་དང་། སོར་ཆུད་པར་བྱེད་པའི་སྟོབས་དང་། རྟེན་གྱི་སྟོབས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The action of repentance, antidotal action, the power of restraint, and the power of support.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.59.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-066-007-56</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྣམ་པར་སུན་འབྱིན་པ་ཀུན་ཏུ་སྤྱོད་པ་ནི་མི་དགེ་བའི་ལས་སྤྱད་ན་དེ་ལ་འགྱོད་པ་མང་བ་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-066-007-56"/>“The action of repentance is to feel intense remorse for any non-virtuous action you have committed.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.59.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-066-007-57</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ལ་གཉེན་པོ་ཀུན་ཏུ་སྤྱོད་པ་ནི་མི་དགེ་བའི་ལས་བྱས་ནས་ཀྱང་དགེ་བའི་ལས་ལ་ཤིན་ཏུ་བརྩོན་པའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-066-007-57"/>“Antidotal action is to put great effort into virtuous actions once you have committed a non-virtuous action.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.59.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-066-007-58</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ལ་སོར་ཆུད་པར་བྱེད་པའི་སྟོབས་ནི་སྡོམ་པ་ཡང་དག་པར་བླངས་པས་མི་ཕྱེད་པའི་སྡོམ་པ་ཐོབ་པའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-066-007-58"/>“The power of restraint is to make a pledge and thereby refrain from any similar action.<tei:note xml:id="UT22084-066-007-20"/>
                </seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.59.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-066-007-59</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ལ་རྟེན་གྱི་སྟོབས་ནི་སངས་རྒྱས་དང་། ཆོས་དང་། དགེ་འདུན་ལ་སྐྱབས་སུ་འགྲོ་བ་དང་། བྱང་ཆུབ་ཀྱི་སེམས་མི་གཏོང་བ་སྟེ། </seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-066-007-59"/>“The power of support is to take refuge in the Buddha, Dharma, and Saṅgha, and not to forsake the mind of awakening.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.59.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-066-007-59</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་སྟོབས་དང་ལྡན་པ་ལ་རྟེན་པས་སྡིག་པས་ཟིལ་གྱིས་གནོན་པར་མི་ནུས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>By relying on such powerful forces, you will be immune to misdeeds.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.59.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-066-007-21</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱམས་པ་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོ་ཆོས་བཞི་པོ་དེ་དག་དང་ལྡན་ན་སྡིག་པ་བྱས་ཤིང་བསགས་པ་ཟིལ་གྱིས་ནོན་པར་འགྱུར་རོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-066-007-21"/>“O Maitreya, bodhisattva mahāsattva, if you possess these four factors, you will overcome any misdeeds that you have committed and accumulated.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.59.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-066-007-21</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོས་མདོ་འདི་རྟག་ཏུ་བཀླག་པར་བྱའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The bodhisattva mahāsattva should continually read this sūtra,</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.59.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-066-007-21</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཁ་ཏོན་དུ་བྱའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>recite it aloud,</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.59.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-066-007-21</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བསམ་པར་བྱའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>and reflect [and meditate] on it,</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.59.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-066-007-21</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བསྒོམ་པར་བྱའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>[and reflect] and meditate on it,</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.59.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-066-007-21</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མང་དུ་བྱའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>doing so many times.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.59.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-066-007-21</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེས་ན་ཉེས་པར་སྤྱད་པ་འབྲས་བུ་འབྱིན་མི་ནུས་པར་འགྱུར་རོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Through this, the effects of negative conduct will not come about.”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.59.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-066-007-22</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་དེ་སྐད་ཅེས་བཀའ་སྩལ་ནས། </seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-066-007-22"/>Once the Blessed One had said this,</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.59.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-066-007-22</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོ་བྱམས་པ་དང་། དགེ་སློང་དེ་དག་དང་། བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་དེ་དག་དང་། བརྒྱ་བྱིན་ལ་སོགས་པའི་ལྷའི་བུ་རྣམས་དང་། ཐམས་ཅད་དང་ལྡན་པའི་འཁོར་དེ་དག་ཡི་རངས་ཏེ། བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་གསུངས་པ་ལ་མངོན་པར་བསྟོད་དོ།། །།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>the whole assembly, including the bodhisattva mahāsattva Maitreya, the monks, the bodhisattvas, and the ranks of the gods, such as Śakra, were overjoyed and full of praise for what the Blessed One had taught.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.59.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-066-007-23</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཕགས་པ་ཆོས་བཞི་བསྟན་པ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་ཐེག་པ་ཆེན་པོའི་མདོ་རྫོགས་སོ།། །། </seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-066-007-23"/>This concludes the noble Mahāyāna sūtra entitled “Teaching the Four Factors.”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu>
            <prop type="folio">F.59.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-066-007-24</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྒྱ་གར་གྱི་མཁན་པོ་སུ་རེན་དྲ་བོ་དྷི་དང་། ཞུ་ཆེན་གྱི་ལོཙྪ་བ་བན་དེ་ཡེ་ཤེས་སྡེས་བསྒྱུར་ཅིང་ཞུས་ཏེ་གཏན་ལ་ཕབ་པ།། ༄༅༅། །རྒྱ་གར་སྐད་དུ། ཙ་ཏུར་དྷརྨ་ཀ་སཱུ་ཏྲ། བོད་སྐད་དུ། ཆོས་བཞི་པའི་མདོ། སངས་རྒྱས་དང་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-066-007-24"/>Translated, edited, and corrected by the Indian preceptor Surendrabodhi and the principal editor and translator venerable Yeshé Dé.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
    </body>
</tmx>