<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tmx xmlns="http://www.lisa.org/tmx14" xmlns:eft="http://read.84000.co/ns/1.0" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<header creationtool="linguae-dharmae/84000" datatype="PlainText" segtype="block" adminlang="en-us" srclang="bo" o-tmf="TEI" eft:text-id="UT22084-062-005" eft:text-version="v-1.0.6-2023"/>
<body>
<tu id="UT22084-062-005-TU-1">
    <prop type="location-id">translation</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>
                    <tei:ref folio="F.92.a"/>༄༅༅། །རྒྱ་གར་སྐད་དུ།  ཨཱརྱ་ནཱ་ག་ར་ཨ་བ་ལམ་བི་ཀཱ་ནཱ་མ་མ་ཧཱ་ཡཱ་ན་སཱུ་ཏྲ། བོད་སྐད་དུ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg/>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-062-005-TU-2">
    <prop type="location-id">translation</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཕགས་པ་གྲོང་ཁྱེར་གྱིས་འཚོ་བ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་ཐེག་པ་ཆེན་པོའི་མདོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-005-translation"/>The Noble Mahāyāna Sūtra The City Beggar Woman</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-062-005-TU-3">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-062-005-91</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སངས་རྒྱས་དང་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཐམས་ཅད་ལ་ཕྱག་འཚལ་ལོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-005-91"/>Homage to all buddhas and bodhisattvas.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-062-005-TU-4">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-062-005-91</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདི་སྐད་བདག་གིས་ཐོས་པ་དུས་གཅིག་ན།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Thus did I hear at one time.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-062-005-TU-5">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-062-005-91</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་མཉན་ཡོད་ན་རྒྱལ་བུ་རྒྱལ་བྱེད་ཀྱི་ཚལ་མགོན་མེད་ཟས་སྦྱིན་གྱི་ཀུན་དགའ་ར་བ་ན་ལྷ་དང་། ཀླུ་དང་། གནོད་སྦྱིན་དང་། དྲི་ཟ་དང་། ལྷ་མ་ཡིན་དང་། ནམ་མཁའ་ལྡིང་དང་། མིའམ་ཅི་དང་། ལྟོ་འཕྱེ་ཆེན་པོ་དང་། བརྒྱ་བྱིན་དང་། ཚངས་པ་དང་། འཇིག་རྟེན་སྐྱོང་བ་དང་། རྒྱལ་པོ་དང་། བློན་པོ་དང་། བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་དང་། དགེ་སློང་དང་། དགེ་སློང་མ་དང་། དགེ་བསྙེན་དང་། དགེ་བསྙེན་མ་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་བཀུར་སྟིར་བྱས།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>While staying in Śrāvastī, in Prince Jeta’s Grove, Anāthapiṇḍada’s park, the Blessed One was served, honored, venerated, and revered by gods, nāgas, yakṣas, gandharvas, asuras, garuḍas, kinnaras, and mahoragas; by Śakra, Brahmā, and the world protectors; by kings and ministers; and by bodhisattvas, monks, nuns, laymen, and laywomen.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-062-005-TU-6">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-062-005-91</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བླ་མར་བྱས། མཆོད་ཅིང་བརྗེད་དེ། <tei:ref folio="F.92.b"/>པད་མ་ཆུས་མ་གོས་པ་བཞིན་དུ་བཞུགས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Yet he remained like a lotus unsullied by water.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-062-005-TU-7">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-062-005-95</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་དེའི་ཚེ་རྒྱལ་པོ་གསལ་རྒྱལ་གྱིས་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་ལ་མཆོད་པའི་ཕྱིར་སྟོན་ཟླ་ཐ་ཆུང་ས་ཟླ་བ་ཉ་བའི་ཚེས་བཅྭ་ལྔ་ལ། འབྲུ་མར་གྱིས་ཟངས་པོ་ཆེ་སྟོང་བཀང་སྟེ་དངར་ནས་མར་མེ་སྦར་བའི་འོད་ཀྱིས་ཁོ་ར་ཁོར་ཡུག་ཏུ་དཔག་ཚད་བཞིར་སྣང་བས་ཁྱབ་པར་བྱས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-005-95"/>At that time, in order to venerate the Thus-Gone One, on the full moon day of the last month of autumn, King Prasenajit had a thousand large copper cauldrons filled with grain oil and set them out so that the entire area for four leagues around was illuminated by their flames.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-062-005-TU-8">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-062-005-96</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་ཡང་དེའི་ཚེ་མཉན་ཡོད་ཀྱི་གྲོང་ཁྱེར་ཆེན་པོ་ན་དགའ་བྱེད་མ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་གྲོང་ཁྱེར་གྱིས་འཚོ་བ་ཞིག་འདུག་གོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-005-96"/>At the same time, in the great city of Śrāvastī, there was a city beggar woman called Maker of Joy.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-062-005-TU-9">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-062-005-96</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེས་འབྲུ་མར་སྲན་གྲེའུ་དང་སྦྱར་བ་ཉོས་ནས་ཞག་བཞི་ཁ་འཚོས་ཏེ་ཉམ་ཆུང་བར་གྱུར་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>She had bought a tiny amount of oil, as a result of which she had gone without food for four days and had grown weak.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-062-005-TU-10">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-062-005-100</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་འབྲུ་མར་དེ་ཁྱེར་ཏེ་རྒྱལ་བུ་རྒྱལ་བྱེད་ཀྱི་ཚལ་དུ་སོང་ནས་ཁྱམས་ཀྱི་ནང་ལོགས་སུ་མར་མེ་སྦར་ཏེ་བཞག་ནས་འདི་ལྟར་སེམས་བསྐྱེད་དེ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>She took the oil to Prince Jeta’s Grove and, using it to light a lamp at the edge of the courtyard, she made this wish:<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-005-100"/> “Blessed One, with this root of virtue, may I too become a teacher in the future.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-062-005-TU-11">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-062-005-100</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་བདག་དགེ་བའི་རྩ་བ་འདིས་མ་འོངས་པའི་དུས་ན་ཇི་ལྟར་ད་ལྟར་གྱི་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་དགྲ་བཅོམ་པ་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་སངས་རྒྱས་ཇི་ལྟ་བ་བཞིན་དུ་བདག་ཀྱང་མ་འོངས་པའི་དུས་ན་སྟོན་པར་གྱུར་ཏེ་ཆོས་སྟོན་པར་གྱུར་ཅིག །དགེ་འདུན་ཡང་སྡུད་པར་གྱུར་ཅིག་ཅེས་བྱས་སོ། །འདི་ལྟར་ཡང་སེམས་བསྐྱེད་དེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>May I teach the Dharma and gather a community, just as the thus-gone, worthy, perfect, and complete Buddha does now.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-062-005-TU-12">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-062-005-100</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གལ་ཏེ་བདག་མ་འོངས་པའི་དུས་ན་སངས་རྒྱས་སུ་འགྱུར་བ་ཞིག་ན། མར་མེ་འདི་བདག་ཕྱིར་མ་འོངས་ཀྱི་བར་དུ་འབར་བར་གྱུར་ཅིག་ཅེས་བྱས་ནས་མར་མེ་དེ་སྤར་ཏེ་གྲོང་ཁྱེར་དུ་སོང་ན།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>If I am to become a buddha in the future, may this oil lamp continue to burn until I return.” Whereupon she lit the lamp, and returned to the city.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-062-005-TU-13">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-062-005-101</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མར་མེ་དེའི་འོད་ཀྱིས་འཛམ་བུའི་གླིང་ཐམས་ཅད་སྣང་བར་གྱུར་ཏེ་ནམ་ནངས་ཀྱི་བར་དུ་ཡང་མར་མེ་དེ་མ་ཤིའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-005-101"/>The light of that oil lamp illuminated all of Jambudvīpa and the following day the lamp was still burning.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-062-005-TU-14">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-062-005-101</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་ཚེ་དང་ལྡན་པ་མཽང་གལ་གྱི་བུ་ཆེན་པོས་ཆོས་གོས་ཀྱི་མཐའ་མས་མར་མེ་གསད་པར་བྱས་ན་གསད་པར་མ་ནུས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Then Venerable Mahā­maudgalyāyana tried to put it out with the edge of his robe, but he could not.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-062-005-TU-15">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-062-005-101</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་ཚེ་དང་ལྡན་པ་མཽད་གལ་གྱི་བུ་ཆེན་པོས་རྣམ་པར་འཐོར་རླུང་གིས་གསད་པར་བྱས་ཀྱང་གསད་པར་མ་ནུས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Venerable Mahā­maudgalyāyana then tried to extinguish it with gales of wind, but still he could not put it out.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-062-005-TU-16">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-062-005-101</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་ཚེ་དང་ལྡན་པ་མཽང་གལ་གྱི་བུ་ཆེན་པོས་ཚངས་པའི་འཇིག་རྟེན་དུ་འདུག་ནས་སྟོང་གསུམ་འདིར་ཤིང་རྟའི་སྲོག་ཤིང་ཙམ་གྱི་ཆར་གྱི་རྒྱུན་དབབ་པར་བྱིན་གྱིས་བརླབས་ཏེ་མར་མེ་དེའི་སྟེང་དུ་བཏང་ཡང་གསད་པར་མ་ནུས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Venerable Mahā­maudgalyāyana then went to the Brahmā realms and caused sheets of rain the size of chariot axles to fall upon this whole trichiliocosm. However, even though he directed the deluge right over the lamp, still he could not douse it.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-062-005-TU-17">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-062-005-104</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་བཀའ་སྩལ་པ། མཽད་གལ་གྱི་བུ་ཐོང་ཤིག །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-005-104"/>Then the Blessed One said, “Let it be, Maudgalyāyana!</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-062-005-TU-18">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-062-005-104</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མར་མེ་འདི་ནི་བྱང་ཆུབ་ཀྱི་སེམས་ཀྱིས་སྦར་བ་ཡིན་ལ། བྱང་ཆུབ་ཀྱི་སེམས་ནི་ཉན་ཐོས་ཀྱིས་ཟིལ་གྱིས་གནན་པར་མི་ནུས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>This lamp has been lit with a mind set on awakening, and a mind set on awakening cannot be overcome by a śrāvaka.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-062-005-TU-19">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-062-005-104</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ཅིའི་<tei:ref folio="F.93.a"/>ཕྱིར་ཞེ་ན།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>How so?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-062-005-TU-20">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-062-005-104</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཐམས་ཅད་མཁྱེན་པ་ཉིད་ཀྱི་སེམས་ནི་ཉན་ཐོས་དང་། རང་སངས་རྒྱས་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱིས་ཟིལ་གྱིས་གནན་དུ་མེད་པའི་ཕྱིར་རོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Because no śrāvaka or pratyekabuddha can ever overcome a mind set on omniscience.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-062-005-TU-21">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-062-005-105</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་རེ་ཞིག་ན་བུད་མེད་དེ་ཉི་མ་ཤར་ཏེ་གྲོང་ཁྱེར་ནས་ཕྱིར་འོངས་ནས།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-005-105"/>A while later, as the sun was rising, the woman returned from the city.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-062-005-TU-22">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-062-005-105</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེས་མར་མེ་དེ་ཤིན་ཏུ་འབར་བ་མཐོང་བ་དང་། དེ་མཆོག་ཏུ་དགའ་བ་ཆེན་པོས་རྒྱས་པར་གྱུར་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>When she saw that the lamp was still burning brightly, she was filled with tremendous joy.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-062-005-TU-23">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-062-005-106</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་དེའི་ཚེ་འཛུམ་པ་མཛད་དོ། །སངས་རྒྱས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་རྣམས་ཀྱི་ཆོས་ཉིད་ནི་འདི་ཡིན་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-005-106"/>At that moment, the Blessed One smiled.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-062-005-TU-24">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-062-005-106</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་གི་ཚེ་སངས་རྒྱས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་འཛུམ་པ་མཛད་པ་དེའི་ཚེ་སངས་རྒྱས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་རྣམས་ཀྱི་ཞལ་གྱི་སྒོ་ནས་འོད་ཟེར་ཁ་དོག་དུ་མ་འདི་ལྟ་སྟེ། སྔོན་པོ་དང་། སེར་པོ་དང་། དམར་པོ་དང་། དཀར་པོ་དང་། བཙོད་ཀ་དང་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>It is the nature of things that whenever a blessed buddha smiles, rays of light of many colors—blue, yellow, red, white, crimson, and the colors of crystal and silver—stream forth from the blessed buddha’s mouth.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-062-005-TU-25">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-062-005-106</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཤེལ་དང་། དངུལ་གྱི་ཁ་དོག་ལྟ་བུ་དག་བྱུང་བར་གྱུར་ཏེ། འཇིག་རྟེན་གྱི་ཁམས་མཐའ་ཡས་མུ་མེད་པ་དག་སྣང་བས་ཁྱབ་པར་བྱས་ནས་ཚངས་པའི་འཇིག་རྟེན་གྱི་བར་དུ་སོང་སྟེ་ཟླ་བ་དང་ཉི་མའི་འོད་ཀྱང་ཟིལ་གྱིས་མནན་ནས་ཡང་སླར་ལོག་སྟེ་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ལ་ལན་གསུམ་བསྐོར་བ་བྱས་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱི་དབུའི་གཙུག་ཏོར་དུ་ནུབ་པར་གྱུར་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>These illuminate and pervade worlds without end, reaching as far as the Brahmā realms where they outshine even the sun and the moon. They then return once again, and, after circling the blessed one thrice, descend into the uṣṇīṣa at the crown of that blessed one’s head.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-062-005-TU-26">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-062-005-106</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་འོད་ཟེར་དེ་དག་གིས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ལ་ལན་གསུམ་བསྐོར་བ་བྱས་ཏེ་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱི་དབུའི་གཙུག་ཏོར་དུ་མི་སྣང་བར་གྱུར་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>So, indeed, did such rays of light, having circled the Blessed One thrice, disappear into the uṣṇīṣa of the Blessed One’s head.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-062-005-TU-27">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-062-005-108</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ལ་ཚེ་དང་ལྡན་པ་ཀུན་དགའ་བོས་ཚིགས་སུ་བཅད་དེ་གསོལ་པ། རྒྱལ་མཆོག་རྣམ་པར་འདྲེན་པ་གང་ཟག་མཆོག །རྒྱུ་མེད་པར་ནི་འཛུམ་པ་མི་མཛད་ན། །ཅི་ཡི་རྐྱེན་གྱིས་ཞལ་ནི་འཛུམ་མཛད་པ། །འཇིག་རྟེན་ཕན་པ་ཐུགས་བརྩེས་བདག་ལ་གསུངས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-005-108"/>Venerable Ānanda then spoke the following verse to the Blessed One:<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-005-109"/> “Excellent victor, guide, and best of men, You do not smile without reason, So please, with compassion, for the benefit of the world, Tell us what gives you cause to smile.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-062-005-TU-28">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-062-005-110</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་བཀའ་སྩལ་པ། ཀུན་དགའ་བོ་གྲོང་ཁྱེར་གྱིས་འཚོ་བ་འདི་བསྐལ་པ་ཉི་ཤུ་རྩ་བརྒྱད་ཀྱི་བར་དུ་ངན་འགྲོ་ལོག་པར་ལྟུང་བར་འགྲོ་བར་མི་འགྱུར་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-005-110"/>The Blessed One replied, “Ānanda, this city beggar woman will not fall into a lower rebirth for twenty-eight eons.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-062-005-TU-29">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-062-005-110</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྟག་ཏུ་ལྷ་དང་མིའི་ཕུན་སུམ་ཚོགས་པ་དག་ཉམས་སུ་མྱོང་ནས་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་དགྲ་བཅོམ་པ་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་སངས་རྒྱས་ཀུན་དུ་སྣང་བ་ཞེས་བྱ་བར་འགྱུར་རོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>She will experience only the abundance of the human and god realms, and then will become a thus-gone, worthy, perfect, and complete buddha called All-Illuminating.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-062-005-TU-30">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-062-005-111</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་དེའི་ཚེ་ཚིགས་སུ་བཅད་པ་འདི་དག་བཀའ་སྩལ་ཏོ། །སྟོབས་བཅུ་ལྡན་པ་མཆོད་ཕྱིར་ཟངས་ཆེན་ཕྲག་སྟོང་གསལ་རྒྱལ་གྱིས། །མར་མེ་བཟང་པོ་སྦར་བས་<tei:ref folio="F.93.b"/>དཔག་ཚད་བཞིར་ནི་ཀུན་དུ་སྣང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-005-111"/>Then the Blessed One spoke these verses:<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-005-112"/> “To venerate the holder of ten powers, Prasenajit lit a thousand fine lamps In huge copper cauldrons, which illuminated everything for four leagues.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-062-005-TU-31">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-062-005-111</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གྲོང་ཁྱེར་འཚོ་བའི་འབྲུ་མར་སྲན་མ་གྲེའུ་སྦྱར་སྦར་བ་ཡིས། །འཛམ་གླིང་སྣང་བས་ཁྱབ་གྱུར་དེ་ནི་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་ཀྱི་མཐུས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The city beggar woman lit a lamp with a tiny amount of oil And, by the power of the mind set on awakening, it illuminated the whole world.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-062-005-TU-32">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-062-005-113</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མཽད་གལ་གྱིས་ནི་མར་མེ་གསད་འདོད་རྫུ་འཕྲུལ་རྒྱ་ཆེན་བྱས། །རྣམ་པར་འཐོར་བའི་རླུང་གི་ཤུགས་བཏང་གསད་པར་ཡོང་མ་ནུས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-005-113"/>“Maudgalyāyana wanted to extinguish the lamp with his vast magical powers, But even powerful gales could not extinguish it.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-062-005-TU-33">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-062-005-113</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཚངས་པའི་འཇིག་རྟེན་འདུག་ནས་ཆུ་རྒྱུན་ཤིང་རྟའི་སྲོག་ཤིང་ཙམ། །ཕབ་ཀྱང་གསད་པར་མ་ནུས་མར་མེ་ཉི་མའི་འོད་བཞིན་སྣང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Sending down sheets of rain the size of chariot axles from the Brahmā realms, Still he could not douse that lamp, which shone like the sun.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-062-005-TU-34">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-062-005-114</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནི་ཞག་བཞི་ཁ་འཚོས་རྒྱལ་བྱེད་དགའ་བའི་ཚལ་དུ་འོངས། །དགའ་བའི་སེམས་ཀྱིས་བདེ་གཤེགས་ཞབས་ལ་ཕྱག་བྱས་ཐལ་སྦྱར་འདུག །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-005-114"/>“After four days with no food, she came to the delightful Jeta Grove And, with joyful heart, paid respects with folded hands to the feet of the Sugata.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-062-005-TU-35">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-062-005-114</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མཉམ་མེད་འཛུམ་པ་མཛད་པས་ཀུན་དགའ་བོ་ཡང་རབ་དགའ་ནས། །གཟི་བརྗིད་མཐའ་ཡས་འཛུམ་མཛད་འདི་ཡི་འབྲས་བུ་ཇི་འདྲ་གསུངས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The peerless one smiled, and Ānanda, thoroughly delighted, asked, ‘What kind of result does this smile foretell, infinitely radiant one?’</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-062-005-TU-36">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-062-005-115</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དགའ་བྱེད་འདི་ནི་བསྐལ་པ་ཉི་ཤུ་བརྒྱད་ན་རྒྱལ་བར་འགྱུར། །རང་བྱུང་ཀུན་སྣང་ཞེས་བྱ་འོད་ཀྱིས་སྟོང་ཆེན་བཞི་སྣང་བྱེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-005-115"/>“In twenty-eight eons, this Maker of Joy will be a victor, a self-arisen one Known as All-Illuminating, and she will illuminate four great chiliocosms.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-062-005-TU-37">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-062-005-115</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མ་འོངས་དུས་ན་བདེ་བར་གཤེགས་པ་བྱེ་བ་མཆོད་པར་འགྱུར། །དེ་ནི་ཀུན་དུ་འཁོར་ལོས་སྒྱུར་འགྱུར་རྒྱལ་རྣམས་བཀུར་སྟིར་བྱེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>In the future, she will make offerings to ten million sugatas; She will become a universal monarch and venerate the victors.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-062-005-TU-38">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-062-005-116</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སངས་རྒྱས་རྟོགས་པ་བརྗོད་པ་ཡི་ནི་དད་རྣམས་རབ་དགའ་བྱེད། །སྐྱེ་བོ་མཁས་པ་དག་གིས་དེ་ཐོས་སེམས་ཀྱང་རབ་ཏུ་དགའ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-005-116"/>“This exemplary tale about a future buddha will delight the faithful And the wise who hear it will also feel joy.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-062-005-TU-39">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-062-005-116</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ལྟར་རྒྱལ་བ་བསམ་ཡས་སྟོབས་བཅུའི་ཆོས་ཀྱང་བསམ་མི་ཁྱབ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>In this way, the qualities of innumerable victors with the ten powers are inconceivable.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-062-005-TU-40">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-062-005-116</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དགའ་བ་བསྐྱེད་ན་རྣམ་སྨིན་མཚུངས་མེད་བསམ་གྱིས་མི་ཁྱབ་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>So the matchless result of rejoicing in them will also be inconceivable.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-062-005-TU-41">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-062-005-118</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་དེ་སྐད་ཅེས་བཀའ་སྩལ་ནས། ཚེ་དང་ལྡན་པ་ཀུན་དགའ་བོ་དང་། གྲོང་ཁྱེར་གྱིས་འཚོ་བ་དེ་དང་། བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་དེ་དག་དང་། དགེ་སློང་དེ་དག་དང་། ལྷ་དང་། མི་དང་། ལྷ་མ་ཡིན་དང་། དྲི་ཟར་བཅས་པའི་འཇིག་རྟེན་ཡི་རངས་ཏེ། བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་གསུངས་པ་ལ་མངོན་པར་བསྟོད་དོ།། །།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-005-118"/>Thus spoke the Blessed One, and Venerable Ānanda, the city beggar woman, the bodhisattvas and monks, along with the gods, humans, asuras, and gandharvas of the world, rejoiced and thoroughly praised what the Blessed One had said.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-062-005-TU-42">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-062-005-119</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཕགས་པ་གྲོང་ཁྱེར་གྱིས་འཚོ་བ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་ཐེག་པ་ཆེན་པོའི་མདོ་རྫོགས་སོ།། །།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-005-119"/>This concludes The Noble Mahāyāna Sūtra “The City Beggar Woman.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-062-005-TU-43">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-062-005-120</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྒྱ་གར་གྱི་མཁན་པོ་ཛྙཱ་ན་གརྦྷ་དང་། ལོ་ཙྪ་བ་བན་དེ་ཀླུའི་དབང་པོས་བསྒྱུར་བ། རྒྱ་གར་གྱི་མཁན་པོ་བིདྱཱ་ཀ་ར་སིང་ཧ་དང་། ཞུ་ཆེན་གྱི་ལོ་ཙྪ་བ་བན་དེ་དེ་བ་ཙན་དྲས་ཞུས་ཏེ་གཏན་ལ་ཕབ་པ།​། །​།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-005-120"/>Translated by the Indian preceptor Jñānagarbha and Lotsawa Bandé Lui Wangpo. Edited and finalized by the Indian preceptor Vidyākarasiṃha and senior editor Lotsawa Bandé Devacandra.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>

</body>
</tmx>