<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tmx xmlns="http://www.lisa.org/tmx14" xmlns:eft="http://read.84000.co/ns/1.0" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<header creationtool="linguae-dharmae/84000" datatype="PlainText" segtype="block" adminlang="en-us" srclang="bo" o-tmf="TEI" eft:text-id="UT22084-066-009" eft:text-version="v-1.0.2-2023"/>
<body>
<tu id="UT22084-066-009-TU-1">
    <prop type="location-id">translation</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>
                    <tei:ref folio="F.60.b"/>༄༅༅། །རྒྱ་གར་སྐད་དུ། ཨཱརྱ་ཙ་ཏུར་དྷརྨ་ཀཾ་ནཱ་མ་མ་ཧཱ་ཡཱ་ན་སཱུ་ཏྲ། བོད་སྐད་དུ། </seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-066-009-TU-2">
    <prop type="location-id">translation</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཕགས་པ་ཆོས་བཞི་པ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་ཐེག་པ་ཆེན་པོའི་མདོ། </seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The Noble Mahāyāna Sūtra on The Four Factors 
</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-066-009-TU-3">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-066-009-26</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སངས་རྒྱས་དང་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཐམས་ཅད་ལ་ཕྱག་འཚལ་ལོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-066-009-26"/>Homage to all the buddhas and bodhisattvas!
</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-066-009-TU-4">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-066-009-226</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།འདི་སྐད་བདག་གིས་ཐོས་པ་དུས་གཅིག་ན། བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་མཉན་ཡོད་ན་རྒྱལ་བུ་རྒྱལ་བྱེད་ཀྱི་ཚལ་མགོན་མེད་ཟས་སྦྱིན་གྱི་ཀུན་དགའ་ར་བ་ན།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-066-009-226"/>Thus did I hear at one time.
</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-066-009-TU-5">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-066-009-226</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དགེ་སློང་སྟོང་ཉིས་བརྒྱ་ལྔ་བཅུའི་དགེ་སློང་གི་དགེ་འདུན་ཆེན་པོ་དང་ཐབས་ཅིག་ཏུ་བཞུགས་ཏེ། བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའི་ཚོགས་ཆེན་པོ་དང་ཡང་ཐབས་ཅིག་གོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The Buddha was residing in Śrāvastī at Jeta’s Grove, Anāthapiṇḍada’s park, together with a great community of monks, consisting of 1,250 monks, and a great assembly of bodhisattvas.
</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-066-009-TU-6">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-066-009-30</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་དགེ་སློང་རྣམས་ལ་བཀའ་སྩལ་པ། དགེ་སློང་དག་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོས་ཆོས་བཞི་པོ་འདི་དག་ཇི་སྲིད་འཚོའི་བར་དུ་སྲོག་གི་ཕྱིར་ཡང་ཡོངས་སུ་མི་གཏོང་ངོ་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>At that time, the Blessed One addressed the monks: <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-066-009-30"/>“Monks, for as long as they live, bodhisattvas, great beings, should not abandon four factors even at the cost of their lives.
</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-066-009-TU-7">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-066-009-30</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།བཞི་གང་ཞེ་ན།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>What are these four? “
</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-066-009-TU-8">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-066-009-31</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དགེ་སློང་དག་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོས་ཇི་སྲིད་འཚོའི་བར་དུ་བྱང་ཆུབ་ཀྱི་སེམས་སྲོག་གི་ཕྱིར་ཡང་ཡོངས་སུ་མི་གཏང་བ་དང་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-066-009-31"/>Monks, for as long as they live, bodhisattvas, great beings, should not abandon the thought of awakening even at the cost of their lives. “
</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-066-009-TU-9">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-066-009-32</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དགེ་སློང་དག་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོས་ཇི་སྲིད་འཚོའི་བར་དུ་དགེ་བའི་བཤེས་གཉེན་སྲོག་གི་ཕྱིར་ཡང་ཡོངས་སུ་མི་གཏང་བ་དང་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-066-009-32"/>Monks, for as long as they live, bodhisattvas, great beings, should not abandon the spiritual friend even at the cost of their lives. “
</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-066-009-TU-10">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-066-009-33</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དགེ་སློང་དག་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོས་ཇི་སྲིད་འཚོའི་བར་དུ་བཟོད་པ་དང་དེས་པ་སྲོག་གི་ཕྱིར་ཡང་ཡོངས་སུ་མི་གཏང་བ་དང་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-066-009-33"/>Monks, for as long as they live, bodhisattvas, great beings, should not abandon tolerance and lenience even at the cost of their lives.<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="UT22084-066-009-34"/> “
</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-066-009-TU-11">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-066-009-35</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དགེ་སློང་དག་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོས་ཇི་སྲིད་འཚོའི་བར་དུ་དགོན་པ་ལ་གནས་པ་སྲོག་གི་ཕྱིར་ཡང་ཡོངས་སུ་གཏང་བར་མི་བྱ་སྟེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-066-009-35"/>Monks, for as long as they live, bodhisattvas, great beings, should not abandon dwelling in the wilderness<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="UT22084-066-009-135"/> even at the cost of their lives. “
</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-066-009-TU-12">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-066-009-36</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དགེ་སློང་དག་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོས་ཇི་སྲིད་འཚོའི་བར་དུ་ཆོས་བཞི་པོ་འདི་དག་སྲོག་གི་ཕྱིར་ཡང་ཡོངས་སུ་གཏང་བར་མི་བྱའོ། །བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་དེ་སྐད་ཅེས་བཀའ་སྩལ་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-066-009-36"/>Monks, for as long as they live, bodhisattvas, great beings, should not abandon these four factors even at the cost of their lives.”
</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-066-009-TU-13">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-066-009-37</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བདེ་བར་གཤེགས་པས་དེ་སྐད་གསུངས་ནས། སྟོན་པས་གཞན་ཡང་འདི་སྐད་བཀའ་སྩལ་ཏོ། །ཐམས་ཅད་མཁྱེན་ཉིད་སེམས་ནི་མི་གཏོང་ཞིང་། །མཁས་པས་རྫོགས་པའི་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་སྐྱེད་ཅིག །བཟོད་པ་དེས་པའི་སྟོབས་ལ་རབ་གནས་ཏེ། །དགེ་བའི་བཤེས་གཉེན་ཡོངས་སུ་གཏང་མི་བྱ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-066-009-37"/>The Blessed One spoke these words, and once the Sugata had spoken in this way, he, the Teacher, also said the following: <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-066-009-38"/>“Let the wise conceive the thought of perfect awakening, And not cast aside the thought of omniscience;<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="UT22084-066-009-39"/> Let them maintain the strength of tolerance and lenience, And never forsake the spiritual friend. “
</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-066-009-TU-14">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-066-009-40</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།རི་དགས་རྒྱལ་པོ་བཞིན་དུ་འཇིགས་སྤངས་ཏེ། །མཁས་<tei:ref folio="F.61.a"/>པས་དགོན་གནས་རྟག་ཏུ་བསྟེན་པར་བྱ། །ཆོས་འདི་དག་ལ་རྟག་ཏུ་རབ་གནས་ན། །བདུད་རྣམས་བཅོམ་ནས་བྱང་ཆུབ་དེ་འཚང་རྒྱ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-066-009-40"/>If the wise, like the king of beasts, abandon fear, Always remain dwelling in the wilderness, And constantly maintain these factors, They will conquer the māras and attain awakening.”
</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-066-009-TU-15">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-066-009-41</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་དེ་སྐད་ཅེས་བཀའ་སྩལ་ནས། དགེ་སློང་དེ་དག་དང་། བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་དེ་དག་དང་། ཐམས་ཅད་དང་ལྡན་པའི་འཁོར་དེ་དག་ཡི་རངས་ཏེ། བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་གསུངས་པ་ལ་མངོན་པར་བསྟོད་དོ།། །།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-066-009-41"/>When the Blessed One had said this, the monks and bodhisattvas, together with the entire assembly, rejoiced and praised the words of the Blessed One.
</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-066-009-TU-16">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-066-009-42</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཕགས་པ་ཆོས་བཞི་པ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་ཐེག་པ་ཆེན་པོའི་མདོ་རྫོགས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-066-009-42"/>This concludes “The Noble Mahāyāna Sūtra on the Four Factors.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
</body>
</tmx>