<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tmx xmlns="http://www.lisa.org/tmx14" xmlns:eft="http://read.84000.co/ns/1.0" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<header creationtool="monlam-ai/84000" datatype="PlainText" segtype="block" adminlang="en-us" srclang="bo" o-tmf="TEI" eft:text-id="UT22084-076-003" eft:text-version="v-1.0.9-2023"/>
<body>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-1">
    <prop type="location-id">translation</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>
                    <tei:ref folio="F.31.b"/>༄༅༅། །རྒྱ་གར་སྐད་དུ། ཤྲཱི་སེ་ན་ཨ་བ་དཱ་ནཾ། བོད་སྐད་དུ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg/>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-2">
    <prop type="location-id">translation</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དཔལ་གྱི་སྡེའི་རྟོགས་པ་བརྗོད་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The Account of the Noble Deeds of Śrīsena</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-3">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-25</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དཀོན་མཆོག་གསུམ་ལ་ཕྱག་འཚལ་ལོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-25"/>Homage to the Three Jewels!</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-4">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-26</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གླེང་གཞི་མཉན་དུ་ཡོད་པ་ན་སྟེ། དེ་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་དགེ་སློང་རྣམས་ལ་བཀའ་སྩལ་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-26"/>When they were at Śrāvastī, the Blessed One said to the monks, “Monks, I know the fruits of generosity.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-5">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-26</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དགེ་སློང་དག་གལ་ཏེ་ཇི་ལྟར་ངས་སྦྱིན་པའི་འབྲས་བུ་ཡང་ཤེས་ལ་སྦྱིན་པའི་བགོ་བཤའི་འབྲས་བུ་རྣམ་པར་སྨིན་པ་ཡང་ཤེས་བཞིན་དུ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>I also know how the fruits of generosity ripen. What if, like me, sentient beings too knew the fruits of generosity?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-6">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-26</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སེམས་ཅན་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་ཀྱང་སྦྱིན་པའི་འབྲས་བུ་ཡང་ཤེས་ལ་སྦྱིན་པའི་བགོ་བཤའི་འབྲས་བུ་རྣམ་པར་སྨིན་པ་ཡང་ཤེས་སུ་ཟིན་ན་ནི་དེ་ལྟར་ན་ཁམ་གྱི་ཐ་མ་དང་ཁམ་གྱི་མཇུག་ལུས་པ་གང་ཡིན་པ་དེ་ལས་ཀྱང་གལ་ཏེ་ཡོན་གནས་ལེན་པ་པོ་རྙེད་ན། དེ་ལ་མ་བྱིན་ནམ་བགོ་བཤའ་མ་བྱས་ཀྱི་བར་དུ་ཟ་བར་མི་བྱེད་ལ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>What if, like me, they knew how the fruits of generosity ripen? Were this so and were someone to ask them for their last mouthful, the last remaining mouthful of their food, they would not eat it so long as they had not offered it or shared it.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-7">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-26</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་དག་གི་སེམས་ཀྱང་སེར་སྣ་སྐྱེས་པས་ཀུན་ནས་དཀྲིས་ཤིང་འདུག་པར་མི་འགྱུར་བ་ཞིག་ན།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The growth of miserliness would not continue to completely entangle their minds.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-8">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-26</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཇི་ལྟར་ངས་སྦྱིན་པའི་འབྲས་བུ་ཡང་ཤེས་ལ་སྦྱིན་པའི་བགོ་བཤའི་འབྲས་བུ་རྣམ་པར་སྨིན་པ་ཡང་ཤེས་བཞིན་དུ་སེམས་ཅན་རྣམས་ཀྱི་སྦྱིན་པའི་འབྲས་བུ་ཡང་མི་ཤེས་ལ་སྦྱིན་པའི་བགོ་བཤའི་འབྲས་བུ་རྣམ་པར་སྨིན་པ་ཡང་མི་ཤེས་པས་ནི་དེའི་ཕྱིར་དེ་དག་ནི་ཀུན་དུ་འཛིན་པའི་སེམས་ཀྱིས་མ་བྱིན་པའམ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>I know the fruits of generosity. I also know how the fruits of generosity ripen. But unlike me, sentient beings do not know the fruits of generosity. Unlike me, they do not know how the fruits of generosity ripen. This ignorance is why their minds grasp at everything, why they are not generous, and why they eat without generosity.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-9">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-26</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བགོ་བཤའ་མ་བྱས་པར་ཟ་བར་བྱེད་ལ། དེ་དག་གི་སེམས་ཀྱང་སེར་སྣ་སྐྱེས་པས་ཀུན་ཏུ་དཀྲིས་ཤིང་འདུག་<tei:ref folio="F.32.a"/>གོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The growth of miserliness continues to completely entangle their minds.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-10">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-27</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་དེ་སྐད་ཅེས་བཀའ་སྩལ་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-27"/>This is what the Blessed One said.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-11">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-27</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བདེ་བར་གཤེགས་པས་དེ་སྐད་དུ་གསུངས་ནས། གཞན་ཡང་སྟོན་པས་འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་བཀའ་སྩལ་ཏོ། །བགོ་བཤའ་དག་གི་རྣམ་པར་སྨིན།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>After the Well-Gone One had said this, the Teacher<tei:note xml:id="UT22084-076-003-28"/> also said:</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-12">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-27</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཇི་ལྟར་དོན་ཆེན་གྱུར་པ་དེ། །དྲང་སྲོང་ཆེ་རྣམས་གསུངས་པ་བཞིན།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“As the great sages have said, The ripening of sharing is a matter of great import.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-13">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-32</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།སེམས་ཅན་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་ཤེས་ན་ནི།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-32"/>“Thus, if sentient beings knew about this,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-14">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-32</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།མ་བྱིན་བར་དུ་མི་ཟ་ཞིང་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They would not eat so long as they could offer.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-15">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-32</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།སེར་སྣ་ཅན་དུ་མི་འགྱུར་ལ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They would not be miserly,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-16">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-32</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་དག་ཀུན་དུ་འཛིན་པའི་སེམས། །ནམས་ཀྱང་སྐྱེ་བར་མི་འགྱུར་ན།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>And never would they give rise to grasping minds.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-17">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-33</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།གང་ཕྱིར་བྱིས་པ་གཏི་མུག་གིས།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-33"/>“But ignorance obscures immature beings.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-18">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-33</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།བསྒྲིབས་པ་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་མ་ཤེས་པས། །དེ་ཕྱིར་ཀུན་དུ་འཛིན་སེམས་ཀྱིས།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Since they do not know, their minds are grasping.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-19">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-33</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།རྟག་ཏུ་མ་བྱིན་ཟ་བར་བྱེད། །དེ་དག་སེར་སྣ་སྐྱེས་ནས་ཀྱང་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Thus they always eat without first offering,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-20">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-34</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།སེམས་ནི་ཀུན་ནས་དཀྲིས་ཤིང་འདུག །གང་གི་ཚེ་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་མདོ་འདི་བཤད་པ་དེའི་ཚེ་ས་རྣམ་པ་དྲུག་ཏུ་གཡོས་པར་གྱུར་ཅིང་། བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཉིད་ཀྱི་སྐུ་ལས་འོད་ཟེར་རྣམས་བྱུང་བར་གྱུར་ཏོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They become miserly, and their minds are overcome.”<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-34"/> When the Blessed One delivered this discourse, the earth shook in six different ways and light rays shone from the Blessed One’s body.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-21">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-34</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ནས་དགེ་སློང་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱི་ཆོ་འཕྲུལ་བསམ་གྱིས་མི་ཁྱབ་ཅིང་རྨད་དུ་བྱུང་བ་འདི་ལྟ་བུ་མཐོང་བ་ན་ངོ་མཚར་སྐྱེས་ཏེ། སངས་རྒྱས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ལ་ཞུས་པ། བཙུན་པ་རྒྱུ་མ་མཆིས་རྐྱེན་མ་མཆིས་པར་ནི་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་དགྲ་བཅོམ་པ་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་སངས་རྒྱས་རྣམས་འདི་ལྟ་བུའི་རྨད་དུ་བྱུང་བའི་ཆོ་འཕྲུལ་སྟོན་པར་མི་མཛད་ན།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>When the monks saw the Blessed One’s inconceivable and marvelous miracles, they were amazed and inquired of the Buddha, the Blessed One, “Honorable One, the thus-gone, worthy, perfect Buddha would not display such marvelous miracles without causes or conditions.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-22">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-34</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཙུན་པ་འདི་ལྟ་བུའི་རྨད་དུ་བྱུང་བའི་ཆོ་འཕྲུལ་གྱི་རྒྱུ་གང་ལགས། རྐྱེན་གང་ལགས།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>That being so, Honorable One, what are the causes and conditions of such marvelous miracles?”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-23">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-35</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་བཀའ་སྩལ་པ། དགེ་སློང་དག་ཆོ་འཕྲུལ་འདི་ལྟ་བུ་འདི་འབྱུང་བའི་རྒྱུ་ཉན་པར་འདོད་དམ། བཙུན་པ་དེ་ལྟར་འཚལ་ལོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-35"/>“Monks, would you like to hear what caused a miracle like this?” asked the Blessed One.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-24">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-35</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དགེ་སློང་དག་དེའི་ཕྱིར་ལེགས་པར་རབ་ཏུ་ཉོན་ལ་ཡིད་ལ་ཟུང་ཤིག་དང་ངས་བཤད་པར་བྱའོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The monks requested just this. Then the Blessed One replied, “Monks, if this is so, listen carefully, remember my words, and I will tell you.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-25">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-35</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དགེ་སློང་དག་སྔོན་བྱུང་བ་འདས་པའི་དུས་ན་རྒྱལ་པོའི་ཕོ་བྲང་ཨ་རིཥྛ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་འབྱོར་པ་རྒྱས་པ་བདེ་བ་ལོ་ལེགས་པ། སྐྱེ་བོ་མང་པོ་དང་མིས་གང་བ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Monks, at one time there was a royal estate called Ariṣṭa.<tei:note xml:id="UT22084-076-003-37"/> It was wealthy, vast, joyous, with good harvests, and full of people.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-26">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-35</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཆུར་དཔག་ཚད་བཅུ་གཉིས། ཞེང་དུ་དཔག་ཚད་བདུན་པ། གྲུ་བཞི་པ། རྣམ་པར་འབྱེས་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>It was twelve leagues long and seven leagues wide.<tei:note xml:id="UT22084-076-003-38"/> It was partitioned into quadrants.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-27">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-35</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གདུགས་དང་། རྒྱལ་མཚན་དང་། བ་དན་དང་། རྟ་བབས་སྒྲེང་བ་ཞིག་བྱུང་བར་གྱུར་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Parasols, victory banners, and flags were erected over its archways.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-28">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-39</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྒྱལ་པོའི་ཕོ་བྲང་དེར་རྒྱལ་པོ་དཔལ་གྱི་སྡེ་ཞེས་བྱ་<tei:ref folio="F.32.b"/>བ་སྟོབས་ཀྱི་འཁོར་ལོས་སྒྱུར་བ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-39"/>“At this royal estate lived a king named Śrīsena, who was a universal monarch who ruled through force.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-29">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-39</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཟུགས་བཟང་བ། མཛེས་པ། བལྟ་ན་སྡུག་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He had a lovely physique, and was beautiful, pleasing to the eye, and had a good complexion.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-30">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-39</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཁ་དོག་བཟང་པོ་རྒྱས་པ་མཆོག་དང་ལྡན་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He possessed the best attributes in abundance.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-31">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-39</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རང་བཞིན་གྱིས་སྐྱེ་བ་དྲན་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He could remember his past lives naturally, and he was righteous.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-32">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-39</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཆོས་དང་ལྡན་པ། ཆོས་ཀྱི་རྒྱལ་པོ་ཆོས་ཀྱིས་འཛམ་བུའི་གླིང་གི་དབང་ཕྱུག་གི་བདག་པོ་བྱེད་པ་ཞིག་བྱུང་བར་གྱུར་ཏོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He was a Dharma king who ruled Jambudvīpa through righteousness.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-33">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-41</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།རྒྱལ་པོ་དཔལ་གྱི་སྡེའི་མཐུས་ཤིང་རྣམས་རྟག་ཏུ་མེ་ཏོག་དང་འབྲས་བུར་ལྡན་ཞིང་ལྷ་རྣམས་དུས་དུས་སུ་ཆར་ཡང་དག་པར་འབེབས་ལ། ལོ་ཏོག་ཤིན་ཏུ་ཕུན་སུམ་ཚོགས་པར་གྱུར་ཏོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-41"/>“King Śrīsena’s power caused the plants to blossom and bear fruit continuously, the gods to make the rains fall at the right times, and the harvests to be exceedingly abundant.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-34">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-41</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།སེམས་ཅན་རྣམས་ཀྱང་ནད་མེད་པར་གྱུར་ཏེ། སེམས་ཅན་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱང་ཕན་ཚུན་བྱམས་པའི་སེམས་ཀྱིས་གནས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The beings there were free from illness and they all maintained a loving attitude toward each other.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-35">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-42</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།རྒྱལ་པོ་དེའི་བཙུན་མོ་དམ་པ་རྒྱལ་བའི་འོད་ཅེས་བྱ་བ་གཟུགས་བཟང་བ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-42"/>“The king’s noble queen was called Jayaprabhā.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-36">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-42</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མཛེས་པ། བལྟ་ན་སྡུག་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>She had a lovely figure and was beautiful and pleasing to the eye.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-37">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-42</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡན་ལག་དང་ཉིང་ལག་ཐམས་ཅད་ཚང་བ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>She had all her major and minor body parts.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-38">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-42</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡུལ་གྱི་བཟང་མོ་རྒྱལ་པོ་དཔལ་གྱི་སྡེའི་ཤིན་ཏུ་ཡིད་དུ་འོང་བ་དང་། སྡུག་པ་དང་། ཕངས་པ་ཞིག་བྱུང་བར་གྱུར་ཏོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>She was the perfect daughter of that land, and King Śrīsena loved, adored, and cherished her.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-39">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-43</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དགེ་སློང་དག་རྒྱལ་པོ་དཔལ་གྱི་སྡེའི་འཛམ་བུའི་གླིང་གི་མི་ཐམས་ཅད་ལ་དཔྱ་དང་ཤོ་གམ་དང་གྲུ་བཙས་མེད་དེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-43"/>“Monks, King Śrīsena levied no taxes on any of Jambudvīpa’s people; he collected neither road tolls nor boat fares. The harvests made all the people wealthy, and they were peaceful.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-40">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-43</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཞིང་གི་འབྱོར་པ་དང་ལྡན་པ། སྐྱེ་བོ་རྣམས་ཞི་བ། ཁྱིམ་བྱ་རྣམས་དང་ལྡན་པའི་ཡུལ་དང་། གྲོང་ཁྱེར་དང་། གྲོང་རྡལ་དང་། ཡུལ་འཁོར་དང་། རྒྱལ་པོའི་ཕོ་བྲང་བྱུང་བར་གྱུར་ཏོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Families<tei:note xml:id="UT22084-076-003-44"/> filled the lands, cities, towns, countryside, and the king’s estate.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-41">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-45</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དགེ་སློང་དག་རྒྱལ་པོ་དཔལ་གྱི་སྡེ་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔར་གྱུར་ཏེ། ཐམས་ཅད་སྟེར་བ། ཐམས་ཅད་ཡོངས་སུ་གཏོང་བ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-45"/>“Monks, King Śrīsena was a bodhisattva, so he gave away everything. He let go of everything completely—indeed, he let go of everything completely and without attachment.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-42">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-45</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཆགས་པ་མེད་པར་ཡོངས་སུ་གཏོང་བ་དང་། གཏོང་བ་ཆེན་པོ་ལ་ཞུགས་ནས་ཐ་ན་རང་གི་ཤ་ཡང་གཏོང་སྟེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Absorbed in great giving, he even gave away his own flesh.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-43">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-45</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེས་མ་བྱིན་པ་དང་། ཡོངས་སུ་མ་བཏང་བ་ཅི་ཡང་མེད་དོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>There was nothing that he would not give away or let go.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-44">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-46</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དགེ་སློང་དག་རྒྱལ་པོ་དཔལ་གྱི་སྡེའི་རྒྱལ་པོའི་ཕོ་བྲང་ཨ་རིཥྛའི་ཤར་ཕྱོགས་ཀྱི་གྲོང་ཁྱེར་མཐར་སྦྱིན་གཏོང་གི་གནས་བྱས་ཏེ། སྦྱིན་པ་ནི་གཏོང་། བསོད་ནམས་ནི་བྱེད་དོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-46"/>“Monks, at the eastern edge of the city, at Ariṣṭa Estate, King Śrīsena created a site for gift offerings from which he distributed gifts and performed meritorious deeds.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-45">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-46</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ལྷོ་དང་ནུབ་དང་བྱང་གི་གྲོང་ཁྱེར་གྱི་སྒོར་སྦྱིན་པ་ནི་གཏོང་། བསོད་ནམས་ནི་བྱེད་དོ། །སུམ་མདོའི་དབུས་ན་ཡང་སྦྱིན་པ་ནི་གཏོང་། བསོད་ནམས་ནི་བྱེད་དོ། །འདི་ལྟ་སྟེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He distributed gifts and performed meritorious deeds at the city’s southern, western, and northern gates as well, and he distributed gifts and performed meritorious deeds at its intersections.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-46">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-46</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཟས་འདོད་པ་རྣམས་ལ་ནི་ཟས། སྐོམ་འདོད་པ་རྣམས་ལ་ནི་སྐོམ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He would, for example, give food to the hungry and drink to the thirsty.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-47">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-46</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཟའ་བ་དང་། བཅའ་བ་དང་། མར་མེ་དང་། ཕྲེང་བ་དང་། <tei:ref folio="F.33.a"/>དྲི་དང་། བྱུག་པ་དང་། གོས་དང་། མལ་ཆ་དང་། སྟན་དང་། རྒྱབ་རྟེན་དང་། གནས་དང་། གཟུགས་རྣམས་དང་། ཤིང་རྟ་དང་། གླང་པོ་དང་། རྟ་དང་། རྒྱན་རྣམས་དང་། གསེར་གྱི་སྣོད་དངུལ་གྱི་ཕྱེ་མས་ཡོངས་སུ་གང་བ་རྣམས་དང་། དངུལ་གྱི་སྣོད་གསེར་གྱི་ཕྱེ་མས་ཡོངས་སུ་གང་བ་རྣམས་དང་། བ་ལང་གསེར་གྱི་རྭ་དང་། དངུལ་གྱི་རྨིག་པ་བཏགས་པ། ཁར་བའི་བཞོ་སྣོད་དང་། རས་ཟུང་གིས་བཀབ་པ་རྣམས་དང་། གཞོན་ནུ་མ་རྣམས་དང་། རྒྱན་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱིས་བརྒྱན་ནས་སྦྱིན་པ་ནི་གཏོང་། བསོད་ནམས་ནི་བྱེད་དེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He distributed gifts and performed meritorious deeds by giving food, drink, lamps, flower garlands, scents, perfumes, clothes, blankets, mattresses, back supports, shelters, images, horse-carts, elephants, horses, ornaments, golden containers filled with silver dust, silver containers filled with gold dust, oxen with golden horns and silver hoofs, bronze milking containers that were twice covered with cloth, and maidens who were adorned with various ornaments.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-48">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-47</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དགེ་སློང་དག་ཇི་ཙམ་དུ་རྒྱལ་པོ་དཔལ་གྱི་སྡེས་ཅི་ཙམ་གྱིས་འཛམ་བུའི་གླིང་པའི་མི་ཐམས་ཅད་ཕྱུག་པ་དང་། ནོར་མང་བ་དང་། ལོངས་སྤྱོད་ཆེ་བར་གྱུར་པ་དེ་ཙམ་དུ་སྦྱིན་པ་རྣམས་བྱིན་ནོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-47"/>“Monks, King Śrīsena gave gifts until everyone in Jambudvīpa was affluent, prosperous, and deeply contented.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-49">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-47</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཡང་དེའི་ཚེ་རྒྱལ་པོའི་ཕོ་བྲང་ཨ་རིཥྛའི་གྲོང་ཁྱེར་ན་བྱེ་བ་ཕྲག་དགུ་བཅུ་རྩ་དྲུག་གི་མི་རྣམས་གནས་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>At that time, 960 million people lived in the city where the king’s royal estate, Ariṣṭa, was located.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-50">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-47</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྒྱལ་པོ་དཔལ་གྱི་སྡེ་དེ་དག་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱི་སྡུག་པ་དང་ཡིད་དུ་འོང་བར་གྱུར་ཏོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>King Śrīsena was loved and adored by all.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-51">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-47</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།གཞན་ཡང་འདི་སྐྱེས་པ་དང་བུད་མེད་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་མཐོང་བ་ན་ངོམས་པར་མི་འགྱུར་བའི་དགའ་བ་ཐོབ་བོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>What was more, when men and women saw him, they experienced insatiable delight.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-52">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-48</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དགེ་སློང་དག་རྒྱལ་པོ་དཔལ་གྱི་སྡེའི་བློན་པོ་སྟོང་ཕྲག་བཅུ་གཉིས་ཡོད་དེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-48"/>“Monks, King Śrīsena had twelve thousand ministers.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-53">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-48</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བློན་པོ་དེ་རྣམས་ཀྱི་མཆོག་བློ་གྲོས་ཆེན་པོ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་མཁས་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The supreme one among them was called Mahāmati.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-54">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-48</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གསལ་བ། བློ་དང་ལྡན་པ། ཐམས་ཅད་ལ་དབང་བྱེད་པ། རྒྱལ་པོ་ཡོངས་སུ་སྐྱོང་བར་བྱེད་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He was learned, bright, wise, his charisma affected all, and he took great care<tei:note xml:id="UT22084-076-003-49"/> of the king.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-55">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-48</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྒྱལ་པོ་དཔལ་གྱི་སྡེའི་སྡུག་པ་དང་ཡིད་དུ་འོང་བ་དང་། ཕངས་པར་གྱུར་པ་ཞིག་བྱུང་བར་གྱུར་ཏོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>King Śrīsena loved, adored, and esteemed him.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-56">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-48</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེས་འདིའི་གཟུགས་དང་། ཁ་དོག་དང་། རྟགས་དང་། དབྱིབས་མཐོང་བ་ན་ངོམས་པ་མེད་དེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Mahāmati would never tire of gazing upon the king’s form, his complexion, his features, or his shape.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-57">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-48</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྐད་ཅིག་ཀྱང་འདི་དང་མི་འབྲལ་ལོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He could not be separated from the king for even a moment.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-58">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-50</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དགེ་སློང་དག་རྒྱལ་པོ་དཔལ་གྱི་སྡེའི་འཛམ་བུའི་གླིང་གི་མི་ཐམས་ཅད་དགེ་བ་བཅུའི་ལས་ཀྱི་ལམ་ལ་ཡང་དག་པར་སྦྱར་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-50"/>“Monks, King Śrīsena acquainted all of Jambudvīpa’s people with the path of the ten virtuous actions.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-59">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-50</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཤེས་ལྡན་དག་འཛམ་བུའི་གླིང་གི་མི་རྣམས་དགེ་བ་བཅུའི་ལས་ཀྱི་ལམ་རྣམས་ལ་རྟེན་ཅིག །དགེ་བ་བཅུའི་ལས་ཀྱི་ལམ་འདི་རྣམས་ཡང་དག་པར་ཟུང་ཤིག་ཅེས་དགེ་བ་བཅུའི་ལས་ཀྱི་ལམ་ལ་ཡང་དག་པར་སྦྱོར་ཏེ། དགེ་སློང་དག་རྒྱལ་པོ་དཔལ་གྱི་སྡེ་དེ་ལྟ་བུའི་གདམས་ངག་རྗེས་སུ་སྟོན་པར་གྱུར་ཏོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He said to them, ‘People of Jambudvīpa, you must follow the path of the ten virtuous actions. You must adopt the path of the ten virtuous actions correctly.’ Monks, this is how King Śrīsena instructed his subjects.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-60">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-50</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།འདི་ལྟ་སྟེ་འཁོར་ལོས་སྒྱུར་བའི་རྒྱལ་པོ་དེའི་དུས་སུ་གང་འཛམ་བུའི་གླིང་པའི་མི་གང་ལ་ལ་<tei:ref folio="F.33.b"/>དུས་བྱས་ཏེ་ལུས་ཞིག་ནས་དེ་ལྷའི་རིས་དྲུག་ཏུ་སྐྱེ་བར་གྱུར་ཏོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Thus, during the reign of this universal monarch, when people in Jambudvīpa would die and their bodies would perish, they were reborn in one of the six god realms.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-61">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-50</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།གང་ཕལ་ཆེར་ནི་སུམ་ཅུ་རྩ་གསུམ་གྱི་ལྷའི་རིས་སུ་སྐྱེས་སོ། །ཡང་དེའི་ཚེ་སུམ་ཅུ་རྩ་གསུམ་གྱི་ལྷ་རྣམས་ཀྱི་ལྷའི་གྲོང་ཁྱེར་བལྟ་ན་སྡུག་ཅེས་བྱ་བ་ལྷའི་ཚོགས་ཀྱིས་ཀུན་ཏུ་གང་ངོ་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Most were born in the Heaven of the Thirty-Three, and the divine city Darśanīya was filled with crowds of gods from the Heaven of the Thirty-Three.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-62">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-50</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ནས་དེར་གོ་སྐབས་མེད་པར་གྱུར་པ་དང་། བལྟ་ན་སྡུག་གི་ཕྱི་རོལ་ཡོངས་འདུ་དང་། ཤིང་རྟ་སྣ་ཚོགས་ཅན་དང་། དགའ་བའི་ཚལ་ལ་སོགས་པའི་སྐྱེད་མོས་ཚལ་རྣམས་སུ་གནས་པར་གྱུར་ཏོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>When it became too crowded and there was not enough space in the divine city, the gods dwelled on the outskirts of Darśanīya at the Pārijāta and in groves such as Caitraratha, Nandanavana, and so forth.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-63">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-50</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ནས་སྔོན་སྐྱེས་པའི་སུམ་ཅུ་རྩ་གསུམ་གྱི་ལྷའི་ཚོགས་ཀྱིས་ཡང་དག་པའི་འབྱོར་པ་དེ་མཐོང་སྟེ། རབ་ཏུ་དགའ་ནས་ལྷའི་དབང་པོ་བརྒྱ་བྱིན་ལ་འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་སྨྲས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Following this influx, the gods who had been born earlier in the Heaven of the Thirty-Three viewed the perfect accomplishments of the newcomers and were overjoyed. They spoke to Śakra, lord of the gods, saying,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-64">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-50</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཀཽ་ཤི་ཀ་གང་དུ་རིའི་རྒྱལ་པོ་རི་རབ་དེ་ཉིད་ལྷའི་བུ་དེ་དག་གིས་གང་སྟེ་ལྷའི་ཚོགས་ནི་འཕེལ་བར་གྱུར།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>‘Kauśika, how is it that Mount Sumeru is filled with gods, and the divine assembly has increased, while the demigods’ assembly has decreased?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-65">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-50</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལྷ་མ་ཡིན་གྱི་ཚོགས་ནི་འགྲིབ་པར་གྱུར་པའི་ངོ་མཚར་འདི་ལ་གཟིགས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>We are beholding something marvelous.’</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-66">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-51</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ནས་ལྷའི་དབང་པོ་བརྒྱ་བྱིན་གྱིས་ལྷའི་བུ་རྣམས་ལས་ཐོས་ནས་རིའི་རྒྱལ་པོ་རི་རབ་ཐམས་ཅད་ལ་བལྟ་བར་བརྩམས་པ་དང་། ཇི་ཙམ་ན་རིའི་རྒྱལ་པོ་རི་རབ་ལྷའི་ཚོགས་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་ཀུན་ནས་གང་བ་མཐོང་ངོ་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-51"/>“After hearing about this from the gods, Śakra, lord of the gods, inspected Mount Sumeru, and as soon as he did, he too saw that Mount Sumeru was teeming with multitudes of gods.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-67">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-51</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།མཐོང་ནས་ཀྱང་འདི་སྙམ་དུ་སེམས་ཏེ། རྒྱུ་གང་དང་རྐྱེན་གང་གིས་སེམས་ཅན་འདི་སྙེད་ཅིག་འདིར་སྐྱེས་པར་གྱུར་སྙམ་ནས་འཛམ་བུའི་གླིང་ཐམས་ཅད་ལ་བལྟ་བར་བརྩམས་པ་དང་། ཇི་ཙམ་ན་རྒྱལ་པོ་དཔལ་གྱི་སྡེའི་མཐུ་ཡིན་པར་མཐོང་ངོ་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Seeing this, he thought, ‘What causes and conditions led this many sentient beings to be born here?’ With this in mind, he began to inspect all of Jambudvīpa, and as soon as he did, he saw that it was a result of King Śrīsena’s influence.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-68">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-51</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ནས་ལྷའི་དབང་པོ་བརྒྱ་བྱིན་སེམས་རབ་ཏུ་དགའ་བས་སུམ་ཅུ་རྩ་གསུམ་གྱི་ལྷ་རྣམས་ལ་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Then, with great joy, Śakra, lord of the gods, said to the gods of the Heaven of the Thirty-Three:</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-69">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-52</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གྲོགས་པོ་དག་ཁྱེད་རྣམས་ཉོན་ཅིག །འཛམ་གླིང་དབང་ཕྱུག་རྒྱལ་པོ་ནི།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-52"/>“ ‘Friends, you must listen! There is a king, a ruler of Jambudvīpa,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-70">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-52</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དཔལ་གྱི་སྡེ་ཞེས་རྣམ་གྲགས་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Who is renowned as Śrīsena.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-71">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-53</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།རྟག་ཏུ་ཆོས་ལ་གཞོལ་བ་དང་། །རྒྱལ་པོ་ཆེན་པོ་ཆོས་ལ་གནས།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He is always inclined toward the Dharma.<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-53"/> “ ‘This great king lives by the Dharma.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-72">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-53</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཐོག་མ་བར་དང་མཐར་དགེ་ཞིང་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>In the beginning, middle, and end, he is always virtuous.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-73">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-53</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།སེམས་ཅན་ཀུན་ལ་ཕན་པར་དགའ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He delights in helping all sentient beings</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-74">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-53</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།གཙོ་བོ་མི་རྣམས་དགེ་བ་ལ། རྟག་ཏུ་ཡང་དག་སྦྱོར་བར་བྱེད།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>And, principally, he continually brings humans to virtue.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-75">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-54</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།རྟག་ཏུ་སྙིང་རྗེའི་བདག་ཉིད་ཅན།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-54"/>“ ‘He is constantly compassionate,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-76">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-54</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཕྱི་རོལ་དངོས་པོ་རབ་གཏོང་ཞིང་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He gives away his external possessions,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-77">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-54</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ནི་ཤ་ཡང་སློང་བ་ལ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>And to those who ask for his flesh,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-78">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-54</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།རྗེས་སུ་བརྩེ་བ་ཉིད་ཀྱིས་སྟེར།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He gives this away too, with love.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-79">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-55</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ནང་ངམ་ཡང་ན་ཕྱི་རོལ་ལ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-55"/>“ ‘Whether that which is asked for is external or internal,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-80">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-55</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ནི་ཡོངས་སུ་འཛིན་མེད་པར།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Without any sense of grasping</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-81">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-55</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།རྗེས་བརྩེ་ཉིད་ཀྱི་གཏོང་བྱེད་ཅིང་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He bestows everything with kindness</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-82">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-55</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།བྱང་ཆུབ་མཐར་དབྱུང་བ་ལ་བརྩོན།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>And works diligently to achieve awakening.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-83">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-56</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེས་ནི་རྣམ་དག་གསེར་བཞིན་དུ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-56"/>“ ‘Like refined gold,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-84">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-56</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།<tei:ref folio="F.34.a"/>འགྲོ་བ་ཐམས་ཅད་རབ་བསྒྲུབས་པས།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He accomplishes the wishes of all beings.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-85">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-56</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།རྒྱལ་པོ་དེ་ཡི་མཐུ་ཡིས་ནི།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Through the encouragement of this king</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-86">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-57</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཐམས་ཅད་མཐོ་རིས་ལ་གཞོལ་འགྱུར།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Everyone is inspired to pursue higher rebirths.<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-57"/> “ ‘Because of the influence</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-87">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-57</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།རྒྱལ་པོ་བློ་གྲོས་ཆེ་དེ་ཡི།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Of this great, intelligent king</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-88">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-57</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།མཐུ་ཡིས་སུ་ཡང་དམྱལ་བ་དང་། །ཡི་དགས་དང་ནི་དུད་འགྲོ་ཡི།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>No one will be born in hell, In the preta realm, or the animal realm.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-89">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-59</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།སྐྱེ་གནས་རྣམས་སུ་སྐྱེ་མི་འགྱུར། །དེ་ཡི་གཟི་བརྗིད་མཐུ་ཡིས་ནི།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-59"/>“ ‘This king’s resplendent radiance Illuminates their migrations.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-90">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-59</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཐམས་ཅད་སྣང་བར་འགྲོ་བ་དང་། ། སྦྱིན་དང་ཚུལ་ཁྲིམས་དགའ་འགྱུར་བར། །དགའ་བའི་ཚལ་ན་དགའ་བས་རྩེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They take joy in giving and discipline, And they play joyfully in Nandanavana.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-91">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-60</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དཔལ་གྱི་སྡེ་ལ་རྗེས་བསྟེན་པར།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-60"/>“ ‘Those who follow Śrīsena</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-92">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-60</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།གུས་དང་བཅས་པར་གྱུར་པ་འདི།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Are respectful and live</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-93">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-60</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ལྷ་ཡི་འཇིག་རྟེན་ཉམས་དགའ་བར།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>In pleasurable divine worlds,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-94">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-60</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ཡང་དགའ་བས་རྣམ་པར་སྣང་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Where they shine with joy.’</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-95">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-61</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ནས་སུམ་ཅུ་རྩ་གསུམ་གྱི་ལྷ་དེ་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་ཚིག་དེ་ཐོས་པ་དང་ཡིད་དགའ་བ་དང་། སེམས་རངས་པར་གྱུར་ཏེ། དགའ་བའི་སེམས་སུ་གྱུར་ཅིང་འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་སྨྲས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-61"/>“When the gods of the Heaven of the Thirty-Three heard these words, their minds were overjoyed, and they celebrated.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-96">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-61</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།གང་རྒྱལ་པོ་འདི་ཡན་ལག་དང་ཉིང་ལག་ཀྱང་སྦྱིན་པར་གཏོང་འདོད་པར་རྩོལ་བ་ནི་ངོ་མཚར་ཆེའོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>With such joy in their minds, they exclaimed, ‘This king aspires to fulfill his wish to give away his major and minor body parts—this is marvelous!</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-97">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-61</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།འོན་ཀྱང་འདི་ལྟར་ཡན་ལག་དང་ཉིང་ལག་སྟེར་བ་འདི་ནི་དཀའ་བ་སྟེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Yet it is difficult to give away one’s major and minor body parts.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-98">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-61</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བདག་དང་མཉམ་པར་ཕངས་པ་གཞན་མེད་པས་དེ་ཇི་ལྟར་ན་བདག་ཉིད་ཆེན་པོ་འདི་རང་གི་ལུས་ཀྱི་སྡུག་བསྔལ་བ་ལ་མི་སེམས་པར་ཡན་ལག་དང་ཉིང་ལག་སྦྱིན་པར་གཏོང་བར་གྱུར་ཏེ། འདི་ནི་རྗེས་སུ་དཔག་པར་ནུས་པ་མ་ཡིན་ནོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Since there is no one as dear as oneself, he will not be able to give away his major and minor body parts without concern for his own suffering. This act of giving is not something that one can simply infer.’<tei:note xml:id="UT22084-076-003-62"/>
                </seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-99">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-61</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།བརྒྱ་བྱིན་གྱིས་སྨྲས་པ། གྲོགས་པོ་དག་ཁྱེད་རྣམས་དེ་སྐད་མ་སྨྲ་ཤིག །རྒྱལ་པོ་འདི་ནི་མཐུ་ཆེ་སྟེ་རྫུ་འཕྲུལ་ཆེ་བ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“ ‘Friends,’ replied Śakra, ‘do not say these things! This king is powerful.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-100">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-61</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྙིང་རྗེ་ཆེ་བས་ཐ་ན་རང་གི་ཤ་ཡང་གཏོང་སྟེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He has magical powers and intense compassion. This is why he can give away even his own flesh.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-101">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-61</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདི་ལ་ཡོངས་སུ་མ་བཏང་བ་ཅི་ཡང་མེད་དོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>There is nothing that he cannot relinquish.’</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-102">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-64</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཇི་ཙམ་ན་དུས་གཞན་ཞིག་གི་ཚེ་བཙུན་མོ་རྒྱལ་བའི་འོད་སྟན་ཆེན་པོ་ལ་ཉལ་བ་ན་ཐོ་རངས་ཀྱི་དུས་སུ་རྨི་ལམ་བཞི་རྨིས་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-64"/>“Shortly thereafter, on another occasion, Śrīsena’s queen, Jayaprabhā, went to sleep on her large mattress, and just before dawn she dreamt four dreams. First, she dreamt that Śrīsena carried her down off the mattress and then lifted her back onto it.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-103">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-64</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དཔལ་གྱི་སྡེ་སྟན་ལས་བདག་ཉིད་ཕབ་ནས་སླར་ཡང་བཏེག་པར་མཐོང་བ་དང་། རང་གི་མིག་ཕྱུང་སྟེ་སླར་ཡང་སྐྱེས་པར་མཐོང་བ་དང་། བདག་ཉིད་ཀྱི་དཔུང་པ་གཡས་པ་འདི་བཅད་དེ་ས་ལ་ལྷུང་བ་ཡང་སྐྱེས་པར་མཐོང་བ་དང་། མི་མ་ཡིན་པ་དངུལ་གྱི་རྡོ་བཅག་པའི་མདོག་འདྲ་བ་ཞིག་གིས་རྒྱལ་པོ་དཔལ་གྱི་སྡེའི་དཔུང་པ་གཡོན་པ་མོད་ལ་ཕྱུང་སྟེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Then he gouged out his own eyes, but they were later restored. He chopped off his right arm, which fell to the ground, but it was also restored. Finally, she dreamt of a nonhuman that resembled a stone grinder, made from silver. It suddenly pulled off King Śrīsena’s left arm.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-104">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-64</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཕྲོགས་ནས་སླར་ཡང་སྐྱེ་བར་རྨིས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>After it was thus stolen, however, that too was restored.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-105">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-64</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།གཉིད་སད་པ་དང་འཇིགས་པར་གྱུར། དངངས་པར་གྱུར།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Then she woke up. Filled with fear, she gasped and the hairs on her body stood on end.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-106">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-64</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྤུ་ཟིང་ཞེས་བྱེད་དེ། ངའམ་ལྷ་ལ་སྡུག་<tei:ref folio="F.34.b"/>བསྔལ་འབའ་ཞིག་འབྱུང་བར་མི་འགྱུར་གྲང་ཞེས་བསམས་ནས། དེས་རྒྱལ་པོ་དཔལ་གྱི་སྡེ་ལ་སྨྲས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>She thought, ‘Either the lord or I will experience nothing but suffering.’ She told King Śrīsena of her dreams.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-107">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-64</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་རྨི་ལྟས་ལ་བྱང་བ་ཡིན་པས་འདི་སྙམ་དུ་སེམས་ཏེ། འདིས་རྨི་ལམ་ཇི་ལྟ་བུ་མཐོང་བ་ལས་ན་རིང་པོ་མི་ཐོགས་པར་ཆུང་མ་འདི་ཉིད་སློང་བ་འབྱུང་བར་འགྱུར་རོ་སྙམ་ནས་སྨྲས་པ། མ་འཇིགས་ཤིག །སྒྱུ་མ་ལྟ་བུ་རྨི་ལམ་ལ་སེམས་པས་ཅི་ཞིག་བྱ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He had been trained to interpret dreams, so he thought, ‘As she has seen in her dream, someone will soon come to ask for my wife.’ But he comforted her and said, ‘Do not be afraid—what is the point of thinking about illusion-like dreams?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-108">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-64</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དཔལ་གྱི་སྡེ་སྟན་ལ་བདག་ཉིད་གནས་པར་ཁྱོད་ཀྱིས་མ་མཐོང་ངམ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Do you not see Śrīsena sitting on his mattress?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-109">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-64</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མིག་མི་ཉམས་པར་དེ་བཞིན་དུ་འདུག་པ་དང་། བདག་ཉིད་ཀྱི་དཔུང་པ་གཡས་པ་དེ་བཞིན་དུ་ཡོད་པ་དང་། ངའི་ཡང་དཔུང་པ་གཡོན་པ་གནས་བཞིན་པ་ཉིད་ཅེས་དེས་དབུགས་ཕྱུང་བ་དང་། ཅང་མི་སྨྲ་བར་འདུག་གོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>My eyes are as they were, and my right and left arms are intact.’ The queen sat silently.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-110">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-65</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཇི་ཙམ་ན་མཚན་མོ་གཉིས་པ་ལ་བློན་པོའི་མཆོག་བློ་གྲོས་ཆེན་པོ་ཞེས་བྱ་བའི་རྨི་ལམ་དུ་རྒྱལ་པོ་དཔལ་གྱི་སྡེའི་རིན་པོ་ཆེ་ཐམས་ཅད་ལས་བྱས་པའི་ཁང་བཟངས་མོད་ལ་ཞིག་པ་དང་། རིན་པོ་ཆེ་དེ་རྣམས་ཤ་ཟ་མཐོང་ན་འཇིགས་སུ་རུང་བ་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་ཕན་ཚུན་ཁྱེར་བ་དང་། སླར་ཡང་ཁང་བཟངས་སོ་སོར་སྦྱར་བར་རྨིས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-65"/>“The second night after this, the supreme one among the ministers, the one named Mahāmati, dreamt a dream in which King Śrīsena’s mansion, which was built of various precious stones, collapsed. The precious stones were then taken away by fearful-looking demons. Later, however, he dreamt that the mansion was rebuilt.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-111">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-65</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།སད་པ་དང་འཇིགས་ཤིང་སྐྲག་པ་དང་། ཡི་མུག་སྟེ་སྤུ་ཟིང་ཞེས་བྱེད་པ་དང་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He awoke terrified and distressed, with the hairs on his body standing on end.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-112">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-65</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བསམས་པས་སེམས་ཅན་ཐམས་ཅད་ལ་མཉེས་གཤིན་པ་དང་། ལྷ་དཔལ་གྱི་སྡེའི་སྐུ་ལུས་སློང་བར་མི་འགྱུར་གྲང་། ལྷ་ཡང་ཐམས་ཅད་སྩོལ་བ། ཐམས་ཅད་ཡོངས་སུ་གཏོང་བ། ཆགས་པ་མེད་པར་གཏོང་སྟེ། འདི་ལྟ་སྟེ་དམན་པ་དང་། ལོང་བ་དང་། བཀྲེན་པ་དང་། སྡུག་ཕོངས་པ་རྣམས་ལ་འདི་ཡོངས་སུ་མི་གཏོང་བ་ཅི་ཡང་མེད་དོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He thought, ‘Could someone come to ask for Lord Śrīsena’s body? Could they ask for the body of he who pleases and is affectionate toward all sentient beings, the lord who offers everything, who gives everything completely, he who gives without attachment? There is nothing that he would not give to lesser, blind, hungry, suffering, and deprived beings.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-113">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-65</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།རྒྱལ་པོ་དཔལ་གྱི་སྡེ་ལ་ནི་ཞུ་བར་མི་བྱ་སྟེ། ཤིན་ཏུ་སྤྲོ་བ་སྐྱེ་བར་མི་འགྱུར་གྲང་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>I will not speak of my dream to King Śrīsena. He would be too delighted about it!’</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-114">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-66</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་དེས་གསང་སྟེ་མཚན་མཁན་བོས་ནས་དམ་བསྒོ་སྟེ་ཞེས་སྨྲས་པ། ཤེས་ལྡན་ངས་འདི་ལྟ་བུའི་རྨི་ལམ་རྨིས་པའི་འབྲས་བུ་ཇི་ལྟ་བུར་འགྱུར་བ་ཁྱོད་ཀྱིས་ལུང་སྟོན་ཅིག །མཚན་མཁན་གྱིས་སྨྲས་པ། རྨི་ལམ་ཅི་འདྲ་བ་འདི་ལས་རིང་པོ་མི་ཐོགས་པར་ལྷའི་སྐུ་ལུས་སློང་བ་འོང་བར་འགྱུར་རོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-66"/>“He then called a soothsayer and commanded him, ‘Wise one, you must foretell the significance of the dream that I had.’ The soothsayer said, ‘According to the dream, someone will come soon to ask for the lord’s body.’</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-115">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-66</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།རྨི་ལམ་བསྟན་པ་འདི་ལྟ་བུ་དེ་ཐོས་པ་དང་། བློན་པོ་ཆེན་པོ་བློ་གྲོས་ཆེན་པོ་སྡུག་བསྔལ་དྲག་པོས་གདུངས་ཤིང་མིག་མཆི་མས་གང་བ་དང་། ལག་པ་འགྲམ་པ་ལ་གཏད་དེ་སེམས་<tei:ref folio="F.35.a"/>ཁོང་དུ་ཆུད་པས་གནས་ནས་རྒྱལ་པོ་དཔལ་གྱི་སྡེ་བྱམས་པ་དང་སྙིང་རྗེའི་བདག་ཉིད་ཅན་སེམས་ཅན་ཐམས་ཅད་ལ་མཉེས་གཤིན་པ་ཡོན་ཏན་དུ་མ་དང་ལྡན་པ་ལ་མི་རྟག་པའི་སྟོབས་ཉེ་བར་གནས་པ་ནི་ཧ་ཅང་མྱུར་ཆེས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>When he heard the significance of the dream, the great minister Mahāmati was struck by deep sorrow. His eyes filled with tears, he rested his hand on his cheek, and he sat depressed, pondering how the force of impermanence had arrived too soon for the loving and compassionate King Śrīsena, he who had been so affectionate toward all sentient beings and possessed so many great qualities.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-116">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-67</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ནས་ནུབ་གསུམ་པ་ལ་བློན་པོ་སྟོང་ཕྲག་བཅུ་གཉིས་རྨི་ལམ་ལྔ་རྨིས་ཏེ། ཁྲི་ཡིས་རྒྱལ་པོ་དཔལ་གྱི་སྡེའི་གདུགས་དང་ཅོད་པན་ཕྲོགས་ཏེ་སླར་ཡང་བྱིན་པ་དང་སྐྱེ་བོ་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱི་མགོ་བཅད་ནས་སླར་ཡང་བྱུང་བ་དང་། འཛམ་བུའི་གླིང་གི་མི་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱི་མིག་ཕྱུང་ནས་སླར་ཡང་སྐྱེས་པ་དང་། འཛམ་བུའི་གླིང་གི་མི་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱི་རྐང་པ་དང་ལག་པ་རྣམས་བཅད་ནས་སླར་ཡང་སྐྱེས་པ་དང་རྒྱལ་པོ་དཔལ་གྱི་སྡེ་སེང་གེའི་ཁྲི་ལས་བབ་ནས་སླར་ཡང་འཛེག་པར་རྩོམ་པར་རྨིས་པ་དང་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-67"/>“Then, on the third night, twelve thousand ministers dreamt five dreams. They dreamt that ten thousand beings robbed King Śrīsena of his parasol and crown, but they were then handed back to him; that everyone’s heads were chopped off, but then restored; that the eyes of every human in Jambudvīpa were gouged out, but then restored; that the hands and feet of every human in Jambudvīpa were chopped off, but then restored; and that King Śrīsena attempted to ascend the lion throne again after he had descended from it.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-117">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-67</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇིགས་ཤིང་སྐྲག་ལ་ཡི་མུག་ནས་རྒྱལ་པོ་དཔལ་གྱི་སྡེ་ས་ཆེན་པོ་སྐྱོང་བ་མཛད་པ། བྱམས་པའི་བདག་ཉིད་ཅན་སྙིང་རྗེ་ཆེ་བ། སེམས་ཅན་ཐམས་ཅད་ལ་མཉེས་གཤིན་པ་ལ་མི་རྟག་པའི་སྟོབས་ཉེ་བར་གནས་པར་མི་འགྱུར་གྲང་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The terrified, distressed, and despairing ministers thought, ‘Will the force of impermanence come for King Śrīsena? Will it be the end of this protector of a vast land, he who is so loving and compassionate, he who brings joy and rouses affection in all sentient beings?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-118">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-67</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བདག་ཅག་རྣམས་ལྷ་དང་ལྷན་ཅིག་གནས་པ་ལས་ཐ་དད་པར་གྱུར་པ་དང་། སོ་སོ་བ་དང་བྲལ་བ་དང་བྱེ་བྲལ་མི་འགྱུར་གྲང་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Will we live without the king? Will we be separated? Will we be parted? Will we be alone?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-119">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-67</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཛམ་བུའི་གླིང་པའི་སྐྱབས་དང་དཔུང་གཉེན་མེད་པར་མི་འགྱུར་གྲང་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Will Jambudvīpa lose its protector and defender?’</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-120">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-67</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་མཚན་མཁན་རྣམས་བོས་ནས་སྨྲས་པ་དང་། དེ་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་ཇི་ཙམ་ན་ཐམས་ཅད་འདི་བཞིན་དུ་འགྱུར་ཞེས་ལུང་བསྟན་ཏོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“The ministers then called for soothsayers to ask about the dreams’ significance.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-121">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-69</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།འདི་ལྟ་བུའི་རྨི་ལམ་བསྟན་པ་ཐོས་པ་དང་། གྲོང་ཁྱེར་ཨ་རིཥྛ་ན་གནས་པའི་སྐྱེ་བོའི་ཚོགས་རྣམས་ཉམ་ཐག་པའི་ང་རོས་ངུ་བར་བརྩམས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>After a while, the soothsayers foretold that things would be just as they had dreamt. <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-69"/>“After hearing about the dreams, the populace of Ariṣṭa city was wretched and started to weep aloud.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-122">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-69</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཐོས་པ་གཅིག་ནས་གཅིག་ཏུ་བརྒྱུད་པས་འཛམ་བུའི་གླིང་པའི་མི་ཐམས་ཅད་མྱ་ངན་དྲག་པོའི་སྡུག་བསྔལ་གྱིས་བཅོམ་ནས་ཤིན་ཏུ་སྨྲེ་སྔགས་འདོན་པར་གྱུར་ཏོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Word spread from person to person, and soon everyone in Jambudvīpa wailed because of their suffering and intense grief.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-123">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-69</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ལྟར་གྱུར་པ་དེ་རྒྱལ་པོ་དཔལ་གྱི་སྡེས་ཐོས་སོ། །ཐོས་ནས་ཀྱང་ཡང་བསམས་པ། ངའི་ལུས་སློང་བ་འོང་བར་འགྱུར་རོ་སྙམ་ནས་སེམས་རབ་ཏུ་དགའ་བ་དང་། མགུ་བར་གྱུར་ཏོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>King Śrīsena heard of this and thought, ‘How pleasing and delightful that someone would ask for my body!’ Thus, he made an announcement:</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-124">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-69</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཤེས་ལྡན་དག་འཛམ་བུའི་གླིང་གི་མི་ཁྱེད་རྣམས་བདེ་བ་དང་ཕེབས་པས་དགེ་བ་ལ་གཞོལ་བར་གྱིས་ཤིག །ཁྱེད་རྣམས་སྒྱུ་མ་ལྟ་བུའི་རྨི་ལམ་ལ་སེམས་པས་ཅི་ཞིག་བྱ་ཞེས་འཛམ་<tei:ref folio="F.35.b"/>བུའི་གླིང་པ་ཐམས་ཅད་དུ་དྲིལ་བསྒྲགས་སོ། །དེ་ནས་རྒྱལ་པོ་དཔལ་གྱི་སྡེས་དྲིལ་བསྒྲགས་པ་དེ་ཐོས་པ་དང་། འཛམ་བུའི་གླིང་པའི་མི་ཐམས་ཅད་དབུགས་ཕྱིན་པར་གྱུར་ཏོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>‘Wise ones, people of Jambudvīpa, engage in virtue with joy and calmness. What is the point of thinking about illusion-like dreams?’ When the people of the world heard King Śrīsena’s announcement, they were relieved.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-125">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-70</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཡང་དེའི་ཚེ་དེའི་དུས་ན་རྒྱལ་པོའི་ཕོ་བྲང་ཨ་རིཥྛའི་བྱང་ཕྱོགས་རྒྱང་གྲགས་ཙམ་གྱིས་ཕྱོགས་ན་རི་བོ་ཞིག་ཡོད་དེ། དེ་ན་དྲང་སྲོང་ལྔ་བརྒྱ་ཙམ་གནས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-70"/>“In those days, five hundred sages lived on a mountain about two miles<tei:note xml:id="UT22084-076-003-71"/> north of the royal estate of Ariṣṭa.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-126">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-70</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཇི་ཙམ་ན་དུས་གཞན་ཞིག་གི་ཚེ་དེ་རྣམས་ཀྱི་དོན་དུ་འཇུག་པ་དྲང་སྲོང་གཅིག་དོན་གྱི་བྱ་བ་འགའ་ཞིག་གི་ཕྱིར་རྒྱལ་པོའི་ཕོ་བྲང་ཨ་རིཥྛར་འོངས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>A short time after the dreams, one of the sages came to the king’s estate to do the sages’ bidding.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-127">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-70</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཡང་དུས་དེའི་ཚེ་རྒྱལ་པོ་དཔལ་གྱི་སྡེ་ལྷ་མོ་རྒྱལ་བའི་འོད་དང་ལྷན་ཅིག་ཏུ་ནང་དུ་ཞུགས་ནས་སྐྱེད་མོས་ཚལ་གྱི་སར་སོང་ངོ་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>At that time, King Śrīsena and Queen Jayaprabhā were strolling in the garden.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-128">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-70</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དྲང་སྲོང་དེས་རྒྱལ་བ་དང་ཚེ་རིང་བའི་བརྗོད་པ་བྱས་པ་དང་། དྲང་སྲོང་དེས་ལྷ་མོ་རྒྱལ་བའི་འོད་རྒྱན་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱིས་བརྒྱན་པ་མཐོང་སྟེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The sage exclaimed, ‘May the king be victorious and live for a long time!’ The sage also saw Queen Jayaprabhā adorned with ornaments.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-129">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-70</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདི་ལྟར་ཡང་དེའི་སྐྱེ་བ་སྔ་མའི་ཆུང་མར་གྱུར་པ་ཡང་ཡིན་པས་སྔོན་གྱི་ཆགས་པ་དང་འབྲེལ་པའི་དབང་གིས་ཚུལ་བཞིན་མ་ཡིན་པའི་ཡིད་ལ་བྱེད་པ་སྐྱེས་པར་གྱུར་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>In a past life the queen had been his wife. The influence of this previous desire and their previous relationship caused him to have inappropriate thoughts.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-130">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-70</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ཡིད་ལ་སེམས་ཤིང་ལམ་དེ་ནས་སོང་སྟེ། ལམ་དེ་ནས་འདས་པ་དང་ཇི་ཙམ་ན་དྲང་སྲོང་དེ་རྒྱལ་པོའི་ཕོ་བྲང་གྲོང་ཁྱེར་ཨ་རིཥྛར་བྱ་བའམ། བྱེད་པ་ཐམས་ཅད་བྱས་ཏེ་ཡོངས་སུ་རྫོགས་པ་དང་བསྟི་གནས་སུ་སོང་ངོ་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Thinking these inappropriate thoughts, he walked along the path, completed his chores in Ariṣṭa city, and went back to his dwelling.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-131">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-72</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཇི་ཙམ་ན་དུས་གཞན་ཞིག་གི་ཚེ་དྲང་སྲོང་དེས་བྲམ་ཟེའི་ཁྱེའུ་གཅིག་རིག་བྱེད་འདོན་པ་ཡོངས་སུ་རྫོགས་པ་དང་། དེས་མཁན་པོའི་རྐང་པ་ལ་གཏུགས་ནས་སྨྲས་པ། མཁན་པོ་ལ་ནོར་ཇི་ལྟ་བུ་དབུལ་བར་བགྱི། མཁན་པོས་བཀའ་སྩོལ་ཅིག །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-72"/>“A little while later, on another occasion, a student of this same sage, a brahmin boy, completed his recitation of the Vedas, touched his preceptor’s feet, and asked in gratitude, ‘Preceptor, what wealth can I offer you?’</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-132">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-74</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དྲང་སྲོང་གིས་སྨྲས་པ། དེ་བས་ན་བུ་རྒྱལ་པོ་དཔལ་གྱི་སྡེའི་བཙུན་མོའི་མཆོག་བཙུན་མོ་རྒྱལ་བའི་འོད་སློངས་ལ་ངའི་བསྙེན་བཀུར་བྱ་བ་དང་། མཁན་པོ་ལ་མཁན་པོའི་ནོར་དང་། བླ་མ་ལ་མཆོད་པར་བྱ་བའི་ཕྱིར་བྱིན་ཅིག །དེ་སྐད་ཅེས་སྨྲས་པ་དང་། བྲམ་ཟེའི་ཁྱེའུ་དེ་གནད་དུ་བསྣུན་པའི་རི་དགས་བཞིན་དུ་སྡུག་བསྔལ་དྲག་པོས་གདུངས་ཏེ་མཆོག་ཏུ་ཡི་མུག་པ་དང་། བསམས་པ་གནས་འདི་ནི་འབྱུང་བར་དཀའ་བ་དང་རྙེད་པར་དཀའ་ན།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“The sage replied, ‘Son, if you wish, go ask for King Śrīsena’s supreme queen, Jayaprabhā. Give her to me as your offering, a gift for your preceptor, an homage to your guru.’ <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-74"/>“When this was said, the brahmin boy was overwhelmed by great sorrow and acute despair; he was like a deer whose vital organ has been pierced. He thought, ‘This situation will only come about with difficulty, and it will be no easy task to acquire her.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-133">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-74</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཇི་ལྟར་ཡང་བྲམ་ཟེ་ཉོན་མོངས་པ་དག་ལྟ་བུས་རྒྱལ་པོ་ལ་བཙུན་མོ་རྒྱལ་བའི་འོད་འདི་བྱིན་ཅིག །ཅེས་ཇི་ལྟར་སྨྲ་བར་ནུས།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>How could a troubled brahmin like me ask the king to give him Queen Jayaprabhā?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-134">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-74</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདི་ལྟར་བསླང་བར་བྱ་བ་མ་ཡིན་པའི་དངོས་པོ་འདི་ལ་ཀུན་<tei:ref folio="F.36.a"/>དུ་སྦྱོར་བ་གང་ཡིན་པ་དེས་ན།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Why am I being asked to get something that is unattainable?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-135">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-74</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མཁན་པོ་ངེས་པར་བདག་ལ་དམོད་པ་བྱེད་པར་འདོད་པ་ཡིན་ནོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The preceptor clearly wants to place a curse on me.’</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-136">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-75</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ནས་དྲང་སྲོང་དེས་དེའི་བཞིན་རྣམ་པར་འགྱུར་བས་ནང་གི་བསམ་པ་རྟོགས་ནས་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-75"/>“The change in the boy’s facial expression allowed the sage to realize his thoughts, and the sage said, ‘Son, do not be afraid.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-137">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-75</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བུ་མ་འཇིགས་ཤིག་ཇི་ལྟར་ན་སེམས་འདི་ལྟར་ཁོང་དུ་ཆུད།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Why are you so depressed?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-138">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-75</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྒྱལ་པོ་འདི་ནི་བདག་ཉིད་ཆེ་བ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The king is a great being.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-139">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-75</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཐམས་ཅད་སྟེར་བ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He gives away everything.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-140">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-75</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཐམས་ཅད་ཡོངས་སུ་གཏོང་ཞིང་ཆགས་པ་མེད་པར་ཡོངས་སུ་གཏོང་བས་ཐ་ན་རང་གི་ཤ་ཡང་གཏོང་སྟེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He lets go of everything. He lets go of everything completely and without attachment. He would even give away his own flesh.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-141">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-75</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདི་ལ་ཡོངས་སུ་མ་བཏང་བ་ཅི་ཡང་མེད་དོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>There is nothing that he would not relinquish in this way.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-142">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-75</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།བུ་དེས་ན་རྒྱལ་པོས་བཙུན་མོའི་མཆོག་སྟེར་བར་འགྱུར་གྱིས་ཡི་མུག་པར་མ་བྱེད་ཅིག །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Therefore, son, do not despair; the king will give you his supreme queen.’</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-143">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-76</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་འདི་སྙམ་དུ་སེམས་ཏེ། གལ་ཏེ་མ་སོང་ན་ནི་གང་དམོད་པ་བྱེད་པའི་གནས་དེ་ཡོད་པས་འགྲོ་སྙམ་ནས་དེ་དམོད་པས་འཇིགས་པས་སྨྲས་པ། མཁན་པོ་གལ་ཏེ་དེ་ལྟ་ན་མཆིའོ་ཞེས་དེས་དེའི་རྐང་པ་ལ་གཏུགས་ནས་སོང་སྟེ། རྒྱལ་པོའི་ཕོ་བྲང་ཨ་རིཥྛར་ཕྱིན་ཏོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-76"/>“Then the boy thought, ‘If I do not go, I will be cursed.’ And out of fear of this curse, he said to the sage, ‘Preceptor, if that is so, I will go.’ After touching the sage’s feet, he traveled to the king’s estate, Ariṣṭa.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-144">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-77</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་བཞིན་དུ་ཤིང་ཤུན་གྱི་གོས་གྱོན་ཞིང་དབྱིག་པ་དང་། རིལ་བ་ལག་ན་ཐོགས་ལ་ས་རྡུལ་གྱིས་ལུས་ལ་གོས་པ་དང་། རྒྱལ་པོ་དཔལ་གྱི་སྡེ་ག་ལ་བ་དེར་སོང་སྟེ་ཕྱིན་ནས་རྒྱལ་པོ་དཔལ་གྱི་སྡེ་ལ་རྒྱལ་བ་དང་། ཚེ་སྤེལ་བ་བྱས་ནས་བསམས་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-77"/>“Having applied dust to his body, wearing tree-bark cloth, and holding a staff and a little vase in his hands, the boy went to the site where King Śrīsena was and exclaimed, ‘May the king be victorious and may his life be long!’ Then he thought, ‘Should I ask?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-145">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-77</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཅི་བསླང་ངམ་འོན་ཏེ་མི་བསླང་སྟེར་བར་འགྱུར་རམ་མི་སྟེར་བར་འགྱུར།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Or will he give her to me without my having to ask? Or will he not give her to me?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-146">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-77</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ངའི་ཡིད་ལ་རེ་བ་འབྲས་བུ་དང་བཅས་པར་འགྱུར་རམ། འབྲས་བུ་མེད་པར་འགྱུར་སྙམ་ནས་བདག་ཉིད་སྨོད་བཞིན་དུ་རྒྱལ་པོའི་མདུན་ན་དམན་པའི་བཞིན་གྱིས་ཅང་མི་སྨྲ་བར་འདུག་གོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Will my wishes be fulfilled or not?’ And he stood in front of the king with an unsettled look on his face, castigating himself, not speaking.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-147">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-78</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ནས་རྒྱལ་པོ་དཔལ་གྱི་སྡེས་བསམས་པ། འདི་ནི་ང་ལ་སློང་དུ་འོངས་སོ་སྙམ་ནས་བྲམ་ཟེའི་ཁྱེའུ་དེ་ལ་འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་སྨྲས་སོ། །བྲམ་ཟེ་ཁྱོད་ཀྱི་དགོས་པ་གང་ཡིན་པ་དེ་སྨྲོས།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-78"/>“Thinking that the brahmin boy had come to beg something from him, King Śrīsena asked him, ‘Brahmin, what is it that you want?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-148">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-78</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་རིང་ཁྱོད་ཀྱི་ཡིད་ལ་རེ་བ་ཡོངས་སུ་རྫོགས་པར་བྱའོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Today, I will fulfill your wishes completely.’</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-149">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-78</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་སྐད་ཅེས་སྨྲས་པ་དང་། བྲམ་ཟེའི་ཁྱེའུ་དེ་མི་འཇིགས་པ་སྐྱེས་ནས་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་ལ་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>When the king said this, the brahmin boy gained confidence and replied to the bodhisattva, ‘This is good.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-150">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-78</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ལེགས་ཀྱིས་ལྷ་རི་ག་གེ་མོ་ན་བདག་གི་མཁན་པོ་དྲང་སྲོང་འདོན་དུ་འཇུག་པ་འཁོར་ལྔ་བརྒྱ་དང་གནས་ཏེ་དེ་ལས་བདག་གིས་རིག་བྱེད་འདོན་པ་ཡོངས་སུ་རྫོགས་པས་རྒྱལ་པོ་ཆེན་པོ་ད་ཐུགས་བརྩེ་བས་བཙུན་མོ་རྒྱལ་བའི་འོད་བདག་ལ་སྩོལ་ཅིག །མཁན་པོ་ལ་མཁན་པོའི་ནོར་དང་། བླ་མ་མཆོད་<tei:ref folio="F.36.b"/>པའི་ཕྱིར་བདག་གིས་མཁན་པོ་ལ་དབུལ་བར་བགྱིའོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Lord, on a certain mountain my preceptor lives with his companions; they are five hundred sages who recite the Vedas. I have completed my Vedic studies with him. Great King, through your compassion give me Queen Jayaprabhā, and I will offer her to my preceptor as a gift, an homage to my guru.’</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-151">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-80</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་སྐད་ཅེས་སྨྲས་པ་དང་། རྒྱལ་པོ་དཔལ་གྱི་སྡེ་བརྩེ་བའི་དབང་གིས་ཡིད་མི་དགའ་བར་གྱུར་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-80"/>“When these words were spoken, King Śrīsena was distraught. He loved the queen.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-152">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-80</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཙུན་མོ་རྒྱལ་བའི་འོད་འདི་ང་དང་བྲལ་ན་ཇི་ལྟར་སྲོག་འཛིན་པར་ནུས། འཁོར་དེ་དག་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱང་རྒྱ་མཚོ་ཟབ་མོའི་སྒྲ་མི་གཡོ་བ་དང་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>‘If Queen Jayaprabhā were separated from me,’ he thought, ‘will we survive?’ For a while, all the members of the king’s and queen’s retinues were as quiet as the oceans’ depths.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-153">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-80</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གནད་དུ་བསྣུན་པ་བཞིན་དུ་སྡུག་བསྔལ་དྲག་པོས་གདུངས་པས་རྟབས་བག་ཏུ་འདི་ཅི་འདི་ཅི་ཞེས་སྐྱོ་བས་རབ་ཏུ་གདུངས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Then it was as if a great pain were piercing their vital organs. ‘What is this?’ they cried out. ‘What is this?’</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-154">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-81</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ནས་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔས་སྐད་ཅིག་ཅང་མི་སྨྲ་བར་གནས་ཏེ་བསམས་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-81"/>“The bodhisattva remained silent, in thought.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-155">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-81</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བུ་དང་ཆུང་མ་ལ་སོགས་པ་བྱིན་པ་མེད་པས་ནི་བླ་ན་མེད་པ་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་བྱང་ཆུབ་འཐོབ་པར་མི་འགྱུར་རོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>‘Unsurpassed and perfect awakening cannot be attained without giving up sons, wife, and so forth,’ he pondered.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-156">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-81</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེའི་ཕྱིར་བྲམ་ཟེ་འདི་ལ་དགའ་བས་ཆུང་མ་འདི་སྦྱིན་པར་བྱའོ་སྙམ་དུ་བསམས་ནས་གཉེན་སྡུག་པ་དང་བྲལ་བས་ཞུམ་པའི་སེམས་ཡང་དག་པར་བླངས་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>‘Therefore, I must happily give my wife to this brahmin.’ This thought lifted him out of his sadness at losing a loved one.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-157">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-81</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཕྲལ་དུ་སེང་གེའི་ཁྲི་ལས་བབས་ནས་བྱང་ཆུབ་ཏུ་སྨོན་པའི་སེམས་ཀྱིས་བཙུན་མོ་རྒྱལ་བའི་འོད་ལྷའི་བུ་མོ་བཞིན་དུ་རྣམ་པར་མཛེས་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He descended from the lion throne immediately, and keeping in mind the aspirational mind of awakening, he took the goddess-like, intensely beautiful Queen Jayaprabhā with his left hand and held a golden vase in his right.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-158">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-81</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཁྱོ་དང་བྲལ་བའི་གདུང་བས་ཤིན་ཏུ་དབུགས་རིང་པོ་ཕྱུང་སྟེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The queen felt great pain at the prospect of being separated from her husband and sighed heavily.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-159">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-81</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མཆི་མས་གང་བའི་མིག་དང་། མུན་པར་གཡང་ས་ཆེན་པོར་ལྷུང་བ་བཞིན་དུ་མཆོག་ཏུ་སྡུག་བསྔལ་བས་གདོང་ཕབ་པ་ལག་པ་གཡོན་པས་བཟུང་སྟེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Her eyes filled with tears and her face dropped. She suffered as if she had fallen into a deep, dark abyss.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-160">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-82</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལག་པ་གཡས་པས་གསེར་གྱི་བུམ་པ་ཐོགས་ནས་བྲམ་ཟེའི་ཁྱེའུ་དེ་ལ་འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་སྨྲས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-82"/>“ ‘Come here, come here great brahmin,’ the king said to the brahmin boy:</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-161">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-82</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།བྲམ་ཟེ་ཆེན་པོ་ཚུར་ཤོག །ཚུར་ཤོག །བྲམ་ཟེའི་དམ་པ་གཟུགས་བཟང་བ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“ ‘Handsome, fine brahmin,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-162">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-82</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།སྡུག་པའི་ཆུང་མ་འདི་ལོང་ཤིག །སྦྱིན་པ་འདི་ཡིས་མྱུར་དུ་ནི།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>You may take my beloved wife. May this act of generosity swiftly bring</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-163">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-83</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།བྱང་ཆུབ་དམ་པ་ཐོབ་པར་ཤོག །ཅེས་སྨྲས་ནས་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔས་བྲམ་ཟེ་དེའི་ལག་པར་ཆུའི་རྒྱུན་བླུགས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The attainment of true awakening.’<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-83"/> “Then, maintaining the mind of awakening, he poured water onto the brahmin’s palm.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-164">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-83</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ནས་ཡང་དགེ་སློང་དག་རྒྱལ་པོ་དཔལ་གྱི་སྡེས་ཆུའི་རྒྱུན་བླུགས་པའི་རྗེས་ཐོགས་ཉིད་ལ་དེའི་ཚེ་འཕྲལ་དུ་ས་རྣམ་པ་དྲུག་ཏུ་གཡོས་པར་གྱུར་ཏོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Monks, at the very instant that King Śrīsena poured the water, the earth shook in six different ways.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-165">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-83</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ནས་བྲམ་ཟེའི་ཁྱེའུ་དེས་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའི་གཏོང་བ་དང་། གཏོང་བ་ལས་ཀྱང་ཤིན་ཏུ་གཏོང་བ། ཤིན་ཏུ་དཀའ་བ་དེ་མཐོང་བ་དང་། མཆོག་ཏུ་ངོ་མཚར་སྐྱེས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Having witnessed how a bodhisattva gives, a great act of giving, an extremely difficult act of giving, the brahmin boy was utterly seized with wonder.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-166">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-83</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ནམ་མཁའི་ངོས་ན་གནས་པའི་ལྷ་བརྒྱ་སྟོང་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་ཀྱང་ཅ་ཅོའི་སྒྲ་བཏོན་ཏོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The act even caused hundreds of thousands of sky-dwelling gods to murmur in amazement.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-167">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-83</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་མ་ཐག་ཏུ་ཡང་སྐར་མདའ་ལྟུང་བ་དང་། ཕྱོགས་འབར་བ་དང་། བར་སྣང་གི་ལྷ་ཡང་རྔ་རྡུང་<tei:ref folio="F.37.a"/>བར་གྱུར་ཏོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Instantly, meteors fell, blazing in all directions, and the celestial gods beat their drums.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-168">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-84</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ནས་བྲམ་ཟེའི་ཁྱེའུ་དེ་རྒྱལ་པོ་འགྱོད་པར་མ་གྱུར་གྲང་སྙམ་ནས་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་ལ་མངོན་པར་བསྟོད་དེ། བདེ་ལེགས་སུ་གྱུར་ཅིག་ཅེས་སྨྲས་ནས་བཙུན་མོ་རྒྱལ་བའི་འོད་ཁྱེར་ཏེ་རིངས་པ་རིངས་པར་བསྟི་གནས་སུ་སོང་སྟེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-84"/>“Fearing that the king might change his mind, the brahmin boy praised the bodhisattva, uttered some prayers for his prosperity, and left quickly for home, taking Queen Jayaprabhā with him.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-169">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-84</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མཁན་པོ་ལ་བྱིན་པ་དང་། བཙུན་མོ་རྒྱལ་བའི་འོད་ཉ་ཆུ་ལས་བཏོན་པ་བཞིན་དུ་སྡུག་པ་དང་བྲལ་བའི་སྡུག་བསྔལ་དྲག་པོས་གདུངས་ཤིང་ཉམ་ཐག་པ་དང་། བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཉིད་ལ་མངོན་པར་སེམས་ཤིང་འགྲོ་བ་ཐམས་ཅད་མུན་པ་མུན་ནག་ཏུ་གྱུར་པ་བཞིན་དུ་ཤེས་ཤིང་ཀྱི་ཧུད་རྒྱལ་པོ་ཆེན་པོ་ཀྱི་ཧུད་རྒྱལ་པོ་ཆེན་པོ་ཞེས་མཆོག་ཏུ་གདུང་བའི་སེམས་དང་ཟས་བཅད་པ་ལ་ཞུགས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He then gave the queen to his teacher. For Queen Jayaprabhā, being separated from her beloved was like being a fish taken out of water. She was wretched, but she knew that thinking about or following the bodhisattva would be in vain, like wandering from shadows into pitch darkness. Therefore, she merely lamented, ‘Alas, Great King. Alas, Great King.’ Her sadness even caused her to refuse food.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-170">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-85</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ས་གཡོས་པ་དེས་བརྒྱ་བྱིན་གྱི་གནས་གཡོས་པར་གྱུར་ཏོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-85"/>“As the queen suffered, the shaking caused by King Śrīsena’s deed rattled even Śakra’s abode.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-171">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-85</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཆོས་ཉིད་ཀྱིས་ལྷ་རྣམས་ཀྱི་ཤེས་པ་འོག་ཏུ་མཐོང་བ་འཇུག་གི་གོང་དུ་ནི་མ་ཡིན་ནོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The gods spontaneously know what happens below them but not what happens above them.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-172">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-85</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ནས་ལྷའི་དབང་པོ་བརྒྱ་བྱིན་གྱིས་བསམས་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Śakra, lord of the gods, therefore wondered:</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-173">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-86</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཤིན་ཏུ་གྲགས་པར་ས་གཡོས་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-86"/>“ ‘The earth quakes with a tremendous sound.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-174">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-86</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།མཚན་མ་འདི་ནི་སུའི་མཐུ་ཡིན།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Whose power is behind this sign?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-175">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-86</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།གང་གི་མཐུ་ནི་ཅི་འདྲ་བ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>What kind of power is it?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-176">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-86</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཤིན་ཏུ་གསལ་བར་འདི་ཤེས་བྱ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>I must know this very clearly.’</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-177">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-87</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།འཛམ་བུའི་གླིང་ཐམས་ཅད་ལ་བལྟ་བར་བརྩམས་པ་དང་། ཇི་ཙམ་ན་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་འདི་ལྟ་བུ་མཆོག་ཏུ་དཀའ་བའི་ལས་བྱེད་པ་མཐོང་ངོ་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-87"/>“He began to search all over Jambudvīpa. After a while, he discovered that the shaking was a result of the bodhisattva’s extremely difficult act.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-178">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-87</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།མཐོང་ནས་ཀྱང་མཆོག་ཏུ་ངོ་མཚར་སྐྱེས་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>When he understood this, he was awed.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-179">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-87</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སུམ་ཅུ་རྩ་གསུམ་གྱི་ལྷ་རྣམས་ལ་སྨྲས་པ། གྲོགས་པོ་དག་ཁྱེད་ཅག་རྣམས་རྒྱལ་པོ་དཔལ་གྱི་སྡེའི་ངོ་མཚར་དང་རྨད་དུ་བྱུང་བའི་ལས་ལ་ལྟོས།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>To the gods of the Heaven of the Thirty-Three, he said, ‘Consider the incredible, amazing act King Śrīsena has performed.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-180">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-87</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་ཞིག་འདི་ལྟར་སྡུག་པ་དང་། འདི་ལྟར་ཡིད་དུ་འོང་བ་དང་། འདི་ལྟར་ཕངས་པའི་ཆུང་མ་ལ་མི་སེམས་ཏེ་རྩྭ་བཞིན་དུ་ཡོངས་སུ་གཏོང་ངོ་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Who can give away such a loving, beautiful, and dear wife without any hesitation, as if they were giving away straw?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-181">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-87</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།གྲོགས་པོ་དག་རྣམ་གྲངས་དེས་ཀྱང་འདི་ལྟར་ཤེས་པར་བྱ་སྟེ། བདག་ཉིད་ཆེན་པོ་འདི་རང་གི་ཡན་ལག་དང་ཉིང་ལག་རྣམས་ཀྱང་ཕངས་པ་མེད་པར་གཏོང་བ་ཡིན་ནོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Friends, through this act we know the great being will give away even his major and minor body parts, without hesitation.’</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-182">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-88</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ལྷ་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་སྨྲས་པ། ཀཽ་ཤི་ཀ་བུ་དང་བུ་མོ་ནི་དེ་བས་ཡོངས་སུ་གཏོང་བར་བྱེད་ཀྱི། འདི་ལྟ་སྟེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-88"/>“ ‘Kauśika,’ replied the gods, ‘we believe that he can give away his sons and daughters.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-183">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-88</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡན་ལག་དང་ཉིང་ལག་སྟེར་བ་འདི་ནི་དད་པར་བྱ་བ་མ་ཡིན་ཏེ་ཤིན་ཏུ་དཀའོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>But we do not believe he can give away his major and minor body parts. It is too difficult.’</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-184">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-88</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་སྐད་ཅེས་སྨྲས་པ་དང་། ལྷའི་དབང་པོ་བརྒྱ་བྱིན་གྱིས་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Śakra, lord of the gods, responded,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-185">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-88</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གྲོགས་པོ་དག་ཞོག་ཞོག །སྤུའི་རྩེ་མོའི་<tei:ref folio="F.37.b"/>ཆུའི་ཐིགས་པས་རྒྱ་མཚོ་མ་གཞལ་ཅིག །ནམ་མཁའ་འདོམ་གྱིས་མ་གཞལ་ཅིག །ཉི་མ་དང་སྲིན་བུ་མེ་ཁྱེར་འོད་མ་སྙོམ་ཅིག །རིའི་རྒྱལ་པོ་རི་རབ་དང་ཡུངས་འབྲུར་མ་སྙོམ་ཅིག །གཞན་ཡང་ངས་ཁྱེད་ཅག་རྣམས་ཀྱི་མངོན་སུམ་དུ་བྱ་ཡིས།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>‘Friends, leave it be, leave it be. Do not measure the ocean against a drop of water so small it rests on the tip of a hair strand. Do not measure space with your arms. Do not compare the light of a firefly to the sun. Do not compare the size of a seed to Mount Sumeru. I will produce evidence for you all.’</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-186">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-90</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་ལྷའི་དབང་པོ་བརྒྱ་བྱིན་གྱིས་དེ་ཉིད་ཀྱི་ནམ་ནངས་པ་ན་སུམ་ཅུ་རྩ་གསུམ་གྱི་ལྷ་རྣམས་ལ་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-90"/>“At dawn, Śakra, lord of the gods, spoke again to the gods of the Heaven of the Thirty-Three.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-187">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-90</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཀྱེ་མའོ་གྲོགས་པོ་དག་ཤེས་པར་གྱིས་ཤིག་ཅེས་སྨྲས་ཏེ། ནང་པར་ཉིད་ལངས་ནས་ལྷའི་བུ་བཞི་དང་ཐབས་ཅིག་ཏུ་སུམ་ཅུ་རྩ་གསུམ་གྱི་གནས་ལས་བབས་ཏེ་གྲོང་ཁྱེར་ཨ་རིཥྛ་དང་ཧ་ཅང་མི་རིང་བའི་ནགས་ཀྱི་ཚང་ཚིང་དུ་ཞུགས་ནས་བྲམ་ཟེ་རྒན་པོའི་ཆ་བྱད་དུ་བྱས་ནས་རང་གི་ལུས་ཀྱི་ལྟེ་བ་མན་ཆད་སོག་ལེས་བཅད་པ་བཞིན་དུ་སྟོན་ཅིང་ཀུན་ནས་ཁྲག་འཛག་པ་ཁྲི་བསྐྱོད་ནས་ལྷའི་བུ་བཞི་བྲམ་ཟེའི་ཆ་བྱད་འཛིན་པས་ཕ་དང་བྲལ་བའི་སྡུག་བསྔལ་གྱིས་ཉམ་ཐག་པ་ལྟར་ཉམ་ཐག་པའི་ང་རོས་ཆོ་ངེས་འདེབས་ཤིང་བཏེག་པར་མངོན་པར་སྤྲུལ་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>‘Look, friends! Now you shall understand!’ That morning, he and four other gods from the Heaven of the Thirty-Three descended to earth, alighting in a forest near Ariṣṭa city. Śakra transformed himself into an old brahmin whose body had been hacked away below the navel, as if by a saw. Blood gushed from all sides of the wound. The other four gods of the Heaven of the Thirty-Three emanated as this old brahmin’s sons. They lifted him onto a stretcher while wailing wretchedly at the agony of losing their father.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-188">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-90</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ངའི་ལུས་འདིའི་ཕྱེད་སྟག་གིས་བཅད་དེ་ཟོས་སོ་ཞེས་འདི་ལྟར་བསྟན་པར་བྱའོ་སྙམ་ནས་ཡིད་ལ་བསམས་པ་བཞིན་དུ། ཉི་མ་ཤར་བའི་དུས་སུ་ནགས་ཚང་ཚིང་དེ་ནས་བྱུང་སྟེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They left the forest at sunrise, traveling toward the city, intending to claim that the old brahmin’s lower body had been eaten by a tiger.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-189">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-90</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གྲོང་ཁྱེར་དུ་མངོན་པར་ཕྱོགས་ནས་ཀུན་དུ་ཆས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They arrived at the city gate quickly.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-190">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-90</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཁྲག་གི་དྲི་དེ་ལ་ཡང་སྟེང་ནས་ཁྭ་དང་ཆུ་སྐྱར་དང་། བྱ་རྒོད་རྣམས་རྗེས་སུ་འབྲང་ངོ་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Hawks, gulls, and vultures hovered in the sky above them, drawn by the smell of the old brahmin’s blood.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-191">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-90</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།འོག་ནས་ཀྱང་ཁྱི་དང་ཝ་རྣམས་རྗེས་སུ་འབྲང་བཞིན་དུ་རིངས་པ་རིངས་པར་གྲོང་ཁྱེར་གྱི་སྒོར་སོང་ངོ་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Dogs and foxes trailed behind them on the ground.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-192">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-91</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ཡང་འདི་ལྟར་སྙིང་རྗེའི་གནས་སུ་གྱུར་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-91"/>“The old brahmin looked pitiful.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-193">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-91</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྐྱེས་པ་དང་བུད་མེད་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་མཐོང་ནས་སྙིང་རྗེས་གདུངས་པའི་ཡིད་ཀྱིས་གཅིག་ལ་གཅིག་སྨྲ་བ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>His plight moved the men and women who saw him. Some asked each other,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-194">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-91</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གྲོགས་དག་བྲམ་ཟེ་འདི་རྐེད་པར་ཆད་ནས་འདིའི་དབང་པོ་ཡང་མ་འཁྲུགས་པ་ཇི་ལྟར་འཚོ་བར་འགྱུར།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>‘Friends, how is the old brahmin still alive when he has no lower body? How are his organs intact?’</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-195">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-91</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཞན་ཞིག་གིས་སྨྲས་པ། འདི་མི་མ་ཡིན་གྱི་ཤ་ཟ་མིའི་ཆ་བྱད་ཀྱིས་བདག་ཅག་བཟའ་བའི་ཕྱིར་འདིར་འོངས་ཀྱི།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Others speculated, ‘He must be a nonhuman demon who has come to devour us.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-196">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-91</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མི་རྐེད་པར་ཆད་པ་ནི་འཚོ་བ་མེད་དོ། །དེ་སྐད་ཅེས་ཐོས་པ་དང་སྐྱེས་བུ་སྡར་མ་ནི་འཇིགས་པས་བྲོས་པར་བརྩམས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>How else would someone survive without his lower body?’ When the fainthearted heard this, they ran away out of fear.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-197">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-91</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།སྐྱེས་བུ་དཔའ་བོ་གཞན་ཞིག་འདི་སྙམ་དུ་འདི་ནི་ཤ་ཟ་ཞིག་སྟེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>But one brave man thought, ‘He must be a demon.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-198">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-91</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ལྟ་ན་ཡང་ཚོར་བས་ཉེན་བཞིན་དུ་འདི་ལྟར་དབང་པོ་རྣམས་བདེ་བར་སྣང་ན་དེ་ཇི་ལྟ་བུ་ཡིན།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>If he isn’t a demon, how could he appear to have his faculties despite his imperiled state?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-199">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-91</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བདག་<tei:ref folio="F.38.a"/>གིས་འདི་ལ་མི་མ་ཡིན་ནམ་ཤ་ཟར་གྱུར་པ་ཡིན་པར་དྲི་བར་བྱས་ན་འདིས་ཚིག་ཐོན་པར་དཀའ་མོད་ཀྱི། གལ་ཏེ་ཚིག་ཐོན་ན་ནི་ངོ་མཚར་དུ་འགྱུར་རོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>I will ask him if he is a nonhuman or a demon. It will be difficult for him to speak, but if he does, that would be astonishing.’</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-200">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-91</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཇི་ཙམ་ན་གཞན་ཞིག་ལྟད་མོ་སྐྱེས་ནས་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>A while later, one of the others who saw the spectacle asked,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-201">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-91</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྲམ་ཟེ་ཁྱོད་ཅི་མི་ཡིན་ནམ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>‘Brahmin! Are you a human or a demon?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-202">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-91</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འོན་ཏེ་ཤ་ཟ་ཡིན་ཁྱོད་ཀྱི་ལུས་འདི་རྐེད་པར་སུས་བཅད་ནས་གནས་སྐབས་འདི་ལྟ་བུར་བྱས།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Who cut off the lower half of your body and left you in this state?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-203">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-91</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཁྱོད་ནི་ག་ལས་འོངས།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Where did you come from?’</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-204">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-92</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་ལྷའི་དབང་པོ་བརྒྱ་བྱིན་གྱིས་བདག་ཉིད་འདི་ལྟར་ཁྲིའི་སྟེང་དུ་འདུག་ཅིང་སྡུག་བསྔལ་དྲག་པོའི་ཚོར་བས་ཉེན་པ་བཞིན་དུ་ཉེ་བར་སྟོན་ཅིང་དེའི་ཚེ་ཚིགས་སུ་བཅད་པ་འདི་དག་སྨྲས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-92"/>“Then Śakra, lord of the gods, in the form of the old brahmin, lying on the stretcher and acting as if he were in tremendous pain, replied in verse:</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-205">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-92</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཤི་བི་པ་ཁྱེད་མ་འཇིགས་ཤིག །བྲམ་ཟེ་ང་ཡིན་སྲིན་པོ་མིན།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“ ‘Man of Śibi, be not afraid. I am a brahmin, not a demon.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-206">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-92</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།སྔོན་གྱི་ལས་ཀྱི་ཉེས་པ་ཡིས།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Because of past deeds,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-207">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-92</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།གནས་སྐབས་འདི་འདྲ་ཐོབ་པར་གྱུར།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>I have ended up in this state.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-208">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-94</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།འདི་ཉིད་དུ་ནི་ཀུན་བཤད་ན།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-94"/>“ ‘Were I to explain everything,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-209">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-94</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དུས་ནི་ཀུན་དུ་འདའ་བར་འགྱུར།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>My time would run out.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-210">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-94</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།འཆི་བདག་མྱུར་དུ་འོངས་ནས་ནི།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The Lord of Death is coming quickly.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-211">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-94</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།སྲོག་ནི་འཕྲོག་པར་འགྱུར་དུ་འོང་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He will snatch my life away.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-212">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-95</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཆོས་ཀྱི་རྒྱལ་པོའི་སྤྱན་སྔར་ནི།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-95"/>“ ‘Please report all this To your Dharma king.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-213">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-95</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།འདི་དག་ཀུན་ཀྱང་བཤད་པར་བྱ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>It is certain that I must experience</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-214">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-96</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།སྔོན་གྱི་ལས་ཀྱི་མཚན་ཉིད་ནི། །དེ་རིང་ང་ལ་འབྲས་བཅས་གྱུར།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The fruits of past actions today.<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-96"/> “ ‘Where can I gaze upon the great one?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-215">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-96</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཡོན་ཏན་ཀུན་གྱིས་རྣམ་མཛེས་ལ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Where is the one adorned with all good qualities,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-216">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-96</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཟླ་བ་ལྟ་བུར་ཞི་བ་དང་། །སྦྱིན་དང་ཚུལ་ཁྲིམས་ལ་དགའ་བའི།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The one who is as peaceful as the moon, The one who loves giving and discipline?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-217">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-97</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།གཙོ་བོ་གང་དུ་མཐོང་བར་འགྱུར།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-97"/>“ ‘Where does the Dharma king live?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-218">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-97</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།རྒྱ་མཚོ་བཞིན་དུ་ཟབ་གྱུར་ཅིང་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Where lives the one who is as deep as the ocean,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-219">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-97</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།རི་རབ་ལྟ་བུར་མི་གཡོ་བ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The one who is as stable as Mount Sumeru,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-220">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-97</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།འཇིག་རྟེན་ཀུན་གྱི་གཙོར་གྱུར་པ། །ཆོས་ཀྱི་རྒྱལ་པོ་གང་ན་བཞུགས།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He who is chief among all beings?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-221">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-98</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།འཇིགས་ཤིང་སྐྲག་པ་རྣམས་ཀྱི་སྐྱབས། །སློང་བ་རྣམས་ནི་བགྲོད་བྱའི་མཆོག །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-98"/>“ ‘Where is he who is a refuge for the fearful? Where is the one to whom all beggars travel,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-222">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-98</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྙན་སྨྲ་སྦྱིན་དང་ཚུལ་ཁྲིམས་ལྡན། །བདག་ཉིད་ཆེ་དེ་གང་ན་བཞུགས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The one who speaks pleasantly, He who gives generously and upholds discipline?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-223">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-99</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བདག་མདུན་འཆི་བ་ཉེར་འོང་གིས། །ཤི་བི་པ་རྣམས་མྱུར་དུ་སྨྲོས།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-99"/>“ ‘Quickly, death is looming before me. Tell me, people of Śibi, where can I see him?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-224">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-99</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཐུགས་རྗེ་ཅན་དེ་མ་གཏོགས་པར།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>No one but the great compassionate one</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-225">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-99</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།གང་ལ་ལུས་ཕྱེད་སུ་ཞིག་སྟེར།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Will give me half his own body.’</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-226">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-100</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ལྟར་རྒྱལ་པོའི་ལམ་ནས་སྙིང་རྗེ་བ་དང་། དམན་པ་དང་ཞུམ་པའི་ཚིག་སྨྲ་ཞིང་རིམ་གྱིས་རྒྱལ་པོ་དཔལ་གྱི་སྡེའི་ཕོ་བྲང་སྒོར་སོང་བ་དང་། སྲོག་ཆགས་བརྒྱ་སྟོང་དུ་མ་རྣམས་ཀྱང་ངོ་མཚར་སྐྱེས་ནས་རྗེས་བཞིན་རྗེས་བཞིན་འབྲངས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-100"/>“In this manner, the old brahmin kept wailing pitifully, uttering weak and disheartened words as he made his way along the path toward the gate of King Śrīsena’s royal estate. Hundreds and thousands of astonished beings followed after him.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-227">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-100</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཡང་བར་སྐབས་དེར་ལྷ་དང་ཀླུ་དང་གནོད་སྦྱིན་དང་ལྷ་མ་ཡིན་དང་ནམ་མཁའ་ལྡིང་དང་མིའམ་ཅི་དང་ལྟོ་འཕྱེ་ཆེན་པོའི་<tei:ref folio="F.38.b"/>ཚོགས་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་ད་རྒྱལ་པོ་དཔལ་གྱི་སྡེའི་ཕྱིས་འབྱུང་བའི་རྒུད་པ་ཆེན་པོ་དེ་དང་། ལུས་ཀྱི་ཚོར་བ་དྲག་པོ་དེ་ཤེས་ནས་སྡུག་བསྔལ་དྲག་པོས་གདུངས་ཏེ་ཆོ་ངེས་འདེབས་པ་ལ་ཞུགས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>As they proceeded, crowds of gods, nāgas, yakṣas, asuras, garuḍas, kinnaras, and mahoragas, those who understood the physical damage and bodily pain King Śrīsena was about to endure, were tormented by sadness and began to lament.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-228">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-100</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཀྱི་ཧུད་རྒྱལ་པོ་དཔལ་གྱི་སྡེ་བྱམས་པའི་བདག་ཉིད་ཅན་སྙིང་རྗེ་དང་ལྡན་པ་སེམས་ཅན་ཐམས་ཅད་ལ་མཉེས་གཤིན་པ་མི་རྟག་པ་ཉིད་ཀྱི་སྟོབས་ཉེ་བར་གནས་པ་ནི་སྡུག་བསྔལ་ལོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>‘Alas,’ they cried, ‘it is painful to learn that the loving, compassionate King Śrīsena, who is peaceful and affectionate toward all sentient beings, is about to suffer and will be overpowered by impermanence.’</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-229">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-101</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ཐོས་པ་དང་སྐྱེ་བོའི་ཚོགས་རྣམས་སྨྲེ་སྔགས་འདོན་པར་གྱུར་ཏོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-101"/>“Hearing this, the throngs of people began to lament, too.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-230">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-101</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཡང་དེའི་ཚེ་འཛམ་བུའི་གླིང་ཐམས་ཅད་འཁྲུགས་ཤིང་ཀུན་དུ་འཁྲུགས་པར་གྱུར་པ་དང་། དུ་བས་མུན་པར་གྱུར་པ་ལ་སྐར་མདའ་ལྟུང་བ་དང་། ཕྱོགས་སྲེག་པ་དང་། བར་སྣང་ལ་ལྷ་རྣམས་རྔ་རྡུང་བར་ཡང་གྱུར་ཏོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>At this time, the whole of Jambudvīpa descended into turmoil and chaos spread everywhere. Smoke darkened the land, meteors fell blazing in all directions, and the celestial gods beat their drums.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-231">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-102</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཡང་དེའི་ཚེ་རི་ལ་གནས་པའི་དྲང་སྲོང་དེས་བཙུན་མོ་རྒྱལ་བའི་འོད་འདི་ལྟར་ཁྱོ་དང་བྲལ་བའི་གདུང་བས་དབུགས་ཤིན་ཏུ་རིང་པོར་འབྱིན་ཅིང་ཟས་མི་ཟ་ལ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-102"/>“While all this was happening, the brahmin who lived in the mountains, who had been offered Queen Jayaprabhā, noticed her distress at being separated from her husband.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-232">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-102</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདུ་ཤེས་མེད་པར་མཐོང་ནས་སྙིང་རྗེས་སེམས་འདར་ནས་བསམས་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He noticed that she sighed heavily, refused to eat, and gave no thought to him.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-233">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-102</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མ་ལ་ངས་རྒྱལ་པོ་དཔལ་གྱི་སྡེ་ལ་དབུལ་བར་བྱའོ་སྙམ་ནས་བཙུན་མོ་རྒྱལ་བའི་འོད་དབུགས་ཕྱུང་ངོ་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>His heart trembled with compassion for her, and he thought, ‘I should give her back to King Śrīsena.’ Queen Jayaprabhā was greatly relieved when he assured her that he would do this.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-234">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-103</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།འཛམ་བུའི་གླིང་ཐམས་ཅད་འཁྲུགས་ཤིང་ཀུན་དུ་འཁྲུགས་པར་ཡང་མཐོང་ངོ་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-103"/>“He also saw that the whole of Jambudvīpa had descended into great turmoil, and chaos had spread everywhere.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-235">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-103</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།མཐོང་ནས་ཀྱང་ཡང་བྲམ་ཟེའི་ཁྱེའུ་ལ་སྨྲས་པ། བྲམ་ཟེའི་བུ་འདི་ལྟར་འཛམ་བུའི་གླིང་འདི་ཕྱོགས་ཐམས་ཅད་དུ་བས་མུན་པར་གྱུར་ལ་འཁྲུགས་ཤིང་ཀུན་དུ་འཁྲུགས་པར་གྱུར་པ་དང་། ཉི་མ་དང་ཟླ་བ་གཉིས་ཀྱང་ལྷམ་མེ་མ་ཡིན།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Seeing this, he said to his disciple, the brahmin boy, ‘Brahmin boy, Jambudvīpa is dark with smoke in every direction; it has descended into great turmoil, and chaos has spread everywhere. Not even the sun and moon are shining, bright and steady.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-236">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-103</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལྷང་ངེ་མ་ཡིན། ལྷན་ནེ་མ་ཡིན་པས་ངེས་པར་ན་འཛམ་བུའི་གླིང་འདིར་ཡུན་མི་རིང་བ་ཉིད་དུ་སྐྱེས་བུ་ཆེན་པོ་འགའ་ཞིག་འགག་པར་འགྱུར་རོ། །དེ་ནས་དེའི་ཚེ་དྲང་སྲོང་དེས་ཚིགས་སུ་བཅད་དེ་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Surely, in a short time Jambudvīpa’s great being will cease to exist.’ Then the brahmin recited the following verses:</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-237">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-104</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མི་འམ་ཅི་ཡི་ཚོགས་དང་ནགས་ཀྱི་ལྷ་རྣམས་དང་། །ནམ་མཁར་གནས་པའི་ལྷ་རྣམས་ཀྱང་ནི་སྨོད་པར་བྱེད།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-104"/>“ ‘The kinnaras, the forest-dwelling gods, And even the celestial gods complain.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-238">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-104</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཟླ་བ་འོད་མེད་ཉི་མས་མུན་པ་སེལ་མི་བྱེད།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The moon has no light; the sun cannot dispel the darkness.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-239">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-104</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་རིང་རོལ་མོ་བརྡུངས་ན་སྒྲ་ནི་གྲག་མ་གྱུར།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Not even musical instruments make a sound today.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-240">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-105</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཤིང་ཚོགས་མེ་ཏོག་འབྲས་བུར་ལྡན་པ་འདི་དག་ཀྱང་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-105"/>“ ‘Trees with fruit and flowers are falling,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-241">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-105</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།རླུང་གིས་བསྐྱོད་པ་བཞིན་དུ་ས་ལ་ལྷུང་གྱུར་ལ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>As if blown over by the wind.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-242">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-105</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཇི་ལྟར་འཇིགས་ཤིང་རྩུབ་པའི་སྒྲ་ཀུན་གྲག་པས་ན།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Given that everyone has heard the fearsome and awful sounds,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-243">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-105</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།གྲོང་ཁྱེར་དག་ཏུ་སྡུག་བསྔལ་མི་བཟད་འབྱུང་བར་གསལ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>It is clear that the city will experience unbearable sorrow.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-244">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-106</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།<tei:ref folio="F.39.a"/>གྲོང་ཁྱེར་ཨ་རིཥྛ་ན་གནས་དགའི་སྐྱེ་བོ་འདི་ཀུན་ཤིན་ཏུ་སྡུག་བསྔལ་ཞིང་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-106"/>“ ‘All the residents in the delightful city Ariṣṭa are suffering.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-245">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-106</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཕན་ཚུན་སོ་སོར་མྱ་ངན་ཟུག་རྔུས་ངེས་བཅོམ་སྒྲ་རྣམས་རབ་ཏུ་གྲོལ་བའི་བཞིན།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Expressing grief and pain among themselves, They say, “We are definitely defeated.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-246">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-106</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ལྷ་མོ་ལྟ་བུའི་བཞིན་ལྡན་བུད་མེད་འདི་དག་ཁང་པའི་མཆོག་ན་སྨྲེ་སྔགས་འདོན།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Young women with faces like goddesses wail on rooftops.<tei:note xml:id="UT22084-076-003-108"/>
                </seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-247">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-109</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།འདི་ན་མི་དག་དྲག་པོས་རབ་ཏུ་ངུ་དང་དེར་ནི་དུར་ཁྲོད་འཇིགས་བཞིན་ནོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-109"/>“ ‘The people weep profusely as if they were in a terrifying cemetery.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-248">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-109</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ནམ་མཁར་གནས་པའི་སྤྲིན་འདི་ཆུ་མེད་པར་སྒྲ་སྒྲོགས།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>These clouds hanging in the sky thunder but do not rain.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-249">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-109</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ས་ལ་གནས་པའི་ཆུ་རྣམས་ཀྱང་ནི་སྐམས་པར་གྱུར།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Even the waterholes resting in the earth are drying up.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-250">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-109</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།རྨ་བྱ་རྣམས་ཀྱང་ནགས་ཀྱིས་བཅོམ་བཞིན་སྒྲ་བསྒྲགས་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Peacocks scream as if the forest were crushing them.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-251">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-110</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།མི་རྣམས་ཀྱང་ནི་འཁྲུག་བཅས་ཁྱིམ་དུ་རྣམ་པར་རྒྱུ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-110"/>“ ‘People rush between their homes in turmoil.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-252">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-110</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཆུ་ལ་རླུང་གིས་བསྐྱོད་པའི་གྲུ་བཞིན་ས་རྣམས་གཡོས།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Their lands shake as if they were a ship at sea, battered by winds.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-253">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-110</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཕྱག་དར་དང་འདྲེས་རླུང་ནི་མཁའ་ལ་རབ་ཏུ་ལྡིང་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Gales blast piles of garbage and dust into the air.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-254">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-110</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཨ་རིཥྛ་ན་འཇིགས་སྐྱེད་མཚན་མ་མང་བས་ནི།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>There are many signs of demise in Ariṣṭa.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-255">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-111</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།བྲམ་ཟེ་ཁྱེའུ་འདི་ལས་ཀྱི་རྗེས་འཐུན་ཡུལ་དུ་དེང་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-111"/>“ ‘Brahmin boy, today in this land with which you have a karmic connection,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-256">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-111</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།བཀྲ་མི་ཤིས་པའི་མཚན་མ་ནི། །ད་ལྟ་འདི་ན་རྣམ་མང་སྟེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>There are many inauspicious signs.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-257">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-111</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་བས་བདག་ཅག་ཤིས་པ་ཡི།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>It is only reasonable that we set off</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-258">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-111</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཕྱོགས་སུ་འགྲོ་བ་ཤིན་ཏུ་རིགས།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Toward a place that is auspicious.’</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-259">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-113</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།བྲམ་ཟེའི་ཁྱེའུ་རྣམས་གཞན་ཡང་ཇི་ལྟར་ཤིང་འདི་དག་ཐམས་ཅད་རྒྱལ་པོའི་ཕོ་བྲང་ཨ་རིཥྛ་ག་ལ་བ་དེར་འདུད་པར་གྱུར་ཏེ། དེ་བས་ན་ཀྱེ་མ་བྲམ་ཟེའི་ཁྱེའུ་རྣམས་ངེས་པར་དེ་རིང་ཉིད་རྒྱལ་པོའི་ཕོ་བྲང་ཨ་རིཥྛར་ཉེ་བར་འཚེ་བ་དང་གནོད་པའི་འཇིགས་པ་ཆེན་པོ་འབྱུང་བར་འགྱུར་རོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-113"/>“ ‘Alas, brahmin boys,’ the sage continued, ‘just as these trees are being blown in the direction of the Ariṣṭa royal estate, so it is certain, brahmin boys, that there will long be tremendous fear of harm and destruction in Ariṣṭa.’</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-260">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-114</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ནས་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སྟེང་གི་ཁང་བཟངས་ཀྱི་གཞི་ལ་གནས་པས་སྐྱེ་བོའི་ཚོགས་ཆེན་པོའི་ཆོ་ངེའི་སྒྲ་ཐོས་པ་དང་། རིངས་པ་རིངས་པར་རིན་པོ་ཆེ་ལས་བྱས་པའི་ཁང་བཟངས་ལས་བབས་ནས་སེང་གེའི་ཁྲི་ཆེན་པོ་ལ་འདུག་སྟེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-114"/>“At the same time, in Ariṣṭa, the bodhisattva was seated on the top floor of his mansion. Hearing a large crowd of people lamenting below, he came down from his mansion made of precious stones and sat on his large lion throne.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-261">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-114</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཤིན་ཏུ་རྟབས་བག་གིས་ཤེས་ལྡན་དག་འདི་ཅི་ཡིན་འདི་ཅི་ཡིན་ཞེས་དྲིས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Urgently he asked, ‘Wise ones, what is it? What is happening?’</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-262">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-115</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།བར་སྐབས་དེར་ལྷའི་དབང་པོ་བརྒྱ་བྱིན་ལྷའི་བུ་བཞི་པོ་དེ་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་འཕྲལ་དུ་རྒྱལ་པོའི་ཁབ་ཏུ་ཁྱེར་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-115"/>“The four gods carried Śakra, lord of the gods, into the king’s court on his stretcher, and then placed the stretcher on the floor.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-263">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-115</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མོད་ལ་ཁྲི་སའི་སྟེང་དུ་བཞག་པ་དང་། ཁྲི་ལ་བསྐྱོན་པ་ལུས་ཀྱི་ཕྱེད་བཅད་པ་དེ་ལས་ཁྲག་ཀུན་ནས་འཛག་ཅིང་རབ་ཏུ་འཛག་པ་དང་། ལག་པ་གཡས་པ་བརྐྱང་སྟེ་སྙིང་རྗེ་རྗེ་སྐད་དུ་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་ལ་རྒྱལ་བ་དང་ཚེ་སྤེལ་བ་བྱས་ནས་མཆི་མས་ཁེངས་པའི་མིག་དང་། རང་གི་ལུས་ཀྱི་ཕྱེད་ཉེ་བར་སྟོན་ཅིང་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་ལ་སྨྲས་པ། <tei:ref folio="F.39.b"/>འཇིག་རྟེན་ན་ཁྱོད་སྙིང་རྗེ་ཅན།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Blood dripped from his bisected body, but he still extended his right hand and in a pitiable voice called out salutations of victory and long life to the bodhisattva. As his eyes filled with tears, he displayed his bisected body to the bodhisattva, and implored him, ‘You are this world’s compassionate one.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-264">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-115</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།གཞན་གྱི་སྡུག་བསྔལ་གྱིས་སྡུག་བསྔལ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>You suffer the pains of others. Lord, protect me.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-265">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-115</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཉིད་ཀྱི་སྐུ་ཡི་ཕྱེད་སྩལ་བས། །གཙོ་བོ་བདག་ནི་བསྐྱབ་ཏུ་གསོལ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Give me half your body.’</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-266">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-116</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་སྐད་ཅེས་ཐོས་པ་དང་། བློན་པོ་ཆེན་པོའི་མཆོག་བློ་གྲོས་ཆེན་པོས་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-116"/>“Hearing this request, Mahāmati, supreme among ministers, said, ‘Lord, this person is not human.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-267">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-116</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལྷ་འདི་མི་མ་ལགས་ཀྱི་ཤ་ཟའམ་ཤ་ཟས་བྱིན་གྱིས་བརླབས་པར་གྱུར་པ་ཞིག་སྟེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He must be a demon or someone possessed by demons.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-268">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-116</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མི་ནི་རྐེད་པར་བཅད་པ་འཚོ་ཞིང་སྔོན་ཇི་ལྟར་གནས་པ་བཞིན་ཚིག་ཏུ་སྨྲ་བ་ནི་མི་སྲིད་དོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>A human would not survive being sliced in half at the waist. It is impossible and unheard of.’</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-269">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-117</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་སྐད་ཅེས་སྨྲས་པ་དང་། ལྷའི་དབང་པོ་བརྒྱ་བྱིན་གྱིས་སྨྲས་པ། ཤི་བི་པ་ཁྱེད་ཅག་རྣམས་མ་འཇིགས་ཤིག །ང་ནི་ཤ་ཟ་མ་ཡིན་གྱི་གཞན་དུ་ན་ང་ནི་བྲམ་ཟེ་ཡིན་མོད་ཀྱི།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-117"/>“To this, Śakra, lord of the gods, responded, ‘People of Śibi, you need not be afraid. I am not a demon.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-270">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-117</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དབུལ་བས་བདག་གིས་བུ་དང་ཆུང་མ་བཞག་སྟེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>On the contrary, I am a brahmin.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-271">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-117</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ནོར་གྱི་བསམ་པས་རྒྱལ་པོ་དཔལ་གྱི་སྡེའི་ཐད་དུ་ཆས་ནས་རིམ་གྱིས་སོང་བ་ན་རྒྱལ་པོའི་ཕོ་བྲང་འདིར་ཉི་མ་ནུབ་པ་ན་ཕྱིན་པ་དང་གྲོང་ཁྱེར་གྱི་སྒོ་རྣམས་བཅད་པར་གྱུར་ཏོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>I left my wife and children because we were poor and, intent on creating wealth, I traveled in King Śrīsena’s direction.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-272">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-117</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ནས་གྲོང་ཁྱེར་དང་ཧ་ཅང་མི་རིང་བ་ན་བསོད་ནམས་ཁང་ཡོད་པར་བདག་སོང་སྟེ། ནུབ་མོ་གནས་པ་ན་ལམ་གྱིས་དུབ་པས་གཉིད་མཐུག་པོས་ནོན་པ་དང་། སྔོན་གྱི་ལས་ཀྱི་ཉེས་པས་ནུབ་མོ་གཅན་གཟན་སྟག་འོངས་ནས་བདག་གི་ལུས་ཀྱི་ཕྱེད་སོག་ལེ་ལྟ་བུའི་མཆེ་བ་ཤིན་ཏུ་རྣོན་པོས་བཅད་ནས་ཁྱེར་ཏེ་སོང་ངོ་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>I came to the royal estate slowly, and by the time I arrived the sun had set, and the city’s gates were closed. I stayed at a manor not far from the city.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-273">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-117</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེར་བདག་ཚོར་བ་དྲག་པོས་ཀུན་དུ་བཅོམ་པས་གཉིད་སད་པ་དང་། ཇི་ཙམ་ན་བདག་གི་ལུས་ཀྱི་རོ་སྨད་ཕྱེད་པོ་སྟག་གིས་སོག་ལེས་དྲས་པ་ལྟར་བཅད་པས་བདག་ཚོར་བ་དྲག་པོས་ཀུན་དུ་བཅོམ་ཡང་སྔོན་བྱས་པའི་མི་དགེ་བའི་ལས་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་ཀུན་དུ་བཟུང་བས་ཤི་བར་ནི་མ་གྱུར་གྱི།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>While I was there, I was overcome by the weariness of traveling and fell into a deep sleep. Because of my previous negative deeds, during the night a tiger came along and used its sharp, saw-like teeth to cut my body in half and steal away the lower half.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-274">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-117</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཅིག་ཏུ་སྡུག་བསྔལ་བ་དང་། གཅིག་ཏུ་དྲག་པ་དང་། གཅིག་ཏུ་རྩུབ་པ་དང་། གཅིག་ཏུ་ཚ་བ་དང་། གཅིག་ཏུ་ཡིད་དུ་མི་འོང་བའི་ཚོར་བ་རྣམས་མྱོང་ཞིང་ཉམ་ཐག་པའི་ང་རོས་སྨྲེ་བར་གྱུར་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>When I awoke, I experienced an extreme sensation. The tiger may have used its saw-like teeth to cut my body in half, but because I recognized this was caused by my previous actions, I did not die. Still, my suffering was incomparable. It was incomparably violent. It was incomparably harsh. It was incomparably intense. It was an incomparably overwhelming pain, and how I screamed in my misery!</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-275">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-118</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བདག་དེ་ལྟར་ཉམ་ཐག་པའི་སྨྲེ་སྔགས་ཐོས་པ་དང་ནམ་མཁའི་དཀྱིལ་ན་གནས་པའི་ལྷ་གཞན་དག་གིས་བདག་དབུགས་དབྱུང་བའི་ཕྱིར་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-118"/>“ ‘When the celestial gods overheard my cries, they consoled me. A goddess said:</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-276">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-118</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མ་འཇིགས་མ་འཇིགས་བྲམ་ཟེའི་མཆོག །ཁྱོད་ནི་ཚེ་ནི་རིང་བར་མཐོང་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“ ‘ “Be not afraid, best of brahmins, be not afraid. We foresee a long life for you.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-277">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-118</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཨ་རིཥྛར་ནི་མྱུར་སོང་ན།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Once you have swiftly traveled to Ariṣṭa,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-278">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-118</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཁྱོད་ནི་ལེགས་པ་དག་ཏུ་འགྱུར།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>You will be fine.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-279">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-120</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ན་ཀུན་སྟེར་རྒྱལ་པོ་ནི།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-120"/>“ ‘ “A king lives there who grants everything.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-280">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-120</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དཔལ་གྱི་སྡེ་ཞེས་རྣམ་གྲགས་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He is known as Śrīsena.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-281">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-120</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།<tei:ref folio="F.40.a"/>དེ་ཡི་ལུས་ཀྱི་ཕྱེད་བསླངས་ན།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>If you beg him for half his body,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-282">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-120</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ནི་ངེས་པར་ཁྱེར་ལ་སྟེར།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He will certainly give it to you.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-283">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-121</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཞེས་སྨྲས་ནས་ལྷ་མོ་དེ་དེ་ཉིད་དུ་མི་སྣང་བར་གྱུར་ཏོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-121"/>“ ‘Having said this, the goddess disappeared.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-284">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-121</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ནས་བདག་གིས་ལྷ་མོའི་ཚིག་ཐོས་པ་དང་། འཚོ་བར་རེ་བ་ཀུན་དུ་སྐྱེས་ཏེ། འཚེ་བ་ཡང་ཆུང་བར་གྱུར་ཏོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>As I heard these words from the goddess, my hope of survival grew, and the pain subsided.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-285">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-121</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ན་བདག་གི་ལུས་ཀྱི་ཕྱེད་རོ་སྨད་མེད་པས་ལངས་ཡང་མ་ནུས་ན་འགྲོ་བར་ལྟ་ག་ལ་ནུས་སྙམ་ནས་ཡང་ཡི་མུག་པར་གྱུར་པ་དང་། སྟེས་དབང་གིས་ཉི་མ་ཤར་བའི་ཚེ་གཉེན་འདི་བཞི་འོངས་པར་གྱུར་ཏོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Then I became dejected again as I realized I could not get up, let alone walk, with only half of my body. Coincidentally, at dawn, my four kin arrived.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-286">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-121</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།འདི་དག་གིས་ཀྱང་བདག་ཉམ་ང་བར་ཞུགས་པ་མཐོང་བ་དང་། འདི་འཆི་བ་ཉིད་དོ་སྙམ་ནས་ངུ་བར་གྱུར་ཏོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They started to cry when they saw my desperate state and thought I would die.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-287">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-121</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ནས་བདག་གིས་དེ་རྣམས་ལ་དབུགས་དབྱུང་བའི་ཕྱིར་ལྷ་མོའི་ཚིག་རྒྱས་པར་སྨྲས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>To console them, I told them in detail about the goddess’s words.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-288">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-121</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ནས་བདག་འདི་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་ཁྲི་ལ་བསྐྱོན་ཏེ་འདིར་ཁྱེར་ཏེ་འོངས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They placed me on this stretcher and carried me here.’</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-289">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-122</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་སྐད་ཅེས་སྨྲས་ནས་ལྷའི་དབང་པོ་བརྒྱ་བྱིན་གདོང་མཆི་མའི་རླབས་ཀྱིས་གང་བ་ལྟ་བུར་བདག་ཉིད་ཉེ་བར་སྟོན་ཅིང་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་ལ་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-122"/>“Having spoken these words, the face of Śakra, lord of the gods, was awash with waves of tears. He then said to the bodhisattva:</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-290">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-122</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྒྱལ་པོ་ཆེན་པོ། བདག་ནི་དབུལ་ཞིང་ན་བ་དང་། །རྒན་པ་དང་ནི་བྲམ་ཟེ་ཉིད།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“ ‘Great King, I am poor and sick. I am also an old man and a brahmin.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-291">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-122</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།རང་གི་སྐུ་ཕྱེད་སྩལ་བ་ཡིས།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Please give me half your body,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-292">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-122</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།རྙེད་དཀའི་སྲོག་ནི་སྩལ་དུ་གསོལ། །བདག་གི་སྲོག་ནི་སྒྲུབ་བྱེད་པའི།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>To grant me this life so difficult to find.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-293">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-124</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།སྦྱིན་པ་ཐུགས་རྗེས་སྩལ་དུ་གསོལ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-124"/>“ ‘Please compassionately grant me</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-294">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-124</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དོན་གྱི་མཆོག་ཕྱིར་སྦྱིན་པ་ནི།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The gift of preserving my life.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-295">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-124</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།སྐུ་ཕྱེད་སྦྱིན་པར་སྩལ་དུ་གསོལ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Please give me half your body, Such a gift being the highest of aims.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-296">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-125</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཉིད་ཀྱི་སྐུ་ཡི་ཕྱེད་སྩལ་བས།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-125"/>“ ‘By giving me half of your body</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-297">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-125</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།བསོད་ནམས་རྒྱ་མཚོ་ལྟར་རྒྱ་ཆེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The merit accrued will be as vast as the ocean.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-298">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-125</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་བཞིན་མཁའ་ལྟར་མཐའ་མེད་པའི། །བསོད་ནམས་ཁྱོད་ཀྱིས་ཐོབ་པར་འགྱུར།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Similarly, the merit you will gain Will be as limitless as space.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-299">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-126</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།བདག་གི་ཚོར་བ་དྲག་པོ་དང་། །བཀྲེས་སྐོམ་མི་བཟད་ལ་གཟིགས་ནས།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-126"/>“ ‘Having seen my excruciating pain And my unbearable hunger and thirst,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-300">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-126</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།མཆོག་ཏུ་ཐུགས་རྗེ་མཛད་ནས་ནི།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Exercise supreme compassion</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-301">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-126</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།སྐུ་ཡི་ཕྱེད་ནི་བདག་ལ་སྩོལ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>And give me half your body!</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-302">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-127</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་དགེ་ཁྱོད་ཆོས་ལ་གནས།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-127"/>“ ‘Virtuous bodhisattva, you abide by the Dharma.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-303">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-127</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།གལ་ཏེ་ཐམས་ཅད་མཁྱེན་ཉིད་མཉམ་བཞེད་ན།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>If you claim to become the equal of an omniscient one,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-304">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-127</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།བདག་ལ་སྐུ་ཕྱེད་འདིར་སྩོལ་དེ་རིང་ནི།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Then please give me half your body today.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-305">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-127</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཤིན་ཏུ་རྙེད་དཀའི་སྲོག་ནི་ཐོབ་པར་མཛོད།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Let me keep this life so difficult to find.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-306">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-128</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།རྒྱལ་པོ་ཆེན་པོའི་སྐུ་ཡི་ཕྱེད།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-128"/>“ ‘Great King, give to me half of your body,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-307">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-128</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཤིན་ཏུ་གཏང་དཀའ་བདག་སྩོལ་ལ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Which is so difficult to give;</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-308">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-128</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཆོས་དང་དེ་བཞིན་གྲགས་པ་ཡིས།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>If you do, the Dharma, and likewise your fame,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-309">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-128</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།འགྲོ་བ་ཀུན་ལ་ཁྱབ་པར་མཛོད།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Will spread throughout the entire world.’</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-310">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-129</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ནས་ཚིག་འདི་ཐོས་པ་དང་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སྔོན་གོམས་པའི་དགེ་བའི་རྩ་བའི་བག་ཆགས་བློ་ལ་བསྒོས་པས་སྙིང་<tei:ref folio="F.40.b"/>རྗེས་སེམས་འདར་ཞིང་སློང་བ་དེ་དབུགས་དབྱུང་བའི་ཕྱིར་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-129"/>“Upon hearing these words, the bodhisattva’s past habits of virtue and his stores of positive predispositions infused his mind, causing him to shake with compassion.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-311">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-129</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྲམ་ཟེ་ཆེན་པོ་མ་འཇིགས་ཤིག །ད་རིང་པོ་མི་ཐོགས་པར་ལུས་འདི་རྫོགས་པར་འགྱུར་བ་དང་། ཡིད་ལ་རེ་བ་ཡོངས་སུ་རྫོགས་པར་འགྱུར་གྱིས།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>‘Great brahmin,’ he consoled him, ‘do not be afraid. Your body will soon be whole. Your wishes will be fulfilled.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-312">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-129</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཡོ་མེད་པའི་སེམས་ཀྱིས་ཁྱོད་ལ་ལུས་ཀྱི་ཕྱེད་སྦྱིན་པར་བྱའོ་ཞེས་སྨྲས་ནས་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཡིད་རབ་ཏུ་དགའ་བ་དང་ཚིགས་སུ་བཅད་དེ་སྨྲས་པ། ཀྱེ་མ་རང་གི་ལུས་སློང་བ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>With an unwavering mind, I offer you half my body.’ His heart filled with joy, the bodhisattva then spoke the following verses:</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-313">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-130</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཡུན་མི་རིང་བར་བལྟ་བར་བྱ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-130"/>“ ‘O, soon you will see me</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-314">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-130</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ང་ཡི་ཡན་ལག་གཏང་བ་ནི།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Give away my body.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-315">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-130</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དཀའ་བར་འགྱུར་བ་མ་ཡིན་ནོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>It will not be very difficult To give away my limbs.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-316">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-131</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཇི་ལྟར་ཡབ་ཀྱི་བུ་གཅིག་ང་ཡིན་ཡང་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-131"/>“ ‘Although I am my father’s only son,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-317">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-131</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ལྟ་ན་ཡང་ང་ཡི་ལུས་འདི་ཁྱེར།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>You can take my body.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-318">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-131</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ལུས་ནི་བྱིན་པས་བྱང་ཆུབ་རྙེད་གྱུར་ཅིང་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Offering my body will result in great awakening.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-319">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-132</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།འགྲོ་འདི་ཤིན་ཏུ་སྡུག་བསྔལ་ལས་གྲོལ་ཤོག །དེ་ནས་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔས་བརྒྱ་བྱིན་བྲམ་ཟེའི་ཆ་བྱད་འཛིན་པ་རྣམ་པ་འདི་ལྟ་བུའི་ཚིག་སྨྲ་བ་ཐོས་པ་དང་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>May it alleviate the intense suffering of all beings.’<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-132"/> “The bodhisattva had heard Śakra’s words, which he had spoken in the form of a brahmin.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-320">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-133</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡིད་རབ་ཏུ་མགུ་ཞིང་དགའ་བས་མིག་གདངས་བཞིན་དུ་བྲམ་ཟེ་དེ་ལ་སྨྲས་པ། བྲམ་ཟེ་ལུས་འདིའི་ཕྱེད་ལེགས་པར་བྱིན་གྱིས་བར་ཆད་མེད་པར་ལེགས་པར་ལོང་ཤིག་ཅེས་སྨྲས་ནས་འཁོར་དེ་དག་ཐམས་ཅད་ལ་བལྟས་ཏེ་སྐྱེས་བུ་གཞན་ཞིག་ལ་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Therefore, with an entirely satisfied mind and his eyes open, he said, ‘Brahmin, I will give you half my body. Take it without any qualms.’<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-133"/> “Looking around, he saw his attendants and said to one of them, ‘O, you, go quickly and bring me an exceedingly sharp saw.’</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-321">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-134</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཀྱེ་སྐྱེས་བུ་ཁྱོད་རིངས་པར་སོང་ལ་སོག་ལེ་ཤིན་ཏུ་རྣོ་བ་ཁྱེར་ལ་ཤོག་ཤིག །དེ་ནས་སྐྱེས་བུ་དེ་བརྒྱ་བྱིན་གྱིས་ཀུན་ཏུ་རྨོངས་པར་བྱས་པས་ཤིན་ཏུ་རིངས་པ་རིངས་པར་སོག་ལེ་ཉེ་བར་ཁྱེར་ཏེ་འོངས་ནས་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-134"/>“As he had been enchanted by Śakra, the attendant quickly found a saw and brought it to the bodhisattva.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-322">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-134</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལྷ་སོག་ལེ་འཚལ་ཏེ་མཆིས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>‘Lord,’ he said, ‘here is a saw.’</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-323">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-134</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ནས་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔས་རིངས་པ་རིངས་པར་བློན་པོ་ལ་སྨྲས་པ། ཁྱེད་ཅག་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་ཇི་སྲིད་དུ་བྲམ་ཟེ་འདི་འཆི་བདག་གིས་འཇིག་རྟེན་ཕ་རོལ་དུ་མ་ཁྱེར་བ་དེ་སྲིད་དུ་ངའི་རོ་སྨད་སོག་ལེས་མྱུར་དུ་ཆོད་ཅིག་དང་། ངས་བྲམ་ཟེ་འདི་ལ་སྦྱིན་པ་བྱའོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Promptly, the bodhisattva said to his ministers, ‘Quickly cut off my lower body and give it to the brahmin, before the Lord of Death takes him to the other world. I offer it to the brahmin.’</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-324">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-136</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ནས་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་མཆོག་ཏུ་མི་བཟད་པའི་ཚིག་སྨྲས་པ་ཐོས་པས་རྡོ་རྗེ་ལྷུང་བས་ཀུན་དུ་སྐྲག་པ་བཞིན་དུ་གྲོང་ཁྱེར་ན་གནས་པའི་སྐྱེ་བོའི་ཚོགས་ཐམས་ཅད་ཤིན་ཏུ་ཡི་མུག་པར་གྱུར་ཏེ། སྡུག་བསྔལ་ལོ། །སྡུག་བསྔལ་ལོ་ཞེས་གསང་མཐོན་པོས་ངུ་བར་གྱུར་ཏོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-136"/>“The sound of the bodhisattva’s utterly horrifying words created panic in the city as if they were lightning strikes.<tei:note xml:id="UT22084-076-003-137"/> ‘Oh, the sorrow, the sorrow!’ the people cried in secret and from on high.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-325">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-136</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ནས་བློན་པོ་ཆེན་པོ་བློ་གྲོས་ཆེན་པོ་ཟུག་རྔུས་གནད་དུ་བསྣུན་པ་བཞིན་དུ་སྡུག་བསྔལ་དྲག་པོས་ཉམ་ཐག་སྟེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Then Mahāmati, the great minister, was wretched with intense pain, as if a vital organ had been pierced, and his face was as wet from crying as from the rain.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-326">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-136</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཉིད་ཀྱི་སྐུ་ལ་ཆགས་པ་མེད་པར་ཡོངས་སུ་གཏོང་ངོ་སྙམ་བསམས་ནས་གདོང་<tei:ref folio="F.41.a"/>ལ་མཆི་མ་ཆར་ལྟར་བབ་པ་དང་། རྐང་པ་གཉིས་ལ་བཏུད་དེ་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་བཟློག་པའི་ཕྱིར་སྨྲས་པ། ལྷ་འདི་མི་སྲིད་དེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He feared the bodhisattva would give away his body without any attachment to it, and seeking to change his mind, he bowed down at his feet and said, ‘Lord, this is not possible.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-327">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-136</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདི་ལྟ་སྟེ་ལུས་སོག་ལེས་བཅད་ནས་བཅད་པའི་ལུས་ནི་ངེས་པར་འཆི་བར་འགྱུར་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>If your body is cut by a saw, you will certainly die.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-328">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-136</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཆི་ན་ལས་སུ་མི་རུང་བའི་རོར་གྱུར་ལ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>If you die, you will become a useless corpse.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-329">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-136</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལས་སུ་མི་རུང་བས་ནི་བྲམ་ཟེ་ལ་ཡང་བྱས་པ་དོན་མ་མཆིས་པར་འགྱུར་རོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>A useless corpse is no good to this brahmin. Giving your life to him is pointless.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-330">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-136</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།གང་གཞན་གྱི་ཡན་ལག་བཅད་པ་གཞན་གྱི་ཡན་ལག་ལ་འབྱོར་བར་འགྱུར་བ་འདི་ཡང་གནས་མ་མཆིས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Cutting one person’s limb off and attaching it to another does not work.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-331">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-136</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ལྟ་ན་ནི་ལྷའི་ངལ་བ་ཡང་དོན་མ་མཆིས་པར་འགྱུར་རོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Your divine efforts will be in vain.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-332">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-136</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་བས་ན་བཟོད་པར་མཛོད་ལ་བདག་ཉིད་དོན་མ་མཆིས་པར་གསོད་པར་མི་མཛད་ཅིང་ཉིད་ཀྱི་སྲོག་ཡོངས་སུ་མི་གཏོང་བར་གསོལ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Please, be patient. Do not kill yourself in vain. Do not give up your life.’</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-333">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-138</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ནས་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔས་བློན་པོ་ཆེན་པོ་བློ་གྲོས་ཆེན་པོ་དབུགས་དབྱུང་བའི་ཕྱིར་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-138"/>“Consoling the great minister Mahāmati, the bodhisattva replied, ‘Mahāmati, leave it be, leave it be.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-334">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-138</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བློ་གྲོས་ཆེན་པོ་ཞོག་ཞོག །ངས་ནམ་ཞིག་བླ་ན་མེད་པ་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་བྱང་ཆུབ་ཐོབ་ནས་འཁོར་བར་རྒྱུ་བའི་སེམས་ཅན་བསྒྲལ་བར་བྱའོ་ཞེས་ཡིད་ལ་རེ་བ་འདི་ལ་ངའི་བྱང་ཆུབ་ཀྱི་བར་ཆད་མ་བྱེད་ཅིག །བུ་དག་གཞན་ཡང་ཤིན་ཏུ་ཡུན་རིང་པོར་སྡུག་པ་དང་ཡང་དག་པར་འདུས་པར་གྱུར་པ་ཡང་ངེས་པར་འབྲལ་བའི་མཐའ་ཅན་དུ་འགྱུར་བ་འདི་ནི་འཇིག་རྟེན་གྱི་རང་བཞིན་ཡིན་ནོ་ཞེས་སྨྲས་ནས་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔས་སོག་ལེ་ལ་བལྟས་ཏེ། སོག་ལེ་འདིས་ངའི་བླ་ན་མེད་པ་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་བྱང་ཆུབ་ཀྱི་ཚོགས་ཀྱི་ཕྱོགས་གཅིག་ཏུ་འགྱུར་རོ་ཞེས་རྗེས་སུ་སེམས་ཤིང་ཡང་བློན་པོ་ལ་སྨྲས་པ། ཇི་སྲིད་དུ་བྲམ་ཟེ་འདི་སྲོག་དང་བྲལ་བར་མ་གྱུར་གྱི་བར་དུ་ཁྱོད་ཀྱིས་ངའི་ལུས་ཀྱི་ཕྱེད་རོ་སྨད་མྱུར་དུ་ཆོད་ཅིག །བྲམ་ཟེ་འདི་ཤི་ན་ངའི་བསམ་པ་འབྲས་བུ་མེད་པར་འགྱུར་རོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>At some point, I hope to attain unsurpassed, perfect awakening and liberate saṃsāra’s beings. Do not hinder my awakening. It is the nature of our existence that we must all separate, even from those who have been very dear to us for a long time, like our children.’ Having said this, he glanced once again at the saw and said, ‘This saw is an incomparable object that will direct my merit toward unsurpassed and perfect awakening.’ This is how he thought of it, and again he said to his minister, ‘Cut off the lower half of my body as soon as you can, before the brahmin dies. Otherwise, my intent will be fruitless.’</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-335">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-139</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ལྟར་བློན་པོ་ཆེན་པོ་བློ་གྲོས་ཆེན་པོས་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའི་དེ་ལྟ་བུའི་རང་གི་ལུས་ཡོངས་སུ་གཏོང་བའི་བསམ་པ་ཤེས་ནས་དེ་མཆི་མ་ཆར་བཞིན་དུ་བབ་པའི་གདོང་དང་། བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའི་རྐང་པ་ནས་བཟུང་སྟེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-139"/>“Mahāmati, the great minister, knew then that the bodhisattva was determined to give away his body. He held the bodhisattva’s feet in both his hands and kissed them.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-336">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-139</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གདོང་གི་མཆུས་འོ་བྱས་ནས་སྙིང་རྗེ་རྗེ་སྐད་དུ་སྨྲེ་སྔགས་འདོན་པར་གྱུར་ཏེ། ཀྱི་ཧུད་ཇི་ལྟར་ན་འཛམ་བུའི་གླིང་ཡོངས་སུ་སྐྱོང་བ་མཛད་པ། སྙིང་རྗེ་ཆེ་བ། ཡོན་ཏན་དུ་མ་དང་ལྡན་པ། སེམས་ཅན་ཐམས་ཅད་ལ་མཉེས་གཤིན་པའི་ལྷ་ལ་དེ་རིང་ཉིད་དུ་མི་<tei:ref folio="F.41.b"/>རྟག་པ་ཉིད་ཀྱི་སྟོབས་ཉེ་བར་གནས་པར་གྱུར།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>As tears flowed down his face like rain, he despaired and, overwhelmed with compassion, said to the bodhisattva, ‘Alas, the force of impermanence will strike the lord today. The lord takes care of all of Jambudvīpa, he is the compassionate one, he has innumerable qualities, and he pleases and is affectionate to all sentient beings.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-337">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-139</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཀྱེ་མའོ་མི་རྟག་པ་ཉིད་ཀྱི་སྟོབས་དང་ལྡན་པའོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>But, alas, impermanence is powerful!</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-338">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-140</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།གང་འཇིག་རྟེན་དུ་ལྷ་ཡང་མཐོང་བའི་སྐྱེས་བུ་དེ་རྣམས་ནི་སྐལ་བ་ཅན་ཡིན་ནོ་ཞེས་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའི་གདོང་ལ་ཤིན་ཏུ་ཡུན་རིང་དུ་མིག་མི་འཛུམས་པར་བལྟས་ནས་ལྷའི་མི་རྟག་པ་ཉིད་ལ་བལྟ་མི་ནུས་སོ་ཞེས་བསམས་ནས་སྐད་ཅིག་དེ་ཉིད་ལ་མིག་བཙུམས་ནས་བརྒྱལ་ནས་སའི་སྟེང་དུ་འགྱེལ་བར་གྱུར་ཏོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Whoever has seen the lord was fortunate.’<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-140"/> “Having spoken, he stared at the bodhisattva’s face for a long time without blinking. Then, as he contemplated how he could not bear to witness the bodhisattva’s death, his eyes closed and he fell to the ground unconscious.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-339">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-140</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ནས་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔས་སྐྱེས་བུ་ཤིང་མཁན་གཞན་གཉིས་ཤིག་ལ་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The bodhisattva then spoke to two carpenters who happened to be present:</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-340">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-140</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཞིན་བཟངས་དག་འདིར་ངའི་སྦྱིན་པའི་ཕ་རོལ་ཏུ་ཕྱིན་པ་ཡོངས་སུ་རྫོགས་པའི་གྲོགས་བྱ་བའི་ཕྱིར་ཁྱེད་ཅག་གཉིས་ཀྱིས་སོག་ལེ་ཐོགས་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>‘Good people,<tei:note xml:id="UT22084-076-003-141"/> will you help me complete the perfection of generosity?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-341">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-140</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ངའི་ལུས་ཀྱི་ཕྱད་རོ་སྨད་མྱུར་དུ་ཆོད་ཅིག །བྲམ་ཟེའི་ཡིད་ལ་རེ་བ་ཡོངས་སུ་རྫོགས་པར་བྱའོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Will you take this saw and quickly cut off the lower half of my body? Let us fulfill the brahmin’s wish.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-342">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-140</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ངའི་བྱང་ཆུབ་རྙེད་པའི་ཡིད་ལ་རེ་བ་ཡོངས་སུ་རྫོགས་པར་འགྱུར་རོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Let us fulfill my wish to attain awakening.’</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-343">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-142</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ནས་ཤིང་མཁན་དེ་གཉིས་ཡུལ་རྨུས་པ་ལྟ་བུའི་མཆི་མའི་གདོང་ཅན་གྱིས་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའི་རྐང་པ་ལ་གཏུགས་ཏེ་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-142"/>“Tears of immense sadness covered the two carpenters’ faces like stormy weather. They touched the bodhisattva’s feet and said,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-344">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-142</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལྷ་འདི་སྐད་གསུང་བ་ནི་རིགས་པ་མ་ལགས་ཏེ། དེ་ཅིའི་ཕྱིར་ཞེ་ན། གལ་ཏེ་གཞན་འགའ་ཞིག་ལྷའི་ཐུགས་སུ་མི་བྱོན་པ་བགྱིད་ན་དེ་ལ་ཡང་བདག་ཅག་གིས་བཟློག་པར་བགྱི་བ་ལགས་ན། ལྷ་ཉིད་ཀྱི་སྐུ་ལ་མཚོན་གྱིས་འདེབས་པར་ཇི་ལྟར་རྔོ་ཐོགས།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>‘Lord, your words are inappropriate. If someone else were to challenge you, we could oppose them. But how are we to use a weapon against you?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-345">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-142</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལྷ་གཞན་ཡང་གལ་ཏེ་བདག་ཅག་གཉིས་ཀྱིས་ཐུགས་རྗེ་ཆེ་བ། བྱམས་པའི་བདག་ཉིད་ཅན། སེམས་ཅན་ཐམས་ཅད་ལ་མཉེས་གཤིན་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>You are compassionate, loving, pleasing, and affectionate toward all sentient beings.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-346">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-142</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཛམ་བུའི་གླིང་ཡོངས་སུ་སྐྱོང་བར་མཛད་པ་ཁྱེད་ཀྱི་སྐུ་ལ་སོག་ལེས་གཅོད་པར་བགྱིད་ན་ངེས་པར་འཕྲལ་དུ་རང་གི་ལས་ཀྱིས་དམྱལ་བར་ལྟུང་བར་འགྱུར་རོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>You take care of all of Jambudvīpa. If we were to use this saw to cut through your body, our actions would cause us to fall instantly into hell.’</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-347">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-144</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔས་སྨྲས་པ། བུ་དག་ངའི་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའི་བཟོད་པའི་བདུད་རྩི་ཐ་མའི་བར་ཆད་ཁྱེད་ཅག་མ་བྱེད་ཅིག །དེ་བས་ན་ཚུར་ཤོག །ཇི་སྲིད་དུ་བྲམ་ཟེ་འདི་གསོན་པ་དེ་སྲིད་དུ་ངའི་བྱང་ཆུབ་ལ་གྲོགས་བྱ་བའི་ཕྱིར་མྱུར་དུ་ངའི་ལུས་ཀྱི་ཕྱེད་རོ་སྨད་ཆོད་ཅིག །དེ་ནས་ལྷའི་དབང་པོ་བརྒྱ་བྱིན་གྱིས་སྐྱེས་བུ་ཤིང་མཁན་གཉིས་ཇི་ལྟར་དེ་ལ་ཀུན་དུ་འཇུག་པར་འགྱུར་བ་དེ་ལྟར་བྱིན་གྱིས་བརླབས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“ ‘Sons,’ responded the bodhisattva, ‘do not block the final outpouring of the immortal elixir of a bodhisattva’s patience. Come here, help me to awaken. Cut off the lower half of my body while the brahmin is still alive.’<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-144"/> “Śakra, lord of the gods, used his power to compel the two carpenters to begin the process.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-348">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-144</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཡང་བར་སྐབས་དེར་སྲོག་ཆགས་བརྒྱ་སྟོང་དུ་མ་འདུས་པ་རྣམས་དང་། ནམ་མཁའི་ངོས་ན་ལྷ་བརྒྱ་སྟོང་དུ་མ་རྣམས་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་<tei:ref folio="F.42.a"/>དེའི་ཤིན་ཏུ་དཀའ་བ་དང་། བ་སྤུ་ལྡང་བའི་ལས་དེ་བལྟ་བར་འདོད་ནས་འདུས་པར་གྱུར་ཏོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>A little while later, hundreds of thousands of people had gathered in the royal estate and hundreds of thousands of gods had gathered in the sky. They had flocked to see the bodhisattva perform this extremely difficult task, a task so difficult it made their body hairs stand on end.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-349">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-144</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ནས་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་མཆོག་ཏུ་དགའ་བསི་རང་གི་ལུས་ཡོངས་སུ་གཏོང་བར་འདོད་ནས་སློང་བ་དེ་ལ་བྱམས་པས་ཁྱབ་པར་བྱས་ཏེ་འཕྲལ་དུ་སེང་གེའི་ཁྲི་ལས་བབས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The bodhisattva stepped down instantly from his lion throne. His intention to give away his body gave him extreme joy, and he was overwhelmed by his love for the brahmin who asked for it.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-350">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-145</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དགེ་སློང་དག་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་དཔལ་གྱི་སྡེ་སེང་གེའི་ཁྲི་ལས་བབས་པའི་རྗེས་ཐོགས་ཉིད་ལ་འཛམ་བུའི་གླིང་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱི་གདུགས་དང་། རྒྱལ་མཚན་དང་། བ་དན་དེ་དག་ཐམས་ཅད་རྒྱལ་པོའི་ཕོ་བྲང་ཨ་རིཥྛ་ག་ལ་བ་དེར་འདུད་པར་གྱུར་ཏོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-145"/>“Monks, at the very instant the bodhisattva Śrīsena stepped down from his lion throne, all of Jambudvīpa’s parasols, banners, and flags bent toward Ariṣṭa Estate.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-351">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-145</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།རྒྱལ་པོའི་ཕོ་བྲང་གྲོང་ཁྱེར་ཨ་རིཥྛའི་ཕྱོགས་བཞིར་སྐར་མདའ་ལྟུང་བ་དང་། གྲོང་ཁྱེར་ན་གནས་པའི་སྐྱེ་བོའི་ཚོགས་ཀྱིས་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་དང་བྲལ་བའི་ཉམ་ཐག་པས་སྒྲ་བསྒྲགས་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Meteors fell toward it from the four directions. But those who dwelled in the city wailed with the pain of separation.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-352">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-146</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྲམ་ཟེ་སྡིག་པ་ཅན་འདིས་རྒྱལ་པོ་དཔལ་གྱི་སྡེ་གསོད་པར་འགྱུར་གྱིས་མྱུར་དུ་གྲོང་ཁྱེར་འདི་ནས་ཕྱིར་ཕྱུང་ཤིག །དེ་ནས་ལྷའི་དབང་པོ་བརྒྱ་བྱིན་གྱིས་ཇི་ལྟར་སྒྲ་སུས་ཀྱང་མ་ཐོས་པ་དེ་ལྟར་བྱིན་གྱིས་བརླབས་ཤིང་སྐྱེ་བོའི་ཚོགས་དེ་རྨོངས་པར་བྱས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>‘This evil brahmin is going to kill King Śrīsena!’ they shouted. ‘Throw him out of here!’<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-146"/> “Śakra, lord of the gods, prevented the people from hearing what was happening. They were stupefied.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-353">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-146</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།བར་སྣང་དང་ས་ལ་རྒྱུ་བའི་གནོད་སྦྱིན་རྣམས་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་རང་གི་ལུས་ལ་ལྟོས་པ་མེད་པར་ཤེས་ནས་སྡུག་བསྔལ་དྲག་པོ་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་གདུངས་ནས་ཉམ་ཐག་པའི་ང་རོས་ཆོ་ངེས་འདེབས་པར་བརྩམས་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The yakṣas, those who dwell in space and on the ground, came to know that the bodhisattva was unconcerned with his body and wailed in the torment of their immense sorrow. ‘Alas,’ they cried, ‘King Śrīsena!</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-354">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-146</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཀྱི་ཧུད་རྒྱལ་པོ་དཔལ་གྱི་སྡེ་འཛམ་བུའི་གླིང་ཡོངས་སུ་སྐྱོང་བར་བྱེད་པ། སེམས་ཅན་ཐམས་ཅད་ལ་ཐུགས་བརྩེ་བ། ཐམས་ཅད་ནས་ཐམས་ཅད་དུ་ལུས་གཏོང་བར་གྱུར་ཏོ། །དེ་ནས་ཡང་ཕོ་བྲང་གི་ནང་ན་གནས་པའི་ལྷ་ཞིག་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་དེ་ལྟ་བུའི་རང་གི་ལུས་ཡོངས་སུ་གཏོང་བར་ཤེས་ནས་ཆོ་ངེས་འདེབས་པར་རྩོམ་ཞིང་འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་ཀྱང་སྨྲས་སོ། །ཇི་ལྟར་ད་ལྟར་འདི་ལྟ་བུའི་སློངས་མོ་པ་འོངས་ནས་རྒྱལ་པོ་དཔལ་གྱི་སྡེ་ཡོན་ཏན་དུ་མ་དང་ལྡན་པ་ཐམས་ཅད་ནས་ཐམས་ཅད་དུ་མི་འཚོ་བར་གྱུར།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He who takes care of everyone in Jambudvīpa, he who is compassionate toward all sentient beings, he will give up his entire body!’ A deity who lived on the royal estate also came to know that he would give up his entire body, and lamented aloud, ‘King Śrīsena, he who is endowed with so many qualities, is not going to survive because of this beggar!’</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-355">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-147</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔས་ཕྱོགས་བཞིར་བལྟས་ཏེ་ཡང་དག་པའི་སྨོན་ལམ་འདེབས་པ་ལ་ཞུགས་པ་གང་གྲོང་ཁྱེར་འདི་ན་གནས་པའི་ལྷ་དང་། ཀླུ་དང་། གནོད་སྦྱིན་དང་། མིའམ་ཅི་རྣམས་བདག་ལ་གསོན་ཅིག །བདག་འདིར་གཏོང་བར་བྱེད་དེ།<tei:ref folio="F.42.b"/>
                </seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-147"/>“After this, the bodhisattva looked around in the four directions. ‘Gods, nāgas, yakṣas, and kinnaras, all you who dwell in this city, listen! Make pure prayers for me! I am making this gift today.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-356">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-147</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཏོང་བ་ཤིན་ཏུ་གཏོང་བ་རང་གི་ལུས་ཡོངས་སུ་གཏོང་བར་བྱེད་ཀྱིས་བདག་གི་ལུས་ཡོངས་སུ་གཏོང་བ་དེ་ཡང་རྒྱལ་པོའི་ཕྱིར་མ་ཡིན། མཐོ་རིས་ཀྱི་ཕྱིར་མ་ཡིན།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>I am making the greatest of gifts, the gift of one’s body. I am not making this gift for myself, the king, nor to attain rebirth in a higher realm.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-357">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-147</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བརྒྱ་བྱིན་གྱི་ཕྱིར་མ་ཡིན། ཚངས་པའི་ཕྱིར་མ་ཡིན།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>I am not making it for Śakra or for Brahmā.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-358">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-147</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཁོར་ལོས་སྒྱུར་བའི་རྒྱལ་པོའི་ཕྱིར་མ་ཡིན་གྱི།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>I am not making it to become a universal monarch.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-359">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-147</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཞན་དུ་ན་བདག་གིས་ཅི་ནས་བླ་ན་མེད་པ་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་བྱང་ཆུབ་མངོན་པར་རྫོགས་པར་སངས་རྒྱས་ནས་སེམས་ཅན་མ་བསྒྲལ་བ་རྣམས་བསྒྲལ་བར་བྱ་བ་དང་། མ་གྲོལ་བ་རྣམས་དགྲོལ་བར་བྱ་བ་དང་། དབུགས་མ་ཕྱིན་པ་རྣམས་དབུགས་དབྱུང་བར་བྱ་བ་དང་། ཡོངས་སུ་མྱ་ངན་ལས་མ་འདས་པ་རྣམས་ཡོངས་སུ་མྱ་ངན་ལས་བཟླ་བའི་བདེན་པ་དང་བདེན་པའི་ཚིག་འདིས་ངལ་བ་འབྲས་བུ་དང་བཅས་པར་གྱུར་ཅིག །བདག་མངོན་པར་བྱང་ཆུབ་ནས་ཀྱང་མཚན་མ་ཅུང་ཟད་ཅིག་འབྱུང་བར་གྱུར་ཅིག་ཅེས་སྨྲས་ཏེ་བྲམ་ཟེ་དེ་ལ་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>I make this gift to attain unsurpassed and perfect awakening. I make it to liberate sentient beings who are not yet liberated. I make it to console those who need consoling, to unbind those who are bound. By the truth of my words, may it be accomplished. May some small sign of my awakening appear!’</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-360">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-148</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེས་པ་ཁྱོད་ཀྱི་ཀུན་དུ་རྟོག་པ་འབྱོར་པར་གྱུར་ཅིག །ཁྱོད་ཀྱི་ཡིད་ལ་རེ་བ་ཡོངས་སུ་རྫོགས་པར་གྱུར་ཅིག །ངའི་ཡང་བླ་ན་མེད་པའི་བྱང་ཆུབ་ཡོངས་སུ་རྫོགས་པར་གྱུར་ཅིག །དེ་ནས་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཉེ་དུའི་སྐྱེ་བོ་རྣམས་དང་། གྲོང་ཁྱེར་པའི་སྐྱེ་བོ་རྣམས་ལ་བཟོད་པར་བྱས་ཤིང་དམན་པ་དང་། ནད་པ་རྣམས་དབུགས་ཕྱུང་ནས་སྐྱེས་བུ་ཤིང་མཁན་དེ་གཉིས་ལ་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-148"/>“To the brahmin, he said, ‘By this action, may you attain all you have imagined. May all your wishes be fulfilled. And may I realize unsurpassed awakening completely.’<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-150"/> “The bodhisattva asked his relatives and the city’s inhabitants for patience. He consoled the poor and stricken, before speaking to the two carpenters.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-361">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-148</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཞིན་བཟངས་དག་ཚུར་ཤོག །ཇི་སྲིད་དུ་བྲམ་ཟེ་འདི་དུས་མ་བྱས་ཀྱི་བར་དུ་སོག་ལེ་ཟུང་ལ་ངའི་ལུས་ལྟེ་བ་ཡན་ཅད་ཆོད་ཅིག །འགྲོ་བ་སྡུག་བསྔལ་གྱིས་ཟིན་པ་འདི་དག་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱང་ངས་ཡོངས་སུ་བསྐྱབ་པར་བྱའོ་ཞེས་བྱམས་པས་ཁྱབ་པར་བྱས་ནས་སྐྱེས་བུ་གཅིག་གིས་རྒྱབ་ནས་བརྟེན་ཏེ། འཕྲལ་དུ་རྐང་པ་གཉིས་ས་ལ་བརྐྱང་ནས་གན་རྐྱལ་དུ་ཕབ་བོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>‘Good people, come here. Before the brahmin’s time runs out, saw at my navel. May I protect all beings who suffer!’ In this way, with love suffusing all, and with the help of a man who supported him, he promptly lay down on his back and stretched out his legs.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-362">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-151</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དགེ་སློང་དག་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཕབ་མ་ཐག་ཡང་ས་ཆེན་པོ་རྣམ་པ་དྲུག་ཏུ་གཡོས་པར་གྱུར་ཏོ། །དེ་ནས་བཙུན་མོ་བུད་མེད་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་དེ་ལྟ་བུའི་གཏམ་ཐོས་ནས་མྱ་ངན་དྲག་པོས་གདུངས་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-151"/>“Monks, as the bodhisattva was lowered onto the ground, the great earth shook in six different ways. The ladies of the court were deeply tormented when they heard the news and rushed to the bodhisattva’s side. Tears poured down their faces like rain. They let their hair fall and beat their chests in mourning.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-363">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-151</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཀྱི་ཧུད་འདི་ནི་སྡུག་བསྔལ་ལོ་ཞེས་གདོང་ལས་མཆི་མ་ཆར་བཞིན་དུ་འབབ་ཅིང་སྐྲ་རྣམས་བཀྲོལ་ཏེ་བྲང་རྡུང་ཞིང་རྟབས་བག་ཏུ་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་གང་ན་བ་དེར་སོང་སྟེ་ཕྱིན་ནས་ལྷ་མོ་ལྟ་བུ་སྡུག་པ་དང་<tei:ref folio="F.43.a"/>བྲལ་ནས་རྟབས་བག་ཏུ་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའི་རྐང་པ་ལ་གཏུགས་ནས་སྙིང་རྗེ་རྗེ་སྐད་དུ་སྨྲེ་སྔགས་འདོན་པར་རྩོམ་པ་ན།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>‘Alas,’ they cried, ‘the pain!’ They were no longer attractive like goddesses. They touched the bodhisattva’s feet briefly and wailed, ‘Please have mercy!’</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-364">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-151</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཀྱི་ཧུད་འཛམ་བུའི་གླིང་ཡོངས་སུ་སྐྱོང་བར་མཛད་པ། སེམས་ཅན་ཐམས་ཅད་ལ་མཉེས་གཤིན་པ། སྙིང་རྗེ་ཆེ་བ། ཡོན་ཏན་དུ་མ་དང་ལྡན་པའི་ལྷ་ལ་དེང་ཉིད་དུ་མི་རྟག་པ་ཉིད་ཀྱི་སྟོབས་ཉེ་བར་གནས་པ་འདི་སྡུག་བསྔལ་ལོ། །དེང་འདིར་བདག་ཅག་ལྷ་དང་ལྷན་ཅིག་པ་ལས་ཐ་དད་པར་གྱུར་ཏེ། སོ་སོ་བ་དང་། བྱེ་བ་དང་བྲལ་བར་གྱུར་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>‘Alas,’ they cried, ‘it pains us that the power of impermanence is now at hand and today will separate, isolate, detach, and remove us from our relationships with this lord. He is the lord who protects all of Jambudvīpa, who pleases and is affectionate toward all sentient beings, who has immense compassion, and who has innumerable good qualities.’</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-365">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-155</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་ཀྱང་སྨྲས་ཏེ། ལྷ་བཟོད་པར་མཛོད་ཅིག །ཉིད་ཀྱི་སྲོག་མེད་པར་མཛད་པས་འཛམ་བུའི་གླིང་ན་གནས་པའི་སྐྱེ་བོའི་ཚོགས་ཐམས་ཅད་མགོན་མེད་པར་མི་མཛད་དུ་གསོལ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-155"/>“ ‘Lord,’ they persisted, ‘please have patience with us! Please don’t leave all of the communities of people living in Jambudvīpa without a protector by taking your own life.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-366">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-155</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལྷ་བཙུན་མོའི་འཁོར་རྣམས་དང་། མཛོད་དང་བང་བ་རིན་པོ་ཆེ་སྣ་ཚོགས་ཀྱིས་རྒྱས་ཤིང་ཡོངས་སུ་གང་བ་ལ་གཟིགས་སུ་གསོལ། འཛམ་བུའི་གླིང་གི་སྐྱེ་བོའི་ཚོགས་རྟག་ཏུ་རབ་ཏུ་དགའ་བ་རྣམ་པ་སྣ་ཚོགས་པ་ལ་ཡང་གཟིགས་སུ་གསོལ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Lord, please look at the ladies of the court and your vast treasuries and storehouses filled with myriad precious gems. Look at Jambudvīpa’s people, who are always experiencing many types of happiness.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-367">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-155</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལྷ་རྣམས་ཀྱི་དགའ་བའི་ཚལ་གྱི་སྐྱེད་མོས་ཚལ་ལྟ་བུའི་གྲོང་ཁྱེར་ཨ་རིཥྛ་བཟང་བ་མང་པོ་ཕུན་སུམ་ཚོགས་པར་སྐྱེ་བོ་རབ་ཏུ་དགའ་བ་རྣམས་བསྟེན་པ་ལ་ཡང་གཟིགས་སུ་གསོལ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Look at the city of Ariṣṭa, which resembles a divine park complete with an abundance of fine features, where so many joyful people live.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-368">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-156</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།མགོན་པོ་ཁྱོད་ཀྱིས་རྣམ་ཀུན་དུ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-156"/>“ ‘Protector, you have always taken care of everyone</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-369">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-156</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།སྲས་ལྟར་ཡོངས་སུ་བསྐྱངས་པ་རྣམས།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>As if they were your own children.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-370">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-156</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཁྱོད་བྲལ་མེ་ཡིས་ངེས་གདུངས་ནས། །ལུས་ཅན་ཇི་ལྟར་གནས་པར་འགྱུར།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>How will these beings survive When they are surely scorched by the fire of losing you?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-371">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-157</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཁྱོད་དང་བྲལ་ན་བདག་ཅག་ཀུན། །ཤིན་ཏུ་འཆི་བདག་དབང་དུ་འགྱུར།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-157"/>“ ‘If separated from you, We will all be overpowered by the Lord of Death.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-372">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-157</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།མགོན་པོ་ཁྱོད་དང་རྣམ་བྲལ་ན།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>O Protector, if we are separated from you,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-373">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-157</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།བདག་ཅག་འཚོ་བར་མི་ནུས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>We will not be able to survive!</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-374">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-158</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།བཙུན་མོ་མྱ་ངན་གྱིས་གདུངས་དང་། །སེམས་ཅན་གཅིག་ཏུ་སྡུག་བསྔལ་ན།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-158"/>“ ‘If the queen is stricken by suffering, And if sentient beings all suffer as one, We pray that you look upon us, ruler of humans,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-375">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-158</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཐུགས་རྗེ་ལྡན་པའི་ཐུགས་རྗེ་ཡིས། །མི་དབང་དེ་ནི་གཟིགས་སུ་གསོལ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>With the compassion of one who embodies compassion.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-376">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-159</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།སེམས་ཅན་རྣམས་ལ་མཉེས་གཤིན་ལྷ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-159"/>“ ‘Lord who is affectionate toward all beings,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-377">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-159</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།བཟོད་མཛོད་སྲོག་ནི་མི་གཏོང་གསོལ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Please take care of us—don’t give away your life!</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-378">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-159</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།མགོན་པོ་དཔའ་བོ་ཁྱོད་གཤེགས་ན།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Who will be our protector, our hero, if you pass on?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-379">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-159</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།སུ་ཞིག་འཇིག་རྟེན་སྐྱོང་བར་འགྱུར།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Who will protect the world?’</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-380">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-160</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ནས་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔས་དེ་རྣམས་ཀྱི་སྙིང་རྗེ་རྗེ་སྐད་དུ་དེ་ལྟར་སྨྲེ་སྔགས་འདོན་པ་ཐོས་པ་དང་། སྙིང་རྗེས་གདུངས་པའི་ཡིད་ཀྱིས་དེ་རྣམས་དབུགས་དབྱུང་བའི་ཕྱིར་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-160"/>“After hearing their pitiable lament, the bodhisattva’s heart was heavy with compassion.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-381">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-160</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཁྱེད་ཅག་རྣམས་ཀྱི་མྱ་<tei:ref folio="F.43.b"/>ངན་གྱིས་ཆོག་གིས། ཤིན་ཏུ་ཡུན་རིང་པོར་སྡུག་པ་དང་ཕྲད་པར་གྱུར་པ་ཡང་ངེས་པར་ཐ་མར་འབྲལ་བའི་མཐའ་ཉིད་དུ་འགྱུར་བ་འདི་ནི་འཇིག་རྟེན་གྱི་རང་བཞིན་ཡིན་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>‘Your lament is understandable,’ he said to console them, ‘but it is the way of the world that we must separate even from those we have known for a long time.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-382">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-160</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཁྱེད་ཅག་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་རྟག་ཏུ་དགེ་བའི་ཆོས་རྣམས་ལ་བག་ཡོད་པར་གྱིས་ཤིག་ཅེས་སྨྲས་ནས་ཤིང་མཁན་དེ་གཉིས་ལ་འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་སྨྲས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>For this reason, you should always be mindful of virtuous deeds.’ Then he turned to the two carpenters again and said, ‘Good people, come here.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-383">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-161</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།བཞིན་བཟངས་དག་རིངས་པར་ཤོག་ལ་ལུས་ཡུན་རིང་པོ་མི་ཐོགས་པར་ཆོད་ཅིག་ཅེས་སྨྲས་པ་ཙམ་གྱིས་དེ་གཉིས་ཀྱང་བརྒྱ་བྱིན་གྱིས་ཀུན་དུ་རྨོངས་པར་བྱས་པས་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའི་ལུས་ལྟེ་བ་མན་ཆད་ལ་འཕྲལ་དུ་སོག་ལེས་བཏབ་སྟེ། རིང་པོར་མ་ཐོགས་པར་ཆོད་པར་གྱུར་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Without taking too much time, cut my body.’<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-161"/> “Because Śakra had enchanted them, the two carpenters immediately began sawing the bodhisattva’s body at his navel.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-384">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-161</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་བློན་པོ་ཆེན་པོ་བློ་གྲོས་ཆེན་པོས་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའི་ཤིན་ཏུ་དཀའ་ཞིང་བཟོད་པར་དཀའ་བའི་སྡུག་བསྔལ་མི་བཟད་པ་དྲན་པའི་མྱ་ངན་དྲག་པོས་ཀུན་དུ་སྐྲག་པའི་ཡིད་ཀྱིས་རྟབས་བག་ཏུ་ཤིང་མཁན་གཉིས་བཟློག་ཅིང་འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་སྨྲས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Mahāmati, revived and imagining the unbearably intense pain the bodhisattva was experiencing, rebuked the two carpenters.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-385">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-161</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཀྱི་ཧུད་ཀྱི་ཧུད་ཁྱེད་ཅག་གཉིས་ཀྱི་རྩོལ་བ་འདི་ཅི་ཞིག །འདི་ལྟར་ཁྱེད་ཅག་གཉིས་ཀྱིས་བྱམས་པའི་བདག་ཉིད་ཅན།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>‘Alas,’ he cried, ‘alas! What are the two of you doing! How can you kill the compassionate one?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-386">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-161</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སེམས་ཅན་ཐམས་ཅད་ལ་མཉེས་གཤིན་པ། ཡོན་ཏན་དུ་མ་དང་ལྡན་པ། འཛམ་བུའི་གླིང་ཡོངས་སུ་སྐྱོང་བ། སྐྱོན་མེད་པ། གནོད་པ་མི་བྱེད་པ་འདི་ཇི་ལྟར་གསོད།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>How can you kill the one who is pleasing and affectionate to everyone, he who has numerous good qualities, he who takes care of all of Jambudvīpa, he who is faultless and harms none?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-387">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-161</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མི་གཏི་མུག་ཅན་ཁྱེད་ཅག་འདི་ལྟ་བུའི་ཆོས་ཀྱི་རྒྱལ་པོ་ཇི་ལྟར་གསོད་པར་སྤྲོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>How can you ignorant people take joy in killing a Dharma king?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-388">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-161</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཁྱེད་ཅག་གཉིས་ས་ཆེན་པོའི་ལྷ་མོ་འདིས་ཇི་ལྟར་འཇོག །ཁྱེད་ཅག་གཉིས་ལ་ལྷ་དང་། ཀླུ་དང་། གནོད་སྦྱིན་དང་། ལྷ་མ་ཡིན་དང་། དྲི་ཟ་དང་། ནམ་མཁའ་ལྡིང་དང་། མི་འམ་ཅི་དང་། ལྟོ་འཕྱེ་ཆེན་པོ་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་རྡོ་རྗེ་རྩེ་གཅིག་པ་དང་། འཁོར་ལོ་དང་། མདའ་བོ་ཆེ་དང་། མཚོན་རྩེ་གཅིག་པ་ལ་སོགས་པའི་མཚོན་རྣམས་ཇི་སྟེ་མ་བསྣུན།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>How does this great land’s goddess allow you to live? Why haven’t you been pierced by the single-pointed vajra? The weapon-wheel? The great arrow? The single-pointed weapons of the gods, nāgas, yakṣas, asuras, gandharvas, garuḍas, kinnaras, and mahoragas?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-389">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-161</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཁྱེད་ཅག་གཉིས་འདི་ལྟ་བུའི་འཕགས་པ་མ་ཡིན་པའི་ལས་བྱེད་ན་ལུས་རྣམ་པ་སྟོང་དུ་ཇི་ལྟར་མ་ལྷགས།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>You have committed such an ignoble act. How is it that your bodies have not exploded into a thousand pieces?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-390">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-161</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཁྱེད་ཅག་གཉིས་རང་གི་ལུས་ཀྱིས་འཕྲལ་དུ་དམྱལ་བར་ཇི་ལྟར་མ་ལྷུང་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Why haven’t you fallen instantly into hell, in this very body?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-391">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-162</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མི་གཏི་མུག་ཅན་ཁྱེད་ཅག་གཉིས་བདག་ཉིད་ཆེན་པོ་འདིས་བུ་བཞིན་མ་བསྐྱངས་སམ་ཞེས་འདི་དང་གཞན་ཡང་རྣམ་པ་མང་པོ་སྨྲས་ནས་ཀྱི་ཧུད་ལྷ་ཞེས་བློན་པོ་ཆེན་པོ་བློ་གྲོས་ཆེན་པོ་རིངས་པར་སྟན་<tei:ref folio="F.44.a"/>ལས་ལངས་ཏེ། ལག་པ་གཉིས་ཀྱིས་སོག་ལེ་བཟུང་ནས་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའི་ལུས་ལ་མཆི་མ་འཛག་པས་བརླན་པར་བྱས་ཏེ་ཟློག་པར་བྱེད་དོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Didn’t this great being also treat you as his sons? You ignorant beings!’<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-162"/> “He said these things and many others besides. ‘Alas, lord!’ he cried, and getting up from his seat, Mahāmati, the great minister, grabbed the saw with his own two hands, and as his tears wet the bodhisattva’s body, he pushed the two carpenters away.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-392">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-162</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ནས་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔས་ཞུམ་པའི་ཡིད་དེ་ལ་དབུགས་དབྱུང་བའི་ཕྱིར་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>To console the discouraged Mahāmati, the bodhisattva said,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-393">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-162</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བུ་ཞོག་ཞོག་མྱ་ངན་མ་བྱེད་ཅིག །སྡུག་པ་དང་ཕངས་པ་དང་ཡིད་དུ་འོང་བ་དང་མངོན་པར་དགའ་བ་ཐམས་ཅད་ངེས་པར་ཐ་དད་པར་གྱུར་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>‘Son, leave it be, leave it be. Do not lament. It is certain that we will be separated from those dear to us, those we love, those who draw near to us, and those of whom we are extremely fond.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-394">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-162</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སོ་སོ་བ་དང་བྱེ་བ་དང་འབྲལ་བར་འགྱུར་རོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>We will be isolated, divided, and separated.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-395">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-162</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།གཞན་ཡང་བུ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Moreover, son:</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-396">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-163</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བསགས་པ་ཀུན་གྱི་མཐའ་ཟད་ཅིང་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-163"/>“ ‘The end of all accumulation is dispersion.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-397">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-163</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།བསླང་བའི་མཐའ་ནི་འགྱེལ་བར་འགྱུར།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The end of rising is falling.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-398">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-163</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཕྲད་པའི་མཐའ་ནི་འབྲལ་བ་སྟེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The end of meeting is parting.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-399">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-163</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།གསོན་པའི་མཐའ་ནི་འཆི་བ་ཡིན།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The end of living is dying.<tei:note xml:id="UT22084-076-003-164"/>
                </seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-400">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-165</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེའི་ཕྱིར་ཁྱོད་ལུས་སློང་བ་ལ་བར་ཆད་མ་བྱེད་ཅིག །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-165"/>“ ‘Therefore, do not stop those who ask for my body.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-401">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-165</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ཅིའི་ཕྱིར་ཞེ་ན།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg/>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-402">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-165</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བློ་གྲོས་ཆེན་པོ་སྔོན་བྱུང་བ་ན་ངའི་ལུས་སློང་བ་ན་ལྷ་མོ་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་བར་ཆད་བྱས་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Mahāmati, in the past, another person tried to ask for my body but goddesses stopped them.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-403">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-165</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་ངའི་བར་ཆད་བྱས་པས་ངའི་བླ་ན་མེད་པའི་བྱང་ཆུབ་ལ་བར་ཆད་བྱས་ལ་བདག་ཉིད་ཀྱང་བསོད་ནམས་མ་ཡིན་པ་མང་པོ་སྐྱེས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Not only did those goddesses prevent me from achieving unsurpassed awakening, they also created much nonvirtue.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-404">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-165</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།གལ་ཏེ་ངའི་ལུས་སློང་བ་ལ་ལྷ་མོ་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་བར་ཆད་མ་བྱས་པར་གྱུར་ན་ནི་ཡུན་རིང་པོ་མི་ཐོགས་པར་ངས་བླ་ན་མེད་པ་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་བྱང་ཆུབ་འཐོབ་པར་འགྱུར་རོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>If the goddesses had not prevented that person asking for my body, I would have attained unsurpassed and perfect awakening by now.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-405">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-166</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།བུ་གཞན་ཡང་ས་ཕྱོགས་འདི་ཉིད་དུ་སྟག་མོ་ཞིག་བཀྲེས་པའི་སྡུག་བསྔལ་གྱི་ཚོར་བ་མང་པོས་ལུས་གདུངས་པས་བུ་ཟ་འདོད་པ་མཐོང་བ་དང་། མཆོག་ཏུ་སྙིང་རྗེའི་དབང་དུ་སོང་བའི་ཡིད་ཀྱིས་ཡོངས་སུ་བསྐྱབ་པའི་ཕྱིར་དེ་མ་ཐག་བདག་ཉིད་ཡོངས་སུ་བཏང་བས་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་བྱམས་པ་བསྐལ་པ་བཞི་བཅུར་ཞུགས་པ་ཕྱིར་ལུས་པར་བྱས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-166"/>“ ‘What is more, son, in this very place I met a tigress whose hunger pains were so intense that she wanted to eat her own cubs. Out of supreme compassion, I gave myself to her immediately so that she might be saved. By so doing, I surpassed<tei:note xml:id="UT22084-076-003-167"/> the deeds of the bodhisattva Maitreya, who had set out for buddhahood forty eons before that.<tei:note xml:id="UT22084-076-003-168"/>
                </seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-406">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-169</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།གཞན་ཡང་བློ་གྲོས་ཆེན་པོ་ང་ཤི་བི་པའི་རྒྱལ་པོར་གྱུར་པ་ན་ཡང་བྲམ་ཟེ་རྒན་པོ་ཞིག་སློང་བ་མཐོང་སྟེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-169"/>“ ‘Another time, Mahāmati, when I was king of the Śibi people, an old brahmin came seeking the gift of sight.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-407">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-169</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྙིང་རྗེས་བསྐྱོད་པའི་ཡིད་ཀྱིས་སློང་བའི་ཡིད་ལ་རེ་བ་ཡོངས་སུ་རྫོགས་པར་བྱ་བའི་ཕྱིར་རང་ཉིད་ཀྱི་ཨུད་པ་ལ་སྔོན་པོའི་ལོ་མ་ལྟ་བུ་དྲི་མ་མེད་པ། ཤིན་ཏུ་མཛེས་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Moved by compassion, I immediately extracted my unimpaired eyes and gave them to him, while they were still stained with blood.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-408">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-170</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སེམས་ཅན་སྐྱེ་བོའི་མིག་དང་ཡིད་འཕྲོག་པ་མ་ཉམས་པའི་མིག་གཉིས་འཕྲལ་དུ་ཁྲག་དང་བཅས་པར་ཕྱུང་ནས་བྱིན་ནོ། །གཞན་ཡང་བློ་གྲོས་ཆེན་པོ་ཡང་ང་རྒྱལ་པོ་ཟླ་འོད་དུ་གྱུར་པ་ན་ཡང་བྲམ་ཟེ་དྲག་པོའི་<tei:ref folio="F.44.b"/>མིག་མགོ་སློང་བ་ལ་མཆོག་ཏུ་སྙིང་རྗེས་བསྒོས་པའི་ཡིད་ཀྱིས་ལྷ་དང་། ཀླུ་དང་། གནོད་སྦྱིན་དང་། དྲི་ཟ་དང་། ལྷ་མ་ཡིན་དང་། ནམ་མཁའ་ལྡིང་དང་། མི་འམ་ཅི་དང་། ལྟོ་འཕྱེ་ཆེན་པོ་དང་། གྲུབ་པ་དང་། རིག་པ་འཛིན་པའི་ཚོགས་རྣམས་དང་།  ལྷ་བརྒྱ་སྟོང་དུ་མ་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་བཀག་ཀྱང་ངས་འགྲོ་བ་འདི་དག་མགོན་མེད་པར་མཐོང་ནས་བླ་ན་མེད་པ་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་བྱང་ཆུབ་མངོན་པར་རྫོགས་པར་བྱང་ཆུབ་སྟེ། སེམས་ཅན་རྣམས་འཁོར་བའི་འབྲོག་དགོན་པ་ལས་ཐར་བར་བྱ་སྙམ་ནས་བྱམས་པས་ཁྱབ་པར་བྱས་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>My eyes had been as unstained as an utpala flower, a blue lotus. They were extremely beautiful and captured the hearts and attention of all people—indeed, all beings.<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-170"/> “ ‘Yet another time, Mahāmati, when I was a king named Candraprabha, a brahmin rudely asked me for not only my eyes but also my head. Groups of nāgas, yakṣas, gandharvas, asuras, garuḍas, kinnaras, mahoragas, siddhas, vidyādharas, and hundreds of thousands of gods tried to stop me from making this gift. Despite all this opposition, I saw that sentient beings had no protector, and with the loving intention to liberate them from saṃsāra’s wilderness, I aspired to attain unsurpassed and perfect awakening.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-409">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-170</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རང་གི་ནོར་བུ་དང་གསེར་དང་དངུལ་དང་བཻ་དཱུརྱ་དང་རྡོ་རྗེ་དང་ཨིན་དྲ་ནཱི་ལ་དང་། མར་གད་ཀྱིས་ཀུན་དུ་བརྒྱན་པ། ཨུད་པ་ལ་སྔོན་པོའི་ལོ་མ་ལྟ་བུའི་རལ་གྲིས་རང་གི་མགོ་རྩྭ་བཞིན་དུ་བཅད་ཅིང་བཅད་ཅིང་བྱིན་ནོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>My sword was the blue color of an utpala flower. It was decorated with precious gems, gold, silver, beryl, diamonds, sapphires, and emeralds. I picked it up and chopped off my head as if it were a blade of grass, and then I gave it to the brahmin.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-410">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-171</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།གཞན་ཡང་བློ་གྲོས་ཆེན་པོ་ཡང་ང་ཤི་བི་པའི་རྒྱལ་པོར་གྱུར་པ་ན་ཕུག་རོན་སྐྱབས་མེད་པ་ཞིག་ཁྲས་འཇིགས་ཤིང་སྐྲག་ལ་སྡུག་བསྔལ་ཞིང་བཞིན་རྨོགས་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-171"/>“ ‘Another time, Mahāmati, when I was again king of the Śibi people, I saw an unprotected, terrified pigeon, ducking and diving as it was chased by a hawk.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-411">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-171</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྐྱབས་མེད་པ་སྐྱབས་སུ་འོངས་པ་མཐོང་སྟེ། མཆོག་ཏུ་སྙིང་རྗེས་འདར་བའི་ཡིད་ཀྱིས་བྱ་ཕུག་རོན་ཁྲ་ལས་ཡོངས་སུ་བསྲུང་ཞིང་བླུ་བའི་ཕྱིར་རང་གི་ཤ་བཅད་ཅིང་བཅད་ཅིང་བྱིན་ནོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>As I watched the unprotected pigeon seek refuge, I shook with supreme compassion. To protect the pigeon from the hawk and to deceive the hawk, I cut off a piece of my own flesh and gave it to the hawk.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-412">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-172</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།གཞན་ཡང་བླ་ན་མེད་པ་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་བྱང་ཆུབ་མངོན་པར་འདོད་པར་བྱ་བའི་ཕྱིར་ས་ཕྱོགས་འདི་ཉིད་དུ་རྐང་པ་དང་ལག་པ་དང་བུ་དང་ཆུང་མ་སྟོང་ཕྲག་ཡོངས་སུ་བཏང་བ་བྱས་ན་ཡང་སུས་ཀྱང་བར་ཆད་མ་བྱས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-172"/>“ ‘In the past, in this very land, I have given thousands of legs, hands, sons, and wives for the sake of unsurpassed and perfect awakening, and no one stopped me.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-413">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-172</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེའི་ཕྱིར་འདི་ལྟར་རིག་པར་བྱ་སྟེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>You should understand this, Mahāmati.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-414">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-173</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ངའི་ལུས་སློང་བ་ལ་ཁྱོད་བར་ཆད་མ་བྱེད་ཅིག །དེ་ནས་བློན་པོ་ཆེན་པོ་བློ་གྲོས་ཆེན་པོས་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའི་རྫུ་འཕྲུལ་ཆེན་པོ་སྐྱེས་ནས་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་ལ་དད་པ་ཆེན་པོ་སྐྱེས་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>And you should not stop the brahmin seeking my body.’ <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-173"/>“Following this, the great minister Mahāmati understood that the bodhisattva had given rise to great miraculous powers, and he developed profound faith in him.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-415">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-173</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་ཅང་མི་སྨྲ་བར་གྱུར་ཅིང་མཆི་མའི་དབའ་རླབས་ཀྱིས་ཡང་དང་ཡང་དུ་གདོང་ཁེབས་བཞིན་དུ་བསམས་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>This great minister remained silent while waves of tears flowed down his face continually.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-416">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-173</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཀྱི་ཧུད་འཇིག་རྟེན་པ་འདི་དག་ནི་སྐལ་བ་ངན་པ་སྟེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He thought, ‘Alas, these beings are unfortunate.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-417">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-173</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མྱུར་བ་ཉིད་དུ་ཆོས་ཀྱི་རྒྱལ་པོ་འདིས་བོར་བར་འགྱུར་རོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They will soon lose their Dharma king.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-418">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-173</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཀྱི་ཧུད་ཆོས་ཀྱི་རྒྱལ་མཚན་འགྱེལ་བར་འགྱུར་རོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Alas, the Dharma’s victory banner is about to fall.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-419">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-345</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཆོས་ཀྱི་སྒྲོན་མ་ཤི་བར་འགྱུར་རོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-345"/>“ ‘The lamp of Dharma will be extinguished.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-420">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-345</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཆོས་ཀྱི་སྒྲོན་མ་མི་སྣང་བར་འགྱུར་རོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The lamp of Dharma will disappear.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-421">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-345</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཆོས་ཀྱི་རྔ་ཆག་པར་འགྱུར་རོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The Dharma drum is about to break.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-422">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-345</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཆོས་ཀྱི་རྒྱ་མཚོ་སྐམས་པར་<tei:ref folio="F.45.a"/>འགྱུར་རོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The ocean of Dharma will dry up.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-423">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-346</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཆོས་ཀྱི་རི་བོ་རྙིལ་བར་འགྱུར་རོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-346"/>“ ‘The great mountain of Dharma will soon crumble.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-424">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-346</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཆོས་ཀྱི་གྲོང་ཁྱེར་ཆོམས་པར་འགྱུར་རོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The city of Dharma will soon be looted.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-425">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-346</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཆོས་ཀྱི་གྲུ་ཞིག་པར་འགྱུར་རོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The ship of Dharma will soon disintegrate.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-426">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-174</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཆོས་ཀྱི་ཤིང་ཕྱུང་བ་ནི་ཀྱི་ཧུད་སྡུག་བསྔལ་ལོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>When the Dharma tree is uprooted, it is painful indeed.<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-174"/> “ ‘The wheel of time is about to crush</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-427">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-174</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།འདི་ནི་འཇིག་རྟེན་ཀུན་གྱི་ཕ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The father of the entire world,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-428">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-174</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།སེམས་ཅན་ཀུན་ལ་ཕན་བྱེད་པ། །དུས་ཀྱི་འཁོར་ལོས་བཅོམ་ནས་ནི།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Who has helped all beings.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-429">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-174</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།རྒྱལ་པོ་ཆེན་པོ་མེད་པར་འགྱུར།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The great king will be no more.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-430">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-175</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།གང་ཕྱིར་མི་བཟད་དུས་འདིར་ནི། །རྣམ་པ་སྟོང་དུ་མ་གས་པ། །སྙིང་གི་བདག་ཉིད་ཆེན་པོ་ནི། །རྡོ་རྗེ་ཆེན་པོ་བཞིན་གྱུར་ཏམ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-175"/>“ ‘Yet, in this unbearable moment, Why hasn’t this great being’s mind Been shattered into a thousand pieces, But is instead like a great vajra?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-431">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-176</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཤིས་པའི་དུས་ནི་ཀུན་དུ་འདས།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-176"/>“ ‘The good times are all gone.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-432">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-176</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།མི་བཟད་དུས་ནི་ཉེ་བར་གནས།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Unbearable times are now at hand.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-433">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-177</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཤེས་རབ་ལྡན་མི་མང་པོ་དང་། །འཇིག་རྟེན་དག་ཀྱང་བརླག་པར་འགྱུར།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>There will not be many wise people left And worldly ones will also be destroyed. <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-177"/>“</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-434">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-177</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཇི་ལྟ་ཇི་ལྟར་མཐོང་གྱུར་པའི། །ས་ཡི་མཚན་མ་དུ་མ་ཡིས། །ངེས་པར་ཡུན་ནི་མི་རིང་བར། །རྒྱལ་པོ་སེང་གེ་མེད་པར་འགྱུར།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>‘Through many omens of the earth, Which can be clearly seen, It is certain that it won’t be long Before the lion king is no more.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-435">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-179</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དྲི་མེད་མི་ཡི་ཉི་མ་འདི།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-179"/>“ ‘This stainless sun of humanity,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-436">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-179</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཤིན་ཏུ་རྙེད་དཀའ་དེ་ནུབ་འགྱུར།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>So difficult to find, is about to set.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-437">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-179</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཡུན་མི་རིང་བར་འཇིག་རྟེན་འདིར། །མི་སྣང་བ་ནི་འབྱུང་བར་འགྱུར།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Before long, it will no longer Shine forth in this world.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-438">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-180</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།སེམས་ཅན་ཀུན་ལ་ཕན་པ་ཡི། །རྒྱལ་པོ་ཆེན་པོ་འདི་མེད་དེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-180"/>“ ‘In the absence of this great king Who benefits all sentient beings,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-439">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-180</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཕྱི་ནས་འཇིག་རྟེན་མི་སྣང་ན།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>When his light no longer illumines the world,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-440">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-180</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།སུ་ཞིག་འཇིག་རྟེན་སྐྱོང་བར་འགྱུར།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Who will there be to protect the world?’</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-441">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-181</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ནས་ལྷའི་དབང་པོ་བརྒྱ་བྱིན་གྱིས་ཇི་ལྟ་ཇི་ལྟར་རྨོངས་པར་བྱས་པ་དེ་ལྟར་མྱ་ངན་ཆུང་བར་གྱུར་ནས་སོག་ལེས་བཏབ་པར་གྱུར་ཏོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-181"/>“After this speech, the two carpenters whom Śakra, lord of the gods, had enchanted recovered enough from their grief to reapply the saw to the bodhisattva’s body.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-442">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-181</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ནས་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔས་ཤིང་མཁན་དེ་གཉིས་ལ་བཞིན་བཟངས་དགེ་ཁྱེད་ཅག་གཉིས་ཀྱིས་སོག་ལེ་མྱུར་དུ་དྲོངས་ལ་ངའི་ལུས་ཀྱི་ཕྱེད་རོ་སྨད་ཆོད་ཅིག །བྲམ་ཟེ་འདི་ཤི་བར་གྱུར་ན་ངའི་ངལ་བ་འབྲས་བུ་མེད་པར་མི་འགྱུར་གྲང་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The bodhisattva encouraged them. ‘Well done, good people! Cut off the lower half of my body more quickly! Won’t my travail be fruitless if the brahmin dies?’</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-443">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-182</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་ཤིང་མཁན་དེ་གཉིས་བརྒྱ་བྱིན་གྱི་མཐུས་ཀུན་དུ་རྨོངས་པས་ཉམ་ཐག་པའི་ང་རོས་ཆོ་ངེས་འདེབས་ཤིང་སྐྱེ་བོའི་ཚོགས་ཆེན་པོས་བཀག་བཞིན་དུ་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་རང་གི་ལུས་ལ་སོག་ལེས་འདྲ་བར་བརྩམས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-182"/>“There was a great crowd of people wailing, mourning, and attempting to stop the two carpenters from following the bodhisattva’s instructions and cutting his body, but Śakra had stupefied them.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-444">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-182</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ནས་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་བྱང་ཆུབ་ཡིད་ལ་སྨོན་ཅིང་དགའ་བའི་ཡིད་ཀྱིས་སློང་བའི་ཡིད་ལ་རེ་བ་ཡོངས་སུ་རྫོགས་པར་བྱའོ་ཞེས་བསམས་ནས་ཅང་མི་སྨྲ་བར་གནས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The bodhisattva kept silent, aspiring for awakening and joyously intending to fulfill the gift seeker’s wishes.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-445">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-182</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ནས་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའི་ལུས་ཀྱི་ལྟེ་བར་སོག་ལེས་བཅད་པ་ལས་ཁྲག་གི་ཚོགས་ཆེན་པོ་འབབ་པར་གྱུར་ཏོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>After a while, a great deal of blood gushed from the bodhisattva’s middle where the saw was cutting.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-446">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-182</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ནས་བློན་པོ་བློ་གྲོས་ཆེན་པོ་འདི་ལྟར་སོག་ལེས་<tei:ref folio="F.45.b"/>བཅད་པ་ཚོར་བ་དྲག་པོས་ཉེན་པའི་ཁྲག་འབབ་པ་མཐོང་བ་དང་། ལྷ་བཀྲོངས་པ་ནི་སྡུག་བསྔལ་ལོ་ཞེས་བསམས་ནས་རེ་ཐག་ཆད་པར་གྱུར་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Seeing this, the great minister Mahāmati became despondent and fell unconscious, thinking, ‘It is too painful to see the lord killed.’</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-447">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-183</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཕྲལ་དུ་བརྒྱལ་ནས་སའི་སྟེང་དུ་འགྱེལ་བར་གྱུར་ཏོ། །ནམ་མཁའི་དཀྱིལ་ན་གནས་པའི་ལྷ་དང་། ཀླུ་དང་། གནོད་སྦྱིན་དང་། དྲི་ཟ་དང་། ལྷ་མ་ཡིན་དང་། ནམ་མཁའ་ལྡིང་དང་། མིའམ་ཅི་དང་། ལྟོ་འཕྱེ་ཆེན་པོའི་ཚོགས་རྣམས་ཀྱང་མྱ་ངན་དྲག་པོས་གདུངས་ཏེ་ངུ་བར་བརྩམས་ཏེ། དེ་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་ངུ་བའི་མཆི་མ་བླགས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-183"/>“Wracked by intense grief, masses of sky-dwelling gods, nāgas, yakṣas, gandharvas, asuras, garuḍas, kinnaras, and mahoragas started to cry.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-448">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-183</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ནས་སྐྱེ་བོའི་ཚོགས་ཆེན་པོས་འདི་ཅི་ཞིག་ཡིན་སྙམ་ནས་སྟེང་དུ་བལྟ་བར་བརྩམས་པ་དང་། ཇི་ཙམ་ན་ལྷ་བརྒྱ་སྟོང་དུ་མ་རྣམས་ངུ་བར་མཐོང་ངོ་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>As their tears flowed, the crowds of people below wondered what was happening and looked up at the sky. There they saw hundreds of thousands of weeping gods, which made them fall further into grief.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-449">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-183</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ནས་སྐྱེ་བོའི་ཚོགས་ཆེན་པོ་ཤས་ཆེར་མྱ་ངན་དྲག་པོས་གདུངས་ཏེ་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་གནས་སྐབས་འདི་ལྟ་བུར་ཤིན་ཏུ་སྡུག་བསྔལ་བར་མཐོང་ནས།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They saw the bodhisattva in great pain and, becoming utterly confused, they thought,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-450">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-184</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཀྱི་ཧུད་ལྷ་བཀྲོངས་པ་ནི་སྡུག་བསྔལ་ལོ་ཞེས་བསམས་ནས་ཀུན་དུ་རྨོངས་པར་གྱུར་ཏོ། །དེ་ནས་ལྷའི་དབང་པོ་བརྒྱ་བྱིན་དེ་སྲོག་ཆགས་བརྒྱ་སྟོང་དུ་མ་འདི་རྣམས་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའི་མྱ་ངན་གྱིས་གདུངས་པས་ཤིན་ཏུ་སྙིང་རྗེ་ཞིང་ཞུམ་པ་མཐོང་བ་དང་མྱུར་བར་སྙིང་རྗེའི་ཡིད་ཀྱིས་བསམས་པ་བདག་ཉིད་ཆེ་བ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>‘Alas! It is so very painful to see the lord killed!’<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-184"/> “A few moments later, Śakra, lord of the gods, gazed with intense compassion and concern upon the hundreds of thousands of beings who were stricken by the bodhisattva’s tragedy. Then compassionate thoughts suddenly arose in him.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-451">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-184</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སེམས་ཅན་ཐམས་ཅད་ལ་མཉེས་གཤིན་པ། སྙིང་རྗེ་ཅན་ཐམས་ཅད་སྟེར་བ་འདིའི་ལུས་ལ་འདི་ལྟར་ཚོར་བ་དྲག་པོའི་ལས་ཀུན་དུ་སྦྱོར་བ་ནི་བཟང་པོ་མ་ཡིན་ནོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>‘It is not right to cause intense pain to this great being who is so kind and affectionate toward all sentient beings and who gives away everything out of compassion.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-452">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-184</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།གཞན་དུ་ན་ད་ནི་ཇི་ལྟར་སྲོག་མི་འཇིག་པར་གྱུར་པ་དེ་ལྟར་བྱའོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>I will do the opposite. I will make him immortal.’</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-453">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-185</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ནས་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཤིང་མཁན་དེ་གཉིས་ཀྱིས་སོག་ལེས་དྲུད་ཅིང་སོག་ལེ་རྣོན་པོས་ལུས་བཅད་པའི་ཚོར་བ་དྲག་པོས་གདུངས་པ་དང་། བརྟན་པའི་སྟོབས་དང་ལྡན་པས་སློང་བ་ལ་བྱམས་པའི་སེམས་སྐྱེས་ནས་བསམས་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-185"/>“As the two carpenters cut his body with the sharp saw, the bodhisattva suffered intense pain. But he had the power to keep his mind stable and generate a loving attitude toward the gift seeker.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-454">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-185</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ངས་འཁོར་བའི་སྐྱོན་གྱི་རང་བཞིན་ཤེས་ནས་བརྩོན་འགྲུས་སྲ་ཞིང་བརྟན་པ་དང་ལྡན་པས་ལུས་ཕྱོགས་གཅིག་བཅད་པ་འདི་ལས་འདི་ལྟ་བུའི་སྡུག་བསྔལ་སྐྱེ་ན། སེམས་ཅན་སྔ་མ་རྣམས་ཕལ་ཆེར་དམྱལ་བར་སྐྱེས་ནས་ཤིན་ཏུ་སྡུག་བསྔལ་བའི་ཚོར་བ་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་གདུངས་པ་ལྟ་སྨོས་ཀྱང་ཅི་དགོས། དེ་ནས་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་ཅན་ཐམས་ཅད་ལ་རྗེས་སུ་འགྲོ་བ་<tei:ref folio="F.46.a"/>བྱམས་པའི་སེམས་རྣམ་པར་བཞག་སྟེ། བླ་ན་མེད་པ་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་བྱང་ཆུབ་མངོན་པར་རྫོགས་པར་སངས་རྒྱས་ནས་སེམས་ཅན་རྣམས་འདི་ལྟ་བུའི་སྡུག་བསྔལ་ལས་ཐར་བར་བྱའོ་ཞེས་སེང་གེའི་སྒྲ་བསྒྲགས་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>‘If I have understood the nature of saṃsāra’s faults and thereby gained firm and lasting perseverance but am nonetheless suffering this much pain as my body is cut in half, what can be said of the excruciating painful sensations suffered by the majority of sentient beings when they previously took rebirth in hell!’ Thinking thus, the bodhisattva established a loving mind that encompassed all sentient beings, and with a lion’s roar, he declared, ‘By attaining unsurpassed and perfect awakening, I must free sentient beings from such suffering!’</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-455">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-186</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྡུག་བསྔལ་དྲག་པོས་གདུངས་པའི་རང་གི་སེམས་སྤྲོ་བར་བྱ་བའི་ཕྱིར་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-186"/>“In order to uplift his own mind that was wracked by such intense pain, the bodhisattva also said the following:</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-456">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-186</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇིག་རྟེན་སྡུག་བསྔལ་ལྟོས་ལ་ཡིད་ཁྱོད་སྐྱོན་སྤངས་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“ ‘Look at the world’s suffering, mind, and abandon your faults!</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-457">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-186</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཤིན་ཏུ་བརྟན་པ་རྒྱ་ཆེ་བསྐྱེད་པ་ཉིད་དུ་གྱིས།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Be very steady and develop vastness in scope.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-458">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-186</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།འགྲོ་བ་སྐྱེ་རྒ་ན་འཆི་སྡུག་བསྔལ་གྱིས་གདུངས་པའི། །འདི་ནི་སྐྱབས་གྱུར་ཡིད་ཀྱིས་བཟོད་ཉིད་བརྟན་པར་གྱིས།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Be mentally stable in patient endurance so as to protect These beings tormented by the pain of birth, aging, sickness, and death.’</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-459">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-188</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།གཞན་ཡང་ཀྱེ་སེམས་ཅན།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-188"/>And again he said: “ ‘Alas, these poor sentient beings!</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-460">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-188</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་ཕྱིར་འགྲོ་ཀུན་འཁོར་བ་ཡི།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Because you are the cause for all beings</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-461">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-188</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།རྒྱ་མཚོ་ལས་རྒལ་རྒྱུ་ཡིན་གྱིས།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>To cross over the ocean of saṃsāra,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-462">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-188</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་བས་ཁྱོད་ནི་གནོད་པ་རྣམས།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>It would be unreasonable for you</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-463">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-188</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།མི་བཟོད་པ་ནི་རིགས་མ་ཡིན།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>To not patiently endure such harms.’</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-464">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-190</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ལྟར་རང་གི་སེམས་ཡང་དག་པར་བཞག་ནས་སེམས་ཅན་ཐམས་ཅད་རྗེས་སུ་འགྲོ་བའི་སྙིང་རྗེ་ཉེ་བར་བཞག་སྟེ་བསམས་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-190"/>“These were the ways the bodhisattva truly settled his mind and established a compassionate attitude toward all sentient beings.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-465">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-190</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཀྱེ་མའོ་འཁོར་བ་ན་གནས་པའི་སེམས་ཅན་གྱི་སྡུག་བསྔལ་ནི་ཀྱེ་མ་མི་བཟད་པ་ཡིན་ལ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He thought to himself, ‘Alas! The suffering of beings who are stuck in saṃsāra is unbearable.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-466">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-191</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཁོར་བའི་སེམས་ཅན་དེ་རྣམས་ཀྱི་དོན་དུ་འཁོར་བའི་སྡུག་བསྔལ་ཐམས་ཅད་མནགས་པར་སྤྲོ་བར་བྱས་ཀྱིས་སེམས་ཅན་འགའ་ཡང་སྡུག་བསྔལ་བའི་སྐལ་བ་ཅན་དུ་མ་གྱུར་ཅིག །དགེ་སློང་དག་སེམས་བསྐྱེད་མ་ཐག་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའི་ལུས་བཅད་པའི་ཚོར་བ་འཕྲལ་དུ་རྒྱུན་ཆད་པར་གྱུར་ཏོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>For the sake of these beings in saṃsāra, by rejoicing in patiently enduring all saṃsāra’s suffering, may no sentient being have the misfortune of suffering!’<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-191"/> “Monks, the very instant the bodhisattva generated this mind of awakening, the pain produced by his body being sawed abruptly ceased.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-467">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-191</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ནས་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔས་བསམས་པ། ཅིའི་ཕྱིར་ངའི་ལུས་བཅད་པའི་ཚོར་བ་འགགས་པར་གྱུར།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The bodhisattva wondered, ‘Why did the pain of my body being sawed in two cease?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-468">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-191</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སོག་ལེ་འགའ་ཞིག་གིས་བཏོན་པར་མ་གྱུར་གྲང་སྙམ་ནས་སོག་ལེ་དེ་ལ་བལྟས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Did they stop sawing?’ He checked, but he could still see the saw.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-469">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-191</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།བལྟས་ནས་ཀྱང་མཆོག་ཏུ་ཡིད་མི་བདེ་བར་གྱུར་ནས་འདར་བར་གྱུར་ཏོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Having seen it, he felt extremely distressed and started to shake.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-470">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-192</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ནས་ལྷའི་དབང་པོ་བརྒྱ་བྱིན་གྱིས་དེའི་བསམ་པ་ཤེས་ནས་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-192"/>“Reading the king’s mind, Śakra, lord of the gods, said:</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-471">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-192</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཉམ་ཆུང་ནད་པ་ཇི་བཞིན་དུ། །རྒྱལ་པོ་ཅི་ཕྱིར་འདར་བར་བྱེད།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“ ‘King, why do you shake so, Like a feeble, sickly person?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-472">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-192</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།བདག་གི་ལུས་ཕྱེད་བཅད་ན་ཡང་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Look at how my body is cut in half,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-473">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-192</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།སེམས་ནི་མི་འདར་བ་ལ་ལ་ལྟོས།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Yet my mind is not shaken.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-474">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-194</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཁྱོད་ནི་ཐམས་ཅད་སྟེར་བ་ཞེས། །ས་སྟེང་ཀུན་དུ་གྲགས་པ་ལ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-194"/>“ ‘You are renowned all over the earth For saying that you give everything away.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-475">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-194</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།འགྱོད་པར་བྱེད་པ་མི་རིགས་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>So it doesn’t make sense to feel regret,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-476">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-194</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཁྱོད་ཚིག་བརྫུན་དུ་མ་གྱུར་ཏམ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Or else your words would be lies.’</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-477">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-195</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ནས་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔས་སྨྲས་པ། བྲམ་ཟེ་དོན་དེའི་ཕྱིར་ལུས་འདར་བ་མ་ཡིན་ལ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-195"/>“ ‘Brahmin,’ responded the bodhisattva, ‘this is not why my body shakes.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-478">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-195</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འགྱོད་པར་གྱུར་<tei:ref folio="F.46.b"/>པ་འགའ་ཡང་ཡོད་པ་མ་ཡིན་ནོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>I have no regrets whatsoever.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-479">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-195</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།འོན་ཀྱང་སོག་ལེ་འདིས་ངའི་ལུས་ཀྱི་ཕྱེད་སྨད་ཚབས་ཆེར་ཞུགས་ཀྱང་མ་ཆོད་པ་དང་། དེ་ལ་ང་འདི་སྙམ་དུ་སེམས་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>I am shaking at this thought: “The saw has penetrated deep into my body, but so far my lower body has not been severed.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-480">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-195</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ངའི་སྦྱིན་པ་མ་རྫོགས་པར་མི་འགྱུར་གྲང་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>What if I am unable to make this gift?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-481">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-195</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ང་ལ་སློང་བའི་ཡིད་ལ་རེ་བ་ཡང་ཡོངས་སུ་རྫོགས་པར་མི་འགྱུར་གྲང་ཞེས་དོན་དེ་རྗེས་སུ་སེམས་ཤིང་ལུས་འདར་ཏེ་སོག་ལེས་དྲག་ཏུ་གཅོད་པར་མི་འདོད་པ་མ་ཡིན་ནོ། །དེ་ལ་དེ་སྐད་ཅེས་སྨྲས་པ་དང་ལྷའི་དབང་པོ་བརྒྱ་བྱིན་མཆོག་ཏུ་ངོ་མཚར་སྐྱེས་ནས་ཅང་མི་སྨྲ་བར་གནས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>What if I am not able to fulfill the gift seeker’s wish?” I would be happy if they were to saw my body with more force.’ Hearing this, Śakra, lord of the gods, was completely in awe of the bodhisattva and fell silent.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-482">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-196</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།བར་སྐབས་དེར་མི་དེ་གཉིས་བརྒྱ་བྱིན་གྱིས་ཀུན་དུ་རྨོངས་པར་བྱས་པས་དེ་གཉིས་ཀྱིས་སོག་ལེ་རྣོན་པོས་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའི་ལུས་ཀྱི་ཕྱེད་རོ་སྨད་བཅད་མ་ཐག་ཏུ་སའི་སྟེང་དུ་བཞག་པ་དང་འགུལ་བར་གྱུར་ཏོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-196"/>“In the meantime, the two carpenters whom Śakra had enchanted finished cutting the bodhisattva’s body in half. They placed the lower half of his body on the ground and it began to twitch.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-483">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-196</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ནས་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་རང་གི་ལུས་བཅད་པའི་སྡུག་བསྔལ་མི་སེམས་པར་རིངས་བག་ཉིད་དུ་སྐྱེས་བུ་དེ་གཉིས་ལ་འདི་སྐད་སྨྲས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Without thinking of his own suffering—the suffering of having his body cut in half—the bodhisattva addressed the two men:</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-484">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-196</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།བཞིན་བཟངས་དག་ཁྱོད་ཅག་གཉིས་ཀྱིས་མྱུར་དུ་ངའི་ལུས་འདི་རིངས་པ་རིངས་པར་བྲམ་ཟེའི་ལུས་ལ་སྦྱོར་ཅིག །དེ་གཉིས་ཀྱིས་ཀྱང་དེ་བཞིན་དུ་བྱས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>‘Good people, join my lower half to the brahmin’s body without delay.’ They did as he instructed.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-485">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-196</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།སྦྱར་བ་ཙམ་གྱིས་ལྷའི་དབང་པོ་བརྒྱ་བྱིན་གྱིས་ཇི་ལྟར་སྐད་ཅིག་མ་དེ་ཉིད་ལ་རྨ་ཀུན་དུ་འབྱོར་ཅིང་མཉམ་པར་གནས་པ་དང་། མདོག་འདྲ་བར་སྣང་བ་དེ་ལྟར་བྱིན་གྱིས་བརླབས་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>At the moment the two body halves were joined, Śakra, lord of the gods, imbued the body with a blessing that made its wounds heal, the joints join together well, and the two bodies’ skin tones match.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-486">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-196</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྐད་ཅིག་མ་དེ་ལ་སྟོན་ཅིང་ཡང་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་དགའ་བར་བྱ་བའི་ཕྱིར་ལྷའི་དབང་པོ་བརྒྱ་བྱིན་ཁྲི་ལས་ལངས་ཏེ་འཆག་པ་དང་ལངས་པ་དང་འདུག་པར་གྱུར་ཏོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He showed everyone the body, and to please the bodhisattva, he, Śakra, lord of the gods, stood up from his stretcher, walked around, stood still, and then sat down.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-487">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-197</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ནས་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་དེ་ལྟར་སློང་བ་པོའི་ལུས་ཡོངས་སུ་རྫོགས་ཤིང་ཡིད་ལ་རེ་བ་ཡོངས་སུ་རྫོགས་པར་མཐོང་བ་དང་མཆོག་ཏུ་དགའ་བས་ཀུན་དུ་རྒྱས་པའི་ཡིད་ཀྱིས་ངལ་བ་འབྲས་བུ་དང་བཅས་པར་གྱུར་ཅིང་ཡིད་ལ་རེ་བ་ཡོངས་སུ་རྫོགས་པར་གྱུར་ཏོ་སྙམ་ནས་རབ་ཏུ་དགའ་བའི་ཡིད་ཀྱིས་བསམས་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-197"/>“Seeing that his labors had borne fruit, that the gift seeker had a complete body and his wishes had been fulfilled, the bodhisattva’s mind overflowed with joy.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-488">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-197</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཇི་ལྟར་ངས་བྲམ་ཟེ་འདི་ལ་རང་གི་ལུས་བྱིན་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>‘I have saved this brahmin’s life,’ he thought to himself, ‘and staved off his fear of death by giving him my body.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-489">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-198</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྡུག་པའི་སྲོག་གིས་བསྐྱབས་ཤིང་འཆི་བའི་འཇིགས་པ་ལས་ཡོངས་སུ་བསྐྱབས་པའི་དགེ་བའི་རྩ་བ་འདིས་འདི་ལྟར་ང་བླ་ན་མེད་པ་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་བྱང་ཆུབ་ཏུ་མངོན་པར་རྫོགས་པར་སངས་རྒྱས་ནས་བྲམ་ཟེ་འདི་འཁོར་བའི་སྡུག་བསྔལ་ལས་བསླངས་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>May the seed of this virtue cause me to attain unsurpassed and perfect awakening. Then may I be able to rescue this brahmin from the suffering of saṃsāra and establish him in nirvāṇa where he will experience the ultimate happiness.’ <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-198"/>“As he thought this, the bodhisattva was overwhelmed.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-490">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-198</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཤིན་ཏུ་<tei:ref folio="F.47.a"/>མཐར་ཐུག་པའི་བདེ་བ་མྱ་ངན་ལས་འདས་པ་ལ་རབ་ཏུ་འཇོག་པར་གྱུར་ཅིག་ཅེས་སྨྲས་ནས་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཚོར་བ་དྲག་པོས་གདུངས་པ་དང་། ཡིད་ཀྱིས་བྱང་ཆུབ་ཏུ་སྨོན་པ་བྱས་ནས་མིག་བཙུམས་ཏེ་བརྒྱལ་བས་གནས་པར་གྱུར་ཏོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Even as he aspired to awaken, he slipped into unconsciousness, and his eyes began to close.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-491">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-198</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ནས་ལྷའི་དབང་པོ་བརྒྱ་བྱིན་གྱིས་དེ་མ་ཐག་ཏུ་རིངས་པ་རིངས་པར་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའི་ལུས་ལ་འཕྲལ་དུ་སྟོབས་བསྐྱེད་པ་ཡང་འཚོ་བའི་སྨན་གྱིས་ཡང་དག་པར་གསོས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Śakra, lord of the gods, revived him immediately. He used medicines and care to treat and heal him.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-492">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-199</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དགེ་སློང་དག་དེ་ནས་རྒྱལ་པོ་དཔལ་གྱི་སྡེའི་ལུས་ཀྱི་ཕྱེད་བཅད་པའི་རྗེས་ཐོགས་ཉིད་ལ་ཡང་དེའི་ཚེ་སྟོང་གསུམ་གྱི་སྟོང་ཆེན་པོའི་འཇིག་རྟེན་གྱི་ཁམས་འདི་ལན་རྣམ་པ་གསུམ་དུ་གཡོས་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-199"/>“Monks, in the instant King Śrīsena’s body was cut in half, the trichiliocosm shook in three different ways:</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-493">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-199</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཡོས་རབ་ཏུ་གཡོས། ཀུན་དུ་རབ་ཏུ་གཡོས། འགུལ་རབ་ཏུ་འགུལ། ཀུན་དུ་རབ་ཏུ་འགུལ་ཏོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>it shook, shook a lot, and shook extremely much.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-494">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-199</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཤིན་ཏུ་ཡོངས་སུ་གཏོང་བ་ཉིད་དང་། རྨད་དུ་བྱུང་བའི་ཡོངས་སུ་གཏོང་བ་ཉིད་ས་ཆེན་པོ་འདིས་མ་ཐེག་པས་སྒྲ་ཤིན་ཏུ་སྒྲོགས་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>It also rocked, rocked a lot, and rocked extremely much. This great earth was unable to support the bodhisattva’s great act of generosity.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-495">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-199</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདི་ལྟ་སྟེ་ཁར་བའི་སྣོད་ཆེན་པོ་ཀུན་དུ་བརྡུངས་ནས་སྒྲ་འབྱིན་པ་བཞིན་དུ་དེའི་ཚེ་དེའི་དུས་ན་ས་ཆེན་པོ་འདི་ཉིད་ཤིན་ཏུ་སྒྲ་སྒྲོགས་པར་གྱུར་ཏོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>It was a marvelous gift of everything and thus it resounded—it resounded as if all the world’s cauldrons had been beaten at once.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-496">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-199</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།རི་དང་རི་སུལ་དང་ཆུ་བོ་དང་རྒྱ་མཚོའི་ཚོགས་རྣམས་ལས་ཀྱང་འཇིགས་པའི་སྒྲ་ཆེན་པོ་བྱུང་བར་གྱུར་ཏོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Mountains, ravines, rivers, and oceans all emitted horrifying noises.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-497">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-199</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཕྱོགས་བཞི་ནས་ཀྱང་འཇིགས་སུ་རུང་བའི་དུ་བའི་སྤྲིན་ཆེན་པོ་བྱུང་བར་གྱུར་ཏོ། །ཀུན་ནས་སྐར་མདའ་ལྟུང་བ་དང་། ཕྱོགས་སྲེག་པ་དང་། བར་སྣང་ལ་ཡང་ལྷའི་བུ་རྣམས་རྔ་རྡུང་བར་གྱུར་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Terrifying smoke appeared from the four directions. Meteors fell from all sides. Falling stars blazed in every direction. The gods beat drums in the sky.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-498">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-200</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྟོང་གསུམ་གྱི་སྟོང་ཆེན་པོའི་འཇིག་རྟེན་གྱི་ཁམས་འདི་ཐམས་ཅད་མུན་པ་མུན་ནག་ཏུ་གྱུར་ཏོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-200"/>“The trichiliocosm first darkened and then turned pitch black.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-499">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-200</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ནམ་མཁའི་དཀྱིལ་ན་འགྲོ་བའི་ལྷ་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་ཀྱང་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའི་མྱ་ངན་གྱིས་གདུངས་པས་ཅ་ཅོའི་སྒྲ་བཏོན་ཏོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Even the gods traversing the center of the sky chattered about a bodhisattva tormented with sorrow.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-500">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-200</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།བར་སྣང་ལས་ཀྱང་ལྷ་རྣམས་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའི་སྟེང་ནས་ལྷའི་ཨུད་པ་ལ་རྣམས་འཐོར་ཞིང་པད་མ་དང་། པུན་ད་རཱི་ཀ་དང་། ཨ་ཀ་རུའི་ཕྱེ་མ་དང་། ཏ་ག་རུའི་ཕྱེ་མ་དང་། ཏ་མ་ལའི་ལོ་མའི་ཕྱེ་མ་དང་། ཙན་དན་གྱི་ཕྱེ་མ་དང་། ལྷ་རྣམས་ཀྱི་མེ་ཏོག་མན་དཱ་ར་བ་རྣམས་ཀྱང་འཐོར་རོ། །གོས་རྣམས་ཀྱང་འཐོར་བར་བྱེད་དོ། །ལྷའི་རོལ་མོ་ཡང་རབ་ཏུ་རྡུང་ངོ་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They arranged utpala flowers above the bodhisattva and showered him with pink and white lotus flowers. They also sprinkled agaru, tagara, cinnamon-leaf, and sandalwood incense on him, and the flowers of the gods’ tree, the mandārava.<tei:note xml:id="UT22084-076-003-201"/> They even draped their clothes on him, danced, and played divine music loudly.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-501">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-200</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།འཛམ་བུའི་གླིང་གི་མི་ཐམས་ཅད་དེར་ཡུད་ཙམ་ཞིག་མཆོག་ཏུ་རྨོངས་པར་གྱུར་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>All of Jambudvīpa’s people were deeply puzzled by these noises.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-502">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-202</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།<tei:ref folio="F.47.b"/>གྲོང་ཁྱེར་ན་གནས་པའི་སྲོག་ཆགས་བརྒྱ་སྟོང་དུ་མ་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའི་ལུས་ཀྱི་ཕྱེད་བཅད་པ་མཐོང་བ་དང་། སྡུག་བསྔལ་དྲག་པོས་གདུངས་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-202"/>“When the city’s inhabitants, hundreds and thousands of people, saw the bodhisattva’s body cut, they were tormented by intense grief.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-503">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-202</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཀྱི་ཧུད་ལྷ་བསད་པ་ནི་སྡུག་བསྔལ་ལོ་ཞེས་སྒྲ་གཅིག་ཏུ་བསྒྲགས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>With a single voice they cried out in their grief, ‘Alas, seeing the lord killed is painful!’</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-504">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-203</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ནས་ལ་ལ་ནི་ས་ལ་འགྲེ་ལྡོག་གོ། །ལ་ལ་ནི་དཔུང་པ་བརྐྱང་ནས་ཆོ་ངེས་འདེབས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-203"/>“Some rolled on the ground, others flailed their arms and wailed.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-505">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-203</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ལ་ལ་ནི་མཆི་མའི་རླབས་ཀྱིས་སྐད་འཛེར་བར་ཚིག་འདོན་མི་ནུས་ཏེ། སྐད་ཆེན་པོ་དང་བྲང་རྡུང་ངོ་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The voices of some became hoarse from passionate sobbing. They were unable to clearly voice their words, yet still they screamed and beat their chests.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-506">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-203</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ལ་ལ་ནི་མི་རྟག་པ་ཉིད་ཀྱི་སྟོབས་དང་ལྡན་ཞེས་སེམས་སྡུག་བསྔལ་དང་བཅས་ཤིང་ཡིད་མི་བདེ་བ་དང་ལྡན་པས་ཅང་མི་སྨྲ་བར་འདུག་གོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Others remained silent, their minds mournful and unsettled, thinking, ‘Impermanence is powerful indeed!’</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-507">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-204</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ནས་ལྷའི་དབང་པོ་བརྒྱ་བྱིན་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་བླ་ན་མེད་པ་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་བྱང་ཆུབ་ལས་རི་རབ་ལྟར་ཤིན་ཏུ་མི་གཡོ་བར་ཤེས་ཤིང་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའི་རྨད་དུ་བྱུང་བ་ཡོངས་སུ་གཏོང་ལ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-204"/>“Śakra, lord of the gods, was convinced that the bodhisattva’s resolve to attain unsurpassed and perfect awakening was as immovable as Mount Sumeru. He marveled at how the bodhisattva had given so completely.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-508">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-204</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ཡང་བ་སྤུ་ལྡང་བ་ནི་ཤིན་ཏུ་དགའ་ཞིང་ཕུལ་དུ་དབྱུང་བ་མཐོང་བ་དང་། ངོ་མཚར་གྱིས་མིག་གདངས་ཏེ་ལྷའི་བུ་དེ་བཞི་དང་ལྷན་ཅིག་ཏུ་བྲམ་ཟེའི་ཆ་བྱད་མི་སྣང་བར་བྱས་ནས་རང་གི་གཟུགས་ཀྱིས་གནས་ཏེ་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་ལ་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The hairs on his body stood on end. He was filled with joy and witnessed something outstanding. Marveling at this, he opened his eyes, and together with the other four gods, he dissolved his brahmin semblance, and he and the four gods appeared in their own forms. Śakra then spoke to the bodhisattva:</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-509">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-204</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྒྱལ་པོ་ཆེན་པོ་བདག་ནི་ལྷའི་དབང་པོ་བརྒྱ་བྱིན་ལགས་ཀྱི་བྲམ་ཟེ་མ་ལགས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>‘Great King! I am no brahmin, I am Śakra, lord of the gods.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-510">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-204</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།རྒྱལ་པོ་ཆེན་པོ་ལེགས་སོ་ལེགས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Well done, Great King, well done!</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-511">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-204</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཀྱེ་མའོ་ཁྱོད་ཀྱི་བརྩོན་འགྲུས།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>How amazing, your diligence!</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-512">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-204</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཀྱེ་མའོ་མ་བཅོས་པར་བརྟན་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>How amazing, your uncontrived resolve!</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-513">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-204</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཀྱེ་མའོ་རང་གི་ལུས་ལ་མ་ཆགས་པར་ཡོངས་སུ་གཏོང་བ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>How amazing that you gave your body so completely, without clinging!</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-514">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-204</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཀྱེ་མའོ་སེམས་ཅན་རྣམས་ལ་སྙིང་བརྩེ་བ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>How amazing, your compassion toward sentient beings and love for them!</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-515">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-204</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཀྱེ་མའོ་སྦྱིན་པ་ལ་དགའ་བ་ལེགས་སོ་ལེགས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Your joy in giving! Well done, well done!</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-516">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-204</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།རྒྱལ་པོ་ཆེན་པོ་ཁྱོད་གང་དུ་སྡུག་བསྔལ་དྲག་པོས་བཅོམ་ཡང་སྙིང་རྗེས་རང་གི་ལུས་སྦྱིན་པ་ལ་སེམས་མི་ལྡོག་པ་དེ་ནི་ལེགས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Great King, even though you were overwhelmed by intense suffering, you did not change your mind about giving away your body.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-517">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-204</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།རྒྱལ་པོ་ཆེན་པོ་ཁྱོད་ལ་དྲི་ཡིས་ཁྱོད་ཤིན་ཏུ་དཀའ་བའི་བརྩོན་པ་འདི་ལྟ་བུས་ཅི་ཞིག་དོན་དུ་གཉེར།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Great King, I have a question for you: what was the reason you underwent such hardship and such a prolonged trial?’</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-518">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-205</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔས་སྨྲས་པ། ཀཽ་ཤི་ཀ་ངའི་ལུས་ཀྱི་སྦྱིན་པ་འདིས་བླ་ན་མེད་པ་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་བྱང་ཆུབ་མངོན་པར་རྫོགས་པར་སངས་རྒྱས་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-205"/>“ ‘Kauśika,’ replied the bodhisattva, ‘by giving away my body, I wish to attain unsurpassed and perfect awakening.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-519">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-205</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སེམས་ཅན་རྣམས་འཁོར་བ་ལས་བསྒྲལ་བར་བྱའོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>I wish to liberate sentient beings from saṃsāra.’</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-520">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-206</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།བརྒྱ་བྱིན་གྱིས་སྨྲས་པ། རྒྱལ་པོ་ཆེན་པོ་ཁྱོད་རང་གི་ལུས་ཡོངས་སུ་ཟད་པའམ། གཏོང་བའམ། ཡོངས་སུ་བཏང་བས་ཁྱོད་ཀྱི་<tei:ref folio="F.48.a"/>སེམས་རྣམ་པ་གཞན་དུ་གྱུར་པའམ། འགྱོད་པར་མ་གྱུར་གྲང་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-206"/>“Śakra then asked, ‘Great King, as your body was deteriorating, as you offered your body, as you gave it away completely, did you have any regrets? Did your mental state change at all?’</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-521">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-206</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔས་སྨྲས་པ། ཀཽ་ཤི་ཀ་ང་ལ་ནི་འགྱོད་པ་མེད་དོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“ ‘Kauśika, I had no regrets,’ replied the bodhisattva.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-522">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-208</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།བརྒྱ་བྱིན་གྱིས་སྨྲས་པ། ཇི་ལྟར་ཤེས་པར་བྱ། བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔས་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-208"/>“ ‘How can we know this?’ Śakra asked. “ ‘Kauśika,’ said the bodhisattva, ‘to prove it, I will allow you to place the lower half of my body wherever you like.’</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-523">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-210</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཀཽ་ཤི་ཀ་དེའི་ཕྱིར་ངའི་ལུས་ཀྱི་ཕྱེད་བཅད་པ་འདི་གནས་ཇི་ལྟ་བ་བཞིན་དུ་ཞོག་ཤིག །དེ་ནས་ལྷའི་དབང་པོ་བརྒྱ་བྱིན་གྱིས་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའི་ལུས་ཀྱི་ཕྱེད་བཅད་པ་དེ་གནས་ཇི་ལྟ་བ་བཞིན་དུ་བཞག་གོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-210"/>“Śakra, lord of the gods, then put the lower half of the bodhisattva’s body in a place of his liking.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-524">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-210</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ནས་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔས་སེམས་ཅན་ཐམས་ཅད་ལ་རྗེས་སུ་འགྲོ་བའི་བྱམས་པའི་སེམས་ཉེ་བར་བཞག་ནས་བདེན་པ་གསོལ་བར་བྱེད་ཅིང་དེའི་ཚེ་ཚིགས་སུ་བཅད་དེ་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The bodhisattva established a loving attitude toward all sentient beings, and invoking truth at that time, he spoke the following verses:</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-525">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-211</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཇི་ལྟར་བྱང་ཆུབ་འདོད་གྱུར་ནས། །སྙིང་རྗེས་ལུས་ནི་བཏང་བས་ན། །སེར་སྣ་མེད་ཅིང་ཞུམ་མེད་དེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-211"/>“ ‘As I wish for awakening, I did not experience miserliness or sadness When I let go of my body compassionately.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-526">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-211</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེང་ནི་འགྱོད་པར་གྱུར་པ་མེད།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Now, I have no regrets.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-527">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-212</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།འགྱོད་པའི་སེམས་ཀྱང་མེད་གྱུར་ན།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-212"/>“ ‘And as I have no regrets, Śakra,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-528">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-212</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།བདེན་ཚིག་འདི་དང་ལེགས་བྱས་པས།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>May the truth of my words and goodness of my actions</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-529">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-212</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།བརྒྱ་བྱིན་དེང་ནི་ང་ཡི་ལུས།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Now restore my body,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-530">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-212</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།འདི་ནི་སྔོན་གྱི་ཇི་བཞིན་དུ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Exactly as it was before.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-531">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-213</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དབང་པོ་མ་ལུས་རྫོགས་གྱུར་ཅིག །དགེ་སློང་དག་ཚིགས་སུ་བཅད་པ་དེ་སྨྲས་པའི་རྗེས་ཐོགས་ཉིད་ལ་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའི་ལུས་འཕྲལ་དུ་སྔོན་གྱི་ཇི་ལྟ་བ་བཞིན་དུ་གྱུར་ཏོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>May all my senses be complete!’<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-213"/> “Monks, as soon as he spoke these verses, the bodhisattva’s body was restored.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-532">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-213</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ནམ་མཁའི་དཀྱིལ་ན་གནས་པའི་ལྷ་དང་། ཀླུ་དང་། གནོད་སྦྱིན་དང་། ནམ་མཁའ་ལྡིང་དང་། མིའམ་ཅི་དང་། ལྟོ་འཕྱེ་ཆེན་པོ་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་ངོ་མཚར་དེ་མཐོང་བ་དང་། ངོ་མཚར་ཀྱིས་མིག་གདངས་ཏེ། ཅ་ཅོ་དང་ག་ཞའི་སྒྲ་སྒྲོགས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The sky-dwelling gods, nāgas, yakṣas, garuḍas, kinnaras, and mahoragas who witnessed this were wide-eyed in amazement and started babbling and laughing.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-533">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-213</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།སྐྱེ་བོའི་ཚོགས་ཆེན་པོ་འདི་དག་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱིས་ཀྱང་ངོ་མཚར་དང་རྨད་དུ་བྱུང་བ་དང་། ལྷ་དང་མི་རྣམས་ཡིད་སྡུག་པར་བྱེད་པའི་ཆོ་འཕྲུལ་དང་། བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའི་ལུས་ཡོངས་སུ་རྫོགས་པ་མཐོང་བ་དང་སྲོག་སྟོར་བ་ལས་སླར་རྙེད་པ་བཞིན་དུ་མཆོག་ཏུ་ངོ་མཚར་སྐྱེས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The crowds of people gathered there were also awed and amazed. Both gods and humans were overjoyed at this magical display. When they saw that the bodhisattva’s body was completely restored, they developed wonder as if they had found their own lives after having lost them.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-534">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-213</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་ཀྱང་སྨྲས་ཏེ། ཀྱེ་མ་ཁྱེད་ནི་སླར་འཚོ་བའི། །ངོ་མཚར་དག་ནི་བལྟ་བར་གྱིས།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They said, ‘How amazing! Let us gaze upon this marvel of your resurrection!</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-535">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-213</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ས་དང་ནགས་སུ་བཅས་པ་ཡི། །འཇིག་རྟེན་འདི་ནི་སྐལ་བར་ལྡན།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The beings of this world, those on the land and in the forest, are fortunate indeed!’</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-536">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-214</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ནས་ལྷའི་དབང་པོ་བརྒྱ་བྱིན་གྱིས་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའི་ལུས་སྔོན་གྱི་ཇི་ལྟ་བ་བཞིན་དུ་གྱུར་པར་མཐོང་བ་དང་ངོ་མཚར་གྱིས་གདུངས་པའི་མིག་དང་། སྤྲོ་བ་བསྐྱེད་པའི་ཕྱིར་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-214"/>“When Śakra, lord of the gods, saw that the bodhisattva’s body had been restored to its original state, he was overwhelmed. To please the bodhisattva, he said, ‘Great King, your mind is heroic.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-537">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-214</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྒྱལ་པོ་ཆེན་པོ་ཁྱོད་ཀྱི་བླ་ཤིན་<tei:ref folio="F.48.b"/>ཏུ་དེས་པ་དང་། ཁྱོད་ཀྱི་སྨོན་ལམ་མི་འགྱུར་བ་དང་། ཁྱོད་ཀྱི་སེམས་ཅན་ལ་སྙིང་རྗེ་ཆེན་པོས་རྗེས་སུ་ཞུགས་པ་ནི་ལེགས་སོ་ལེགས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Your aspiration is steadfast, and you engage with sentient beings out of great compassion. Well done, well done!</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-538">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-214</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།གང་ཡང་ཁྱོད་ནི་ཡིད་ཀུན་དུ་སྐྲག་པར་བྱེད་པ་རྣམས་ལ་མི་འཇིགས་པས་ཁྱོད་ཀྱི་འབད་པ་འདི་ཉིད་ཀྱིས་ཡུན་རིང་པོར་མི་ཐོགས་པར་བླ་ན་མེད་པ་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་བྱང་ཆུབ་མངོན་པར་རྫོགས་པར་འཚང་རྒྱ་བར་འགྱུར་རོ། །ལྷའི་དབང་པོ་བརྒྱ་བྱིན་གྱིས་དེའི་ཚེ་ཚིགས་སུ་བཅད་དེ་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>You are not afraid of anyone who attempts to frighten you. Due to your efforts, you will, therefore, attain unsurpassed and perfect awakening in a short while.’ Śakra, lord of the gods, then recited the following verses:</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-539">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-215</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཀྱེ་མ་ཁྱོད་ཀྱི་བརྩོན་རབ་དྲག །བརྟན་པ་ཉིད་ཀྱང་བླ་ན་མེད།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-215"/>“ ‘Ah! Your diligence is great and fierce. Your steadfastness is unsurpassed.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-540">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-215</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཀྱེ་མའོ་སེམས་ཅན་ལ་སྙིང་བརྩེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Ah! Your compassion for beings!</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-541">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-215</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཀྱེ་མའོ་བྱང་ཆུབ་ཡིད་ལ་བརྟན།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Ah! Your determination to awaken!</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-542">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-216</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཀྱེ་མའོ་མི་རིང་འཇིག་རྟེན་འདི།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-216"/>“ ‘Ah! How wonderful would the world be</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-543">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-216</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།མགོན་པོ་ཁྱོད་ཀྱིས་སྐྱོང་གྱུར་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>If you, lord, were its ruler!</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-544">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-216</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།སྡུག་བསྔལ་རྒྱ་མཚོ་དྲག་འཇིགས་ལས།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>You will travel beyond suffering’s fearful and ferocious ocean;</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-545">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-216</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཡང་དག་མྱ་ངན་འདའ་བར་མཛད།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>You will attain nirvāṇa!’</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-546">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-217</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་སྐད་ཅེས་སྨྲས་པ་དང་། ལྷའི་དབང་པོ་བརྒྱ་བྱིན་མཆི་མ་ཆར་བཞིན་དུ་འབབ་ཅིང་སྐད་འཛེར་བཞིན་དུ་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་ལ་བཟོད་པ་གསོལ་བར་བརྩམས་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-217"/>“As he said these words, Śakra, lord of the gods, shed tears like rain, and in a hoarse voice he sought forgiveness from the bodhisattva.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-547">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-217</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྒྱལ་པོ་ཆེན་པོ་གང་བདག་གིས་ཉམས་བསྐྱེད་པའི་བསམ་པས་ཚོར་བ་དྲག་པོ་ལས་ཀུན་དུ་སྦྱོར་བར་མཛོད་ཅིག །གཞན་ཡང་གང་གི་ཚེ་ཁྱོད་ཀྱིས་བླ་ན་མེད་པ་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་བྱང་ཆུབ་མངོན་པར་རྫོགས་པར་སངས་རྒྱས་པ་དེའི་ཚེ་ན་ཡང་བདག་ལ་དགོངས་ཤིག །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>‘O Great King,’ he said, ‘thinking that you might meet with failure, I coerced you to suffer excruciating pain. Please forgive me.<tei:note xml:id="UT22084-076-003-218"/> And please think of me when you attain unsurpassed and perfect awakening.’</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-548">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-219</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔས་སྨྲས་པ། ཀཽ་ཤི་ཀ་བཟོད་ཀྱིས་དེ་བཞིན་དུ་བྱས་ཏེ་ངས་ཀྱང་དྲན་པར་བྱའོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-219"/>“ ‘Kauśika,’ replied the bodhisattva, ‘I am patient.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-549">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-219</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།བར་སྐབས་དེར་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའི་མཐུས་དེ་མ་ཐག་ཏུ་ནམ་མཁའ་ལས་ལྷའི་རིན་པོ་ཆེའི་ཆར་རྣམ་པ་སྣ་ཚོགས་པ་ཡིད་དུ་འོང་བ་འཛམ་བུའི་གླིང་ཐམས་ཅད་དུ་བབ་པར་གྱུར་ཅིང་འཛམ་བུའི་གླིང་ཐམས་ཅད་དུ་རྒྱན་རྣམ་པ་སྣ་ཚོགས་ཀྱིས་གང་བར་གྱུར་པ། ལྷའི་སྣང་བ་བས་ཀྱང་གསལ་བར་གྱུར་ཏོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>I will do as you ask and remember you.’ In that instant, due to the bodhisattva’s power, a variety of divine, enchanting, precious gems rained down upon all of Jambudvīpa. All of Jambudvīpa was ornamented by myriad precious stones, and it became even brighter than the realms of the gods.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-550">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-220</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ནས་རི་ལ་གནས་པའི་དྲང་སྲོང་དེ་ངོ་མཚར་འདི་ལྟ་བུ་རྨད་དུ་བྱུང་བ་མཐོང་བ་དང་། ངོ་མཚར་གྱིས་བསྡུས་པའི་ཡིད་ཀྱིས་བསམས་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-220"/>“The sage who lived in the mountains had witnessed all these marvels, and he was overwhelmed.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-551">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-220</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྔོན་མ་བྱུང་བའི་ངོ་མཚར་བྱུང་བ་འདི་ཅི་ཞིག་ཡིན།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>‘What are these marvels?’ he thought. ‘Have such marvels ever been seen before?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-552">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-220</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདི་ལྟ་བུའི་མཐུ་སུའི་ཡིན་སྙམ་མོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Whose power occasions this?’</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-553">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-221</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ནས་དྲང་སྲོང་དེ་ལ་བསྟི་གནས་ན་གནས་པའི་ལྷ་གཞན་གྱིས་གཏམ་འདི་རྒྱས་པར་སྨྲས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-221"/>“A god who lived in the same place as he told him the story in detail.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-554">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-221</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ནས་དྲང་སྲོང་དེ་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའི་ཤིན་ཏུ་དཀའ་ཞིང་བ་<tei:ref folio="F.49.a"/>སྤུ་ལྡང་བའི་སྐད་ཐོས་པ་དང་ཡང་དག་པར་དགའ་བས་བ་སྤུ་ལྡང་ཞིང་སེམས་ཅན་ཆེན་པོ་བཀུར་བར་འོས་ཞེས་བསམས་ནས་འཁོར་ལྔ་བརྒྱ་དང་བཙུན་མོ་རྒྱལ་བའི་འོད་ཁྲིད་དེ་རིངས་པ་རིངས་པར་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའི་ཐད་དུ་ཕྱིན་ནས།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>As he listened to the story of the bodhisattva’s extraordinary, awe-inspiring austerities, the sage came to genuinely admire him. ‘This great being is worthy of veneration,’ he thought. After that, he hastily led his five-hundred-strong retinue and Queen Jayaprabhā to the bodhisattva.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-555">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-221</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྒྱལ་བ་དང་ཚེ་འཕེལ་བར་བྱས་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>There they uttered salutations of victory and long life to the king.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-556">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-221</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བརྒྱ་བྱིན་དང་ལྷན་ཅིག་སྨྲས་པ། ལྷ་ཡི་བུ་མོ་བཟང་འདྲ་བའི། །བུ་མོ་སྡུག་པ་འདི་རྣམས་ལ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>In unison with Śakra, the sage said, ‘Lord, you have protected these fine, goddess-like, beautiful women.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-557">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-221</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།མགོན་པོ་ཁྱོད་ཀྱིས་བསྐྱང་བ་དང་། །དགེ་མ་འདི་དང་དགྱེས་པར་མཛོད།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Now please enjoy life with this virtuous woman.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-558">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-221</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཁྱིམ་ཐབ་མི་འཕྱོ་བཙུན་མོ་སྡུག །འདི་ནི་ཁྱེད་ལ་དབུལ་ལགས་ཀྱིས།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>I offer you back the beautiful queen. She has not been unhappy with her husband.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-559">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-223</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཁྱེད་ཀྱིས་ཡང་ནི་སློང་བ་ལ། །ནམ་དུ་ཡང་ནི་མ་སྩལ་ཅིག །དེ་ནས་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔས་དྲང་སྲོང་དེ་དང་ལྷ་རྣམས་ཀྱི་དབང་པོ་བརྒྱ་བྱིན་གྱིས་གསོལ་བ་བཏབ་པ་སྙིང་རྗེས་ཅི་ཡང་མི་སྨྲ་བར་ཁས་བླངས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Please do not give her away again to anyone else who asks for her.’<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-223"/> “The bodhisattva compassionately accepted the request of the sage and Śakra, lord of the gods, by remaining silent.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-560">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-223</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ནས་ལྷའི་དབང་པོ་བརྒྱ་བྱིན་གྱིས་ལྷའི་བུ་ལས་སྣ་ཚོགས་པ་ལ་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Śakra, lord of the gods, then summoned Viśvakarma, the architect of the gods.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-561">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-223</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལས་སྣ་ཚོགས་པ་ལྷའི་སེང་གེའི་ཁྲི་མྱུར་དུ་ཤོམས་ཤིག །ང་ཉིད་ཀྱིས་རྒྱལ་པོ་དཔལ་གྱི་སྡེ་དབང་བསྐུར་བར་བྱའོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>‘Viśvakarma,’ he said, ‘please set up a divine lion throne quickly. I would like to honor King Śrīsena myself.’</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-562">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-224</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཀཽ་ཤི་ཀ་ལེགས་ཀྱིས་དེ་ལྟར་བགྱིའོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-224"/>“ ‘That is excellent, Kauśika,’ Viśvakarma responded.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-563">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-224</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ལྷའི་བུ་ལས་སྣ་ཚོགས་པས་ལྷའི་དབང་པོ་བརྒྱ་བྱིན་ལས་མཉན་ནས་སྐད་ཅིག་མ་དེ་ཉིད་ལ་རིན་པོ་ཆེ་སྣ་ཚོགས་ཀྱིས་ཉེ་བར་མཛེས་པ། ཀུན་ནས་མུ་ཏིག་དང་། མུ་ཏིག་གི་ཚོགས་ཀྱི་དོ་ཤལ་འཕྱང་བའི་ལྷའི་སེང་གེའི་ཁྲི་མངོན་པར་སྤྲུལ་ཏོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>‘I will do as you instruct.’ Indeed, at the very moment he was listening to Śakra, lord of the gods, Viśvakarma, the architect of the gods, magically created a lion throne. It was decorated with a variety of precious gems, and it was garlanded with pearls on all sides.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-564">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-224</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ནས་ལྷའི་དབང་པོ་བརྒྱ་བྱིན་གྱིས་རང་ཉིད་ཀྱི་ལག་པ་གཉིས་ཀྱིས་བཟུང་ནས་ལྷའི་སེང་གེའི་ཁྲི་ལ་བཞག་སྟེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Śakra, lord of the gods, took the bodhisattva with both his hands and escorted him onto the divine lion throne.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-565">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-224</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལྷ་བརྒྱ་སྟོང་དུ་མ་རྣམས་དང་ལྷན་ཅིག་ཏུ་ལྷའི་རོལ་མོ་རྣམས་ཀུན་དུ་རྡུང་བཞིན་དུ་བསྙེན་བཀུར་ཆེན་པོ་བྱས་ནས་རྒྱལ་པོར་དབང་བསྐུར་བས་དབང་བསྐུར་ཏོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Hundreds of thousands of gods played and sang melodious music for him. Having shown great respect in this way, they crowned him.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-566">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-225</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།བར་སྐབས་དེར་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའི་མཐུས་ས་རྣམ་པ་དྲུག་ཏུ་གཡོས་པ་དང་ལྷ་རྣམས་དགའ་བ་དང་། མགུ་བས་ཡང་རྣམ་པ་སྣ་ཚོགས་པའི་མེ་ཏོག་གི་ཆར་དང་། རིན་པོ་ཆེའི་ཆར་ཡང་ཕབ་སྟེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-225"/>“During the coronation, the bodhisattva’s power caused the earth to shake in six different ways. Out of joy and satisfaction, the gods showered flowers and precious gems on Jambudvīpa.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-567">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-225</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཛམ་བུའི་གླིང་ཐམས་ཅད་དུ་མེ་ཏོག་དང་རིན་པོ་ཆེའི་ཆར་པུས་མོ་ནུབ་ཙམ་གྱིས་གཡོགས་པར་གྱུར་ཏོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>So many fell that the flowers and gems were piled up to the peoples’ knees.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-568">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-225</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ལྷ་དང་མི་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་འབྱོར་པ་བསམ་གྱིས་མི་ཁྱབ་པར་གྱུར་པ་དེ་རྣམས་མཐོང་བ་དང་། ངོ་མཚར་དུ་གྱུར་ཅིང་རྨད་དུ་བྱུང་བ་སྐྱེས་ཏེ་ཆེད་དུ་རྗོད་<tei:ref folio="F.49.b"/>པ་ཆེད་དུ་བརྗོད་དེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>In sheer amazement at seeing this amount of wealth, the gods and humans exclaimed, ‘Amazing!</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-569">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-225</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཨེ་མའོ་རྒྱལ་པོ་དཔལ་གྱི་སྡེའི་བསོད་ནམས་ཀྱི་སྟོབས།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>How powerful is King Śrīsena’s merit!</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-570">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-225</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཨེ་མའོ་ངོ་མཚར་ཆེའོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Amazing! It is wondrous!’</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-571">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-226</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ནས་ལྷའི་དབང་པོ་བརྒྱ་བྱིན་ལྷ་བརྒྱ་སྟོང་དུ་མ་དང་ཐབས་ཅིག་ཏུ་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཡང་དག་པར་དགའ་བར་བྱས་ནས་རང་གི་གནས་སུ་སོང་ངོ་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-226"/>“After thoroughly pleasing the bodhisattva, Śakra, lord of the gods, along with hundreds of thousands of other gods, returned to his abode.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-572">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-226</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།རི་ལ་གནས་པའི་དྲང་སྲོང་དེ་ཡང་འཁོར་ལྔ་བརྒྱ་དང་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་ལ་མངོན་པར་བསྟོད་དེ་བསྟི་གནས་ཉིད་དུ་སོང་ངོ་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The sage and his retinue of five hundred also returned home, after openly praising the bodhisattva.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-573">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-227</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ནས་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔས་སྐྱེ་བོའི་ཚོགས་ཆེན་པོས་མངོན་པར་བཏུད་ཅིང་ཡུན་རིང་དུ་ཆོས་ཀྱི་རྒྱལ་པོ་བྱེད་པར་གྱུར་ཏོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-227"/>“After these events, the much-venerated bodhisattva ruled as a Dharma king for a long time.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-574">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-227</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།འཛམ་བུའི་གླིང་གི་དམན་པ་དང་། ལོང་བ་དང་བཀྲེན་པ་དང་སྡུག་ཕོངས་པ་ཐམས་ཅད་ནོར་གྱིས་ཚིམ་པར་བྱས་ནས་དགེ་བ་བཅུའི་ལས་ཀྱི་ལམ་ལ་རབ་ཏུ་བཞག་སྟེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He satiated Jambudvīpa’s poor, blind, hungry, and destitute by granting them wealth, and he led everyone along the path of the ten virtuous actions.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-575">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-227</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདོད་པ་ན་སྤྱོད་པའི་ལྷ་དྲུག་ཀུན་དགའ་བར་བྱས་ནས་དུས་གཞན་ཞིག་གི་ཚེ་སྲོག་ཆགས་བརྒྱ་སྟོང་དུ་མ་རྣམས་དང་དེ་ལྷན་ཅིག་ཏུ་དུས་བྱས་ཏེ་དགའ་ལྡན་གྱི་ལྷའི་རིས་སུ་སྐྱེས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He thoroughly satisfied all six classes of gods in the desire realm. At another time, he caused them, along with hundreds of thousands of others, to be reborn in Tuṣita heaven.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-576">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-228</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་བཀའ་སྩལ་པ། དགེ་སློང་དག་དེའི་ཚེ་དེའི་དུས་ན་རྒྱལ་པོ་དཔལ་གྱི་སྡེ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་དེ་གཞན་ཞིག་ཡིན་པ་སྙམ་དུ་ཐ་ཚོམ་མམ་ཡིད་གཉིས་སུ་གྱུར་ན་ཁྱེད་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་དེ་ལྟར་མི་བལྟའོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-228"/>After telling this tale, the Blessed One said, “Monks, do not have any doubts or confusion that King Śrīsena was someone other than me.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-577">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-228</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།གཞན་དུ་ན་ང་ཉིད་དེའི་ཚེ་དེའི་དུས་ན་རྒྱལ་པོ་དཔལ་གྱི་སྡེ་ཞེས་བྱ་བར་གྱུར་ཏེ། དེའི་ཚེ་རང་གི་ལུས་ཡོངས་སུ་བཏང་ངོ་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>At that time, I was the king and I gave away my body.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-578">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-228</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དགེ་སློང་དག་དེའི་ཚེ་དེའི་དུས་ན་རྒྱལ་པོ་དཔལ་གྱི་སྡེའི་བཙུན་མོ་རྒྱལ་བའི་འོད་དུ་གྱུར་པ་གང་ཡིན་པ་དེ་ནི་གྲགས་འཛིན་མ་འདི་ཉིད་ཡིན་ཏེ། དེའི་ཚེ་དེའི་དུས་ན་བཙུན་མོ་རྒྱལ་བའི་འོད་ཅེས་བྱ་བར་གྱུར་ཏོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Monks, the one who was King Śrīsena’s wife back then, Queen Jayaprabhā, is none other than Yaśodharā.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-579">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-228</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དགེ་སློང་དག་བློན་པོའི་མཆོག་བློ་གྲོས་ཆེན་པོར་གྱུར་པ་གང་ཡིན་པ་དེ་ནི་དགེ་སློང་ཤཱ་རིའི་བུ་འདི་ཉིད་ཡིན་ཏེ། དེའི་ཚེ་དེའི་དུས་ན་བློན་པོ་བློ་གྲོས་ཆེན་པོར་གྱུར་ཏོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The supreme one among the ministers, Mahāmati, is none other than the monk Śāriputra.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-580">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-228</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དགེ་སློང་དག་ལྷའི་དབང་པོ་བརྒྱ་བྱིན་དུ་གྱུར་པ་གང་ཡིན་པ་དེ་ནི་རྒྱལ་པོ་གཟུགས་ཅན་སྙིང་པོ་འདི་ཉིད་ཡིན་ཏེ། དེའི་ཚེ་དེའི་དུས་ན་ལྷའི་དབང་པོ་བརྒྱ་བྱིན་དུ་གྱུར་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Śakra, lord of the gods, is none other than King Bimbisāra.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-581">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-228</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དགེ་སློང་དག་སུམ་ཅུ་རྩ་གསུམ་གྱི་ལྷ་གང་ཡིན་པ་དེ་རྣམས་ནི་རྒྱལ་པོ་གཟུགས་ཅན་སྙིང་པོ་དང་ལྷན་ཅིག་ཏུ་བདེན་པ་མཐོང་བ་ལྷ་བརྒྱད་ཁྲི་པོ་འདི་ཉིད་ཡིན་ནོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Those who were the gods of the Heaven of the Thirty-Three at that time are none other than the eighty thousand gods who realized the truth simultaneously with King Bimbisāra.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-582">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-228</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དགེ་སློང་དག་གྲོང་ཁྱེར་གྱི་སྐྱེ་བོའི་ཚོགས་གང་ཡིན་པ་དེ་ནི་རྒྱལ་པོ་གཟུགས་<tei:ref folio="F.50.a"/>ཅན་སྙིང་པོ་གང་དག་དང་ཐབས་ཅིག་ཏུ་ངའི་ཐད་དུ་འོངས་པའི་མ་ག་དྷཱའི་བྲམ་ཟེ་དང་ཁྱིམ་བདག་འདི་དག་ཉིད་ཡིན་ནོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The masses of people in the city of Ariṣṭa are none other than the brahmins and householders of Magadha who come to me along with King Bimbisāra.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-583">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-228</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དགེ་སློང་དག་རི་ལ་གནས་པའི་དྲང་སྲོང་དུ་གྱུར་པ་གང་ཡིན་པ་དེ་ནི་དགེ་སློང་མཽད་གལ་གྱི་བུ་ཆེན་པོ་འདི་ཉིད་ཡིན་ཏེ། དེའི་ཚེ་དེའི་དུས་ན་དྲང་སྲོང་དུ་གྱུར་ཏོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Monks, the sage who lived in the mountains is none other than the monk Maudgalyāyana.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-584">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-228</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།གང་གིས་ངའི་དྲུང་དུ་བཙུན་མོ་རྒྱལ་བའི་འོད་སློང་བའི་དྲང་སྲོང་བྲམ་ཟེའི་ཁྱེའུ་གང་ཡིན་པ་དེ་ནི་ཤཱཀྱའི་བུ་མོས་འཚོ་མ་འདི་ཉིད་ཡིན་ཏེ། དེའི་ཚེ་དེའི་དུས་ན་བྲམ་ཟེའི་ཁྱེའུར་གྱུར་ཏོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The young brahmin boy who came to me to beg for Queen Jayaprabhā is none other than the Śākya lady Gopā.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-585">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-228</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དགེ་སློང་དག་ཤིང་མཁན་གཉིས་པོར་གྱུར་པ་གང་ཡིན་པ་དེ་ནི་ལྷས་བྱིན་དང་། ཀོ་ཀ་ལི་ཀ་འདི་དག་ཡིན་ཏེ། དེའི་ཚེ་དེའི་དུས་ན་ཤིང་མཁན་གཉིས་སུ་གྱུར་ཏོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Monks, the two who were carpenters at that time are Devadatta and Kokālika.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-586">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-229</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།སྨོན་ལམ་དེའི་དབང་གིས་འདིར་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པའི་ཆོ་འཕྲུལ་རྣམ་པ་འདི་ལྟ་བུ་བྱུང་བར་གྱུར་ཏོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-229"/>“It is due to the power of his prayers that such miracles of the Thus-Gone One manifested.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-587">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-229</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དགེ་སློང་དག་དེའི་ཕྱིར་འདི་ལྟར་བསླབ་པར་བྱ་སྟེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Monks, therefore, you too must train in this way.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-588">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-229</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་སྦྱིན་པ་རྣམས་བཏང་བ་དང་བསོད་ནམས་དག་བྱའོ་ཞེས་དེ་ལྟར་བསླབ་པར་བྱའོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>You must train by telling yourselves, ‘I will practice generosity and perform meritorious acts.’ ”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-589">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-230</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་དེ་སྐད་ཅེས་བཀའ་སྩལ་ནས་དགེ་སློང་དེ་དག་ཡི་རངས་ཏེ། བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་གསུངས་པ་ལ་མངོན་པར་བསྟོད་དོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-230"/>When the Blessed One had said these words, the monks rejoiced and praised the Blessed One’s words.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-590">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-231</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སངས་རྒྱལ་པོ་དཔལ་གྱི་སྡེའི་རྟོགས་པ་བརྗོད་པ་རྫོགས་སོ།། །།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-231"/>This completes “The Account of the Noble Deeds of King Śrīsena.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-076-003-TU-591">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-076-003-233</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྒྱ་གར་གྱི་མཁན་པོ་དྷརྨཱ་ཤྲཱི་བྷ་དྲ་དང་། ཞུ་ཆེན་གྱི་ལོཙྪ་བ་དགེ་སློང་ཤེས་རབ་ལེགས་པས་བསྒྱུར། སྒྲ་བསྒྱུར་གྱི་ལོཙྪ་བ་ཆེན་པོ་དགེ་སློང་རིན་ཆེན་བཟང་པོས་བཅོས་ཏེ་གཏན་ལ་ཕབ་པ།།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-003-233"/>This was translated by the Indian preceptor Dharmaśrībhadra and the chief editor-translator Sherab Lekpa. It was then revised and finalized by the translator Rinchen Zangpo.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
</body>
</tmx>