<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tmx xmlns="http://www.lisa.org/tmx14" xmlns:eft="http://read.84000.co/ns/1.0" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<header creationtool="linguae-dharmae/84000" datatype="PlainText" segtype="block" adminlang="en-us" srclang="bo" o-tmf="TEI" eft:text-id="UT22084-077-002" eft:text-version="v-1.2.21-2023"/>
<body>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-1">
    <prop type="location-id">translation</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>
                    <tei:ref folio="F.14.a"/>༄༅། །རྒྱ་གར་སྐད་དུ། སེ་ཀྐོདྡེ་ཤ། བོད་སྐད་དུ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg/>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-2">
    <prop type="location-id">translation</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དབང་མདོར་བསྟན་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Summary of Empowerment</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-3">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-96</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དཔལ་རྡོ་རྗེ་སེམས་དཔའ་ལ་ཕྱག་འཚལ་ལོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-96"/>Homage to Glorious Kālacakra!</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-4">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-96</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཟླ་བ་བཟང་པོས་གསོལ་པ། སྟོན་པ་དབང་བསྐུར་རྣམ་བདུན་དང་། །རྣམ་གསུམ་དེ་བཞིན་བླ་ན་མེད། །འཇིག་རྟེན་འདས་པའི་དངོས་གྲུབ་ཕྱིར། །མདོར་བསྡུས་པ་ཡིས་བདག་ལ་གསུངས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Sucandra requested: The sevenfold and threefold empowerment, And also the unsurpassable one, O Teacher— Explain them to me in short, For the sake of mundane and supramundane accomplishments!</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-5">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-100</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་བཀའ་སྩལ་པ། །ཉོན་ཅིག་ཟླ་བཟང་དབང་བསྐུར་དོན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{1}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-100"/> The Illustrious One replied: Listen, O Sucandra!</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-6">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-100</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྣམ་པ་བདུན་དང་རྣམ་གསུམ་མཆོག །རྩ་ཡི་ཀུན་སྤྱོད་རྩོལ་བ་ནི། །མདོར་བསྟན་པ་ཡིས་ཁྱོད་ལ་བཤད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>I will explain to you in summary The empowerment and its purpose; these sevenfold, Threefold, and unsurpassable empowerments; And the movement in the channels and its control.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-7">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-102</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྒྱུད་དུ་མདོར་བསྟན་རྣམ་གསུམ་དང་། །རྒྱས་པར་བཤད་པ་རྣམ་གསུམ་འགྱུར། །རབ་ཏུ་མདོར་བསྟན་མདོར་བསྟན་ཆེ། །རབ་ཏུ་རྒྱས་པར་བཤད་པ་གཞན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{2}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-102"/> In the tantras there are three types of summaries And three types of explanations [pertaining to the Sekoddeśa], Including the precise summary, the extensive summary, The precise explanation, and the other (i.e., the extensive explanation).</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-8">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-103</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མདོར་བསྟན་རྒྱས་པར་བཤད་པ་ཉིད། །རྒྱུད་ཡང་དག་པར་བསྡུས་པར་བརྗོད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{3}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-103"/> The summary and explanation Are referred to as the recitation of the tantra.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-9">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-103</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རབ་ཏུ་མདོར་བསྟན་རྒྱས་བཤད་པ། །དཀའ་འགྲེལ་ཚིག་ནི་འབྱེད་པའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The precise summary and the [precise] explanation Are word-by-word commentaries.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-10">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-104</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མདོར་བསྟན་ཆེན་པོ་རྒྱས་བཤད་པ། །འགྲེལ་བཤད་ཐམས་ཅད་དོན་སྟོན་བྱེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{4}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-104"/> The extensive summary and the [extensive] explanation Are commentaries that indicate the entirety of the meaning.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-11">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-104</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནི་མངོན་ཤེས་ཐོབ་རྣམས་ཀྱིས། །བྱ་ཡི་མཁས་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་མིན་ཉིད། །དེ་ལྟར་མཐའ་དྲུག་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་དག །རྡོ་རྗེའི་རྣལ་འབྱོར་རྣམ་བཞི་དང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They must be composed by those who have obtained supramundane knowledge, Not by mere scholars.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-12">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-106</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྫོགས་པའི་བྱང་ཆུབ་བཞི་རྣམས་དང་། །ཕུང་ཁམས་སྐྱེ་མཆེད་རིགས་དྲུག་རྣམས། །དག་པ་འཇིག་རྟེན་ཁམས་ལ་སོགས། །ལེའུ་ལྔ་ཡི་གཞུང་རྣམས་ཀྱིས། །བདེན་གཉིས་དང་པོའི་སངས་རྒྱས་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{5}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-106"/> Through these six [summaries and explanations], The tantra of the Ādibuddha called Kālacakra is perfect: Perfect through fourfold vajrayoga; Perfect through the four types of awakening; {6}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-108"/> Perfect through the psycho-physical aggregates, Elements, sense bases, and six families; Perfect through the five chapters, on the world realm and so forth; And perfect through [adherence to the principle of] two truths.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-13">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-109</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དུས་ཀྱི་འཁོར་ལོ་མངོན་རྗོད་བྱེད། །དང་པོར་དབང་བསྐུར་བདུན་པོ་གང་། །བྱིས་པ་རྣམས་ནི་གཞུག་པའི་ཕྱིར། །རྣམ་གསུམ་འཇིག་རྟེན་ཀུན་རྫོབ་ཀྱིས། །དམ་པའི་དོན་གྱིས་བཞི་བའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{7}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-109"/> First, there is the sevenfold empowerment To introduce the childish; Then the threefold one in terms of the relative truth of the world; And the fourth in terms of the ultimate truth.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-14">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-110</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བདེན་པ་གཉིས་ཀྱི་ཆོས་རྣམས་ཀྱི། །རྡོ་རྗེ་ཅན་བདག་གིས་བསྟན་པ། །འཇིག་རྟེན་ཀུན་རྫོབ་བདེན་པ་དང་། །དམ་པའི་དོན་གྱི་བདེན་པས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{8}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-110"/> The teaching of myself, the vajra holder, Concerning phenomena, is in terms of the twofold truth: The relative truth of the world And the ultimate truth.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-15">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-111</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཆུ་དང་ཅོད་པན་དར་དཔྱངས་དང་། །རྡོ་རྗེ་དྲིལ་བུ་བརྟུལ་ཞུགས་ཆེ། །མིང་དང་རྗེས་གནང་ཡང་དག་ལྡན། །དབང་བསྐུར་རྣམ་བདུན་མི་ཡི་བདག །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{9}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-111"/> The sevenfold empowerment, O King, Consists of those of water, Crown, ribbon, vajra and bell, Great vow, name, and permission.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-16">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-112</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལུས་ངག་སེམས་ནི་ལེགས་དག་པ། །མངོན་<tei:ref folio="F.14.b"/>པར་དབང་བསྐུར་གཉིས་གཉིས་སོ། །རྗེས་གནང་ཡེ་ཤེས་ཡང་དག་དག །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{10}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-112"/> The purification of body, speech, and mind, With two each, comprise the first six empowerments; The purification of wisdom, the permission empowerment.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-17">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-113</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཞན་པ་ཁམས་སོགས་དག་པ་ལས། །ཆུ་ནི་ཁམས་ཀྱི་དག་པ་སྟེ། །ཅོད་པན་ཕུང་པོ་རྣམ་སྦྱོང་བྱེད། །དར་དཔྱངས་ཕ་རོལ་ཕྱིན་པ་དག །རྡོ་རྗེ་དྲིལ་བུ་མི་འགྱུར་ཆེ། །སངས་རྒྱས་སྐད་རྒྱུན་མི་འཆད་པ། །ཉི་ཟླ་གཅིག་ཏུ་དག་པར་བྱེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The other purifications are the purification of the elements and so forth: {11}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-113"/> The water empowerment is the purification of the elements; That of the crown is the purification of the psycho-physical aggregates; That of the ribbon is the purification of the perfections; Those of the vajra and the bell are for the great immovable bliss {12}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-114"/> And one’s uninterrupted buddha speech, respectively— They are the purification of the sun and moon [so that they are united] into one.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-18">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-113</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡུལ་དང་དབང་པོ་ལེགས་དག་པ། །འཕོ་མེད་རྡོ་རྗེའི་བརྟུལ་ཞུགས་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The purification of the objects and sense faculties Is the vajra vow that remains intact.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-19">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-115</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མིང་ནི་བྱམས་སོགས་ཡང་དག་དག །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{13}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-115"/> The name empowerment is the purification of love, compassion, joy, and equanimity.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-20">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-115</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྗེས་གནང་སངས་རྒྱས་ཉིད་དག་བྱེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>That of permission is the purification for achieving buddhahood.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-21">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-115</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དབང་བསྐུར་བདུན་པོ་འདི་རྣམས་ནི། །དཀྱིལ་འཁོར་བཞེངས་ནས་སྦྱིན་པར་བྱ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>These seven empowerments must only be given After having created the maṇḍala.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-22">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-116</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བུམ་པ་གསང་བའི་དབང་བསྐུར་དང་། །ཤེས་རབ་ཡེ་ཤེས་མངོན་བརྗོད་པ། །སླར་ཡང་ཤེས་རབ་ཆེན་པོ་ཉིད། །དེ་ཡི་ཡེ་ཤེས་མངོན་རྗོད་བྱེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{14}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-116"/> Next follows the vase empowerment, the secret empowerment, That called wisdom from a prajñā, Then, again, that of great prajñā, Which is known as wisdom gained from her.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-23">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-117</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འགྱུར་དང་འགྱུར་དང་དེ་ནས་འཛག །དེ་ནས་གཞན་ཡང་མི་འཛག་པའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{15}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-117"/> The first three are, respectively, moving, moving, and vibrating, And the supreme one is beyond vibration.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-24">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-118</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལུས་ངག་སེམས་ནི་ལེགས་དག་པས། །དབང་བསྐུར་གསུམ་པོ་རིམ་པ་ཡིས། །བཞི་པ་ཡེ་ཤེས་ཡང་དག་དག །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The first three empowerments are taken, respectively, As the purification of body, speech, and mind, {16}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-118"/> And the fourth is the purification of wisdom.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-25">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-118</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལུས་ངག་སེམས་ནི་དག་པར་བྱེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The purification of body, speech, and mind.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-26">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-118</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱིས་པ་དར་མ་དེ་ནས་རྒན། །བཞི་པ་སྐྱེ་དགུའི་བདག་པོའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The three correspond to the level of a child, adult, and elder, And the fourth to the level of the universal ancestor.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-27">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-119</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཤེས་རབ་ནུ་མར་ཡན་ལག་ནི། །རེག་པས་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་འཕོའི་བདེ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{17}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-119"/> From touching the breast of the prajñā, There is the bliss of descending bodhicitta.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-28">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-119</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འོ་མ་འཛིན་པས་དབང་བསྐུར་བ། །གང་ལས་བདེ་ཐོབ་དེ་བྱིས་པའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The adept empowered by the breast is the child Because such bliss is attained from touching the breast.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-29">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-120</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡུན་རིང་གསང་བར་སྤྲོས་ལས་སྐྱེས། །བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་ནི་འཕོ་བའི་བདེ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{18}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-120"/> From moving the vajra in the secret part for a long time, The bliss of the further-descending bodhicitta has arisen.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-30">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-120</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གསང་བའི་དབང་བསྐུར་གསང་བ་ནི། །གང་ལས་བདེ་ཐོབ་དེ་དར་མ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The adept empowered by the secret part is the adult Because such bliss is attained from the secret part.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-31">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-121</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡུན་རིང་གསང་བར་སྤྲོས་ལས་སྐྱེས། །རྡོ་རྗེའི་རྩེ་མོར་གཡོ་བའི་བདེ། །ཤེས་རབ་ཡེ་ཤེས་དབང་བསྐུར་བ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{19}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-121"/> From moving the vajra in the secret part for a long time, The bliss of vibration has arisen at the tip of the vajra.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-32">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-121</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་ལས་གཡོ་བའི་བགྲོད་དེ་རྒན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The adept empowered by the wisdom from a prajñā is the elder Because of having realized the bliss from vibration.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-33">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-122</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཕྱག་རྒྱ་ཆེན་པོ་རྗེས་ཆགས་ལས། །སྐྱེས་པ་གཡོ་མེད་བདེ་བ་ནི། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{20}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-122"/> That which has arisen from passion for the mahāmudrā Is bliss without vibration.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-34">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-122</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཤེས་རབ་ཆེན་པོའི་དབང་བསྐུར་བ། །གང་ལས་གཡོ་མེད་རྟོགས་པ་དེ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The adept empowered by the great prajñā is the universal ancestor Because he realizes the [blissful] state without vibration.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-35">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-123</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྐྱེ་དགུའི་བདག་པོར་རྣམ་ཤེས་བྱ། །སྐྱོབ་པ་ཐམས་ཅད་སྐྱེད་མཛད་པ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{21}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-123"/> The universal ancestor should be known As the creator of all protectors.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-36">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-124</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྡོ་རྗེ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེ། །བྱང་སེམས་གཉིས་མེད་མི་འགྱུར་<tei:ref folio="F.15.a"/>བ། །འདི་ནི་དམ་ཚིག་སེམས་དཔར་འགྱུར། །རྡོ་རྗེའི་རྣལ་འབྱོར་རྣམ་པ་བཞི། །དུས་ཀྱི་འཁོར་ལོ་འདིར་བཤད་པ། །རྣལ་འབྱོར་པ་ཡི་ཐར་སྟེར་བྱེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Being in a state without duality or movement, He is called Vajrasattva, the Great Being, and Bodhisattva, {22}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-124"/> The Commitment Being, Fourfold Vajrayoga, And finally, here, Kālacakra— The one bestowing liberation on yogins.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-37">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-125</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདི་ཉིད་ཀྱི་ནི་སྒྲུབ་པ་བྱ། །རབ་གསལ་བསམ་གྱིས་མི་ཁྱབ་པའི། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{23}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-125"/> This practice must be accomplished Through manifestations, that are not mentally produced (Skt.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-38">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-125</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དུ་སོགས་མཚན་མ་དེ་རྣམས་ཀྱི། །ཤེས་རབ་གཟུགས་བརྙན་ནམ་མཁའ་མཉམ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>acintitaiḥ), Namely, the ten signs beginning with smoke, Which are reflections of insight, similar to the sky.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-39">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-126</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡོད་དང་མེད་ལས་རྣམ་པར་འདས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{24}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-126"/> They are beyond existence and nonexistence. Their status (Skt.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-40">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-126</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རང་གི་སེམས་ཀྱི་རྐྱེན་གྱི་དོན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>artha) is certain from one’s own experience.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-41">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-126</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྡུལ་ཕྲན་ལས་སྐྱེས་ཚོགས་པ་རྣམས། །ཀུན་ནས་ཡོངས་སུ་དོར་བ་ཡིས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They are entirely devoid Of accumulations of atoms and particles.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-42">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-127</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དུ་བ་སྨིག་རྒྱུ་མཁའ་སྣང་དང་། །སྒྲོན་མ་འབར་བ་ཟླ་ཉི་མ། །མུན་ཅན་ཆ་དང་ཐིག་ལེ་ཆེ། །སྣ་ཚོགས་གཟུགས་བརྙན་འོད་གསལ་བ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{25}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-127"/> They are smoke, a mirage, A firefly, a lamp, a flame, the moon, the sun, Darkness, digit of the moon, and the great drop— This clear reflection of everything.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-43">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-128</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཀབ་དང་མ་བཀབ་མིག་དག་གིས། །སྟོང་པར་འདི་ནི་རྗེས་བརྟགས་མིན། །རྨི་ལམ་བཞིན་དུ་གཟུགས་མཐོང་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{26}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-128"/> With eyes neither closed nor open, This reflection is seen in emptiness, Like in a dream.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-44">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-128</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྟག་ཏུ་གཟུགས་དེ་བསྒོམ་པར་བྱ། །དངོས་མེད་གཟུགས་ལ་སྒོམ་པ་དེ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Without conceptualizing it, One must constantly meditate on this reflection.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-45">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-129</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྣལ་འབྱོར་པ་ཡི་བསྒོམ་པ་མིན། །དངོས་པོ་དངོས་མེད་སེམས་ཀྱི་མིན། །སྟོང་པར་མ་བརྟགས་མཐོང་ཕྱིར་རོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{27}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-129"/> Once the reflection [is seen] in the non-existent (i.e., cloudless sky), The meditation is not the [conceptual] meditation of yogins; To the mind appears neither existence nor nonexistence, Because of seeing the reflection of emptiness without having imagined them.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-46">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-131</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཇི་ལྟར་པྲ་ཕབ་མེ་ལོང་ལ། །གཞོན་ནུ་མས་མཐོང་དངོས་མེད་སྐྱེས། །དེ་བཞིན་འདས་དང་མ་འོངས་ཆོས། །མཁའ་ལ་དེ་ཉིད་རྣལ་འབྱོར་བས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{28}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-131"/> Just as a virgin sees in the divinatory mirror The magical image of something unreal, So, too, the yogin of true reality sees in space Past and future phenomena.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-47">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-132</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདི་ལས་དངོས་པོ་དངོས་མེད་འགྱུར། །དངོས་པོ་སྟོང་པའི་དོན་མཐོང་ཕྱིར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{29}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-132"/> The object in the reflection is not something real Because she sees what is empty of real entities.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-48">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-132</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དངོས་པོ་དངོས་མེད་དོན་ཡོད་པ། །སྒྱུ་མ་རྨི་ལམ་མིག་འཕྲུལ་བཞིན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Something consisting of nonexistent entities Is like an illusion, a dream, or magic.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-49">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-133</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མེད་པའི་ཆོས་ཅན་དག་ལ་ཆོས། །སྐྱེ་བ་འདི་ནི་རབ་ཏུ་མཐོང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{30}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-133"/> Yet, even though it does not exist, The manifestation of a phenomenon is observed.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-50">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-133</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡིད་བཞིན་ནོར་ལྟར་མཐའ་ཡས་པའི། །སེམས་ཅན་བསམ་པ་ཡོངས་རྫོགས་བྱེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>It is like a wish-fulfilling jewel That fulfills the hopes of limitless beings.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-51">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-134</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>པྲ་ཕབ་པ་ཡི་གཞོན་ནུ་མས། །མ་མཐོང་བ་ཡི་རྐུན་པོ་མཐོང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{31}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-134"/> In the magical image, the virgin Sees a thief and so forth not yet seen [by the officiants].</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-52">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-134</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཉི་ཚེ་བ་ཡི་མིག་དག་གིས། །སོང་ནས་སྒྲུབ་པ་པོ་ཡིས་མཐོང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Having gone there, the officiants of the divination See him with their ordinary eyes.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-53">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-135</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གལ་ཏེ་ཡོད་པའི་གཟུགས་མཐོང་ན། །རང་གི་གདོང་པ་ཅིས་མི་མཐོང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{32}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-135"/> If she sees a real form, Why does she not see her own face?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-54">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-135</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གལ་ཏེ་མེད་པའི་གཟུགས་མཐོང་ན། །རི་བོང་རྭ་ནི་ཇི་ལྟར་མིན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>But if she sees an unreal form, Why does she not see a hare’s horn?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-55">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-136</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཞན་གྱི་མིག་གིས་མི་མཐོང་ཞིང་། །རང་གི་མིག་གིས་མཐོང་མིན་པ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{33}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-136"/> She sees neither with other/superior eyes, Nor with her own eyes.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-56">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-136</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྐྱེ་བ་མེད་པ་མཐོང་བ་ནི། །གཞོན་ནུ་མ་ཡི་བུ་<tei:ref folio="F.15.b"/>ཇི་བཞིན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>What is being seen has not arisen— It is like the child of a virgin.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-57">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-137</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཟུགས་བརྙན་མཐོང་ན་དེ་ནས་ནི། །བར་མ་ཆད་པར་སྲོག་རྩོལ་བྱ། །སྟེང་འོག་རྩ་གསུམ་པོ་རྣམས་ལ། །ལུས་ངག་སེམས་ནི་འགོག་པ་ལས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{34}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-137"/> Once the reflection is seen, One must immediately perform breath control, Because body, speech, and mind Should be arrested in the three upper and three lower channels.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-58">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-138</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཟླ་ཉི་སྒྲ་གཅན་བཤང་གཅི་དང་། །ཁུ་བ་འབབ་པའི་ལམ་རྣམས་སུ། །ཆུ་མེ་སྟོང་པ་ས་རླུང་དང་། །ཡེ་ཤེས་ཁམས་རྣམས་སྐྱེད་རྣམས་ལ། །གང་ཞིག་ཟླ་ཉི་མུན་ཅན་དང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{35}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-138"/> With regard to the channels—which are the path for The moon, the sun, Rāhu, excrement, urine, and semen, And which correspond to the families of the elements of Water, fire, space, earth, wind, and wisdom— {36}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-139"/> The channels of body, speech, and mind are taught to be, With regard to the vital wind and downward-moving wind, respectively, The channels of the moon, the sun, and Rāhu, As well as those of excrement, urine, and semen.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-59">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-140</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཤང་གཅི་ཁུ་བ་འབབ་མ་རྣམས། །སྲོག་དང་ཐུར་སེལ་རིམ་པ་ཡིས། །ལུས་ངག་སེམས་ཀྱི་རྩ་རྣམས་སོ། །ཟླ་བ་ཐབས་ཀྱི་སྐུ་ཡིན་ཏེ། །ཉིན་མོར་བྱེད་པ་ཤེས་རབ་གསུང་། །ཤེས་རབ་སྐུ་ནི་བཤང་བའི་རྩ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{37}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-140"/> The moon is the body of means, The sun is the speech of insight, The channel of excrement is the body of insight, The channel of urine is the speech of the omnipresent.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-60">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-141</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཅི་བ་འབབ་མ་གཙོ་བོའི་གསུང་། །སྟེང་འོག་ཐུགས་ཀྱི་རྩ་གཉིས་དག །མུན་ཅན་ཁུ་བ་འབབ་མའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{38}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-141"/> One upward and one downward—the two channels of mind Carry Rāhu and the semen, respectively.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-61">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-141</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཐབས་ཀྱི་ཐུགས་ནི་མུན་པ་ཅན། །ཁུ་བ་འབབ་མ་ཤེས་རབ་ཀྱི། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The mind of means is the channel of Rāhu, And the mind of insight is the channel of semen.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-62">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-142</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྟེང་འོག་རིགས་དྲུག་འདི་རྣམས་ནི། །སྐུ་གསུང་ཐུགས་ཀྱི་རྣལ་འབྱོར་ལས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{39}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-142"/> Upward and downward and combined with body, speech, and mind, These channels are the six families.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-63">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-142</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཤེས་རབ་ཐབས་དངོས་ཡན་ལག་གིས། །ལུས་ཅན་ཀུན་ལ་ཡང་དག་གནས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They reside in embodied beings As the aspects of means and the aspects of insight.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-64">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-143</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཆི་ལྟས་ལུས་ངག་རྩ་དག་ལ། །སྟེང་འོག་ལྷག་པའི་རླུང་རྣམས་ཀྱིས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{40}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-143"/> Due to strong winds above and below, Signs of death emerge in the channels of body and speech.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-65">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-143</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མུན་ཅན་ཁུ་བ་འབབ་མ་ལ། །སྐྱེ་བ་དང་ནི་འཆི་བ་གནས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Birth, death, and duration Are related to the channels of Rāhu and of semen.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-66">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-144</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྐྱེ་དང་འཆི་དང་འཁྲིག་པ་ཡི། །དུས་སུ་ཁུ་བ་འབབ་པའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{41}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-144"/> At the time of birth, death, and during intercourse, The channel of semen [swells].</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-67">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-144</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མུན་ཅན་མ་ཡང་སྟེང་དུ་འབབ། །ཉི་མའི་འཕོ་བ་མཉམ་པ་ལ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Rāhu flows upward during equinox, When the sun passes [from one sign to the other].</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-68">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-145</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དུས་སྦྱོར་འཆར་བའི་མངོན་མཚམས་སུ། །དབུ་མ་ནས་ནི་མཉམ་པ་འབབ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{42}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-145"/> At the moment of transit, [each time] the ascendant rises, The middle channel carries the breath of equinox.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-69">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-145</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྐང་པ་དང་བཅས་ལྔ་བཅུ་དྲུག །འབྱུང་དང་འཇུག་པའོ་མི་ཡི་བདག །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>It lasts fifty-six and one-quarter breaths, O protector of men, Counting inhalation and exhalation as one.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-70">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-146</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བདུན་ཅུ་རྩ་ལྔས་ལྷག་པ་ཡི། །དྲུག་བརྒྱ་ཉིན་དང་མཚན་ལའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{43}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-146"/> In one day and night there are six hundred Seventy-five [breaths in the middle channel].</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-71">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-147</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དྲུག་བརྒྱ་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་ལྷག་པ་ཡི། །སྟོང་ཕྲག་ཉི་ཤུ་རྩ་གཅིག་པོ། །འདི་ཡིས་དམན་པ་གང་དེ་རྣམས། །གཡོན་དང་གཡས་པའི་རྩར་འབབ་བོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The winds—twenty-one thousand Six hundred times {44}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-147"/> Minus those [675 breaths]— Flow in the left and right channels.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-72">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-147</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཕྱོགས་གསུམ་དང་བཅས་ལོ་གསུམ་རྣམས། །ལོ་བརྒྱ་རྣམས་ལས་དབུ་མའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They flow in the middle channel for three years And three fortnights during one hundred years.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-73">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-148</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྟེང་དུ་གཡོན་གཡས་ཟླ་ཉི་མ། །བརྐྱང་མ་ལུག་དང་སེར་སྐྱ་གཞན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{45}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-148"/> In the upper part, the left and right channels Are the moon, lalanā, and iḍā; and the sun, piṅgalā, and the other (i.e., rasanā).</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-74">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-148</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཆུ་དང་མེ་ཡི་རང་བཞིན་ཅན། །པདྨ་རིན་ཆེན་འཛིན་པར་འདོད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>These two have the nature of water and fire, And are taken to hold the lotus (i.e., Amitābha) and the jewel (i.e., Ratnasambhava).</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-75">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-149</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འོག་ཏུ་བཤང་གཅི་འབབ་པ་དག །ས་དང་<tei:ref folio="F.16.a"/>རླུང་གི་རང་བཞིན་ཅན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{46}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-149"/> In the lower part, there are the two channels of excrement and urine, Having the nature of earth and wind.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-76">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-149</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དབུ་མའི་རྩ་དང་གཡོན་པ་ཡང་། །འཁོར་ལོ་རལ་གྲི་འཛིན་པར་འདོད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They are the middle and left channels, And are known to hold the disc (i.e., Vairocana) and the sword (i.e., Amoghasiddhi).</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-77">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-150</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྟེང་དང་འོག་ཏུ་དབུ་མ་གཡས། །སྒྲ་གཅན་ཁུ་བ་རབ་འབབ་པ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{47}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-150"/> In the upper and the lower part, the middle and right channel, Are those of Rāhu and semen.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-78">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-150</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྟོང་པ་ཡེ་ཤེས་རང་བཞིན་ཅན། །རྡོ་རྗེ་རྡོ་རྗེ་འཛིན་པར་འདོད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They have the nature of emptiness and wisdom, And both are known to hold vajras (i.e., Akṣobhya and Vajrasattva).</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-79">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-151</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཟླ་བའི་ལམ་གྱིས་བཤང་བའི་རྩ། །ཉི་མས་གཅི་བ་འབབ་པ་སྟེ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{48}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-151"/> The channel of excrement connects with the path of the moon, The channel of urine with the path of the sun, And the channel of semen with the path of Rāhu.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-80">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-151</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྐྱེ་འཆི་མཉམ་པ་ཆགས་པ་ལ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The latter is responsible for birth, death, [the breath of] equinox, and intercourse.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-81">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-152</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྒྲ་གཅན་ཁུ་བ་རབ་ཏུ་འབབ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{49}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-152"/> The avadhūtī above the navel is called Suṣumnā, the channel of darkness.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-82">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-152</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལྟེ་བའི་སྟེང་དུ་ཀུན་འདར་མ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The channel of the semen below is called Sky-goer face (Skt.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-83">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-152</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་དེ་ཡིད་བཟང་མུན་པ་འབབ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>khagamukhā) and conch-shell channel (Skt.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-84">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-152</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འོག་ཏུ་ཁུ་བ་འབབ་གང་དེ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>śaṅkhinī).</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-85">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-153</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མཁའ་འགྲོ་གདོང་དང་དུང་ཅན་མ། །ལྟེ་བའི་ཆུ་སྐྱེས་སྙིང་མགྲིན་དང་། །དཔྲལ་བ་གཙུག་ཏོར་འདམ་སྐྱེས་ལ། །ས་ཆུ་མེ་རླུང་སྟོང་པ་རྣམས། །རབ་ཏུ་འབབ་པ་སྡུད་པ་ཡིས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{50}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-153"/> Passing through the lotuses of the navel, heart, throat, Forehead, and crown of the head, [The vital wind in the avadhūtī] transports earth into water, water into fire, Fire into wind, and wind into emptiness—in the mode of dissolution.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-86">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-154</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འབྱུང་འགྱུར་དེ་ནི་འཇུག་པ་དག །བསྐྱེད་པས་འཇུག་སྟེ་ས་ལའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{51}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-154"/> Exhaling and inhaling again, It reenters the earth element by way of production.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-87">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-155</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལྟེ་བ་ནས་ནི་ལྟེ་བའི་དབུས། །ཨ་བདྷཱ་ཏཱིར་འགྲོ་དང་འོང་། །ལྟེ་གསང་ནོར་བུའི་ཆུ་སྐྱེས་ལ། །ལུས་ངག་སེམས་རྣམས་འབབ་པ་ནི། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The avadhūtī runs From center to center {52}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-155"/> And carries body, speech, and mind At the navel and the secret lotus of the jewel.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-88">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-155</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འབྱུང་དང་དེ་ནི་འཇུག་པ་དག །སྡུད་དང་སྐྱེད་པའི་རང་བཞིན་ཅན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Exhaling and inhaling, It has the nature of dissolution and production, respectively.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-89">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-156</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དུང་ཅན་སྐྱེ་བོ་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱི། །ཐུར་སེལ་རླུང་ནི་འབབ་པའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{53}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-156"/> The śaṅkhinī carries the downward-moving wind Of all living beings.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-90">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-156</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདི་རྣམས་བུད་མེད་བདེ་བ་ལས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Due to the bliss of [enjoying] women, It carries semen; and at the time of menstruation it carries blood.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-91">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-157</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཁུ་བ་ཁྲག་འབབ་དུས་དག་ཏུ། །ཤེས་རབ་ཐབས་དངོས་ཡན་ལག་གིས། །སྟེང་དུ་གཡས་དང་གཡོན་དག་དང་། །འོག་ཏུ་བཤང་གཅི་འབབ་པ་དང་། །རྔུལ་དང་ཁུ་བ་འབབ་པ་དག །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{54}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-157"/> The left and right channels above, And those carrying excrement and urine below, Refer to the factors of insight and means respectively, As do the channels of menstrual blood and semen.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-92">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-158</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྔུལ་འབབ་ཕྱིར་དེ་གཏུམ་མོ་སྟེ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{55}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-158"/> Carrying menstrual blood, the śaṅkhinī is called caṇḍālī.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-93">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-158</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཁུ་བ་འབབ་ཕྱིར་མཁའ་འགྲོ་གདོང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Carrying semen, it is called khagamukhā.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-94">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-158</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྟེང་དུ་བརྗོད་དུས་བུད་མེད་ཀྱི། །གཡུང་མོ་སྐྱེས་བུའི་ཀུན་འདར་མའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Above, the avadhūtī is called ḍombī in women referring to menstruation; In men it is called avadhūtī.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-95">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-159</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྣམ་ཤེས་ལ་སོགས་དཀྱིལ་འཁོར་ལྔ། །རྟག་ཏུ་གཡོན་པའི་རྩ་ལའོ། །ས་སོགས་གཡས་པའི་རྩ་ལ་སྟེ། །དབུས་སུ་དྲུག་པ་འབབ་པའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{56}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-159"/> The five maṇḍalas, starting with consciousness, Always flow in the left channel; The ones starting with earth, in the right channel; The sixth (i.e., that of wisdom), in the middle channel.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-96">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-160</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལྟེ་བའི་པདྨའི་འདབ་མ་ལ། །དཀྱིལ་འཁོར་དྲུག་ཅུ་རྣམས་རིམ་བཞིན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{57}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-160"/> On the lotus petals at the level of the navel are, In successive order, sixty maṇḍalas.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-97">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-161</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཡོན་དང་གཡས་པའི་དུས་སྦྱོར་ནི། །ལུག་སོགས་གླང་ལ་སོགས་པ་ལ། །རྩ་བ་གཡོན་དང་དེ་ནས་གཡས། །སྟེང་དང་དབུས་སུ་རིམ་པས་རླུང་། །ས་སོགས་དཀྱིལ་འཁོར་རེ་རེ་ཞིང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>At the time of the left and right ascendants, Constituted by the six starting with Aries and the six starting with Taurus, {58}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-161"/> The vital breath flows in the two nostrils in due order To the base, the left, the right, above, and to the middle, Passing through one maṇḍala after the other, Starting with earth, during each daṇḍa.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-98">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-163</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དབྱུག་གུས་སྣ་བུག་དག་ལའོ། །རིམ་པས་ཆུ་ཚོད་འབབ་<tei:ref folio="F.16.b"/>པ་ནི། །དྲུག་ཅུ་དང་བཅས་སུམ་བརྒྱའི་དབུགས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{59}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-163"/> One nāḍikā successively Carries 360 breaths.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-99">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-163</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བརྒྱ་ཕྲག་བཅྭ་བརྒྱད་དབུགས་དེ་རྣམས། །ཆུ་ཚོད་ལྔར་ནི་འབབ་པའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Five of them Carry 1,800.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-100">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-165</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཆུ་ཚོད་དྲུག་ཅུ་ཉིན་མཚན་དུ། །ལུས་ལ་དཀྱིལ་འཁོར་རྣམས་ཤེས་པའོ། །འདབ་མའི་དབུས་དང་དེ་ནས་ཤར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{60}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-165"/> One day and night have 60 nāḍikās; They are the maṇḍalas of the body [starting with earth].</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-101">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-165</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཡས་གཡོན་གཞན་དུ་རིམ་པ་ཡིས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The vital breath flows to the center of the petals (space) and then, in due order, Above (wind), to the right (fire), left (water), and below (earth).</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-102">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-166</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཡོན་པར་རྟག་ཏུ་ནམ་མཁའ་སོགས། །གཡས་པར་ས་སོགས་གཞན་ལས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{61}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-166"/> In the left nostril the elements always start with space, And in the right with earth in reverse order.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-103">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-166</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཡོན་པར་རྣམ་ཤེས་སོགས་འབྱུང་བ། །གཡས་པར་ས་སོགས་སྡུད་པའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>In the left occurs formation starting with consciousness, And in the right occurs dissolution starting with earth.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-104">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-167</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ནུབ་དང་ཤར་དུ་འཛིན་མ་རླུང་། །ཕན་ཚུན་ཤེས་རབ་ཐབས་ཡིན་ཏེ། །མཐེ་བོང་མིང་མེད་དག་གིས་ནི། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{62}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-167"/> The earth is below and the wind above— They are insight and means respectively.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-105">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-167</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་ཕྱིར་ཁ་ལ་དབང་བསྐུར་བ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Therefore, the [secret] empowerment happens through The thumb and the ring finger in the mouth [of the disciple].</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-106">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-168</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཡས་དང་གཡོན་དུ་མེ་དང་ཆུ། །ཕན་ཚུན་ཤེས་རབ་ཐབས་ཡིན་ཏེ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{63}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-168"/> Fire is on the right and water on the left— They are insight and means respectively.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-107">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-168</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གུང་མོ་མཛུབ་མོ་གཉིས་དག་གིས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Therefore, the mudrā of the sword is formed with The middle and index fingers.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-108">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-169</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་ཕྱིར་རལ་གྲིར་འགྱུར་བའོ། །ཟླ་ཕྱེད་རྣམ་པའི་ཕྱག་རྒྱ་ནི། །མཆེ་བ་གྲི་གུག་མཐེ་ཆུང་སྟེ། །སྟོང་པ་མི་འགྱུར་སྟེང་འོག་ཏུ། །ཕན་ཚུན་ཐབས་དང་ཤེས་རབ་བོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{64}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-169"/> The void is above and the immovable below— They are insight and means respectively; Therefore, the mudrā of the fangs, which has the shape of a half-moon, Is formed with the little fingers looking like a hooked knife.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-109">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-170</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དཀྱིལ་འཁོར་བཅུ་པོ་ཡང་དག་སྦྱོར། །སོར་མོ་རྣམས་ནི་ཕན་ཚུན་དུ། །མགོ་བོར་ལག་མཐིལ་སྦྱར་བ་ལ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{65}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-170"/> The union of the ten maṇḍalas Is that of the ten fingers, one [hand] with the other, Palms joined above the head.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-110">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-170</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གྲི་གུག་དང་བཅས་རྩེ་གཅིག་གོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>This is the mudrā of the one-pointed vajra and knife.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-111">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-171</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དབུ་མའི་རྩ་ལ་མཉམ་པ་དེ། །སྐྱེད་དང་སྡུད་པའི་བྱེད་པ་པོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{66}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-171"/> The equinox in the middle channel Causes creation and dissolution.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-112">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-171</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཕུང་པོ་ཁམས་དང་རྡོ་རྗེ་གསུམ། །གཅིག་ཉིད་དབུ་མར་སོན་པ་ནའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Having entered the middle channel, the psycho-physical aggregates, Elements, and the three vajras [of body, speech, and mind] become one.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-113">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-172</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཟླ་བ་ཉི་མའི་རྩ་འགགས་ན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{67}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-172"/> When the channels of the moon and the sun are blocked, The channels of excrement and urine become blocked.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-114">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-172</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཤང་བ་གཅི་བའི་རྩ་འགག་གོ །སྒྲ་གཅན་རྩ་ནི་འགགས་པ་ན། །འོག་ཏུ་ཁུ་བ་འབབ་འགག་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>When the channel of Rāhu is blocked, The channel of semen below becomes blocked.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-115">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-173</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྐྱེད་དང་སྡུད་པའི་བྱེད་པ་ཅན། །འདི་རྣམས་གྲོལ་ན་གྲོལ་བར་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{68}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-173"/> When [the upper ones] are released, the respective lower ones are then released, Causing creation and dissolution.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-116">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-173</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྲོག་དང་ཐུར་སེལ་ལམ་གསུམ་གྱི། །འདི་ནི་རྩ་ཡི་ཀུན་སྤྱོད་དོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>This is the movement in the channels Along the threefold paths of both the vital wind and the downward-moving wind.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-117">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-174</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཡོན་པའམ་ནི་གཡས་པ་ལ། །མཚན་མོ་གཅིག་དང་དེ་བཞིན་ལྔར། །ལྷག་པའི་རླུང་ནི་རབ་འབབ་པ། །དེ་ལས་ལོ་གསུམ་ན་འཆིའོ། །གཡས་པ་ཉི་མའི་འཆི་ལྟས་ལ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{69}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-174"/> If excessive vital wind flows In the left or right channels For one or five nights [and days], Then one will die within three years.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-118">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-175</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལྔ་དང་ཕྱོགས་ཆོས་ཉི་ཤུ་དང་། །དེ་ཉིད་གཅིག་ལྷག་གཞན་རིམ་པས། །ཉིན་ཞག་སུམ་ཅུ་གསུམ་རྒྱུ་ན། །གསུམ་གཉིས་གཅིག་ལོ་ཟླ་བ་ནི། །དྲུག་གསུམ་ཟུང་ཟླ་ཉིན་ཞག་ཚེས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{70}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-175"/> [If the vital wind flows] with the death sign of the sun in the right channel, For five, ten, fifteen, twenty, twenty-five, Twenty-six, and twenty-seven [nights and] days, Then for thirty-three (i.e., fifteen, ten, five, and three nights and days), {71}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-176"/> The life of embodied beings will be gone Within a period of three, two, or one year, Six, three, two, or one month, Fifteen, ten, five, or three days, respectively.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-119">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-175</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཕྱོགས་ལྔ་ཡོན་ཏན་གཉིས་<tei:ref folio="F.17.a"/>གཅིག་གིས། །ལུས་ཅན་རྣམས་ཀྱི་ཚེ་འགྲོའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>[Then only] two, [and finally only] one day [are left].</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-120">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-178</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྩ་བ་ནས་གཅིག་ལྷག་པ་ཡིས། །གཡོན་པར་ཟླ་བའི་རྒྱུ་བར་འགྱུར། །ཉི་ཟླ་ཉིན་ཞག་ཟླ་བ་དག །ཉིན་ཞག་གསུམ་རྣམས་ཟླ་བ་གསུམ། །ཉིན་ལ་འཆི་ལྟས་ཟླ་བར་དགེ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{72} <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-178"/>With the ascent of the moon from the base In the left channel, one by one, For days and months, In steps of three days and three months, {73}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-179"/> The days of death signs increase And the months of virtue decrease.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-121">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-178</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཕེལ་འགྲིབ་དེ་ནས་འདི་དག་ལ། །དབུ་མའི་འཆི་བའི་རྒྱུ་བ་ནི། །ལོ་བརྒྱ་ཡོངས་སུ་རྫོགས་པ་ཡིས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Further, death ascends in the middle channel At the completion of one hundred years.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-122">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-180</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མཉམ་དང་མི་མཉམ་ཉིན་ཞག་རྣམས། །སྐྱེ་བར་སྐྱེས་པའི་དཀྱིལ་འཁོར་གྱིས། །དེ་རྒྱུ་གཡས་དང་གཡོན་ལ་ཡང་། །ཕྱོགས་གཉིས་རྣམ་པར་ཉམས་པ་ལས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{74}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-180"/> Its ascent occurs in relation to even and odd days And in relation to the maṇḍalas arisen at the time of birth Once the two parts [of the lotus] on the right and left side [Consisting of six petals each] have been destroyed.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-123">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-181</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཞན་དུ་འཆི་བར་མི་འགྱུར་ཏེ། །ཕྱོགས་གཉིས་ཡང་དག་གནས་པ་ན། །གཡས་དང་གཡོན་པའི་ཀུན་སྤྱོད་དང་། །དཀྱིལ་འཁོར་ལྔ་རྣམས་འབབ་པའི་ཕྱིར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{75}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-181"/> Otherwise, there will be no death When the two parts [of the lotus] remain Due to the movement of [vital wind in those] left and right parts, And because the five maṇḍalas [of earth and the rest] remain active.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-124">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-182</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཆི་ལྟས་མཚན་ཉིད་ཤེས་ནས་ནི། །སྲོག་ནི་ཐིག་ལེར་གཞུག་པར་བྱ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{76}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-182"/> Knowing the defining characteristics of the death signs, [The adept] must bring the vital wind into the drop.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-125">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-182</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཨ་བ་དྷཱུ་ཏཱིའི་ཞབས་བརྟེན་ནས། །མཆོག་ཏུ་མི་འགྱུར་བསྒོམ་པར་བྱ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Based on the bottom of the avadhūtī, Great immovable bliss must be cultivated.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-126">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-183</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྟག་ཏུ་རྡོ་རྗེ་བསླང་བར་བྱ། །ཟླ་ཉིའི་བགྲོད་པ་འཇོམས་པ་ལས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{77}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-183"/> One needs to keep the vajra continuously erect, Because the paths of the moon and the sun are suppressed.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-127">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-184</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཞན་དུ་ཀུན་འདར་ཡན་ལག་ལ། །སྲོག་གི་རླུང་ནི་འཇུག་པ་མེད། །འོག་ཏུའང་དུང་ཅན་མ་ཐུར་སེལ། །དེ་མ་ཞུགས་ལས་འཆི་བའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Otherwise, the vital wind Will not enter the body of the avadhūtī, {78}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-184"/> Nor will the downward-moving wind enter the śaṅkhinī; And, as a consequence, there will be death.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-128">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-184</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཆི་ལྟས་བསླུ་བ་རྣལ་འབྱོར་པའི། །འདི་ནི་དགའ་བ་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>This circumvention of the death signs Will occur through the four joys of the yogin.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-129">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-185</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མགོ་བོའི་པདྨ་གཙུག་ཏོར་ལས། །ཁུ་བ་འོངས་པ་དགའ་བ་སྟེ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{79}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-185"/> The initial joy is the descent of the semen From the lotus at the crown of the head to the one between the eyebrows.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-130">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-185</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མགྲིན་པ་སྙིང་ཁར་མཆོག་དགའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Between the throat and the heart there is the supreme joy; From there, descending further, the intense joy.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-131">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-186</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དགའ་བྲལ་དགའ་བ་དེ་ནས་འགྱུར། །སྣ་ཚོགས་དགའ་བ་ལྟེ་བ་དང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{80}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-186"/> This variegated joy (i.e., intense joy) [occurs until the semen is] at the navel.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-132">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-186</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གསང་བའི་པདྨར་གང་འོངས་པའོ། །གསང་གནས་རྡོ་རྗེ་ནོར་བུའི་བར། །ལྷན་ཅིག་སྐྱེས་དགའ་མི་འཕོ་བ། །རབ་གནས་མྱ་ངན་འདས་པ་མིན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>At this point, having entered the secret lotus, The semen descends into the vajra jewel, Causing coemergent joy—so long as it is not emitted.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-133">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-187</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཆགས་ཆེན་མི་འགྱུར་ཁྱབ་བདག་པོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{81}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-187"/> Therefore he is called the all-pervading lord of immovable great passion.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-134">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-187</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདོད་ཆགས་བྲལ་ལས་འཕོ་མེད་བདེ། །དེ་ནི་མྱ་ངན་འདས་རབ་གནས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Being in nonabiding nirvāṇa, [he avoids these two situations:] [The semen abiding at the crown of the head] due to the lack of passion, And blissful emission, which is abiding nirvāṇa.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-135">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-189</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཁུ་བ་ཟླ་ཆར་གཙུག་ཏོར་དུ། །རྫོགས་པ་གསང་བའི་མཚོ་སྐྱེས་ལ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{82} <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-189"/>The manifestation of the moon drop of semen is located at the crown of the head, And the phase of the full moon in the lotus of the secret part.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-136">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-189</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅུ་དྲུག་ཆ་གང་དེ་ནོར་བུའི། །པདྨར་རྡོ་རྗེའི་རྩེ་མོར་གནས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The sixteenth phase is located in the lotus of the jewel, At the tip of the vajra.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-137">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-190</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་སྟེང་འཕོ་བའི་དུས་སུ་འགྱུར། །ནག་པོའི་ཚེས་གཅིག་འོངས་པ་ན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{83}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-190"/> After that, at the beginning of the dark period, There is the phase of emission.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-138">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-190</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདོད་ཆགས་བྲལ་བས་གནམ་སྟོང་ལ། །ཉི་མ་མཛོད་སྤུའི་<tei:ref folio="F.17.b"/>གནས་སུ་འགྲོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The sun, because of the absence of passion, Arrives at the place of the tuft [between the eyebrows] at the time of the new moon.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-139">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-191</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ཡི་ཆ་ཤས་བཅུ་དྲུག་ལ། །གཙུག་ཏོར་པདྨར་སོན་པའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{84}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-191"/> The sixteenth solar phase Is located in the lotus at the crown of the head.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-140">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-191</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཟླ་བ་ཉམས་པ་ཞེས་བརྗོད་དེ། །ཆགས་པའི་བདེ་ལ་ཆགས་བྲལ་ཕྱིར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Because of non-attachment to passionate bliss in this state, It is called moonless.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-141">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-192</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལུས་ཅན་ཐམས་ཅད་འཆི་བ་ན། །ཟླ་བ་བདུད་རྩིའི་འོག་ཏུ་འགྲོ། །སྟེང་དུ་ཉི་མ་རྡུལ་སྒྲ་གཅན། །རྣམ་ཤེས་དངོས་པོའི་མཚན་ཉིད་ལ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{85}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-192"/> In all corporeal beings, at the time of death, The lunar nectar moves downward; The solar blood upward; and the consciousness, which is Rāhu, To what is characterized by becoming (i.e., rebirth).</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-142">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-193</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ཕྱིར་ཟླ་བ་བདུད་རྩི་ནི། །སྟེང་དུ་བགྲོད་བྱ་མི་ཡི་བདག །འོག་ཏུ་ཉི་མ་རྡུལ་སྒྲ་གཅན། །རྣམ་ཤེས་འགྱུར་མེད་བདེ་བ་ལ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{86}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-193"/> For this reason, O King, You must make the lunar nectar move upward, The solar blood downward, And the consciousness, which is Rāhu, to immovable bliss.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-143">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-194</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སངས་རྒྱས་ཀུན་གྱི་མཛོད་སྤུ་ཡི། །པདྨར་ཟླ་བ་བདུད་རྩི་ཉ། །ཉི་རྡུལ་གནམ་སྟོང་གསང་བར་ཏེ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{87}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-194"/> The full moon of the lunar nectar Occurs for all buddhas in the lotus of the tuft between the eyebrows, And the new moon of solar blood in the secret part.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-144">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-194</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཙུག་ཏོར་ནོར་བུར་དེ་དག་གོ །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The sixteenth phase of these two occurs in the crown of the head and the jewel.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-145">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-195</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཞེས་པ་སྟོན་པའི་རྡོ་རྗེའི་ཚིག །ལུས་ཅན་ཀུན་གྱི་ཕྱིན་ཅི་ལོག །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{88}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-195"/> This vajra verse of the Teacher Is in opposition to the situation of corporeal beings.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-146">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-195</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རབ་གནས་མྱ་ངན་འདས་པ་མིན། །ཁམས་རྣམས་ཕྱིན་ཅི་ལོག་ཏུ་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>His nirvāṇa is nonabiding, In opposition to the elements.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-147">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-196</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ནོར་བུར་ཐུགས་དང་གསང་བར་གསུང་། །ལྟེ་བར་སྐུ་སྟེ་བདེ་ཆེན་ལས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{89}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-196"/> The mind in the jewel, the speech in the secret part, And the body in the navel emerge from great bliss.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-148">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-196</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཆོས་དང་ལོངས་སྤྱོད་རྫོགས་སྤྲུལ་པ། །འདི་རྣམས་དག་པའི་སྐུ་ལས་སྤྲོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The dharmakāya, saṃbhogakāya, and nirmāṇakāya Radiate from this pure body.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-149">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-197</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཐབས་ཀྱི་འོག་ཏུ་རྒྱལ་པོའི་དབང་། །ཤེས་རབ་ཀྱི་ནི་སྟེང་དུ་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{90}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-197"/> What emerges from below, O King, belongs to means, And what emerges from above belongs to insight (Skt.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-150">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-197</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདི་ཡི་དཔྲལ་བར་སྐུ་རྡོ་རྗེ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>prajñā). The body vajra of the prajñā is at the forehead.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-151">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-198</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མགྲིན་སྙིང་ལྟེ་བའི་འདམ་སྐྱེས་ལ། །གསུང་ཐུགས་ཡེ་ཤེས་རྡོ་རྗེ་རྣམས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The vajras of speech, mind, and wisdom {91}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-198"/> Are at the lotuses of the throat, heart, and navel.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-152">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-198</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྤྲུལ་པ་ལ་སོགས་འདི་རྣམས་སྤྲོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They (i.e., the vajras of body, speech, mind, and wisdom) radiate from the nirmāṇakāya and the other bodies.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-153">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-198</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཕུང་པོ་ཁམས་རྣམས་སྤྲོ་བ་ནི། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The psycho-physical aggregates and elements radiate From unobstructed bliss (i.e., the body of Vajrasattva).</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-154">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-199</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྒྲིབ་པ་མེད་པའི་བདེ་བ་ལས། །ལས་ཀྱི་ཕྱག་རྒྱའི་སྙོམས་འཇུག་དང་། །ཡེ་ཤེས་ཕྱག་རྒྱའི་དམིགས་པ་དང་། །ཕྱག་རྒྱ་ཆེན་པོ་གཅིག་སྦྱོར་བས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{92}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-199"/> Due to the union with a karmamudrā, The visualized support of a jñānamudrā, And the unique union with a mahāmudrā, Immovable bliss increases.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-155">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-200</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མི་འགྱུར་བ་དེ་འཕེལ་བར་འགྱུར། །འཕེལ་བའི་འཕེལ་བར་འགྱུར་བ་མེད། །ཉམས་པའི་ཉམས་པ་ཉིད་ཀྱང་མེད། །ནུབ་པ་དེ་ཡི་ནུབ་པ་མེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{93}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-200"/> Of that which has increased, there is no increasing; Of that which has diminished, there is no diminishing.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-156">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-200</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཆར་བ་ཡི་ནི་འཆར་བ་མེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Of that which has set, there is no setting; Likewise, of that which has risen, there is no rising.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-157">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-201</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རབ་ཏུ་གསལ་བའི་རབ་གསལ་མེད། །བཀབ་པའི་བཀབ་པ་ཡང་མེད་དོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{94}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-201"/> Of that which is illuminated, there is no illumination; Of that which is obscured, there is also no obscuring.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-158">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-201</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྐྱེ་བའི་སྐྱེ་བར་འགྱུར་ཉིད་མེད། །འཆི་བའི་འཆི་བ་ཡང་མེད་དོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Of that which is born, there is no taking birth; Of that which is dead, there is no dying.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-159">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-202</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གྲོལ་བའི་གྲོལ་བར་འགྱུར་བའང་མེད། །མི་གནས་པ་ཡི་མི་གནས་མེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{95}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-202"/> Of that which is liberated, there is also no liberation; Of that which does not abide, there is no nonabiding.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-160">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-202</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དངོས་པོ་མེད་པའི་དངོས་མེད་མེད། །དངོས་པོའི་པོ་ཉིད་ཀྱང་མེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Of that which does not exist, there is no nonexistence; Of that which exists, there is no existence.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-161">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-203</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འགྱུར་བའི་འགྱུར་བར་འགྱུར་བའང་མེད། །མི་འགྱུར་བའི་ཡང་མི་འགྱུར་མེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{96}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-203"/> Of that which moves, there is no movement; And of that which does not move, there is no nonmovement.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-162">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-203</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རང་བཞིན་མེད་པའི་<tei:ref folio="F.18.a"/>ཆོས་རྣམས་ཀྱི། །སྐྱེ་འཇིག་སྒྱུ་མ་དེ་བཞིན་ནོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The rise and fall of all phenomena, Which lack their own nature, are thus an illusion.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-163">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-204</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འབྱུང་རྣམས་འཇིག་པར་འགྱུར་མིན་ཏེ། །རང་བཞིན་ཉིད་ཀྱིས་སྐྱེ་མི་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{97}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-204"/> Elements neither come into nor pass out of existence By means of their own nature.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-164">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-204</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྣ་ཚོགས་འདི་ནི་རང་བཞིན་མེད། །དངོས་པོ་དངོས་མེད་མཚན་ཉིད་གཅིག །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>This manifold world lacks its own nature And has the unique characteristics of [apparent] existence and [ultimate] nonexistence.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-165">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-205</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རང་གི་ཤེས་རབ་ལ་འཁྱུད་སེམས། །རྡོ་རྗེ་ནོར་བུའི་པདྨར་སོན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{98}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-205"/> When embracing one’s prajñā (i.e., karmamudrā), the bodhicitta Enters the vajra jewel, which by then is inside the lotus.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-166">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-205</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེར་སོན་ཟླ་བ་གཡོ་བ་དང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>When the moon (i.e., bodhicitta) has entered into the jewel, it is in vibration.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-167">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-205</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མི་གཡོ་བ་དང་མི་འགྱུར་བསྒོམ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The meditation on the unchangeable [mahāmudrā] is free from vibration.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-168">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-206</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལུས་ངག་སེམས་ཀྱི་རྩ་རྣམས་སུ། །སྐུ་གསུང་ཐུགས་རྣམས་བསྒོམ་པ་སྟེ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{99}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-206"/> The meditation on body, speech, and mind Is based on the channels of body, speech, and mind.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-169">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-206</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྡོ་རྗེ་གསུམ་རྣམས་ལེགས་བསྡུས་པ། །ཡེ་ཤེས་དུང་ཅན་མར་བསྒོམ་པའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The fusion of the three vajras [of body, speech, and mind] In the śaṅkhinī is the meditation on jñāna.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-170">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-207</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཤེས་རབ་ཆགས་པས་ཞུ་བ་ཡི། །ཐིག་ལེ་རིམ་པས་མགོ་བོ་ལས། །རྫོགས་པའི་གནས་སུ་ཞུགས་རྣམས་ཀྱང་། །འཆིང་བ་དམ་པའི་དོན་གྱིས་སོ། །ཇི་ལྟར་ཟླ་ཤར་རིམ་པ་ཡིས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{100}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-207"/> Because of attachment to the prajñā, the drops Trickle from the head via the aforementioned stages, And enter the stage of the full [moon].</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-171">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-207</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཆ་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་ནི་རྫོགས་པར་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They are fixed through [meditation on] the ultimate.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-172">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-208</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གྲིབ་མ་ཉམས་པ་རྫོགས་པ་སྟེ། །ཟླ་བ་ཆད་དང་རྫོགས་པ་མིན། །དེ་བཞིན་ཡེ་ཤེས་ཤར་རིམ་པས། །ས་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་ནི་རྫོགས་པར་འགྱུར། །ཉོན་མོངས་ལ་སོགས་ཉམས་པ་རྫོགས། །ཡེ་ཤེས་ཆད་དང་རྫོགས་པ་མིན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{101}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-208"/> Just as the waxing moon Becomes gradually full along its phases— Its fullness due to the receding of its shadow, And not because of being annihilated and made full again— {102}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-209"/> So the waxing wisdom Becomes gradually full along the bodhisattva levels— Its fullness due to the receding of defilements and so forth, And not because of being annihilated and made full again.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-173">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-210</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཇི་ལྟར་རི་བོང་མཚན་མས་དབུས། །རྫོགས་པར་རི་བོང་ཅན་མི་གནས། །དེ་བཞིན་འགྱུར་མེད་བདེ་བར་སེམས། །འཁོར་བའི་བག་ཆགས་མཚན་མ་ཡིས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{103}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-210"/> Just as the moon, with the mark of the rabbit in its middle, Does not remain in the phase of the full moon, So, too, the mind does not remain in unchangeable bliss Because of its mark of saṃsāric imprints.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-174">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-211</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྐྱེད་དང་རབ་ཏུ་ཉམས་པའི་ཕྱོགས། །དཀར་པོ་ནག་པོར་རབ་ཏུ་གནས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{104}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-211"/> The waxing and waning fortnights Are established as the bright and the dark.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-175">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-211</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་དག་དབུས་སུ་རྫོགས་པ་གང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The full moon in between these two Does not remain at its fullest.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-176">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-212</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནི་རྫོགས་པར་མི་གནས་སོ། །སྐད་ཅིག་གཅིག་མངོན་རྫོགས་སངས་རྒྱས། །རྫོགས་པ་ལ་ནི་གཡོ་མི་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{105}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-212"/> Fully complete enlightenment in one instant Is immovable in its fullness.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-177">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-212</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་ཚེ་རྡོ་རྗེ་ནོར་བུར་སེམས། །དེ་ནི་སྐད་ཅིག་ཐམས་ཅད་རྫོགས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>When the bodhicitta is in the vajra jewel, It fills all moments with this experience.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-178">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-213</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དཀར་པོའི་ཕྱོགས་ལ་འདི་མི་གནས། །རེས་འགའ་དཀར་མིན་ལ་མི་འགྲོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{106}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-213"/> [The mind vajra] is neither based on the bright fortnight, Nor does it go to the dark one.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-179">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-213</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཕྱོགས་གཉིས་པོ་ཡི་དབུས་གནས་པ། །རྫོགས་པ་ལ་གནས་གཉིས་སུ་མེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>It is located in the middle of the two sides— Based on the full moon, without duality.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-180">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-214</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཙུག་ཏོར་ལས་ནི་ཤར་བ་དེའི། །རྡོ་རྗེ་ནོར་བུར་རྫོགས་པར་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{107}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-214"/> Its waxing starts from the crown of the head And becomes full in the vajra jewel.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-181">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-214</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ཆགས་བྲལ་ལས་ཆ་ཉམས་པ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Due to lack of passion, these lunar phases are lost.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-182">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-214</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྡོ་རྗེ་ནས་ཉམས་ལ་རབ་རྫོགས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Because of this loss, [The solar blood] starts from the vajra, becoming full [at the crown of the head].</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-183">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-215</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སླར་ཡང་གཙུག་ཏོར་དུ་ཤར་བ། །སླར་ཡང་རྡོ་རྗེ་ནོར་བུར་རྫོགས། །<tei:ref folio="F.18.b"/>
                </seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{108}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-215"/> For corporeal beings, waxing happens again at the crown of the head, And fullness in the [vajra] jewel.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-184">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-215</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ཆགས་བྲལ་ལས་ཆ་ཉམས་པ། །ལུས་ཅན་ཡེ་ཤེས་ཉམས་པ་མིན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Due to lack of passion, these lunar phases are lost, But there is no loss of wisdom (i.e., the sixteenth lunar phase).</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-185">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-216</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདི་ཡི་བདེ་བ་ཆེ་རང་བཞིན། །རྫོགས་པའི་སྒྲ་ཡིས་བརྗོད་པར་བྱ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{109}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-216"/> Its (i.e., bodhicitta’s) nature is great bliss And is praised using the metaphor of the full moon.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-186">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-216</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དངོས་པོ་བར་མ་གཞན་ཐམས་ཅད། །འབྱུང་དང་སྡུད་པའི་རྒྱུ་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>All other things are the cause Of creation and dissolution [of sentient beings’ great bliss].</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-187">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-217</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྲིད་ལས་མྱ་ངན་འདས་པར་འགྲོ། །དེ་ལས་སླར་ཡང་སྲིད་པར་འོང་། །རང་ཕྱོགས་དག་ལས་ཟླ་བཞིན་དང་། །བགྲོད་པ་དག་ལས་སྣང་བྱེད་བཞིན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{110}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-217"/> Just as the moon [proceeds] through its two fortnights And the sun through its two routes, So nirvāṇa proceeds from existence And existence from nirvāṇa.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-188">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-218</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྫོགས་པར་མི་གཡོ་བ་འདི་ནི། །ས་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་ནི་ཡོངས་རྫོགས་ཉིད། །ཉི་ཁྲི་བརྒྱད་གཉིས་བརྒྱ་ཡི་དབུགས། །འགྱུར་མེད་སྐད་ཅིག་ཟོས་རྣམས་ཀྱིས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{111}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-218"/> Immovable great bliss is completed Through the [bodhisattva] levels during the full moon, With the help of 21,600 breaths, Which are devoured by moments of immovable bliss.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-189">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-219</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཕྱོགས་གཉིས་ཡང་དག་གནོན་པ་ནི། །ས་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་ནི་ཡོངས་སུ་རྫོགས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{112}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-219"/> It (i.e., immovable bliss) is without the two fortnights, And is completed through the [bodhisattva] levels.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-190">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-219</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བདེན་དོན་རྣམ་པ་བཅུ་གཉིས་པ། །རྣམ་པ་བཅུ་དྲུག་འགྱུར་བ་མེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Its true meaning has twelve aspects, And its immovable character has sixteen aspects.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-191">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-220</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྣམ་པ་བཅུ་གཉིས་ས་རྣམས་ཀྱིས། །རྫོགས་པ་གཉིས་སུ་མེད་པ་མཆོག །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{113}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-220"/> Through the [bodhisattva] levels it is full In twelve aspects, being supreme nonduality.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-192">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-220</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཆ་ཤས་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་རྫོགས་པའི་སེམས། །རྣམ་པ་བཅུ་དྲུག་མི་འགྱུར་བ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The bodhicitta, which is full through the lunar phases, Has sixteen aspects.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-193">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-221</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དོན་གཅིག་གཉིས་སུ་མེད་པ་ཆོས། །དམ་པའི་དོན་ཏེ་འཇིག་པ་མེད། །རྫོགས་པའི་གནས་སྐབས་སོན་པའི་སེམས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{114}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-221"/> It is of one meaning, a phenomenon beyond duality, The ultimate, indestructible.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-194">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-221</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཀུན་ནས་རབ་ཏུ་རྫོགས་པའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>It is bodhicitta in the state of fullness, Completely full in every way.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-195">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-222</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཆགས་བྲལ་དང་པོ་ཆགས་པ་ཆེ། །རྡོ་རྗེ་ལུས་མེད་མི་འགྱུར་ཆེ། །ཡོངས་སུ་རྫོགས་པ་ཕྱོགས་གཉིས་ཀྱི། །བག་ཆགས་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་འཁྱུད་པའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{115}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-222"/> It is the great passion, which starts with freedom from passion, Vajra body, great immovable bliss, Completely full, and unpolluted By the imprints of both sides (i.e., passion and freedom from passion).</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-196">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-223</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཇི་ལྟར་ཆུ་བོའི་ཆུ་ཞུགས་པ། །དེ་ནི་རྒྱ་མཚོར་ཆུར་མཚུངས་པ། །དེ་བཞིན་དངོས་པོའི་ཚོགས་འདི་དེ། །འགྱུར་བ་མེད་པར་འགྱུར་མེད་མཚུངས། །ཇི་ལྟར་ཁམས་ཀྱི་ཚོགས་པ་འདིས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{116}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-223"/> Just as the waters of rivers become the same As the ocean upon entering it, So, too, the entirety of existence becomes the same As the immovable upon entering it.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-197">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-224</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཟོས་པ་ལས་ནི་རོ་ཉིད་འགྱུར། །ས་བོན་རང་བཞིན་ས་བོན་གྱིས། །འབྲས་བུའི་དུས་སུ་ང་རྒྱལ་སྤངས། །དེ་ལྟར་དངོས་པོའི་ཚོགས་པ་ཡང་། །མཆོག་ཏུ་མི་འགྱུར་ཟོས་པ་ཡིས། །མཆོག་ཏུ་མི་འགྱུར་བ་ཉིད་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{117}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-224"/> Just as a set of metals becomes an elixir When it is devoured [by mercury], And just as the nature of seeds is acquired through the seeds And beyond measure at the time of fruition, {118}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-225"/> So, too, the entirety of existence, When devoured by supreme immovable (bliss), Becomes supreme immovable bliss, Which embraces all aspects.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-198">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-226</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྣམ་པ་ཐམས་ཅད་རང་བཞིན་འཛིན། །མཆེ་བའི་ཚོར་བ་སྡུག་བསྔལ་ནི། །དུག་རྫོགས་གནས་སྐབས་གྱུར་པ་ན། །རྨ་ལ་རིག་མིན་གཞན་དུ་མིན། །ཡུལ་དང་དབང་པོའི་སྒོ་རྣམས་ཀྱིས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{119}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-226"/> He who is bitten does not notice the pain In the wound or elsewhere, Nor does he notice objects through his sense faculties, When the poison develops its full effect.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-199">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-227</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་བཞིན་རྣལ་འབྱོར་དམ་པའི་བདེ། །སེམས་རྫོགས་ཆར་གྱུར་ན་<tei:ref folio="F.19.a"/>རྡོ་རྗེ། །ནོར་བུར་རིག་མིན་གཞན་དུ་མིན། །ཡུལ་རྣམས་དབང་པོའི་སྒོ་རྣམས་ཀྱིས། །ཇི་ལྟར་རོ་ཆེན་ལྕགས་རྣམས་ཀྱི། །ཕྱོགས་གཅིག་ཡང་དག་གནས་པ་ནི། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{120}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-227"/> Likewise, the yogin does not experience true bliss In the vajra jewel or elsewhere, Nor does he notice objects through his sense faculties, When the bodhicitta has reached the phase of the full moon.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-200">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-228</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལྕགས་ལ་དྲག་པོའི་མེས་གདུངས་ན། །ཀུན་ནས་ཀུན་ཏུ་འབིགས་པར་བྱེད། །དེ་བཞིན་ཉིད་དུ་འགྱུར་མེད་བདེ། །ཕྱོགས་གཅིག་ཡང་དག་གནས་པ་ཡང་། །སེམས་ལ་འདོད་པའི་མེས་གདུངས་ན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{121}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-228"/> Just as the great elixir is first present In only one part of the metal, And then penetrates to every part of the metal When red-hot from violent fire, {122}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-229"/> So, too, the immovable bliss is first present In only one part (i.e., the vajra jewel) And then penetrates every part of the mind When the latter is red-hot from the fire of desire.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-201">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-230</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཀུན་ནས་ཀུན་ཏུ་འབིགས་པར་བྱེད། །ཇི་ལྟར་ཕུག་པའི་ལྕགས་རྣམས་ནི། །འགའ་ཞིག་ཏུ་ཡང་དྲི་མ་མེད། །དེ་བཞིན་དུ་ནི་ཕུག་པའི་སེམས། །འགའ་ཞིག་ཏུ་ཡང་བག་ཆགས་མེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{123}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-230"/> Just as metals that are penetrated by the elixir Have no stains anywhere, So, too, the penetrated mindstreams Have no imprints anywhere.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-202">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-231</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལྕགས་ནི་གསེར་ཉིད་དུ་གྱུར་པ། །མེ་ཡིས་དྲི་མ་མེད་པར་འགྱུར། །དེ་བཞིན་ཡང་དང་ཡང་དུ་སེམས། །འདོད་ཆགས་མེ་ཡིས་དྲི་མ་མེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{124}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-231"/> Just as metal transformed into gold Becomes stainless through fire, So, too, the mind, repeatedly red-hot from the fire of passion, Becomes stainless.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-203">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-232</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཇི་ལྟར་ནོར་བུ་ཆེ་རེག་ལས། །རྡོ་ནི་རབ་ཏུ་འབར་བར་འགྱུར། །དེ་བཞིན་འགྱུར་མེད་བདེ་རེག་ལས། །སེམས་ནི་བདེ་བ་ཉིད་དུ་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{125}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-232"/> Just as a stone clearly shines When touched by a great jewel, So, too, the mind becomes blissful Through contact with immovable bliss.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-204">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-233</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདིར་ནི་མང་པོ་བརྗོད་པས་ཅི། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{126}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-233"/> But why all these words here?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-205">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-233</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇིག་རྟེན་ཀུན་རྫོབ་བདེན་པ་ཡིས། །ལྕགས་རྣམས་རབ་ཏུ་འབིགས་བྱེད་པ། །རོ་ཡི་མཐུ་ནི་བརྟག་བྱ་མིན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>On the level of the relative truth of the world, The power of the elixir is incomprehensible In terms of penetrating metal.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-206">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-234</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཅི་ཞིག་སླར་ཡང་དོན་དམ་པས། །བློ་བུར་དྲི་མས་གཡོགས་པ་ཡི། །སེམས་ནི་རབ་ཏུ་འབིགས་བྱེད་པ། །ཡེ་ཤེས་མཐུ་ནི་བརྟག་བྱ་མིན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{127}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-234"/> How much more, on the level of ultimate truth, Is the power of wisdom incomprehensible In terms of penetrating the mind Defiled by adventitious stains?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-207">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-235</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སེམས་ལ་བློ་བུར་དྲི་མ་མེད། །སེམས་ལས་ཡུན་རིང་དུས་ཅན་མིན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{128}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-235"/> The stains are neither externally added to the mind, Nor are they older than the mind.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-208">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-235</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སེམས་མེད་པར་ནི་སྐྱེ་བ་མེད། །སེམས་ལ་མི་ཟད་གནས་པ་མིན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They are neither born elsewhere than the mind, Nor do they remain inexhaustibly in the mind.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-209">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-236</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གལ་ཏེ་འདི་ཉིད་བློ་བུར་པ། །དེ་ཚེ་སྔོན་དུ་སེམས་དྲི་མེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{129}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-236"/> If the stains were externally added, Then the mind would have been stainless beforehand.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-210">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-236</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་ཚེ་སེམས་ལས་དུས་རིང་ཅན། །དེ་ཚེ་དེ་ནི་ཅི་ལས་སྐྱེ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>If they had existed before the mind, Then what could they have arisen from?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-211">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-237</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གལ་ཏེ་སེམས་མེད་པར་སྐྱེ་ན། །དེ་ཚེ་ནམ་མཁའི་མེ་ཏོག་མཚུངས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{130}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-237"/> If they had arisen without the mind, Then they would be like a sky-flower.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-212">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-237</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གལ་ཏེ་སེམས་ལ་རྟག་ཏུ་གནས། །དེ་ཚེ་ཀུན་ཏུ་ཐར་པ་མིན། །ཇི་ལྟར་ཟངས་ཀྱི་དྲི་མ་ནི། །རོ་ཡི་སྦྱོར་བས་ཉམས་པར་འགྱུར། །དེ་ཡི་ཡོད་ཉིད་ཉམས་པ་མེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>If they had always resided in the mind, Then they could never be eliminated.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-213">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-238</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དྲི་མེད་ཉིད་ཀྱིས་ཡང་དག་གནས། །དེ་བཞིན་སེམས་ཀྱི་དྲི་མ་ནི། །སྟོང་ཉིད་སྦྱོར་བས་རྣམ་ཉམས་འགྱུར། །དེ་ཡི་ཡེ་ཤེས་ཉིད་ཉམས་མེད། །དྲི་མེད་ཉིད་ཀྱིས་ཡང་དག་གནས། །<tei:ref folio="F.19.b"/>
                </seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{131}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-238"/> Just as the stains of copper Are eliminated through union with an elixir, And its existence—which remains stainless— Is not eliminated, {132}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-239"/> So, too, the stains of mind Are eliminated through its union with emptiness, And its wisdom—which remains stainless— Is not eliminated.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-214">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-240</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཇི་ལྟར་བཅུད་ཀྱིས་ཕུག་པའི་ལྕགས། །ལྕགས་ཉིད་དུ་ནི་རྗེས་འགྲོ་མིན། །དེ་བཞིན་བདེ་བས་ཕུག་པའི་སེམས། །སྡུག་བསྔལ་ཉིད་དུ་རྗེས་འགྲོ་མིན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{133}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-240"/> Just as iron that has been penetrated by the elixir Does not revert to the nature of iron, So, too, the mind that has been penetrated by bliss Does not revert to a state of suffering.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-215">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-241</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཆགས་བྲལ་ལས་གཞན་སྡིག་པ་མེད། །བདེ་བ་ལས་གཞན་བསོད་ནམས་མེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{134}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-241"/> There is no greater transgression than the lack of passion; No greater merit than supreme bliss.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-216">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-241</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ཕྱིར་འགྱུར་མེད་བདེ་བར་སེམས། །མི་བདག་རྟག་ཏུ་གནས་པར་བྱ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Therefore, the mind should constantly embrace Immovable bliss, O King!</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-217">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-242</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཞོན་ནུ་མ་ཡི་དགའ་བ་ནི། །མེད་པར་བདེ་བ་སྨྲ་མི་ནུས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{135}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-242"/> Without having made love, a young maiden Cannot describe sexual bliss.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-218">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-242</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལང་ཚོའི་དགའ་བ་ཐོབ་པ་ན། །བདེ་བ་ཆེན་པོ་རང་གིས་རིག །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Having made love in her youth, She will know great bliss for herself.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-219">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-243</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་བཞིན་ཏིང་འཛིན་དང་བྲལ་བའི། །བདེ་བ་སྨྲ་བར་ནུས་མ་ཡིན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{136}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-243"/> Likewise, bliss cannot be described By those without meditative concentration.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-220">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-243</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འགྱུར་མེད་ཏིང་འཛིན་ཐོབ་པ་ན། །རྣལ་འབྱོར་པ་ཡིས་རང་རིག་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>When immovable bliss is attained in meditative concentration, The yogins will know it for themselves.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-221">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-244</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འགྱུར་མེད་ལས་སྐྱེས་བདེ་རིག་པ། །ཐམས་ཅད་མཁྱེན་ལའང་ཐེ་ཙོམ་ཟ། །དེ་ལྟ་ན་ཡང་ཡིད་བདེ་མིན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{137}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-244"/> Even the omniscient ones are uncertain About recognizing the bliss which arises from the immovable.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-222">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-244</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཆགས་བྲལ་ཉིད་དུ་མི་བྱའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Thus, a state without passion must be avoided by all means, Because, without it, the mind will lack bliss.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-223">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-245</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཕོས་པ་ལས་ནི་ཆགས་བྲལ་འགྱུར། །ཆགས་བྲལ་ལས་ནི་སྡུག་བསྔལ་འབྱུང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{138}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-245"/> It is recorded that from emission the lack of passion is born, And from the lack of passion, suffering.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-224">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-245</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྡུག་བསྔལ་སྐྱེས་བུའི་ཁམས་ཟད་བྱེད། །ཟད་པ་ལས་ནི་འཆི་བར་བརྗོད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>From suffering, the elements of men are ruined, And from ruining the elements, death will come.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-225">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-246</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཤི་ལས་སླར་ཡང་དེ་རྣམས་ཀྱི། །སྲིད་པའོ་སྲིད་ལས་སླར་འཆི་འཕོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{139}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-246"/> From death a new existence will follow, And from that again, death and transmigration.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-226">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-246</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ལྟར་སེམས་ཅན་གྱི་སྲིད་པ། །ཆགས་བྲལ་ལས་འབྱུང་གཞན་དུ་མིན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Accordingly, the existence of sentient beings Comes from the lack of passion and nothing else.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-227">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-247</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ཕྱིར་འབད་པ་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱིས། །འཕོ་བའི་ཆགས་པ་རྣམ་པར་སྤངས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{140}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-247"/> Therefore, one must avoid with all effort The passion of emission.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-228">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-247</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་གིས་འགྱུར་མེད་བདེ་བར་འགྱུར། །རྣལ་འབྱོར་འཁོར་བར་བཅིངས་པ་ཡིས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>By doing so, the yogin proceeds From the fetters of saṃsāra to immovable bliss.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-229">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-248</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདོད་ལྡན་ཡང་ནི་ཆགས་བྲལ་བར། །འདོད་པའི་བསྟན་བཅོས་སུ་མི་འདོད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{141}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-248"/> Without passion one would not [even] be a [good] lover And not seek out the Kāmaśāstra.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-230">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-248</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བདག་གིས་བརྗོད་པའི་རྒྱུད་དུ་སླར། །རྣལ་འབྱོར་པ་ཅིས་སྡུག་བསྔལ་འདོད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Why, then, would a yogin (likewise) wish for suffering With regard to this tantra proclaimed by me?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-231">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-251</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཁུ་བ་མི་འགྱུར་རང་བཞིན་གྱིས། །མཆོག་ཏུ་མི་འགྱུར་བསྒྲུབ་པར་བྱ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{142} <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-251"/>Through a state in which the semen remains immovable, [The yogin] must attain supreme immovable (bliss).</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-232">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-251</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྟེན་ནི་འཕོ་བ་ཐོབ་པ་ན། །བརྟེན་པའི་འདོད་ཆགས་བྲལ་བ་ཉིད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Once the support has reached the state of emission, The supported will be passionless.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-233">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-253</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྟེན་དང་བརྟེན་པ་ལེགས་རྫོགས་པ། །ཇི་སྲིད་འགྱུར་མེད་ཉིད་དུ་འགྲོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{143}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-253"/> The relation of support and supported remains As long as [the mind] does not proceed to the immovable.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-234">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-253</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སེམས་ཀྱི་འགྱུར་མེད་ཉིད་ཐོབ་ན། །རྟེན་དང་བརྟེན་པའི་མཚན་ཉིད་མེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Once the mind has attained the immovable, It is without the characteristics of support and supported.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-235">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-254</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འགྱུར་མེད་ལས་བྱུང་སྐུ་ཡི་ནི། །མཛོད་སྤུའི་འཁོར་ལོར་སོན་པའི་ཡང་། །ཨཱ་ལི་ཀཱ་ལི་མཉམ་སྦྱོར་བ། །ཧཱུྃ་ཡིག་མི་འདོད་མི་ཡི་བདག །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{144}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-254"/> For the adept whose body has been born from the immovable And whose bodhicitta has reached the cakra at the forehead, Neither the union of the two series of vowels and consonants Nor the syllable hūṁ is needed anymore, O King.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-236">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-255</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྟོང་པ་ལས་བྱུང་གཟུགས་བརྙན་རྒྱུ། །<tei:ref folio="F.20.a"/>མི་འགྱུར་ལས་སྐྱེས་བདེ་བ་འབྲས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{145}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-255"/> The reflection, arisen from emptiness, is the cause, And bliss, born from the immovable, is the result.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-237">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-255</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྒྱུ་ནི་འབྲས་བུས་རྒྱས་བཏབ་པ། །འབྲས་བུ་རྒྱུ་ཡིས་རྒྱས་བཏབ་པའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The cause is sealed by the result, And the result is sealed by the cause.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-238">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-256</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྟོང་ཉིད་གཟུགས་བརྙན་འཛིན་པ་རྒྱུ། །སྙིང་རྗེ་འགྱུར་མེད་འཛིན་པ་འབྲས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{146}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-256"/> Holding the reflection of emptiness is the cause, Holding immovable compassion is the result.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-239">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-256</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྟོང་ཉིད་སྙིང་རྗེ་དབྱེར་མེད་པ། །བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དེ་མི་འཕོ་བའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Bodhicitta—which is inseparable from Emptiness and compassion—is not emitted.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-240">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-257</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མྱ་ངན་འདས་པ་བྲལ་བའི་གཟུགས། །འཁོར་བ་ལས་འདས་མི་འགྱུར་བ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{147}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-257"/> The reflection is free from nirvāṇa And the immovable transcends saṃsāra.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-241">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-257</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་དག་སྦྱོར་བ་གཉིས་མེད་མཆོག །རྟག་དང་ཆད་ལས་ངེས་པར་གྲོལ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Their union is supreme nonduality, Free from eternalism and nihilism.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-242">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-258</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དངོས་མེད་ལས་བྱུང་མཚན་ཉིད་ཕྱིར། །གཟུགས་ནི་དངོས་པོ་མེད་པ་མིན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{148}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-258"/> Because the reflection has the character of having arisen From nonexistence, it is not nonexistent.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-243">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-258</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དངོས་པོ་ལས་བྱུང་མཚན་ཉིད་ཕྱིར། །འགྱུར་བ་མེད་པ་དངོས་པོ་མིན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Because the immovable, in turn, has the character of having arisen From existence, existence does not apply to it.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-244">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-259</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དངོས་པོ་དངོས་མེད་ཡང་དག་སྦྱོར། །རྡོ་རྗེའི་རྣལ་འབྱོར་གཉིས་མེད་མཆོག །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{149}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-259"/> The perfect union of being and nonbeing Is the nondual, supreme vajrayoga.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-245">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-259</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཟུགས་དང་གཟུགས་མིན་རྣམ་པར་གྲོལ། །པྲ་ཕབ་མེ་ལོང་ལ་བཞིན་ནོ། །གཟུགས་ནི་སྲིད་པར་མི་འོང་སྟེ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>It is beyond form and nonform, Like a magical image in a mirror.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-246">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-260</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འགྱུར་མེད་མྱ་ངན་འདས་མི་འགྲོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{150}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-260"/> The reflection is not immersed in cyclic existence, Nor is the immovable immersed in nirvāṇa.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-247">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-260</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཕན་ཚུན་འཁྱུད་པས་ཞི་བ་སྟེ། །མ་ནིང་གི་ནི་གོ་འཕང་མཆོག །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Their mutual connection is peace: The supreme neutral state.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-248">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-261</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཤེས་རབ་རྒྱུ་ལས་མ་བྱུང་ཞིང་། །ཤེས་རབ་རྒྱུ་ལས་བྱུང་བ་འབྲས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{151}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-261"/> Because insight has not arisen from a cause, The result has arisen from insight as [its only possible] cause.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-249">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-261</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཤེས་རབ་རྒྱུ་ལས་མ་སྐྱེས་ཕྱིར། །ཤེས་རབ་ལས་སྐྱེས་རྒྱུ་སྐྱེས་མིན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>That which has arisen from insight has not arisen from a cause, Because insight has not arisen from a cause.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-250">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-262</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ཕྱིར་ཡེ་ཤེས་རྒྱུ་སྐྱེས་མིན། །ཤེས་རབ་ཡེ་ཤེས་བླ་ན་མེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{152}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-262"/> Therefore, the wisdom is the unsurpassable Prajñā cum wisdom, which has not arisen from a cause.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-251">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-262</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འབྲས་བུ་རྒྱུ་ཡིས་གཞན་དང་གཞན། །ཕན་ཚུན་དུ་ནི་རྒྱས་བཏབ་མེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>There is no mutual sealing, one by the other, Through result and cause.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-252">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-263</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྒྱུ་དང་འབྲས་བུ་ཐམས་ཅད་གང་། །དེ་ནི་རྟེན་ཅིང་འབྲེལ་པར་འབྱུང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{153}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-263"/> Cause and result—everything— Has arisen through dependence.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-253">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-263</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཕན་ཚུན་རྒྱ་ཡིས་བཏབ་པའི་གཟུགས། །སྐྱེ་མིན་མྱ་ངན་འདས་པའང་མིན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The reflection, in which [the two] are mutually sealed, Is neither born nor extinguished.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-254">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-264</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཤེས་རབ་ཀུན་ནས་མྱ་ངན་འདས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{154}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-264"/> [Its] prajñā [aspect] is constant extinction And [its upāya aspect,] the supreme immovable, is [always] present (lit.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-255">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-264</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྐྱེ་བ་མཆོག་ཏུ་འགྱུར་བ་མེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“arisen”).</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-256">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-264</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྒྱུ་དང་འབྲས་བུ་རྣམ་ངེས་གྲོལ། །ཕན་ཚུན་དུ་ནི་རྒྱས་བཏབ་མེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Free from cause and effect, There is no mutual sealing.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-257">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-265</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མ་སྐྱེས་པ་དང་མ་འགགས་པའི། །ཤེས་བྱ་གང་ཞིག་འདིར་མཐོང་བ། །དེ་ནི་རང་སེམས་གཞན་མ་ཡིན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{155}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-265"/> The vision of knowable objects in this world, Which are neither born nor extinguished, Are one’s own mind, and nothing else.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-258">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-265</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཕྱི་ཡི་ཤེས་བྱ་རྣམ་འབྱེད་ཕྱིར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>This is because external objects of knowledge are [only mentally] separated [from oneself].</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-259">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-266</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ཕྱིར་བདག་གིས་བདག་ཉིད་ལ། །འགར་ཡང་རྒྱས་གདབ་ནུས་མ་ཡིན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{156}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-266"/> Therefore nothing can seal itself, With itself, anywhere.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-260">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-266</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རལ་གྲི་ཆེན་པོ་བདག་ཉིད་ལ། །བདག་ཉིད་སོ་ཡིས་གཅོད་དམ་ཅི། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Can a great sword cut itself With its own blade?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-261">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-267</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མོ་གཤམ་བུ་མོ་དང་འགྲོགས་པས། །རྨི་ལམ་དུ་ནི་བདེ་འགྱུར་ལྟར། །<tei:ref folio="F.20.b"/>ནམ་མཁའ་ལས་བྱུང་གཟུགས་བརྙན་ནི། །བསྟེན་པས་བདག་ལ་དེ་བཞིན་ནོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{157}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-267"/> Just as one experiences bliss through union In a dream with the daughter of a barren woman, So, too, one experiences bliss for oneself By serving the reflection emerging from space (Viśvamātā, i.e., mahāmudrā).</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-262">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-268</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཤེས་རབ་མ་ཡིན་ཐབས་ཀྱང་མིན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{158}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-268"/> Neither insight nor means [are independent].</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-263">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-268</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདི་ནི་ལྷན་སྐྱེས་ཤེས་རབ་བཅས། །ཀུན་ནས་བདེ་བ་རྫོགས་པ་ལས། །སྒྲིབ་པ་ཐམས་ཅད་སྤངས་པ་སྟེ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The coemergent one (i.e., Kālacakra) in union with his prajñā Is full of bliss, indeed, And without any hindrances.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-264">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-269</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ནམ་མཁའ་བཞིན་དུ་གོས་པ་མེད། །ཡུལ་དང་དབང་པོ་སྤངས་པ་ནི། །ཀུན་ནས་འབྱུང་བ་ཀུན་ལ་གནས། །གཅད་དུ་མེད་པ་དབྱེ་བ་སྤངས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{159}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-269"/> It is unstained like the sky, Without object or sense faculty, Present in everything, Indivisible, without distinctions.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-265">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-270</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རང་བྱུང་རྡོ་རྗེ་སེམས་དཔའ་ནི། །དོན་ཆེན་མཆོག་ཏུ་མི་འགྱུར་བ། །འདོད་ཆགས་ཆེན་པོ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེ། །སེམས་ཅན་ཐམས་ཅད་དགའ་བར་བྱེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{160}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-270"/> Self-arisen are Vajrasattva [at the secret part], The supremely immovable one with the great intent, And Mahāsattva [at the navel], whose passion is great, Giving joy to sentient beings.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-266">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-271</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཞེ་སྡང་ཆེ། །ཉོན་མོངས་ཟད་པ་དགྲ་ཆེན་པོ། །དམ་ཚིག་སེམས་དཔའ་གཏི་མུག་ཆེ། །གཏི་མུག་བློ་སྟེ་གཏི་མུག་སེལ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{161}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-271"/> Self-arisen are Bodhisattva [at the heart], whose hatred is great, The great enemy destroying defilements; And Samayasattva [at the throat], whose delusion is great, Clearing the delusion of deluded intellect.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-267">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-272</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྡོ་རྗེའི་རྣལ་འབྱོར་ཁྲོ་བ་ཆེ། །ལྷ་མིན་ཁྲོ་བོ་དགྲ་ཆེན་པོ། །དུས་ཀྱི་འཁོར་ལོ་ཆགས་པ་ཆེ། །འཕོ་བའི་ཆགས་པ་སེལ་བར་བྱེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{162}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-272"/> Self-arisen are Vajrayoga [at the forehead], whose anger is great, The great enemy of wrathful demons; And Kālacakra [at the crown of the head], whose attachment is great, Removing the passion for fleeting bliss.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-268">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-273</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྡོ་རྗེ་མི་ཕྱེད་ཅེས་པར་བརྗོད། །འདི་ནི་དོན་ཆེན་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{163}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-273"/> “The vajra is indivisible”—with that the Illustrious One Taught [Vajrasattva’s] great intent.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-269">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-273</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སེམས་དཔའ་སྲིད་གསུམ་གཅིག་པ་ཉིད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Being (Skt. sattva) refers to the unity of the threefold existence.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-270">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-273</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མཆོག་ཏུ་མི་འགྱུར་བརྗོད་པར་བྱ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>It is said to be the supreme immovable bliss.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-271">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-274</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མཆོག་ཏུ་མི་འགྱུར་བདེ་བ་རྫོགས། །ས་རྣམས་ཡོངས་སུ་རྫོགས་པ་ཡིས། །འདོད་ཆགས་ཆེན་པོ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེ། །སེམས་ཅན་ཐམས་ཅད་དགའ་བར་བྱེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{164}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-274"/> The one whose supreme immovable bliss is complete, Who has become perfect through the bodhisattva levels, Is Mahāsattva, whose passion is great, Giving joy to all sentient beings.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-272">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-275</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱང་ཆུབ་ལ་གནས་སེམས་དཔའ་ནི། །མི་གཡོ་དེ་ཕྱིར་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས། །ཉོན་མོངས་ལ་སོགས་ཞེ་སྡང་ཚོགས། །ཞེ་སྡང་ཆེན་པོ་དགྲ་ཆེ་བ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{165}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-275"/> Being a hero persevering in enlightenment Without wavering, he is Bodhisattva, Whose hatred is great, the great enemy Of all hatred, defilements, and so forth.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-273">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-276</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དམ་ཚིག་ཟླ་བ་བདུད་རྩི་ཡི། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{166}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-276"/> For he whose lunar nectar or semen has not been emitted, The commitment (Skt.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-274">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-276</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཁུ་བ་འཕོ་མེད་དེ་ཟ་བ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>samaya) is the devouring [of bliss].</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-275">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-276</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དམ་ཚིག་སེམས་དཔའོ་རིགས་པ་འདིས། །གཏི་མུག་བློ་སྟེ་གཏི་མུག་སེལ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Due to these circumstances he is called Samayasattva, Clearer of the delusion of deluded intellect.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-276">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-277</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྡོ་རྗེ་ཐམས་ཅད་གཅིག་པ་ཉིད། །ཤེས་རབ་སྐུ་དང་མི་འགྱུར་བཅས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{167}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-277"/> [Vajrayoga] is the unity of all vajras, Endowed with insight, bodies, and the immovable.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-277">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-277</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཁྲོ་བོ་ཆེན་པོ་དགྲ་ཆེན་པོ། །ཁྲོ་བོའི་གཟུགས་ཅན་བདུད་རྣམས་ཀྱིས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>His anger is great, Being the great enemy of wrathful demons.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-278">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-278</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འགྱུར་མེད་བདེ་བ་ཆེ་ཐབས་ལས། །ནམ་ཡང་སེམས་ཅན་དོན་མི་འདོར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{168}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-278"/> Given his means of great immovable bliss, [Kālacakra] never abandons the welfare of sentient beings.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-279">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-278</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སེམས་ཅན་གྲོལ་ནས་ཆགས་ཆེན་པོ། །འགྱུར་<tei:ref folio="F.21.a"/>བའི་ཆགས་པ་སེལ་བར་བྱེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Having great attachment, he liberates sentient beings And removes the passion for fleeting bliss.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-280">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-279</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདི་རྣམས་རྣམ་པ་དྲུག་ཏུ་བརྗོད། །མི་འགྱུར་ཡེ་ཤེས་ཚོར་བ་དང་། །རྣམ་ཤེས་གཟུགས་དང་འདུ་བྱེད་དང་། །འདུ་ཤེས་དེ་རྣམས་ཕུང་པོའི་རིགས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{169}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-279"/> These six forms of deities are also said To be the families of the six aggregates: Wisdom, sensation, consciousness, matter, karmic formations, And discrimination—all of them in an immovable state.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-281">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-280</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡེ་ཤེས་མེ་དང་ནམ་མཁའ་ས། །རླུང་ཆུ་རྣམས་ཀྱི་རིམ་པ་བཞིན། །ཡིད་མིག་རྣ་བ་ལུས་དང་སྣ། །ལྕེ་རྣམས་ཀྱི་ཡང་དེ་བཞིན་ཉིད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{170}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-280"/> Likewise they are also, in order, The elements of wisdom, fire, space, earth, Wind, and water; the sense faculties of The mind, the eyes, ears, the body, nose, and tongue; {171}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-281"/> And the cognitive objects of mental objects (Skt.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-282">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-280</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྒྲ་རོ་ཆོས་ཀྱི་དབྱིངས་དང་དྲི། །རེག་བྱ་ཁ་དོག་རྣམས་ཀྱི་ཡང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>dharmadhātu), Visible objects, sound, touch, odor, and taste.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-283">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-280</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཁྲོ་བོའི་རྒྱལ་པོ་གདོང་དྲུག་འཇིགས། །རིགས་དྲུག་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་ཡོངས་དག་པ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The terrifying King of Wrath with six faces Is purified with regard to these six families.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-284">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-282</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལུས་དང་གསང་བ་དབང་པོ་སེམས། །རྟག་ཏུ་དཀྱིལ་འཁོར་རྣམ་པ་གསུམ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{172}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-282"/> The body, the secret organ, and the mind have always been The threefold maṇḍala [of the Buddha’s body, speech, and mind].</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-285">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-282</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཤེས་རབ་ཐབས་ཀྱི་རྡོ་རྗེ་གསུམ། །རྡོ་རྗེ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཉིད་དུ་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>These three vajras, each consisting of insight and means, Are in the state of Vajrasattva.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-286">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-283</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདི་ནི་དབང་གི་སྒྲུབ་ཐབས་ཏེ། །མཆོག་ཏུ་མི་འགྱུར་སྒྲུབ་པའི་ཐབས། །རྩ་དང་རིགས་དང་ཡང་དག་ལྡན། །ཟླ་བ་མདོར་བསྟན་པ་ཡིས་བཤད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{173}<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-283"/> These means of accomplishing empowerment, The means of accomplishing the supreme immovable, Together with the channels and families, Have been explained in summary, O [Su]candra.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-287">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-624</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཅེས་པ་འཇིག་རྟེན་ཁམས་ཀྱི་ལེའུར་ལེའུ་ལྔ་པའི་མཆོག་ཏུ་མི་འགྱུར་བའི་དབང་གི་སྒྲུབ་ཐབས་མདོར་བསྟན་པ་རྫོགས་སོ།། །།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>{174} <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-624"/>This concludes the summary of the means of the supreme immovable empowerment (i.e., the “Sekoddeśa”), from the fifth chapter of the [“Paramādibuddha” that begins with the] chapter on the world realm.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-077-002-TU-288">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-077-002-291</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདི་ནི་ཁ་ཆེའི་པཎྜི་ཏ་སོ་མ་ནཱ་ཐ་དང་། །​བོད་ཀྱི་ལོ་ཙཱ་བ་འབྲོ་དགེ་སློང་ཤེས་རབ་གྲགས་པས་བསྒྱུར་ཞིང་ཞུས་ཏེ་གཏན་ལ་ཕབ་པ་ལས། སླར་ཡང་སྒྲ་ཚད་པ་རིན་ཆེན་རྒྱལ་མཚན་གྱིས་དཔལ་ནཱ་རོ་པའི་འགྲེལ་བཤད་དང་མཐུན་པར་བསྒྱུར་ཞིང་ཞུས་ཏེ་དག་པར་བྱས་པའོ།​། །​།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-077-002-291"/>It was translated, edited, and finalized by the Kashmiri paṇḍita Somanātha and the Tibetan translator and monk Dro Sherap Drakpa. Rinchen Gyaltsen retranslated, edited, and corrected it in accordance with the commentary (Skt. ṭīkā) of glorious Nāropa.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>

</body>
</tmx>