<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tmx xmlns="http://www.lisa.org/tmx14" xmlns:eft="http://read.84000.co/ns/1.0" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" version="1.4b">
    <header creationtool="linguae-dharmae/84000" creationtoolversion="2.16.12a" datatype="PlainText" segtype="block" adminlang="en-us" srclang="bo" eft:text-id="UT22084-072-014" eft:text-version="v-1.0.3-2022" eft:source-ref="/db/apps/84000-data/uploads/linguae-dharmae/aligned/31-10-2022/complete/toh314-bo_aligned.txt" eft:seconds-to-revise="0.608"/>
    <body>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-1">
            <prop name="location-id">translation</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མུན་གྱི་ནགས་ཚལ་གྱི་སྒོ་ཞེས་བྱ་བའི་མདོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The Sūtra Entry into the Gloomy Forest</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-2">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-23</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སངས་རྒྱས་དང་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཐམས་ཅད་ལ་ཕྱག་འཚལ་ལོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Homage to all buddhas and bodhisattvas!</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-3">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-23</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།འདི་སྐད་བདག་གིས་ཐོས་པ་དུས་གཅིག་ན།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Thus did I hear at one time.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-4">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-23</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་མཉན་དུ་ཡོད་པ་ན་རྒྱལ་བུ་རྒྱལ་བྱེད་ཀྱི་ཚལ་མགོན་མེད་ཟས་སྦྱིན་གྱི་ཀུན་དགའ་ར་བ་ན་བཞུགས་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The Blessed One was staying in Śrāvastī at Jeta Grove, in the garden of Anāthapiṇḍada.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-5">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-23</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་དེའི་ཚེ་ངམ་གྲོག་གསུམ་པོ་ཞེས་བྱ་བའི་ལྗོངས་ཀྱི་སྐྱེ་བོ་དག་གི་ནང་ནས་རི་ཁྲོད་ཀྱི་གྲོང་ཞིག་ན།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>At that time there was a brahmin named Kambala from a mountain village in the country known as Trigarta.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-6">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-23</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྲམ་ཟེ་ལ་བ་ཅན་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་སྤུན་བུ་འདོད་པའི་ཕྱིར་བྲམ་ཟེའི་རྡོ་ལེབ་ལ་དཀའ་ཐུབ་བྱེད་དེ།ལྷ་སྟོང་ཕྲག་བརྒྱ་ལ་བུ་སློང་ཞིང་གསོལ་བ་འདེབས་པ་དང་ལ་བ་ཅན་ལ་བུ་བཙས་པ་ནི་མིང་རབ་མཐོང་ཞེས་བཏགས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Desiring a son for himself and his kinsmen, Kambala undertook austerities at a place called Brahmin’s Flat Stone. After praying to one hundred thousand gods for a son, he eventually had a boy whom he called Pradarśa.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-7">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-23</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ནུ་བོ་ལ་བཙས་པ་ནི་དགའ་བོ་ཞེས་བཏགས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>To his brother was born another boy, who was called Nanda.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-8">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-23</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།གང་གི་ཉིན་མོ་རབ་མཐོང་བཙས་པ་དེའི་ཉིན་མོ་བྲམ་ཟེ་ལྔ་བརྒྱ་ལ་བུ་ལྔ་བརྒྱ་བཙས་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>On the very day Pradarśa was born, five hundred sons were born to five hundred brahmins.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-9">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-23</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་དག་རིམ་བཞིན་དུ་བུ་ཆེར་སྐྱེས་པ་དང་། རབ་མཐོང་ལ་སོགས་པ་ལྔ་བརྒྱ་ལྷན་ཅིག་ཏུ་རིག་པ་དག་སློབ་པ་ན།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>As they gradually grew older, Pradarśa and the five hundred other boys trained together in the traditional subjects of learning.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-10">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-23</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རབ་མཐོང་ལ་སོགས་པ་རིག་པའི་གནས་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱི་ཕ་རོལ་ཏུ་སོན་ཅིང་ཐམས་ཅད་རྫོགས་པར་ཡང་དག་པར་བྱང་བར་གྱུར་ལ། བསོད་ནམས་ཀྱི་ཚོགས་ཡང་དག་པ་ལས་བྱུང་བའི་སྤྱོད་པ་མཚུངས་པ་མེད་པ་སྟོང་ཕྲག་བརྒྱ་སྙེད་ཐོབ་སྟེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Soon Pradarśa and the others attained mastery and dexterity in all fields of learning, and they obtained a hundred thousand exceptional enjoyments due to their perfect accumulations of merit.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-11">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-26</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དབང་བྱེད་པ་གང་གི་དུས་སུ་བྲམ་ཟེ་མ་ཎ་བ་གཅིག་ཡུལ་དབུས་ནས་འོངས་ཏེ་ཕྱིན་ནས་ཕྲད་པ་དང་། དེ་ལ་གསོང་པོར་སྨྲས་ཏེ་གཏམ་དག་ཀྱང་བྱས་ནས་ངེས་པར་གང་ནས་འོངས་པ་ཡིན་ཞེས་དྲིས་པ་དང་། དེས་སྨྲས་པ་ཡུལ་དབུས་ནས་འོངས་པ་ཡིན་ཏེ་དེ་ཡང་གྲོང་ཁྱེར་ཆེན་པོ་དྲུག་གོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>At that time, a brahmin youth arrived from the Middle Country and encountered the boys. Welcoming him, the boys struck up a conversation and asked, “So, where have you arrived from?” “I’m from the Middle Country,” he replied.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-12">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-26</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེའི་ནང་དག་ན་ཚད་མ་དྲུག་ལ་མཁས་ཤིང་ལྟས་ཀྱི་བྱ་བ་དྲུག་ལ་ཐོགས་པ་མེད་པར་བརྗོད་ནུས་པའི་སྟོན་པ་བཅོ་བརྒྱད་ཡོད་དེ་དེ་ན་ཆུ་ཀླུང་ཡང་འབབ་བོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“There we have six great cities, and in them we have eighteen teachers who are experts in the six correct forms of knowledge and who can lecture without any reticence on the six activities of a brahmin. There is also a river there.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-13">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-26</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་མ་ཡིན་པ་བསོད་ནམས་ཆེན་པོ་དང་ལྡན་པ། དགེ་ཞིང་ཤིས་པ། འཇིག་རྟེན་ཐམས་ཅད་མཁྱེན་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Additionally, there is someone with a great amount of merit who is virtuous and glorious and who knows everything about the world—he is the blessed Buddha.”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-14">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-29</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སངས་རྒྱས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱང་དེ་ནའོ་ཞེས་བྱས་པ་དང་། རབ་མཐོང་གིས་སྒྲ་དེ་ཐོས་པ་དང་། བ་སྤུ་ལངས་ཡིད་གཡོས་རབ་ཏུ་དགའ་སྟེ་དེར་འགྲོའོ་སྙམ་ནས།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>As soon as Pradarśa heard this, his hair bristled and his mind became overjoyed.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-15">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-29</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཕའི་གན་དུ་སོང་སྟེ་ཕྱིན་ནས་ཡབ་བདག་ནི་ཡུལ་དབུས་སུ་མཆིའོ། །དེ་ནས་མུ་སྟེགས་པ་དག་ལས་རྒྱལ་བར་བགྱིའོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Thinking that he must go there, he approached his father and announced, “Father, I will go to the Middle Country.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-16">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-29</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།མཁས་པར་བགྲངས་པ་དག་དང་ངེས་པར་ལྷན་ཅིག་སྨྲ་བར་བགྱིའོ་ཞེས་གསོལ་པ་དང་། ཕས་དེ་ལྟར་གནང་ངོ་།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>I will defeat those with heretical views and debate those regarded as experts.” His father granted him permission.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-17">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-30</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ནས་བསོད་ནམས་ཆེན་པོ་སྦྱིན་པས་དབང་ཕྱུག་ཆེན་པོ་དང་ལྡན་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Pradarśa possessed a majestic presence due to the great merit resulting from generosity, and he was exceedingly generous toward all beings.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-18">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-30</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སེམས་ཅན་ཐམས་ཅད་ལ་གཏོང་བ་ཆེན་པོ་ཅན་དེ་ལྷ་དག་གིས་བསྲུངས་པ་ཞིག་པས་ལྷ་དག་ཉེ་བར་འོང་ཞིང་སྔོན་དུ་འགྲོ་སྟེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He was a person protected by the gods. Accordingly, the gods approached him and went ahead to announce, “You must worship the great Pradarśa!</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-19">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-30</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རབ་མཐོང་ཆེན་པོ་ལ་མཆོད་པ་བྱོས་ཤིག་དང་། ཕན་ཡོན་མང་པོ་དག་གི་འབྲས་བུ་ཆེན་པོ་འབྱུང་བར་འགྱུར་རོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>It will bring you great results in the form of many benefits!”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-20">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-31</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཞེས་སྒྲ་སྒྲོགས་ཤིང་སོང་བ་དང་། རིམ་གྱིས་ལྷ་དང་མིས་མཆོད་པ་བྱས་ཤིང་མཉན་ཡོད་དུ་ཕྱིན་ནོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>In turn, with gods and humans worshiping him, Pradarśa arrived at Śrāvastī.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-21">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-31</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ནས་ལམ་གྱིས་དུབ་པ་རྟ་བསྟིས་ཏེ་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ག་ལ་བ་དེར་སོང་སྟེ་ཕྱིན་ནས། བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱི་ཞབས་ལ་མགོ་བོས་ཕྱག་འཚལ་ཏེ། ཕྱོགས་གཅིག་ཏུ་འཁོད་དོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Having recuperated from the fatigue of his journey, he went to where the Blessed One was dwelling and, bowing his head at the feet of the Blessed One, took his place to one side.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-22">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-33</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་དེ་དག་ལ་ཆོས་བསྟན་པ་མཛད་དེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The Blessed One then taught the Dharma to Pradarśa and the rest of the assembly.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-23">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-33</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེའི་འཁོར་ལྔ་བརྒྱ་པོ་དག་ལྟ་བ་མཆོག་ཏུ་འཛིན་པ་བཤིག་བཅོམ་སྟེ། བདེན་པ་མཐོང་སྟེ་དེ་ཉིད་དུ་རབ་ཏུ་བྱུང་དགེ་སློང་གི་དངོས་པོ་བཟུང་སྟེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>All five hundred members of the assembly had their clinging to false views undermined and destroyed, and seeing the truth, they went forth and took up monkhood on the spot.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-24">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-33</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཉོན་མོངས་པ་ཐམས་ཅད་བཅོམ་ནས་དགྲ་བཅོམ་པ་མངོན་དུ་བྱས་ཏེ་དགའ་བོ་ནི་མ་གཏོགས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Apart from Ānanda, they all vanquished their mental afflictions and became worthy ones.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-25">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-33</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།སྐྱེ་བོ་མང་པོ་ཀུན་གྱིས་ཀྱང་ཆོས་ཁོང་དུ་ཆུད་དོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>A multitude of other people also came to understand the Dharma.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-26">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-36</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།སྟོན་པ་ཆེན་པོ་རབ་མཐོང་ལྟ་བའི་ཕྱིར་ལྷ་ལ་སོགས་པ་དག་ཀྱང་འོངས་ཏེ་དེར་ཕྱིན་པ་དང་། བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་དགེ་སློང་རྣམས་ལ་བཀའ་སྩལ་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Because they had been observing the generous Pradarśa, the gods and others also arrived in the assembly.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-27">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-36</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དགེ་སློང་དག་དགེ་སློང་རབ་མཐོང་འདི་ནི་ངའི་དགེ་སློང་དང་དགེ་སློང་དག་གི་ཉན་ཐོས་དག་ལ་ཇི་ལྟར་ལྷ་དང་མི་མཆོད་པ་བྱེད་པ་དེ་དག་གི་ནང་ན་ལྷ་དང་མིས་མཆོད་པར་བྱ་བའི་མཆོག་ནི་དགེ་སློང་རབ་མཐོང་ཡིན་ནོ་ཞེས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་བཀའ་སྩལ་ཏོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Upon their arrival, the Blessed One said to the monks, “Monks, among my monks and the hearers who are monks—however they may be worshiped by gods and humans—the monk Pradarśa is the supreme object of worship by gods and humans!”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-28">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-38</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ནས་དུས་དེ་ཉིད་དུ་མི་མཇེད་ཀྱི་བདག་པོ་ཚངས་པ་དང་། ལྷ་རྣམས་ཀྱི་དབང་པོ་བརྒྱ་བྱིན་དང་། འཇིག་རྟེན་སྐྱོང་བ་བཞི་དང་། གནོད་སྦྱིན་གྱི་སྡེ་དཔོན་ཆེན་པོ་ཉི་ཤུ་རྩ་བརྒྱད་དང་། དྲི་ཟའི་རྒྱལ་པོ་དང་། གྲུལ་བུམ་གྱི་སྡེ་དཔོན་ཆེན་པོ་ལ་སོགས་པ་རང་རང་གི་གནས་ནས་སོང་སྟེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Immediately thereupon, Brahmā, the lord of the Sahā world; Śakra, chief of the gods; the Four Guardians of the World; the twenty-eight great yakṣa generals; the king of gandharvas; the general of the kumbhāṇḍas; and others departed from their respective abodes and arrived before the venerable great Pradarśa.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-29">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-39</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཚེ་དང་ལྡན་པ་རབ་མཐོང་ཆེན་པོ་ག་ལ་བ་དེར་སོང་སྟེ་ཕྱིན་ནས་ཕྱོགས་གཅིག་ཏུ་འཁོད་དེ་མངོན་དུ་ཕྱོགས་ཐལ་མོ་སྦྱར་ཏེ་འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་སྨྲས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Taking their places to one side, they faced Pradarśa, joined their hands, and said, “Honorable great Pradarśa!</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-30">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-39</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཀྱེ་བཙུན་པ་རབ་མཐོང་ཆེན་པོ་སྔོན་གྱི་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་སངས་རྒྱས་གཤེགས་ཤིང་བཞུགས་པའི་གནས་རང་སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱི་བཞུགས་གནས།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>There is an abode that was visited and inhabited by previous blessed, perfect buddhas.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-31">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-39</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདོད་ཆགས་དང་བྲལ་བ་དག་གིས་གནས་པར་བྱ་བ་དྲང་སྲོང་གི་གནས་སུ་གྱུར།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>It was an abode for solitary buddhas, a place for those devoid of desire, and an abode for sages.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-32">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-39</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ཁོ་ན་ཉིད་ངེས་པར་མཁྱེན་ནས་འདས་པའི་བསྐལ་པ་དགུ་བཅུ་རྩ་གཅིག་ན་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་སངས་རྒྱས་རྣམ་པར་གཟིགས་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་འཇིག་རྟེན་དུ་བྱུང་སྟེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Ninety-one eons ago, the perfect Buddha Vipaśyin, having ascertained the nature of things, appeared in the world.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-33">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-39</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེའི་ཚེ་དགེ་སློང་གསལ་བ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་ལྷ་དང་མིས་མཆོད་པའི་མཆོག་ཏུ་གྱུར་པ་དེའི་གནས་ཀྱང་འདི་ལགས་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>At that time, there was a monk named Shining, who was the most highly revered by gods and humans. He also resided in this place.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-34">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-39</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡུལ་དབུས་ལས་བྱང་ཕྱོགས་ཀྱི་ས་མཚམས་ཀྱི་རི་དུང་གི་ལྟེ་བ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་ནི་རི་དེ་ལ་རྩྭའི་རིགས་དུང་གི་ལྟེ་བ་འདྲ་བ་སྐྱེ་བས་དུང་གི་ལྟེ་བའི་རི་ཞེས་བྱ་བར་བཏགས་པར་གྱུར། རི་དེ་དང་ཉེ་བ་ན་ནགས་ཤིག་ན་ཀླུ་མོ་ཨེ་ནི་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་གནས་པས་ཨཻ་ནིའི་ནགས་ཞེས་བྱ་བར་བཏགས་པར་གྱུར།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>On the northern border of the Middle Country, there was Mount Conch Spire, so called because on it grew grass that resembled the spire of a conch. Nearby was the Eni Forest, so called because the nāga lady Eni resided therein.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-35">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-39</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ན་ཕུག་ཅིག་ཡོད་པ་དང་ཉེ་བར་ཤིང་པ་ཏི་ལི་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་སྐྱེ་བས་པ་ཏི་ལིའི་ཕུག་ཅེས་བཏགས་པར་གྱུར་པ་དེ་ཉིད་དུ་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་སངས་རྒྱས་རྣམ་པར་གཟིགས་ཞེས་བྱ་བ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>In that forest there were caves around which trumpet flower trees grew, and so they were called Pāṭalī Caves.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-36">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-39</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཁོར་དགྲ་བཅོམ་པ་བརྒྱད་ཁྲི་དང་གཤེགས་ཤིང་ཐབས་ཅིག་ཏུ་བཞུགས་པར་གྱུར།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>It was there that the blessed, perfect Buddha Vipaśyin arrived and resided along with his retinue of eighty thousand worthy ones.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-37">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-39</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དགེ་སློང་གསལ་བ་ཡང་དེ་ཉིད་ནའོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The monk Shining was also there.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-38">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-39</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་འཁོར་དང་བཅས་པ་དག་ཀྱང་རིམ་པ་བཞིན་དུ་མྱ་ངན་ལས་འདས།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Then the Blessed One and his retinue gradually passed into nirvāṇa.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-39">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-39</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བསྟན་པ་ནུབ་ནས་རང་སངས་རྒྱས་བདུན་ཁྲི་དག་མངོན་པར་ཤེས་པ་དྲུག་དང་ལྡན་པ་དག་མཉམ་དུ་བྱུང་སྟེ་གཤེགས་ཤིང་བཞུགས་པར་གྱུར།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Once his teaching had disappeared, seventy thousand solitary buddhas who were endowed with the six forms of superknowledge arrived and resided together.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-40">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-39</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རང་སངས་རྒྱས་དེ་དག་ཀྱང་མྱ་ངན་ལས་འདས་ནས་དྲང་སྲོང་དྲུག་ཁྲི་མངོན་པར་ཤེས་པ་ལྔ་དང་ལྡན་པ་དག་ཀྱང་དེ་ཉིད་དུ་གནས་པར་གྱུར་ཏོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>When those solitary buddhas had also passed into nirvāṇa, sixty thousand sages who were endowed with the five forms of superknowledge came to inhabit that same place.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-41">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-42</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།བཙུན་པ་རབ་མཐོང་ཆེན་པོ་དེ་ནས་ཡང་བསྐལ་པ་དྲུག་ཅུ་རྩ་གཅིག་ན་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་སངས་རྒྱས་གཙུག་ཏོར་ཅན་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་འཇིག་རྟེན་དུ་བྱུང་སྟེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Honorable great Pradarśa, thereafter, sixty-one eons ago, the blessed, perfect Buddha Śikhin appeared in the world.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-42">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-42</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེའི་དགེ་སློང་རབ་གསལ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་ལྷ་དང་མིས་མཆོད་པའི་མཆོག་ཏུ་གྱུར་པ་ཡང་དེ་ཉིད་ནའོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>His monk named Luminosity, who was the most highly revered by gods and humans, also resided in that very place.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-43">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-42</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།མཚམས་ཀྱི་རི་དེ་ཉིད་ལ་རྩྭའི་རིགས་རོ་ཧི་ཏཱི་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་སྐྱེ་བས་རོ་ཧི་ཏཱིའི་རི་ཞེས་བྱ་བར་བཏགས་པར་གྱུར།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Because the bordering mountain had rohita grass growing on it, it was called Mount Rohita.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-44">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-42</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཀླུ་མོ་གོས་མེད་ཅེས་བྱ་བ་གནས་པས་གོས་མེད་ཀྱི་ནགས་ཞེས་བྱ་བར་བཏགས་པར་གྱུར།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The forest was called Unclothed Forest because the nāga lady Unclothed resided there.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-45">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-42</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཤིང་ཤིར་ཤ་སྐྱེ་བས་ཤིང་ཤིར་ཤའི་ཕུག་ཅེས་བཏགས་པར་གྱུར།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Because parrot trees grew nearby, the caves were called Parrot Tree Caves.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-46">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-42</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་སངས་རྒྱས་གཙུག་ཏོར་ཅན་འཁོར་དགྲ་བཅོམ་པ་བདུན་ཁྲི་དང་ཡང་དེར་གཤེགས་ཤིང་ཐབས་ཅིག་ཏུ་བཞུགས་པར་གྱུར།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>It was there that the perfect Buddha Śikhin, along with his retinue of seventy thousand worthy ones, arrived and resided together.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-47">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-42</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་དག་ཀྱང་མྱ་ངན་ལས་འདས་བསྟན་པ་ནུབ་ནས།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They too passed into nirvāṇa, and the teaching disappeared.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-48">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-42</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རང་སངས་རྒྱས་དྲུག་ཁྲི་ཡང་དེར་གཤེགས་ཤིང་བཞུགས་པར་གྱུར།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Then, sixty thousand solitary buddhas  arrived and resided in that place.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-49">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-42</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རང་སངས་རྒྱས་དེ་དག་ཀྱང་མྱ་ངན་ལས་འདས་ནས་དྲང་སྲོང་ལྔ་ཁྲི་ཡང་མངོན་པར་ཤེས་པ་ལྔ་དང་ལྡན་པ་དེ་འདི་ཉིད་ན་གནས་པར་གྱུར་ཏོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>When those solitary buddhas had also passed into nirvāṇa, fifty thousand sages who were endowed with the five forms of superknowledge came to inhabit that same place.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-50">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-44</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།བཙུན་པ་རབ་མཐོང་ཆེན་པོ་དེ་ནས་ཡང་བསྐལ་པ་སུམ་ཅུ་རྩ་གཅིག་ན་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་སངས་རྒྱས་ཐམས་ཅད་སྐྱོབ་ཅེས་བྱ་བ་འཇིག་རྟེན་དུ་བྱུང་སྟེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Honorable great Pradarśa, thereafter, thirty-one eons ago, the perfect Buddha Viśvabhū appeared in the world.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-51">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-44</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེའི་དགེ་སློང་ཆོས་གསལ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་ལྷ་དང་མིས་མཆོད་པའི་མཆོག་ཏུ་གྱུར་པ་ཡང་དེ་ཉིད་ནའོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>His monk named Shining Forth Dharma, who was the most highly revered by gods and humans, also resided in that very place.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-52">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-44</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།མཚམས་ཀྱི་རི་དེ་ལ་རྩྭ་རིགས་བྷ་ས་བྷ་ས་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་སྐྱེ་བས་བྷ་ས་བྷའི་རི་ཞེས་བཏགས་པར་གྱུར།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Because the bordering mountain had bhasabha grass growing on it, it was called Mount Bhasabha.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-53">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-44</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཀླུ་མོ་བྲག་ཅེས་བྱ་བ་གནས་པས་བྲག་གི་ནགས་ཞེས་བཏགས་པར་གྱུར།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The forest was called Rock Forest because the nāga lady Rock resided there.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-54">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-44</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཤིང་ཨ་ཤྭད་ཐ་སྐྱེ་བས་ཨ་ཤྭད་ཐའི་ཕུག་ཅེས་བཏགས་པར་གྱུར།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Because pipal trees grew nearby, the caves were called Pipal Tree Caves.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-55">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-44</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་སངས་རྒྱས་ཐམས་ཅད་སྐྱོབ་འཁོར་དགྲ་བཅོམ་པ་དྲུག་ཁྲི་དང་དེ་ཉིད་དུ་གཤེགས་ཤིང་ཐབས་ཅིག་ཏུ་བཞུགས་པར་གྱུར།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>It was there that the perfect Buddha Viśvabhū, along with his retinue of sixty thousand worthy ones, arrived and resided together.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-56">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-44</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་དག་མྱ་ངན་ལས་འདས་བསྟན་པ་ནུབ་ནས་རང་སངས་རྒྱས་ལྔ་ཁྲི་ཡང་གཤེགས་ཤིང་བཞུགས་པར་གྱུར།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They too passed into nirvāṇa, and the teaching disappeared. Then, fifty thousand solitary buddhas also arrived and resided there.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-57">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-44</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རང་སངས་རྒྱས་དེ་དག་ཀྱང་མྱ་ངན་ལས་འདས་ནས་དྲང་སྲོང་མངོན་པར་ཤེས་པ་ལྔ་དང་ལྡན་པ་བཞི་ཁྲི་ཡང་གནས་པར་གྱུར་ཏོ། །འདིར་ནི་བཙུན་པ་རབ་མཐོང་ཆེན་པོ་སྔོན་བྱུང་བ་བསྐལ་པ་བཟང་པོ་འདི་ཉིད་ལ་སྐྱེ་དགུའི་ཚེ་ལོ་བཞི་ཁྲི་ཐུབ་པ་ན། ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་སངས་རྒྱས་ལོག་པར་དད་སེལ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་འཇིག་རྟེན་དུ་བྱུང་སྟེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>When those solitary buddhas had also passed into nirvāṇa, forty thousand sages who were endowed with the five forms of superknowledge came to inhabit the place. “Here, honorable great Pradarśa, during this very Excellent Eon when the lifespan of humans was forty thousand years, the perfect Buddha Krakucchanda appeared in the world.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-58">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-44</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེའི་དགེ་སློང་ཆོས་ལྡན་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་ལྷ་དང་མིས་མཆོད་པའི་མཆོག་ཏུ་གྱུར་པ་ཡང་དེ་ཉིད་ནའོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>His monk named Dharma Endowed , who was the most highly revered by gods and humans, also resided in that very place.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-59">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-44</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།མཚམས་ཀྱི་རིའི་རྩྭའི་རིགས་ཀཽ་ཤི་ཀ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་སྐྱེ་བས་ཀཽ་ཤི་ཀའི་རི་ཞེས་བཏགས་པར་གྱུར།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Because the bordering mountain had kauśika grass growing on it, it was called Mount Kauśika.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-60">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-44</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྤྲིན་ཅེས་བྱ་བའི་ཀླུ་མོ་གཅིག་གནས་པས་སྤྲིན་གྱི་ནགས་ཞེས་བཏགས་པར་གྱུར།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The forest was called Cloud Forest because a nāga lady named Cloud resided there.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-61">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-44</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཤིང་ཨུ་དུམ་བ་ར་སྐྱེ་བས་ཨུ་དུམ་པཱ་རའི་ཕུག་ཅེས་བཏགས་པར་གྱུར།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Because the cluster fig tree grew nearby, the caves were called Cluster Fig Caves.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-62">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-44</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་སངས་རྒྱས་ལོག་པར་དད་སེལ་འཁོར་དགྲ་བཅོམ་པ་ལྔ་ཁྲི་དང་ཐབས་ཅིག་ཏུ་གཤེགས་ཤིང་ཞུགས་པར་གྱུར།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>It was there that the perfect Buddha Krakucchanda, along with his retinue of fifty thousand worthy ones, arrived and resided together.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-63">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-44</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་དག་ཀྱང་མྱ་ངན་ལས་འདས་ནས་མངོན་པར་ཤེས་པ་ལྔ་དང་ལྡན་པ་དྲང་སྲོང་སུམ་ཁྲི་ཡང་དེ་ན་གནས་པར་གྱུར་ཏོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They too passed into nirvāṇa, and thirty thousand sages who were endowed with the five forms of superknowledge  came to inhabit the place.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-64">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-49</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།འདིར་ནི་བཙུན་པ་རབ་མཐོང་ཆེན་པོ་སྔོན་བྱུང་བ་བསྐལ་པ་བཟང་པོ་འདི་ཉིད་ལ་སྐྱེ་དགུའི་ཚེ་ལོ་སུམ་ཁྲི་ཐུབ་པ་ན་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་སངས་རྒྱས་གསེར་ཐུབ་ཅེས་བྱ་བ་འཇིག་རྟེན་དུ་བྱུང་སྟེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Here, honorable great Pradarśa, during this very Excellent Eon when the lifespan of humans was thirty thousand years, the perfect Buddha Kanakamuni appeared in the world.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-65">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-49</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེའི་དགེ་སློང་ཆོས་འཕགས་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་ལྷ་དང་མིས་མཆོད་པའི་མཆོག་ཏུ་གྱུར་པ་ཡང་དེ་ཉིད་ནའོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>His monk named Uplifted by Dharma, who was the most highly revered by gods and humans, also resided in that very place.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-66">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-49</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།མཚམས་ཀྱི་རི་དེ་ལ་རྩྭའི་རིགས་ཁ་དོག་ལྗང་ལོ་ཅན་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་སྐྱེ་བས་ཁ་དོག་ལྗང་ལོ་རི་ཞེས་བཏགས་པར་གྱུར།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Because the bordering mountain had green leafy grass growing on it, it was called Mount Leafy Green.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-67">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-49</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཐིག་ལེ་ཞེས་བྱ་བའི་ཀླུ་མོ་གནས་པས་ཐིག་ལེའི་ནགས་ཞེས་བཏགས་པར་གྱུར།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The forest was called Drop Forest because the nāga lady named Drop resided there.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-68">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-49</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཤིང་ཀ་པི་ཏ་སྐྱེ་བས་ཀ་པི་ཏའི་ཕུག་ཅེས་བཏགས་པར་གྱུར།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Because elephant trees grew nearby, the caves were called Elephant Tree Caves.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-69">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-49</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་སངས་རྒྱས་གསེར་ཐུབ་འཁོར་དགྲ་བཅོམ་པ་བཞི་ཁྲི་དང་གཤེགས་ཤིང་ཐབས་ཅིག་ཏུ་བཞུགས་པར་གྱུར།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>It was there that the perfect Buddha Kanakamuni, along with his retinue of forty thousand worthy ones, arrived and resided together.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-70">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-49</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་དག་ཀྱང་མྱ་ངན་ལས་འདས་བསྟན་པ་ནུབ་ནས།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They too passed into nirvāṇa, and the teaching disappeared.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-71">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-49</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རང་སངས་རྒྱས་སུམ་ཁྲི་ཡང་གཤེགས་ཤིང་བཞུགས་པར་གྱུར།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Then, thirty thousand solitary buddhas arrived and resided there.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-72">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-49</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རང་སངས་རྒྱས་དེ་དག་ཀྱང་མྱ་ངན་ལས་འདས་ནས་མངོན་པར་ཤེས་པ་ལྔ་དང་ལྡན་པ་དྲང་སྲོང་ཉི་ཁྲི་ཡང་དེ་ཉིད་ན་གནས་པར་གྱུར་ཏོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>When those solitary buddhas had also passed into nirvāṇa, twenty thousand sages who were endowed with the five forms of superknowledge came to inhabit that same place.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-73">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-50</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།འདིར་ནི་བཙུན་པ་རབ་མཐོང་ཆེན་པོ་སྔོན་བྱུང་བ་བསྐལ་པ་བཟང་པོ་འདི་ཉིད་ལ་སྐྱེ་དགུའི་ཚེ་ལོ་ཉི་ཁྲི་ཐུབ་པ་ན་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་སངས་རྒྱས་འོད་སྲུང་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་འཇིག་རྟེན་དུ་བྱུང་སྟེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Here, honorable great Pradarśa, during this very Excellent Eon when the lifespan of humans was twenty thousand years, the perfect Buddha Kāśyapa appeared in the world.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-74">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-50</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེའི་དགེ་སློང་ཤེ་ཌོ་ཀ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་ལྷ་དང་མིས་མཆོད་པའི་མཆོག་ཏུ་གྱུར་པ་ཡང་དེ་ཉིད་ནའོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>His monk named Śeḍoka, who was the most highly revered by gods and humans, also resided in that very place.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-75">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-50</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།མཚམས་ཀྱི་རི་ལ་རྩྭའི་རིགས་ཟླ་བ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་སྐྱེ་བས་ཟླ་བའི་རི་ཞེས་བཏགས་པར་གྱུར།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Because the bordering mountain had a type of grass named moon growing on it, it was called Mount Moon.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-76">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-50</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཀླུ་མོ་རྒྱལ་བ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་གནས་པས་རྒྱལ་བའི་ནགས་ཞེས་བྱ་བར་བཏགས་པར་གྱུར།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The forest was called Victorious Forest because the nāga lady Victorious resided there.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-77">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-50</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཤིང་འཛམ་བུ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་སྐྱེ་བས་འཛམ་བུའི་ཕུག་ཅེས་བཏགས་པར་གྱུར།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Because black plum trees grew nearby, the caves were called Black Plum Caves.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-78">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-50</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་སངས་རྒྱས་འོད་སྲུང་འཁོར་དགྲ་བཅོམ་པ་ཉི་ཁྲི་དང་གཤེགས་ཤིང་ཐབས་ཅིག་ཏུ་བཞུགས་པར་གྱུར།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>It was there that the perfect Buddha Kāśyapa, along with his retinue of twenty thousand worthy ones, arrived and resided together.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-79">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-50</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་དག་ཀྱང་མྱ་ངན་ལས་འདས་བསྟན་པ་ནུབ་ནས།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They too passed into nirvāṇa, and the teaching disappeared.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-80">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-50</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རང་སངས་རྒྱས་ཁྲི་ལྔ་སྟོང་གཤེགས་ཤིང་བཞུགས་པར་གྱུར།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Then, fifteen thousand solitary buddhas arrived and resided there.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-81">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-50</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རང་སངས་རྒྱས་དེ་དག་ཀྱང་མྱ་ངན་ལས་འདས་ནས་མངོན་པར་ཤེས་པ་ལྔ་དང་ལྡན་པ་དྲང་སྲོང་ཁྲི་གནས་པར་གྱུར་ཏོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>When those solitary buddhas had also passed into nirvāṇa, ten thousand sages who were endowed with the five forms of superknowledge  came to inhabit the place.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-82">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-51</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།འདིར་ནི་བཙུན་པ་རབ་མཐོང་ཆེན་པོ་བསྐལ་པ་བཟང་པོ་འདི་ཉིད་ལ་སྐྱེ་དགུའི་ཚེ་ལོ་བརྒྱ་ཐུབ་པ་ན་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་སངས་རྒྱས་ཤཱཀྱ་ཐུབ་པ་འཇིག་རྟེན་དུ་བྱུང་སྟེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Now, honorable great Pradarśa, during this very Excellent Eon when the lifespan of humans is one hundred years, the perfect Buddha Śākyamuni has appeared in the world.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-83">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-51</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཕགས་པ་རབ་མཐོང་ཆེན་པོ་ཁྱོད་ལྷ་དང་མིས་མཆོད་པའི་མཆོག་ཏུ་གྱུར་པ་ཡང་འདི་ཉིད་ནའོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>You, noble and great Pradarśa, the monk most highly revered by gods and humans, will reside in that very place.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-84">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-51</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།མཚམས་ཀྱི་རི་ལ་རྩྭའི་རིགས་ཨུ་ཤི་ཤ་སྐྱེ་བས་ཨུ་ཤིའི་རི་ཞེས་བཏགས་པར་གྱུར།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Because the bordering mountain has vetiver grass growing on it, it is called Mount Uśīra.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-85">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-51</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཀླུ་མོ་ཏ་མ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་གནས་པས་ཏ་མའི་ནགས་ཚལ་ཞེས་བཏགས་པར་གྱུར།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The forest is called Gloomy Forest because the nāga lady Gloom resides there.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-86">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-51</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཤིང་ཨ་མྲ་སྐྱེ་བས་ཨ་མྲའི་ཕུག་ཅེས་ད་ལྟར་བཏགས་པ་ཡིན་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Because mango trees grow nearby, the caves are called Mango Caves.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-87">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-51</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཙུན་པ་རབ་མཐོང་ཆེན་པོ་ཨུ་ཤི་ཤའི་རི་བྲག་འདི་ཉིད་དུ་ཐུགས་བརྩེ་བར་དགོངས་ཏེ་བཞུགས་པ་ནི་ལེགས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Honorable great Pradarśa, it would be good if you, thinking compassionately, were to reside on that very Mount Uśīra.”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-88">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-52</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ནས་ཡང་ཚངས་པ་དང་། ལྷའི་དབང་པོ་བརྒྱ་བྱིན་དང་། འཇིག་རྟེན་སྐྱོང་བ་དག་གིས་གནས་བརྟན་ཆེན་པོའི་རྐང་པ་ལ་ཕྱག་འཚལ་ཏེ་ཐལ་མོ་སྦྱར་བ་བྱས་ནས་རབ་ཏུ་གུས་པས་འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་སྨྲས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>At this point Brahmā, Śakra who is chief of the gods, and the Guardians of the World bowed at the feet of the great elder.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-89">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-52</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཐུགས་བརྩེ་བ་ཅན་ནགས་འདི་ནི་གཤེགས་ཤིང་བཞུགས་པའི་གནས་ཡིན་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Joining their hands together, they respectfully addressed him, “O compassionate one, this forest is a place to which you should come and reside.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-90">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-52</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བདག་ཅག་ཀྱང་ཉེ་གནས་བགྱིད་ལ་གཞན་དག་ཀྱང་གཟུང་དུ་གསོལ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Please let us be your disciples, and please accept others as well.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-91">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-52</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནི་སྙན་པར་གྲགས་ཤིང་ལེགས་ཏེ་ཆུ་ནི་གཟིགས་པར་དབྱུང་བར་འཚལ་ལོ་ཞེས་གསོལ་བ་བཏབ་པོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>This forest is praiseworthy and excellent. Please consider the water and extract it!”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-92">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-54</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།གཞན་ཡང་གནོད་སྦྱིན་གྱི་སྡེ་དཔོན་བརྒྱད་པོ་འདི་དག་སྟེ། སིང་ག་ལ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་དང་། ཆོས་སྐྱོང་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་དང་། དོན་གྲུབ་ཅེས་བྱ་བ་དང་། གཞན་ལས་རྒྱལ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་དང་། གླང་རྣ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་དང་། དབྱིག་རྣ་བ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་དང་། ཆོས་ལྡན་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་དང་། ཆོས་འཕགས་ཞེས་བྱ་བས་ཀྱང་གནས་བརྟན་ཆེན་པོའི་རྐང་པ་ལ་ཕྱག་འཚལ་ཏེ་ཐལ་མོ་སྦྱར་ནས་རབ་ཏུ་གུས་པས་འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་སྨྲས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Then the eight yakṣa generals—namely, Siṅgala, Dharma Protector, Successful, Victorious , Bull Ear, Jewel Ear, Dharma Endowed , and Uplifted by Dharma —also bowed at the feet of the great elder. Joining their hands together, they respectfully addressed him:</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-93">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-54</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཐུགས་བརྩེ་བ་ཅན་ནགས་དེ་ནི་གཤེགས་ཤིང་བཞུགས་པའི་གནས་ཡིན་ཏེ་བདག་ཅག་ཀྱང་ཉེ་གནས་བགྱིད་ལ་གཞན་དག་ཀྱང་གཟུང་དུ་གསོལ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“O compassionate one, this forest is a place to which you should come and reside. Please let us be your disciples, and please accept others as well.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-94">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-54</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནི་སྙན་པར་གྲགས་ཤིང་ལེགས་ཏེ་ཆུ་ནི་གཟིགས་པར་དབྱུང་བར་འཚལ་ལོ་ཞེས་གསོལ་བ་བཏབ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>This forest is praiseworthy and excellent. Please consider the water and extract it!”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-95">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-55</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།གཞན་ཡང་གནོད་སྦྱིན་མ་ཆེན་མོ་བརྒྱད་འདི་དག་སྟེ། ཨ་ཤི་ཌི་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་དང་། བུ་མངས་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་དང་། འཕྱང་མ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་དང་། རབ་ཏུ་འཕྱང་མ་དང་། དྲག་མོ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་དང་། གཏུམ་མོ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་དང་། མདུང་ཐུང་འཛིན་ཅེས་བྱ་བ་དང་། བར་སྣང་མ་ཞེས་བྱ་བས་ཀྱང་གནས་བརྟན་ཆེན་པོའི་རྐང་པ་ལ་ཕྱག་འཚལ་ཏེ་ཐལ་མོ་སྦྱར་བ་བྱས་ནས་རབ་ཏུ་གུས་པས་འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་སྨྲས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Then the eight great yakṣīs—namely, Aśiḍi, Many Sons, Hanging Down,  Fully Hanging, Terrible Lady, Fierce Lady, Small Club Holder, and Sky Dweller—also bowed at the feet of the great elder. Joining their hands together, they respectfully addressed him:</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-96">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-55</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཐུགས་བརྩེ་བ་ཅན་ནགས་དེ་ནི་གཤེགས་ཤིང་བཞུགས་པའི་གནས་ཡིན་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“O compassionate one, this forest is a place to which you should come and reside.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-97">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-55</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བདག་ཅག་ཀྱང་ཉེ་གནས་བགྱིད་ལ་གཞན་དག་ཀྱང་གཟུང་དུ་གསོལ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Please let us be your disciples, and please accept others as well.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-98">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-55</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནི་སྙན་པར་གྲགས་ཤིང་ལེགས་ཏེ་ཆུ་ནི་གཟིགས་པར་དབྱུང་བར་འཚལ་ལོ་ཞེས་གསོལ་བ་བཏབ་པོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>This forest is praiseworthy and excellent. Please consider the water and extract it!”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-99">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-56</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་བཞིན་དུ་གཞན་ཡང་ཀླུ་ཆེན་པོ་བརྒྱད་པོ་འདི་དག་སྟེ། སེར་སྐྱ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་དང་། དྲི་མ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་དང་། ཆུ་ལྡན་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་དང་། དྲག་ཤུལ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་དང་། ལྷའི་བང་རིམ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་དང་། བུམ་པའི་བང་རིམ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་དང་། ཉེ་བའི་ཀླུ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་དང་། ཨོ་ཌ་སུ་ཏ་ཞེས་བྱ་བས་ཀྱང་གནས་བརྟན་ཆེན་པོའི་རྐང་པ་ལ་ཕྱག་འཚལ་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Similarly, the eight great nāgas—namely, Tawny, Scent, Watery, Wrathful, Staircase to Heaven, Staircase to a Vase, Nearby Nāga, and Oḍasuta—also bowed at the feet of the great elder.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-100">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-56</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཐལ་མོ་སྦྱར་བ་བྱས་ནས་རབ་ཏུ་གུས་པས་འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་སྨྲས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Joining their hands together, they respectfully addressed him:</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-101">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-56</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཐུགས་བརྩེ་བ་ཅན་ནགས་དེ་ནི་གཤེགས་ཤིང་བཞུགས་པའི་གནས་ཡིན་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“O compassionate one, this forest is a place to which you should come and reside.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-102">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-56</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བདག་ཅག་ཀྱང་ཉེ་གནས་བགྱིད་ལ་གཞན་དག་ཀྱང་གཟུང་དུ་གསོལ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Please let us be your disciples, and please accept others as well.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-103">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-56</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནི་སྙན་པར་གྲགས་ཤིང་ལེགས་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>This forest is praiseworthy and excellent.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-104">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-56</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཆུ་ནི་གཟིགས་པར་དབྱུང་བར་འཚལ་ལོ་ཞེས་གསོལ་བ་བཏབ་པོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Please consider the water and extract it!”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-105">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-57</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།གཞན་ཡང་ཀླུ་མོ་བརྒྱད་པོ་འདི་དག་སྟེ། །མུན་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་དང་། འགྲོ་འདོད་ཅེས་བྱ་བ་དང་། མཐོང་མོ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་དང་། གྲང་མོ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་དང་། ཁུར་དྲང་མོ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་དང་། ལབ་འཐོར་མ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་དང་། སྣ་ཚོགས་སྡེ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་དང་། དྲི་ཟ་མོ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་དག་གིས་ཀྱང་གནས་བརྟན་ཆེན་པོའི་རྐང་པ་ལ་ཕྱག་འཚལ་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Similarly, the eight nāga ladies—namely, Darkness, Eager to Leave, Seer, Cool, Load Carrying, Speech Strewing, Universal Army, and Gandharva Lady—also bowed at the feet of the great elder.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-106">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-57</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཐལ་མོ་སྦྱར་བ་བྱས་ནས་རབ་ཏུ་གུས་པས་འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་སྨྲས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Joining their hands together, they respectfully addressed him:</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-107">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-57</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཐུགས་བརྩེ་བ་ཅན་ནགས་དེ་ནི་གཤེགས་ཤིང་བཞུགས་པའི་གནས་ཡིན་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“O compassionate one, this forest is a place to which you should come and reside.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-108">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-57</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བདག་ཅག་ཀྱང་ཉེ་གནས་བགྱིད་ལ་གཞན་དག་ཀྱང་གཟུང་དུ་གསོལ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Please let us be your disciples, and please accept others as well.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-109">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-57</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནི་སྙན་པར་གྲགས་ཤིང་ལེགས་ཏེ་ཆུ་ནི་གཟིགས་པར་དབྱུང་བར་འཚལ་ལོ་ཞེས་གསོལ་བ་བཏབ་པ་དང་། ཚེ་དང་ལྡན་པ་རབ་མཐོང་ཆེན་པོས་ཅང་མི་སྨྲ་བར་དང་དུ་བླངས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>This forest is praiseworthy and excellent. Please consider the water and extract it!” The venerable great Pradarśa, by remaining quiet, consented to this request.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-110">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-57</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ལྷ་དང་། ལྷ་མ་ཡིན་དང་། ནམ་མཁའ་ལྡིང་དང་། མི་འམ་ཅི་དང་། དྲི་ཟ་དང་། ལྟོ་འཕྱེ་ཆེན་པོ་ལ་སོགས་པ་དེ་དག་གིས་ཚེ་དང་ལྡན་པ་རབ་མཐོང་ཆེན་པོས་ཅང་མི་སྨྲ་བས་དང་དུ་བླངས་པར་རིག་ནས་དགའ་མགུ་ཡི་རངས་པར་གྱུར་ཏོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>And those gods, asuras, garuḍas, kinnaras, gandharvas, mahoragas, and so on happily rejoiced, as they knew that the venerable great Pradarśa had consented to the request by remaining quiet.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-111">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-57</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ནས་ཚེ་དང་ལྡན་པ་རབ་མཐོང་ཆེན་པོས་སྟོན་པའི་ཞལ་དུ་ལྟ་བ་མཐོང་ནས་ཏ་མ་སའི་ནགས་སུ་སོང་སྟེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The venerable great Pradarśa then gazed intently at the Teacher’s face and left for the Gloomy Forest. Arriving there, he stood in the open air and struck the gaṇḍī, the sound of which was heard by the monks as it covered the whole of Jambudvīpa.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-112">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-57</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཕྱིན་ནས་བླ་གབ་མེད་པར་འགྲེང་སྟེ་གཎ་ཌཱི་བརྡུངས་ཏེ་གཎ་ཌཱིའི་སྒྲ་དེས་འཛམ་བུའི་གླིང་ཁྱབ་པར་སྒྲ་གྲགས་པར་གྱུར་པ་ན་དགེ་སློང་དག་གིས་སྒྲ་ཐོས་ཏེ་སེམས་པ་ལ་ཞུགས་པ་དང་། སྒྲ་འདི་ནི་མུན་གྱི་ནགས་ནས་བྱུང་ངོ་སྙམ་མོ། །དེ་ཡང་སྔོན་གྱི་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་སངས་རྒྱས་དག་གི་བཞུགས་གནས། རང་སངས་རྒྱས་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་གནས་བཅས་པ། འདོད་ཆགས་དང་བྲལ་བ་དག་དང་དྲང་སྲོང་དག་གི་གནས་སུ་གྱུར་པ་ཡིན་ལ་ད་ལྟར་ཡང་དེ་ཁོ་ན་བཙུན་པ་རབ་མཐོང་ཆེན་པོ་ཡིན་པར་གོ་ཞིང་ཤེས་ནས་མཐོང་སྟེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They began to think, “This sound has come from the Gloomy Forest.” This being an abode that was also inhabited by the previous perfect buddhas, by the solitary buddhas, by those without desire, and by the sages, the monks knew, understood, and saw that now the sound could only be from the honorable great Pradarśa.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-113">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-57</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དགྲ་བཅོམ་པ་ཁྲི་བརྒྱད་སྟོང་སྙེད་ཀྱིས་མུན་གྱི་ནགས་སུ་ཕྱིན་ཏེ་དབྱར་གྱི་གནས་པ་ཡང་བཅས།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Eighteen thousand worthy ones then traveled to the Gloomy Forest to undertake the summer rains retreat.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-114">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-59</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཚངས་པ་ལྷའི་དབང་པོ་དང་། འཇིག་རྟེན་སྐྱོང་བ་དེ་དག་གིས་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པའི་དབུ་སྐྲ་དང་སེན་མོ་ཁྱེར་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Brahmā, the chief of the gods, and the Guardians of the World brought the hair and nails of the Thus-Gone One.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-115">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-59</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འོངས་ནས་དབུ་སྐྲ་དང་སེན་མོའི་མཆོད་རྟེན་ཞིག་བཞེངས་སུ་གསོལ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Having arrived, they erected a reliquary containing the hair and nails.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-116">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-59</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཙུག་ལག་ཁང་ཞིག་ཀྱང་བརྩིགས། རྡོ་རྗེའི་གཙུག་ལག་ཁང་དུ་མཚན་གསོལ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They also constructed a monastery, which was given the name Vajra Monastery.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-117">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-59</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མི་མཇེད་ཀྱི་བདག་པོ་ཚངས་པ་དང་། འཇིག་རྟེན་སྐྱོང་བ་བཞེས་ཀྱང་སོ་སོ་ནས་གཙུག་ལག་ཁང་རེ་རེ་བཞེངས་སུ་གསོལ། ལོ་དང་པོ་ལ་ལྷ་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་གནས་བཅས།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Brahmā, the lord of the Sahā world, and the Four Guardians of the World also built their own individual monasteries, and the gods resided in them for the first year.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-118">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-59</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལྷའི་དབང་པོ་བརྒྱ་བྱིན་གྱིས་རང་གི་ལག་ནས་ལོ་གཅིག་གི་ཆོས་གོས་ལ་སོགས་པ་ཡོ་བྱད་ཀྱི་རིན་སྦྱར།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>For a full year, Śakra, chief of the gods, personally offered essential supplies such as monks’ robes.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-119">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-59</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལྷའི་བུ་མོ་བདེ་སོགས་ཀྱིས་དགེ་སློང་རེ་རེ་ཞིང་རས་ཡུག་རེ་རེ་ཆོས་གོས་ཀྱི་རྒྱུ་ཡང་ཕུལ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Apsarases such as Blissful also offered each monk cotton cloth for their monks’ robes.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-120">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-60</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་ཚེ་དང་ལྡན་པ་རབ་མཐོང་ཆེན་པོ་གནས་ཁང་དུ་ལྷའི་འཁོར་གྱིས་བསྐོར་ཏེ་གནས་བཅས་པ་ན་འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་སྨྲས་སོ། །གནས་བཅས་པ་འདི་ཡུན་རིང་གནས་བཅས་པར་འགྱུར་བའི་ཕྱིར་ལྷ་དང་མིའི་གྲོང་ཁྱེར་གནས་བཅའ་བའི་ཕྱིར་རྒྱལ་རིགས་རྩུབ་པོ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་ལ་སོགས་པའི་མི་རྣམས་ལ་ཆོས་བསྟན་པས་ཡིད་རབ་ཏུ་དགའ་ཞིང་དད་པར་གྱུར་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Then the venerable great Pradarśa, situated in the large assembly hall and surrounded by a retinue of gods, said, “So that this place may be habitable for a long time to come and contain cities for gods and humans, I have taught the Dharma to people such as the kṣatriya known as Tough Man,  and they have become pleased and devoted.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-121">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-60</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྒྱལ་པོ་ཆེན་པོ་རྩུབ་པོས་དཀོན་མཆོག་གསུམ་ལ་སྐྱབས་སུ་འགྲོ་བ་བྱས་གཞན་དག་ཀྱང་དད་པར་གྱུར་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The great king Tough Man has gone for refuge to the Three Jewels, and others have also become devotees.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-122">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-60</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཕུག་ལྔ་བརྒྱའི་ལས་ཀྱང་བྱས།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Work has been done on five hundred caves.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-123">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-60</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དྲང་སྲོང་མངོན་པར་ཤེས་པ་ལྔ་དང་ལྡན་པ་ལྔ་བརྒྱ་ཡང་རབ་ཏུ་བྱུང་སྟེ། དགྲ་བཅོམ་པ་མངོན་དུ་བྱས།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Five hundred sages endowed with the five forms of superknowledge have also gone forth and achieved the realization of a worthy one.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-124">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-60</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གནས་དེ་ན་བྲམ་ཟེ་སྨྲ་བ་ལ་མཁས་པ་ཅིག་ཡོད་པ་དེ་ལས་རྒྱལ་བར་གྱུར་ཏེ་བཏུལ་ནས་རབ་ཏུ་བྱུང་སྟེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>In this area, there is also a person who is an expert in the religion of the brahmins. I defeated him in debate, and he has gone forth.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-125">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-60</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེས་ཀྱང་དགྲ་བཅོམ་པ་མངོན་དུ་བྱས་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He too has achieved the realization of a worthy one.”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-126">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-62</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཏ་མ་སའི་ནགས་ན་ཚེ་དང་ལྡན་པ་རབ་མཐོང་ཆེན་པོ་ལ་སོགས་པ་དགྲ་བཅོམ་པ་ཁྲི་བརྒྱད་སྙེད་གནས་བཅས་སོ་ཞེས། རྒྱལ་པོའི་ཕོ་བྲང་འཁོར་དང་གྲོང་ཁྱེར་དང་། གྲོང་ཁྱེར་ཀུན་ཏུ་གྲགས་པར་གྱུར།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Thus, it became well known in the palaces of kings and in the cities and towns that the venerable great Pradarśa, along with eighty thousand worthy ones, resided in the Gloomy Forest.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-127">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-62</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྒྱལ་པོ་རྩུབ་པོ་ལ་སོགས་པ་མི་རྣམས་ནི་འཕགས་པའི་དགེ་འདུན་གྱི་སླད་དུ་ཉིན་རེ་བཞིན་དུ་དར་བ་འབུལ་མི་མ་ཡིན་པ་དག་ནི་དེ་བཞིན་དུ་ཞུན་མར་འབུལ་བར་བྱེད།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Every day, people such as King Tough Man offered buttermilk to the noble saṅgha.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-128">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-62</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཞན་ཡང་དགའ་བ་དང་། དང་བས་མགུ་ཞིང་རངས་པས་ལེགས་པར་ལས་དང་བྱ་བ་ཡང་བྱེད་དོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The nonhumans offered ghee, and others, being happy and inspired, were pleased and rejoiced and offered their service.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-129">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-62</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་བཞིན་དུ་ཀླུ་དག་གིས་དགའ་བ་དང་མགུ་བས་ཐ་དད་པའི་བྱེ་བྲག་བཅྭ་བརྒྱད་ཀྱི་བཟའ་བ་དང་། བཅའ་བ་སྦྱར་བ་ཕུལ་ལོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Similarly, the nāgas, being happy and pleased, offered meals of eighteen different varieties.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-130">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-63</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།གཞན་ཡང་འདི་ལྟར་སྐྱེ་དགུའི་ལུས་ཅན་སེམས་བསྐྱེད་པ་འདི་ལྟ་སྟེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Other beings also developed a similar intention.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-131">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-63</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བློན་པོ་དང་རྒྱལ་རིགས་སྤྱིར་འདུས་ཏེ། ཀུན་དགའ་ར་བ་ཞིག་ཀྱང་བྱས་ཏེ། དེ་དག་ཏུ་མེ་ཏོག་གི་ཤིང་དང་། འབྲས་བུའི་ཤིང་མཛེས་པ་འདི་དག་སྟེ། ཨ་མྲའི་ཤིང་དང་། པ་ཏིའི་ཤིང་དང་། སེང་ལྡེང་གི་ཤིང་དང་། ནྱ་གྲོ་དྷའི་ཤིང་དང་། ཨ་ཤྭད་ཐའི་ཤིང་དང་། འབྲས་བུ་གསུམ་གྱི་ཤིང་དང་། མེ་ཏོག་ཙམ་པ་ཀའི་ཤིང་དང་། ཨུ་དུ་ཀའི་ཤིང་དང་། མ་དུ་ཀའི་ཤིང་དང་། བིལ་བའི་ཤིང་དང་། འབྲ་ཧོའི་ཤིང་དང་། འཛམ་བུའི་ཤིང་དང་། དུ་ནའི་ཤིང་དང་། ཆུ་ཤིང་ལ་སོགས་པ་དང་། མེ་ཏོག་མ་ལི་ཀ་དང་། ཀུན་ད་དང་། ཛ་ཧི་ཀ་ལ་སོགས་པ་མཛེས་པ་སྣ་ཚོགས་དགེ་སློང་བདེ་བར་གནས་པ་དགེ་བའི་ཕྱོགས་བྱེད་པ་དང་འཐུན་པ་ཞིག་ཀྱང་བྱས་ཏེ་དགེ་འདུན་ལ་ཕུལ་ལོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>For example, the kṣatriyas and ministers cooperated to establish a park that contained many beautiful flowering and fruit-bearing trees, such as the mango tree, the trumpet flower tree, the cutch, the Indian banyan, the pipal tree, the three myrobalans, the campaka tree, the uduka tree, the licorice tree, the bel fruit tree, the braho tree, the black plum tree, the duna tree, and the banana plant. There were also flowers such as arabian jasmine, downy jasmine, and common jasmine. The rulers and ministers then offered this park to the saṅgha so that the monks would be able to live comfortably and have an abode conducive to wholesome pursuits.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-132">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-66</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ནས་དགེ་སློང་དག་ཐེ་ཚོམ་སྐྱེས་ནས་ཐེ་ཚོམ་ཐམས་ཅད་གཅོད་པ་སངས་རྒྱས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ལ་ཞུས་པ། བཙུན་པ་ཚེ་དང་ལྡན་པ་རབ་མཐོང་གིས་ལས་ཅི་བགྱིས་ན་ལས་གང་ཡང་རྣམ་པར་སྨིན་པ་ཕྱུག་ཅིང་ནོར་མང་ལ་ལོངས་སྤྱོད་དང་ལྡན་པའི་རིགས་སུ་སྐྱེས། གཟུགས་མཛེས་ཤིང་ལྷ་དང་མིས་མཆོད་པའི་མཆོག་ཏུ་གྱུར། བསོད་ནམས་ཆེན་པོ་དང་ལྡན་པ་ཤེས་པར་འཚལ་ལགས་སོ་ཞེས་ཞུས་པ་དང་། བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་བཀའ་སྩལ་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Later, however, the monks came to have doubts, and so they asked the blessed Buddha, who quells all doubts,  “What action did the honorable and venerable Pradarśa previously perform so that now, as this action ripens, he is rich, wealthy, and born in a prosperous lineage, so that he is handsome and the one most highly revered by gods and humans, and so that he is endowed with a great amount of merit? Please make this known to us!”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-133">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-67</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དགེ་སློང་དག་འདས་པའི་བསྐལ་པ་དགུ་བཅུ་རྩ་གཅིག་ན་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་སངས་རྒྱས་རྣམ་པར་གཟིགས་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་རིག་པ་དང་ཞབས་སུ་ལྡན་པ། བདེ་བར་གཤེགས་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The Blessed One responded, “O monks, ninety-one eons ago, the perfect Buddha Vipaśyin appeared in the world.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-134">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-67</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇིག་རྟེན་མཁྱེན་པ། སྐྱེས་བུ་འདུལ་བའི་ཁ་ལོ་སྒྱུར་བ། བླ་ན་མེད་པ། ལྷ་དང་མི་རྣམས་ཀྱི་སྟོན་པ། སངས་རྒྱས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་འཇིག་རྟེན་དུ་བྱུང་སྟེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He was perfect in terms of wisdom and conduct, a well-gone one, a knower of the world, a charioteer for beings, an unsurpassed being, a teacher of gods and humans, and a blessed buddha.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-135">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-67</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྒྱལ་པོ་གཉེན་ལྡན་གྱི་ཁབ་ན་བཞུགས་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He resided in King Bandhumat’s palace.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-136">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-67</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དུས་དེའི་ཚེ་ཞལ་ཞལ་མཁན་གྱི་རིགས་ལས་ཕྱུག་པ་ག་གེ་མོ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་ཞིག་གིས་རྣམ་པར་གཟིགས་ཀྱི་སླད་དུ་གཙུག་ལག་ཁང་བརྩིགས་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>At that time, a certain rich man from the caste of plasterers built a monastery for Vipaśyin.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-137">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-67</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མེ་ཏོག་དང་འབྲས་བུའི་ཤིང་ལེགས་པར་བཙུགས་ཏེ། ཀུན་ཏུ་དྲི་བསུང་གི་ངད་དང་ལྡན་པ་འབྱུང་བར་འགྱུར་ཏེ་ཕུལ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Landscaping it beautifully with flowers and fruit-bearing trees, the man offered the monastery, which was enveloped by pleasing scents , to Vipaśyin.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-138">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-67</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྟོན་པ་དེ་ཉིད་ཀྱི་བསྟན་པ་ལ་ཡང་རབ་ཏུ་བྱུང་།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He also went forth under the teaching of that very Teacher.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-139">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-67</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་སངས་རྒྱས་རྣམ་པར་གཟིགས་མྱ་ངན་ལས་འདས་ནས་སྐུ་གདུང་གི་མཆོད་རྟེན་གྱི་རྨང་གི་འོག་ཏུ་རིན་པོ་ཆེའི་རྡོ་རིང་ཅིག་བསྒྲེང་ངོ་།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>After the perfect Buddha Vipaśyin had passed into nirvāṇa, this monk erected a precious pillar at the foundation of the reliquary that held the Buddha’s relics.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-140">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-67</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཞལ་ཞལ་མཁན་གྱི་རིགས་ལས་རབ་ཏུ་བྱུང་བ་དེའི་འཁོར་མང་པོ་ཡང་རྗེས་སུ་ཡི་རང་ཞིང་མོས་པར་གྱུར་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The people in the retinue of this monk, who had gone forth from the caste of plasterers, rejoiced and felt admiration. Then they made the following aspiration:</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-141">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-67</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཁྱེད་སྟོན་པ་ལ་མོས་པར་གྱུར་པ་དེ་བཞིན་དུ་བདག་ཅག་ཀྱང་དད་ཅིང་མོས་པར་བགྱིད་དེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>‘Just as you admire the Teacher, may we too have faith and admiration.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-142">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-67</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྟོན་པའི་བཀའ་བཞིན་དུ་བགྱིད་ཅིང་མཉེས་པར་བགྱིད་ལ་མི་མཉེས་པར་མ་གྱུར་ཅིག་ཅེས་སྨོན་ལམ་བཏབ་བོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>May we act according to the words of the Teacher and please him. May we not displease him.’ “O monks, what do you think?</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-143">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-67</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དགེ་སློང་དག་ཇི་སྙམ་དུ་སེམས་དེའི་ཚེ་དེའི་དུས་ན་ཞལ་ཞལ་མཁན་གང་ཡིན་པ་དེ་ནི་ཚེ་དང་ལྡན་པ་རབ་མཐོང་ཆེན་པོ་ཉིད་ཡིན་ལ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>At that time, on that occasion, the person who was the plasterer is none other than the venerable great Pradarśa.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-144">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-67</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྐྱེ་དགུའི་ལུས་ཅན་དེ་དག་ནི་ད་ལྟར་གྱི་ལྷ་དང་མི་འདི་དག་ཡིན་ཏེ་ད་ལྟར་ཡང་འདུལ་བར་བྱེད་པ་ཡིན་ནོ། །གཞན་ཡང་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་འོད་སྲུང་གི་བསྟན་པ་ལ་རབ་ཏུ་བྱུང་སྟེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Similarly, those other beings are these gods and humans present here, and now too he is guiding them. “Moreover, he went forth under the teaching of the Blessed Kāśyapa, and his preceptor was the one who was the one most highly revered by gods and humans. He made the following aspiration:</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-145">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-67</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེའི་མཁན་པོ་ནི་ལྷ་དང་མིས་མཆོད་པའི་མཆོག་ཏུ་གྱུར་པ་ཡིན་ཏེ་ཇི་ལྟར་བདག་གི་མཁན་པོ་ལྷ་དང་མིས་མཆོད་པའི་མཆོག་ཏུ་གྱུར་པ་དེ་བཞིན་དུ་བདག་ཀྱང་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་སངས་རྒྱས་ཤཱཀྱ་ཐུབ་པའི་བསྟན་པ་ལ་ལྷ་དང་མིས་མཆོད་པའི་མཆོག་ཏུ་གྱུར་ཅིག་ཅེས་སྨོན་ལམ་བཏབ་བོ། །དེས་ན་ད་ལྟར་ལྷ་དང་མིས་མཆོད་པའི་མཆོག་ཏུ་གྱུར་པ་ཡིན་ནོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>‘Just as my preceptor is the one most highly revered by gods and humans, may I too, under the teaching of the perfect Buddha Śākyamuni,  become the one most highly revered by gods and humans.’ For that reason, he has now become the one most highly revered by gods and humans.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-146">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-70</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ལྟ་བས་ན་དགེ་སློང་དག་གཅིག་ཏུ་གནག་པའི་ལས་ནི་རྣམ་པར་སྨིན་པ་ཡང་གཅིག་ཏུ་གནག་གོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Therefore, O monks, the ripening of thoroughly black deeds is thoroughly black.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-147">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-70</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།རབ་ཏུ་དཀར་བ་ལས་ནི་དཀར་བའོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The ripening of truly white deeds is white.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-148">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-70</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།འདྲེས་པ་ལ་ནི་འདྲེས་པའོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The ripening of mixed deeds is mixed.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-149">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-70</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་བས་ན་དགེ་སློང་དག་རབ་ཏུ་གནག་པ་དང་འདྲེས་མ་དག་ནི་སྤོངས་ཤིག །རབ་ཏུ་དཀར་བ་དག་ལ་སྤྱད་པར་བྱ་སྟེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>For that reason, O monks, abandon truly black deeds and mixed deeds. You must carry out those deeds that are truly white.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-150">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-70</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དགེ་སློང་དག་དེ་བཞིན་དུ་བསླབ་པར་གྱིས་ཤིག །བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་དེ་སྐད་ཅེས་བཀའ་སྩལ་པ་དང་། དགེ་སློང་དེ་དག་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་བཤད་པ་ཡིད་ལ་བྱེད་དེ་མངོན་པར་དགའོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Monks, you should train in this way!” When the Blessed One had said this, the monks contemplated the Blessed One’s speech and were pleased.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-151">
            <prop name="unmatched">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།མུན་གྱི་ནགས་ཚལ་གྱི་སྒོ་ཞེས་བྱ་བའི་མདོ་རྫོགས་སོ།།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>This completes the sūtra “Entry into the Gloomy Forest.”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu id="UT22084-072-014-TU-152">
            <prop name="location-id">UT22084-072-014-73</prop>
            <prop name="revision">v-1.0.3-2022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།།བྱང་ཕྱོགས་རྒྱུད་ཀྱི་ཕྲེང་བའི་མདོ་ཁྲི་པའི་ནང་ནས་ཡུལ་ཟ་ལེན་དྲའི་བྱང་ཕྱོགས་ཀྱི་མཚམས་ཀྱི་རི། ཨུ་ཤི་རིའི་བསྔགས་པའོ།།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>From the ten-thousand-lined Sūtra of the Garland of the Northern Range , this is a description of Mount Uśīra, which is the northern border mountain of the Jālandhara region.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg/>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        </body>
</tmx>