<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tmx xmlns="http://www.lisa.org/tmx14" xmlns:eft="http://read.84000.co/ns/1.0" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<header creationtool="linguae-dharmae/84000" datatype="PlainText" segtype="block" adminlang="en-us" srclang="bo" o-tmf="TEI" eft:text-id="UT22084-075-004" eft:text-version="v-1.0.6-2023"/>
<body>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-1">
    <prop type="location-id">translation</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>
                    <tei:ref folio="F.291.b"/>༄༅། །རྒྱ་གར་སྐད་དུ། སུ་མ་ག་དྷཱ་ཨ་བ་དཱ་ན། བོད་སྐད་དུ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg/>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-2">
    <prop type="location-id">translation</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མ་ག་དྷཱ་བཟང་མོའི་རྟོགས་པ་བརྗོད་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The Exemplary Tale of Sumāgadhā</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-3">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-92</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སངས་རྒྱས་དང་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཐམས་ཅད་ལ་ཕྱག་འཚལ་ལོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-075-004-92"/>Homage to all buddhas and bodhisattvas.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-4">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-92</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg/>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Thus did I hear at one time.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-5">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-92</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སངས་རྒྱས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་མཉན་ཡོད་ན། རྒྱལ་བུ་རྒྱལ་བྱེད་ཀྱི་ཚལ་མགོན་མེད་ཟས་སྦྱིན་གྱི་ཀུན་དགའ་ར་བ་ན་བཞུགས་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The blessed Buddha was dwelling in Śrāvastī, in Prince Jeta’s Grove, Anāthapiṇḍada’s Park.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-6">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-96</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་དེའི་ཚེ་མཉན་ཡོད་ན་མགོན་མེད་ཟས་སྦྱིན་གྱི་བུ་མོ་མ་ག་དྷཱ་བཟང་མོ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་དད་པ་དང་ལྡན་པ། རང་བཞིན་བཟང་བ། བསམ་པ་དགེ་བ། བདག་དང་གཞན་ལ་ཕན་པའི་ཕྱིར་ཞུགས་པ་ཞིག་གནས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-075-004-96"/>At that time, a daughter of Anāthapiṇḍada known as Sumāgadhā, who was faithful, good-natured, virtuous in her thoughts, and engaged in benefiting herself and others, was dwelling in Śrāvastī.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-7">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-97</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཇི་ཙམ་ན་བུ་རམ་ཤིང་འཕེལ་ཞེས་བྱ་བའི་གྲོང་ཁྱེར་ན་ཚོང་དཔོན་གཞན་ཞིག་གནས་པ་ལ། དེའི་བུ་ཁྱུ་མཆོག་བྱིན་ཞེས་བྱའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-075-004-97"/>Meanwhile, in a city known as Puṇḍravardhana, there lived another merchant, whose son was known as Vṛṣabhadatta.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-8">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-97</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ཡང་གཞན་མུ་སྟེགས་པ་སྟེན་པས་གཅེར་བུ་པ་རྣམས་ལ་མངོན་པར་དད་པ་ཞིག་གནས་པ་དང་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>By associating with the heterodox non-Buddhists, he had come to believe in the nirgranthas.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-9">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-97</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་གི་ཚེ་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་ཆོ་འཕྲུལ་ཆེན་པོ་རྣམ་པར་བསྟན་པ་དེའི་ཚེ་མུ་སྟེགས་པ་རྣམས་མཐའ་འཁོབ་ཏུ་ཀུན་དུ་གནས་ཏེ། ལ་ལ་ནི་གྲོང་ཁྱེར་བཟང་བྱེད་ཅེས་བྱ་བ་ནའོ། །ལ་ལ་ནི་མུད་གི་རི་ཀ་ཞེས་བྱ་བའི་ཡུལ་ནའོ། །ལ་ལ་ནི་བུ་རམ་ཤིང་འཕེལ་ཞེས་བྱ་བའི་གྲོང་ཁྱེར་ན་གནས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Whenever the Blessed One performed miraculous displays, the non-Buddhists would remain in the outlying districts—some in the city called Bhadrika, some in the area known as Mudgirika, and some in the city known as Puṇḍravardhana.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-10">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-101</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེའི་ཚེ་དེའི་དུས་ན་ཁྱུ་མཆོག་བྱིན་དེའི་བར་དུ་ཁྱིམ་མ་བྱས་པ་དང་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-075-004-101"/>At that time, Vṛṣabhadatta had not yet established a household.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-11">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-101</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ལ་གཅེར་བུ་པ་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་སྨྲས་པ། མགོན་མེད་ཟས་སྦྱིན་གྱི་བུ་མོ་མ་ག་དྷཱ་བཟང་མོ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་གཟུགས་བཟང་བ། བལྟ་ན་སྡུག་པ། མཛེས་པ། སྐྱེ་བོ་དམ་པ་རྣམས་དང་འདྲ་བ་ཞིག་ཡོད་དོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Concerning that, the nirgranthas said, “There is a daughter of Anāthapiṇḍada called Sumāgadhā, who is beautiful, pleasing to behold, and graceful, the most beautiful woman in the land.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-12">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-103</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཇི་སྲིད་དེས་ཐོས་པ་དང་བདག་ཉིད་གཅེར་བུ་པའི་ཆ་བྱད་དུ་བྱས་ཏེ་མཉན་ཡོད་དུ་སོང་ངོ་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-075-004-103"/>As soon as he heard that, Vṛṣabhadatta assumed the guise of a nirgrantha mendicant and traveled to Śrāvastī.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-13">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-103</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཇི་ཙམ་ན་ཁྱིམ་བདག་མགོན་མེད་ཟས་སྦྱིན་གྱི་ཁྱིམ་དུ་སློང་བའི་ཕྱིར་ཞུགས་པ་དང་། དེས་བུ་མོ་དེ་མཐོང་ངོ་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He entered the home of the householder Anāthapiṇḍada to collect alms, and there he saw the girl.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-14">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-103</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མཐོང་བའི་མོད་ཁོ་ན་ལ་བུ་མོ་དེ་ལ་ཀུན་དུ་ཆགས་པར་གྱུར་ལ། དེ་དེར་བསླངས་པའི་ཚེ་ཞྭའི་ནང་དུ་བླངས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He was enamored the moment he saw her, and when he received the alms, he took them in his hat.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-15">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-103</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་བུ་མོ་དེས་ལོག་པར་སྤྱོད་པ་དེ་མཐོང་བ་དང་། འདི་ནི་ཤེས་བཞིན་མེད་པར་སློངས་མོ་ལེན་ཏོ་ཞེས་བགད་དོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The girl saw his improper behavior and laughingly said, “This one is absentmindedly accepting alms!”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-16">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-105</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་ཁྱུ་མཆོག་བྱིན་དེ་ངོ་ཚ་བར་གྱུར་པ་དང་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-075-004-105"/>Vṛṣabhadatta was ashamed and returned to the city of Puṇḍravardhana.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-17">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-105</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བུ་རམ་ཤིང་འཕེལ་གྱི་གྲོང་ཁྱེར་དུ་སོང་སྟེ་ཕ་ལ་སྨྲས་ནས་དེས་བུ་མོ་དེ་བླངས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>There he spoke to his father, who accepted the girl.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-18">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-106</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མགོན་མེད་ཟས་སྦྱིན་གྱིས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་<tei:ref folio="F.292.a"/>འདས་ལ་ཞུས་པ་དང་། བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་བཀའ་སྩལ་པ། གཞན་དུ་ན་གང་གི་ཚེ་མ་ག་དྷཱ་བཟང་མོ་འདི་བུ་རམ་ཤིང་འཕེལ་དུ་སོང་ན་རབ་ཏུ་བྱུང་བ་རྣམས་ཀྱི་བྱ་བ་དང་། སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱི་བྱ་བ་བྱེད་པར་འགྱུར་རོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-075-004-106"/>Anāthapiṇḍada asked the Blessed One about this, and the Blessed One replied, “Actually, if Sumāgadhā goes to Puṇḍravardhana, she will perform the activity of renunciants and the activity of a buddha.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-19">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-107</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡང་ཇི་སྲིད་ཅིག་ན་ཁྱིམ་བདག་མགོན་མེད་ཟས་སྦྱིན་གྱིས་ཉེ་དུ་རྣམས་ལ་ཡང་གོ་བར་བྱས་ནས་བྱིན་པ་དང་བུ་རམ་ཤིང་འཕེལ་དུ་ཁྱེར་རོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-075-004-107"/>So the householder Anāthapiṇḍada informed her relatives and she was betrothed and conveyed to the city of Puṇḍravardhana.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-20">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-109</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཇི་ཙམ་ན་དུས་གཞན་ཞིག་གི་ཚེ་ཁྱིམ་དེ་ན་གཅེར་བུ་པ་རྣམས་ཟན་ཟ་བ་དང་། དེ་ལ་སྒྱུག་མོས་སྨྲས་པ། དེ་རིང་བདག་ཅག་གི་ཁྱིམ་ན་མཆོད་གནས་རྣམས་བཤོས་གསོལ་གྱིས་ཚུར་ཤོག །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-075-004-109"/>Shortly thereafter, when the nirgranthas were eating at home, Sumāgadhā’s mother-in-law said, “Today, the venerable ones will come to our home for an offering of food.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-21">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-109</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མཆོད་གནས་རྣམས་ལ་ལྟོས་ཤིག །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Come and see the venerable ones.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-22">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-110</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མ་ག་དྷཱ་བཟང་མོས་དེ་ཐོས་པ་དང་དགའ་བ་དང་། མགུ་བ་དང་། རངས་པ་དང་། ཡིད་བདེ་བ་སྐྱེས་ཏེ་བསམས་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-075-004-110"/>On hearing this Sumāgadhā was happy, pleased, gladdened, and cheered.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-23">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-110</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ངེས་པར་བཙུན་པ་ཤཱ་རིའི་བུའམ། མཽད་གལ་གྱི་བུ་ཆེན་པོ་ལ་སོགས་པ་ཉན་ཐོས་ཆེན་པོ་རྣམས་བྱོན་པར་གྱུར་ཏོ་སྙམ་ནས་དེ་ཡིད་རབ་ཏུ་དགའ་བ་དང་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Thinking, “Surely it is the reverend Śāriputra, Mahāmaudgalyāyana, and the other great śrāvakas who have come!”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-24">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-110</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇིགས་པ་མེད་པར་སོང་བ་དང་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>she was greatly pleased and went without hesitation.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-25">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-111</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཅེར་བུ་ནགས་ཀྱི་མ་ཧེ་འདྲ་བ། སྐྲ་རྣམས་བཏོགས་པ། ཕུག་རོན་གྱི་ཕྲུ་གུ་འདྲ་བའི་གཅེར་བུ་པ་རྣམས་མཐོང་ངོ་། །མཐོང་བ་དང་དེའི་མོད་ལ་མ་ག་དྷཱ་བཟང་མོ་ངོ་ཚ་སྟེ། དེ་གདོང་གཞན་དུ་བལྟས་པ་དང་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-075-004-111"/>But as soon as she saw the nirgranthas, who were like naked wild buffalo, with plucked hair like pigeon squabs, Sumāgadhā was embarrassed and averted her face.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-26">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-111</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ལ་སྒྱུག་མོ་དེས་སྨྲས་པ། བུ་མོ་ཁྱོད་ཅིའི་ཕྱིར་ཡི་མུག་པར་གྱུར། དེས་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Her mother-in-law asked, “Daughter, why are you displeased?”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-27">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-373</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་འདི་ལྟ་བུ་མཆོད་གནས་ཡིན་ན་མཆོད་གནས་མ་ཡིན་པ་གོ་ཇི་ལྟ་བུ་ཞིག་ཡོད་པར་འགྱུར། དེ་ལ་དེས་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-075-004-373"/>She replied, “If ones such as these are objects of veneration, who would not be considered a venerable one?”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-28">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-114</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བུ་མོ་ཁྱོད་ལ་འདི་བས་ཆེས་ཁྱད་པར་དུ་འཕགས་པའི་སྟོན་པ་འགའ་ཞིག་ཡོད་དམ་བུ་མོས་སྨྲས་པ་བདག་གི་ཕའི་གཙུག་ལག་ཁང་རྒྱལ་བྱེད་ཀྱི་ཚལ་ན་སངས་རྒྱས་ཞེས་བྱ་བའི་སྟོན་པ་བཞུགས་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-075-004-114"/>Her mother-in-law asked her, “Do you have teachers who are superior to these?”<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-075-004-374"/> The girl replied, “In my father’s monastery, Prince Jeta’s Grove, there is a teacher known as the Buddha.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-29">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-114</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནི་རྒྱུ་བ་དང་། མི་རྒྱུ་བའི་འཇིག་རྟེན་གྱི་མཆོད་གནས་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He is the object of veneration of the entire animate and inanimate world.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-30">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-115</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཁྱོད་ཀྱི་སྟོན་པ་དེ་ཇི་འདྲ་བ་ཞིག །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-075-004-115"/>“What is your teacher like?”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-31">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-115</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>she asked.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-32">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-372</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བདག་གི་སྟོན་པ་བཙོ་མའི་ཚོགས་ལྟར་སེར། །བཙོ་མའི་གསེར་ལྟར་ཤིན་ཏུ་དྲི་མ་མེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-075-004-372"/>The girl replied:<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-075-004-117"/> “My teacher is golden like a heap of campaka flowers, Stainless like refined gold.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-33">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-372</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཚུལ་ཁྲིམས་རྣམ་དག་ཤེས་རབ་ཤིན་ཏུ་དག །འཇིག་རྟེན་གསུམ་ན་མཉམ་མེད་འགྲོ་ལས་འཕགས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>His discipline pure, his wisdom spotless, He is unequaled in the three worlds, the supreme among beings.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-34">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-119</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ཐོས་མ་ཐག་ཏུ་སེམས་རབ་ཏུ་དགའ་བར་གྱུར་ནས་སྨྲས་པ། བུ་མོ་ངེད་ཅག་རྣམས་ལ་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་དེ་སང་བསྟན་པར་ནུས་སམ། མ་ག་དྷཱ་བཟང་མོས་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-075-004-119"/>Upon hearing this, her mother-in-law was overjoyed, and she asked, “Daughter, can you show us that Blessed One tomorrow?”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-35">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-375</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཤོས་གཙང་རྣམས་སྦྱོར་ཅིག་<tei:ref folio="F.292.b"/>དང་། སང་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་སྤྱན་དྲང་བར་བྱའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-075-004-375"/>Sumāgadhā replied, “Prepare offerings of food, and tomorrow I will invite the Blessed One.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-36">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-121</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཇི་ཙམ་ན་དེ་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་སྨྲས་པ། བཤོས་གཙང་རྣམས་སྦྱར་གྱིས་ཁྱོད་ཀྱིས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་སང་སྤྱན་དྲོངས་ཤིག །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-075-004-121"/>Sometime later they said, “The offerings of food have been prepared, so you should invite the Blessed One tomorrow.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-37">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-122</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་མ་ག་དྷཱ་བཟང་མོས་ཁང་པའི་ཡང་ཏོག་གི་སྟེང་དུ་མངོན་པར་འཛེགས་ནས་ཕྱོགས་གང་ན་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་བཞུགས་པའི་ཕྱོགས་དེར་ཐལ་མོ་སྦྱར་ཏེ་ཕྱག་འཚལ་ནས། བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱི་ཡོན་ཏན་རྗེས་སུ་དྲན་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-075-004-122"/>Then Sumāgadhā climbed to the very top of the house. She folded her hands and paid homage in the direction of the Blessed One, recalled the good qualities of the Blessed One, and strewed flowers and made offerings of incense.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-38">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-122</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མེ་ཏོག་རྣམས་གཏོར་ཅིང་སྤོས་ཀྱང་བཏུལ་ནས་གསེར་གྱི་བུམ་པའི་ཆུས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་སྤྱན་དྲང་བའི་ཕྱིར་གསེར་གྱི་བུམ་པའི་ཆུ་ཡང་སྦྲེངས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>In order to invite the Blessed One, she sprinkled water from a golden vase.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-39">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-125</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྙིང་རྗེ་བའི་ཚིག་འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་ཀྱང་སྨྲ་སྟེ། བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཐུགས་རྗེ་ཆེན་པོ་དང་ལྡན་པ། བདག་ནི་རི་དགས་དང་འདྲ་བར་གྱུར་ཅིང་མཐའ་འཁོབ་ན་མཆིས་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-075-004-125"/>Then she spoke these piteous words: “O Blessed One possessed of great compassion, like a wild animal I have come to this frontier, separated from the Three Jewels.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-40">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-125</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དཀོན་མཆོག་གསུམ་དང་བྲལ་བར་གྱུར་པ་ལ་རྗེས་སུ་གཟུང་བར་མཛད་ཅིང་དགེ་སློང་གི་དགེ་འདུན་དང་བཅས་པ་འདིར་གཤེགས་པར་མཛད་དུ་གསོལ། ཡང་འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་ཀྱང་སྨྲས་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Please care for me, and with your saṅgha of monks please come to this place!”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-41">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-388</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཚུལ་ཁྲིམས་རྣམ་དག་ཤེས་རབ་ཤིན་ཏུ་དག །དད་ལྡན་སྙིང་པོ་ཉན་ཐོས་ཆེ་རྣམས་ཀྱིས། །མགོན་མེད་གྱུར་པ་བདག་ལ་རྗེས་གཟུང་བའི། །དོན་མཛད་ཐུགས་རྗེས་གཤེགས་པར་མཛད་དུ་གསོལ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-075-004-388"/>And she spoke these words:<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-075-004-127"/> “Your discipline pure, your wisdom spotless, Great śrāvakas with faithful hearts, Please care for me—I who am without a protector— And out of compassion come to this place.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-42">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-128</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཇི་ཙམ་ན་མེ་ཏོག་དང་སྤོས་དང་གསེར་གྱི་བུམ་པའི་ཆུའང་ནམ་མཁའ་ལ་འཕགས་པར་གྱུར་ཏོ། །བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱང་དེའི་ཚེ་ནང་དུ་ཡང་དག་འཇོག་ལས་བཞེངས་ནས་འཁོར་རྣམ་བཞི་ལ་ཆོས་སྟོན་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-075-004-128"/>Just then the flowers, incense, and water from the golden vase rose into the sky, and at that moment the Blessed One arose from his deep absorption and taught the Dharma to the fourfold assembly.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-43">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-128</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གསེར་གྱི་བུམ་པའི་ཆུ་དེ་ཡང་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱི་སྤྱན་སྔར་བཻ་དཱུརྱའི་སྡོང་བུ་བཞིན་དུ་རྣམ་པར་གནས་སོ། །མེ་ཏོག་དེ་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱི་སྟེང་གི་ནམ་མཁའ་ལ་ཁང་པ་བརྩེགས་པ་བཞིན་དུ་གནས་སོ། །དྲི་ངད་སྤོས་ཀྱང་སྤྲིན་བརྩེགས་པ་བཞིན་དུ་གནས་པར་གྱུར་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The water from the golden vase came to rest before the Blessed One like a staff of beryl, the flowers rested like a pinnacled temple in the sky above the Blessed One, and the fragrant incense came to rest like heaps of clouds.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-44">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-129</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་དེ་མཐོང་བ་དང་། ཚེ་དང་ལྡན་པ་ཀུན་དགའ་བོས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ལ་གསོལ་པ། བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་སྤྱན་འདྲེན་པ་འདི་ག་ལས་མཆིས།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-075-004-129"/>Seeing this, the venerable Ānanda inquired of the Blessed One, “Blessed One, from whence does this invitation come?”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-45">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-130</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་བཀའ་སྩལ་པ། ཀུན་དགའ་བོ་དཔག་ཚད་བརྒྱ་དྲུག་ཅུ་རྩ་གསུམ་ན། བུ་རམ་ཤིང་འཕེལ་གྱི་གྲོང་ཁྱེར་ཡོད་པ་ནས་འོངས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-075-004-130"/>The Blessed One replied, “Ānanda, it came 163 yojanas from the city of Puṇḍravardhana.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-46">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-130</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཀུན་དགའ་བོ་གྲོང་ཁྱེར་དེ་ནི་མུ་སྟེགས་པ་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་བཟུང་བ་ཡིན་པས་རྫུ་འཕྲུལ་གྱི་རྣམ་པར་འཕྲུལ་པས་འགྲོ་བར་བྱའོ་ཞེས་དགེ་སློང་<tei:ref folio="F.293.a"/>རྣམས་ལ་ཚུལ་ཤིང་བྲིམས་ཤིག །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Ānanda, as that city is held by non-Buddhists, we must go there with an extraordinary display of miraculous power. Therefore, distribute the tally sticks to the monks.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-47">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-131</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཇི་ཙམ་ན་ཚེ་དང་ལྡན་པ་ཀུན་དགའ་བོས་རྒན་པའི་གནས་མཐའ་ནས་བཟུང་ནས་ཚུལ་ཤིང་བྲིམས་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-075-004-131"/>Right away, the venerable Ānanda distributed the tally sticks, starting with the most senior monk.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-48">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-131</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་ཀྱང་སྨྲས་སོ། །སང་བུ་རམ་ཤིང་འཕེལ་གྱི་གྲོང་ཁྱེར་དུ་འགྲོ་བར་བྱ་སྟེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He said, “Tomorrow we will go to the city of Puṇḍravardhana.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-49">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-131</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གྲོང་ཁྱེར་དེ་ནི་མུ་སྟེགས་པ་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་ཡོངས་སུ་བཟུང་བས་ཁྱོད་ཅག་རྣམས་ལས་གང་རྫུ་འཕྲུལ་ཐོབ་པ་དེས་ཚུལ་ཤིང་ལོང་ཤིག །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>As that city is completely held by non-Buddhists, those among you who have attained miraculous power must take these tally sticks.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-50">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-131</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཇི་སྲིད་ཅིག་ན་རྒན་པའི་མཐའ་ནས་ཚུལ་ཤིང་ལེན་པར་བརྩམས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Then the process of taking the tally sticks began, starting with the most senior monk.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-51">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-132</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡང་དེ་ན་གནས་བརྟན་གང་པོ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་ཡོད་དེ་དེ་ཡང་རྫུ་འཕྲུལ་མ་ཐོབ་པར་ལག་པ་བརྐྱང་སྟེ་ཚུལ་ཤིང་ལེན་པར་བརྩམས་པ་དང་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-075-004-132"/>Among them was the elder known as Pūrṇa. Although he had not attained miraculous power, he reached out his hand to take a tally stick.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-52">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-132</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ལ་ཚེ་དང་ལྡན་པ་ཀུན་དགའ་བོས་སྨྲས་པ། གནས་བརྟན་མགོན་མེད་ཟས་སྦྱིན་གྱི་ཁྱིམ་དུ་འཇུག་པ་མ་ཡིན་གྱི། གཞན་དུ་དཔག་ཚད་བརྒྱ་དྲུག་ཅུ་རྩ་གསུམ་ན། བུ་རམ་ཤིང་འཕེལ་ཞེས་བྱ་བའི་གནས་ཡོད་དེ། དེར་འགྲོ་དགོས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The venerable Ānanda said to him, “Elder, we are not going to the home of Anāthapiṇḍada, but we must travel to a place 163 yojanas from here known as Puṇḍravardhana.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-53">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-134</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་འདི་སྙམ་དུ་སེམས་ཏེ། ངས་ནི་ཐོག་མ་མེད་པའི་དུས་ནས་གོམས་པའི་ཉོན་མོངས་པ་ནི་སྤངས་ན།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-075-004-134"/>The elder thought, “I have abandoned the defilements to which I had been habituated since beginningless time, so what could be difficult about such miraculous power, which is common even to non-Buddhists?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-54">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-134</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མུ་སྟེགས་པ་རྣམས་དང་ཐུན་མོང་དུ་གྱུར་པའི་རྫུ་འཕྲུལ་ལྟ་ཞིག་དཀའ་བ་ཇི་ཞིག་ཡོད་ནས་བསྐྱེད་པར་མི་བྱ་སྙམ་ནས་དེས་ཀྱང་དུས་དེ་ཉིད་དུ་རྫུ་འཕྲུལ་བསྐྱེད་པ་དང་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>I will not produce it.” Due to that thought, however, at that very moment the miraculous power was produced.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-55">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-134</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཇི་སྲིད་དུ་ཚུལ་ཤིང་གཉིས་པ་མ་བྲིམས་པ་དེ་སྲིད་དུ་དེས་གླང་པོ་ཆེའི་སྣ་འདྲ་བའི་ལག་པ་བརྐྱང་སྟེ་ཚུལ་ཤིང་བླངས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>As the second tally stick had not yet been distributed, the elder reached out his hand like an elephant’s trunk and took the tally stick.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-56">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-135</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཇི་ཙམ་ན་ཚེ་དང་ལྡན་པ་ཀུན་དགའ་བོས་རྒན་པའི་མཐའ་ལོགས་སུ་འདུག་སྟེ་སྨྲས་པ། གང་གིས་རྫུ་འཕྲུལ་གང་ཐོབ་པ་དེས་བུ་རམ་ཤིང་འཕེལ་ཞེས་བྱ་བའི་གྲོང་ཁྱེར་དུ་འགྲོ་བར་བྱའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-075-004-135"/>Meanwhile, Venerable Ānanda, sitting at the head of the elders, said, “Those who have attained miraculous power must go to the city of Puṇḍravardhana.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-57">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-137</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་ཉི་མ་གཉིས་པ་ལ་ནམ་ནངས་ཏེ་དགེ་སློང་རྣམས་རྫུ་འཕྲུལ་གྱི་རྣམ་པར་འཕྲུལ་པས་ཡང་དག་པར་ཆས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-075-004-137"/>Then on the second day, at daybreak, the monks prepared by perfecting their displays of miraculous power.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-58">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-137</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་རྒྱལ་པོ་ཆེན་པོ་བཞི་ཡང་མཉན་ཡོད་གང་ན་བ་དེར་མངོན་པར་བལྟ་བར་བརྩམས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The Four Great Kings also set out in the direction of Śrāvastī.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-59">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-137</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཇི་ཙམ་ན་བར་སྐབས་དེར་ཀུན་ཤེས་ཀཽཎྜི་ནྱ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་རྟའི་ཤིང་རྟ་ལ་ཞོན་ཏེ་གློག་འགྱུ་བའི་སྣང་བ་སྟོན་ཅིང་དལ་བུ་དལ་བུས་ཆར་རབ་ཏུ་འབེབས་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>As they did so, the one known as Ājñātakauṇḍinya, mounted on a horse chariot, displayed a flash of lightning and brought down a gentle rain.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-60">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-137</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ལྟ་བུའི་རང་གི་རྫུ་འཕྲུལ་རྣམ་པར་སྟོན་ཅིང་འོང་ངོ་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Thus demonstrating his miraculous power, he made his entrance.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-61">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-140</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་མ་ག་དྷཱ་བཟང་མོའི་བདག་པོས་དེ་མཐོང་བ་དང་དྲིས་པ། མ་ག་དྷཱ་བཟང་མོ་འདི་ཁྱོད་ཀྱི་སྟོན་པ་དེ་ཡིན་ནམ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-075-004-140"/>Sumāgadhā’s master saw this and asked, “Sumāgadhā, is this your teacher?”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-62">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-376</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེས་སྨྲས་པ། འདི་ནི་ཀུན་ཤེས་ཀཽཎྜི་ནྱ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་ཡིན་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-075-004-376"/>She replied, “This one is known as Ājñātakauṇḍinya.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-63">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-376</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདི་ནི་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་<tei:ref folio="F.293.b"/>ཆོས་ཀྱི་འཁོར་ལོ་དང་པོ་བསྐོར་བ་ན། འདིས་ཐོག་མར་བདག་མེད་པ་མངོན་སུམ་དུ་བྱས་པ་དེ་ཐོག་མར་འོངས་པ་འདི་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He is arriving first since he was the first to realize that there is no self after the Blessed One first turned the wheel of Dharma.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-64">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-142</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བར་སྐབས་དེར་གནས་བརྟན་འོད་སྲུང་ཆེན་པོས་བྲག་གི་རི་ཆེན་པོ་ཤིང་སྣ་ཚོགས་པ་རྣམ་པ་བརྒྱས་ཁྱབ་པ་བྱ་རྣམ་པ་སྣ་ཚོགས་ཀྱིས་ཁྱབ་པ། མེ་ཏོག་སྣ་ཚོགས་པས་ཡང་དག་པར་ཁེབས་པ། གཡའ་ཆུ་སྣ་ཚོགས་ཀྱིས་ཉེ་བར་མཛེས་པར་བྱས་པ་མངོན་པར་སྤྲུལ་ཏེ་སྟེང་གི་ནམ་མཁའ་ལས་འོང་ངོ་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-075-004-142"/>Then the elder Mahākāśyapa made his entrance from the sky above, having magically created a great rocky mountain covered with hundreds of variegated trees and various forms of birds, lushly carpeted with a diversity of flowers, and beautified by manifold rivulets.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-65">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-143</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་ཁྱིམ་བདག་དེས་དེ་མཐོང་ནས་སྨྲས་པ། མ་ག་དྷཱ་བཟང་མོ་འདི་ཁྱོད་ཀྱི་སྟོན་པ་དེ་ཡིན་ནམ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-075-004-143"/>The master of the house saw that and asked, “Sumāgadhā, is this your teacher?”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-66">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-377</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེས་དེ་ལ་སྨྲས་པ། འདི་ནི་འོད་སྲུང་ཆེན་པོ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་ཡིན་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-075-004-377"/>She replied, “This one who now arrives is known as Mahākāśyapa.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-67">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-377</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་སྦྱངས་པའི་ཡོན་ཏན་ལ་གནས་པར་སྨྲ་བ་རྣམས་ཀྱི་མཆོག་ཏུ་གསུངས་པ་སྟེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The Blessed One pronounced him chief among the preachers for his abiding in ascetic practices.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-68">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-377</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདིས་གཅིག་གིས་མ་ཚང་བའི་གླང་དོར་སྟོང་བོར་ཞིང་། སེར་སྐྱ་བཟང་མོ་སྐྱེ་བོ་དགེ་བ་རྣམས་དང་མཚུངས་པ་དང་། དབྱིག་དང་གསེར་མང་པོ་མཆིལ་མའི་ཐལ་བ་བཞིན་སྤངས་ནས་མངོན་པར་བྱུང་སྟེ་རབ་ཏུ་བྱུང་བ་དེ་ནི་འོང་བ་འདི་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He gave up nine hundred ninety-nine pairs of oxen and abandoned, like spittle in the dust, Kapilabhadrā, the most beautiful woman in the land, and great wealth and much gold, and went forth and became a renunciant.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-69">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-146</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བར་སྐབས་དེར་ཚེ་དང་ལྡན་པ་ཤཱ་རིའི་བུས་སེང་གེའི་ཤིང་རྟ་མངོན་པར་སྤྲུལ་ཏེ། སྟེང་གི་ནམ་མཁའ་ལ་རྫུ་འཕྲུལ་གྱིས་འོང་ངོ་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-075-004-146"/>Next, the venerable Śāriputra, having magically created a lion chariot, made his entrance in the sky above using his miraculous power.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-70">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-147</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་ཁྱིམ་བདག་དེས་དེ་མཐོང་བ་དང་དྲིས་པ། མ་ག་དྷཱ་བཟང་མོ་གང་སེང་གེའི་ཤིང་རྟས་འོང་བ་འདི་ཁྱོད་ཀྱི་སྟོན་པ་དེ་ཡིན་ནམ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-075-004-147"/>The master of the house saw that and asked, “Sumāgadhā, is this one who arrives in a lion chariot your teacher?”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-71">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-378</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་དེས་དེ་ལ་སྨྲས་པ། འདི་ནི་དགེ་སློང་ཤཱ་རིའི་བུ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་ཡིན་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-075-004-378"/>She replied, “This is the monk known as Śāriputra.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-72">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-378</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་ཤེས་རབ་དང་ལྡན་པ་རྣམས་ཀྱི་མཆོག་ཏུ་བསྟན་པ་ཡིན་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The Blessed One pronounced him chief among those endowed with wisdom.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-73">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-378</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདི་མའི་མངལ་དུ་ཞུགས་པ་ཙམ་གྱིས་འཛམ་བུའི་གླིང་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱི་རྩོད་པར་སྨྲ་བ་རྣམས་ལས་རྒྱལ་བར་གྱུར་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>As soon as he entered his mother’s womb, he was victorious over all those who engage in of debate throughout the entire world.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-74">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-378</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདི་ནི་སྟོན་པ་གཉིས་པ། མཆོག་གཉིས་པ། ཆོས་ཀྱི་སྡེ་དཔོན། ཆོས་ཀྱི་འཁོར་ལོ་རྗེས་སུ་སྐོར་བ་དེ་ནི་སེང་གེའི་ཤིང་རྟས་འོངས་པ་འདི་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He who arrives in the lion chariot is the second teacher, the second supreme one, the Dharma chief who subsequently turns the wheel of Dharma.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-75">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-149</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེའི་རྗེས་ཐོགས་ཉིད་ལ་ཚེ་དང་ལྡན་པ་མཽད་གལ་གྱི་བུ་ཆེན་པོས་གླང་པོ་ཆེ་ས་སྲུང་འདྲ་བའི་གླང་པོའི་རྒྱལ་པོ་མངོན་པར་སྤྲུལ་ཏེ། སྟེང་གི་ནམ་མཁའ་ལ་རྫུ་འཕྲུལ་གྱིས་འོང་ངོ་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-075-004-149"/>Right after that, the venerable Mahāmaudgalyāyana, having magically created a king of elephants that was like the elephant Airāvaṇa, made his entrance in the sky above using his miraculous power.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-76">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-150</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་ཁྱིམ་བདག་དེས་དེ་མཐོང་ནས། མ་ག་དྷཱ་བཟང་མོ་ལ་དྲིས་པ། གང་གླང་པོའི་རྒྱལ་པོ་ས་སྲུང་འདྲ་བའི་གླང་པོས་འོང་བ་འདི་ཁྱོད་ཀྱི་སྟོན་པ་དེ་ཡིན་ནམ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-075-004-150"/>The master of the house saw that and asked Sumāgadhā, “Is this one who arrives on an elephant that is like Airāvaṇa, the king of elephants, your teacher?”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-77">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-379</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེས་དེ་ལ་སྨྲས་པ། འདི་ནི་དགེ་སློང་མཽད་གལ་གྱི་བུ་ཆེན་པོ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་ཡིན་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-075-004-379"/>She replied, “This is the monk known as Mahāmaudgalyāyana.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-78">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-379</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་རྫུ་<tei:ref folio="F.294.a"/>འཕྲུལ་ཅན་རྣམས་ཀྱི་མཆོག་ཏུ་བསྟན་པ་སྟེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The Blessed One pronounced him chief among those with miraculous power.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-79">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-379</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདིའི་རྫུ་འཕྲུལ་གྱིས་ལྷའི་དབང་པོ་བརྒྱ་བྱིན་གྱི་རྣམ་པར་རྒྱལ་བའི་ཁང་བཟངས་རྐང་པའི་མཐེ་བོས་ཀུན་དུ་སྒུལ་བ་དང་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>With his miraculous power, he shook Vaijayanta, the mansion of Śakra, the lord of the gods, with his big toe, and he tamed the nāga kings Nanda and Upananda.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-80">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-379</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདིས་ཀླུའི་རྒྱལ་པོ་དགའ་བོ་དང་ཉེ་དགའ་བོ་གཉིས་བཏུལ་བ་དེ་གླང་པོའི་ཤིང་རྟས་འོང་བ་འདི་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>It is he who arrives on an elephant chariot.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-81">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-152</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བར་སྐབས་དེར་ཚེ་དང་ལྡན་པ་མ་འགགས་པས་ཤིང་རྟའི་འཕང་ལོ་ཙམ་གྱི་པད་མ་ཐམས་ཅད་གསེར་ལས་བྱས་པ། བཻ་དཱུརྱའི་སྡོང་བུ་ཅན་དངུལ་གྱི་གེ་སར་དང་ལྡན་པ་མངོན་པར་སྤྲུལ་ཏེ། རྫུ་འཕྲུལ་གྱིས་ནམ་མཁའ་ལས་འོང་ངོ་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-075-004-152"/>Next, the venerable Aniruddha made his entrance from the sky using his miraculous power, having magically created a lotus the size of a chariot wheel and made entirely of gold, with a stem of beryl and a stamen of silver.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-82">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-153</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་ཁྱིམ་བདག་དེས་དེ་མཐོང་བ་དང་དྲིས་པ། མ་ག་དྷཱ་བཟང་མོ་འདི་ཁྱོད་ཀྱི་སྟོན་པ་དེ་ཡིན་ནམ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-075-004-153"/>Seeing that, the master of the house asked, “Sumāgadhā, is this your teacher?”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-83">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-153</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེས་དེ་ལ་སྨྲས་པ། འདི་ནི་དགེ་སློང་མ་འགགས་པ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>She replied, “This one is the monk known as Aniruddha.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-84">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-153</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་ལྷའི་མིག་དང་ལྡན་པ་རྣམས་ཀྱི་མཆོག་ཏུ་བསྟན་པ་སྟེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The Blessed One pronounced him chief among those possessed of the divine eye.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-85">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-153</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདི་ནི་བསོད་ནམས་ཀྱི་སྟོབས་ཀྱིས་ཡོངས་སུ་བཟུང་བས་སྣོད་ཚོས་པས་གང་བ་ལྔ་བརྒྱ་སྒོ་ན་གནས་པ་དང་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He conducts himself such that by the power of his merit five hundred vessels filled with cooked food arrive at his door by merely thinking of them.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-86">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-153</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཅུང་ཟད་བསམས་པ་ཙམ་གྱིས་ཆོས་གོས་དང་། བསོད་སྙོམས་དང་། མལ་སྟན་དང་། ནད་ཀྱི་རྐྱེན་སྨན་དང་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>At the slightest thought, robes, alms, food, bedding, medicines for illness, and all necessities arise.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-87">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-153</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡོ་བྱད་རྣམས་འབྱུང་བ་ལ་སྤྱོད་པ་དེ་པད་མའི་ཤིང་རྟས་འོང་བ་འདི་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>It is he who arrives on a lotus chariot.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-88">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-155</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བར་སྐབས་དེར་ཚེ་དང་ལྡན་པ་གང་པོས་ནམ་མཁའ་ལྡིང་གི་ཤིང་རྟ་མངོན་པར་སྤྲུལ་ཏེ། རྫུ་འཕྲུལ་གྱིས་སྟེང་གི་ནམ་མཁའ་ལས་འོང་ངོ་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-075-004-155"/>Then the venerable Pūrṇa made his entrance from the sky above, having magically created a garuḍa chariot.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-89">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-157</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་ཁྱིམ་བདག་དེས་དྲིས་པ་མ་ག་དྷཱ་བཟང་མོ་ནམ་མཁའ་ལྡིང་གི་ཤིང་རྟས་འོང་བ་འདི་ཁྱོད་ཀྱི་སྟོན་པ་དེ་ཡིན་ནམ། དེས་དེ་ལ་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-075-004-157"/>The master of the house asked, “Sumāgadhā, is the one arriving on a garuḍa chariot your teacher?”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-90">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-380</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདི་ནི་དགེ་སློང་གང་པོ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་ཆོས་སྟོན་པ་རྣམས་ཀྱི་མཆོག་ཏུ་བསྟན་པ་དེ་ནམ་མཁའ་ལྡིང་གི་ཤིང་རྟས་འོང་བ་འདི་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-075-004-380"/>She replied, “This one is the monk known as Pūrṇa. The Blessed One pronounced him chief among the teachers of Dharma. It is he who arrives on a garuḍa chariot.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-91">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-380</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བར་སྐབས་དེར་ཚེ་དང་ལྡན་པ་རྟ་ཐུལ་སྤྱོད་ལམ་རབ་ཏུ་ཞི་བས་འོང་ངོ་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Next, the venerable Aśvajit made his entrance in an extremely peaceful manner.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-92">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-160</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་ཁྱིམ་བདག་དེས་དེ་ལ་དྲིས་པ། མ་ག་དྷཱ་བཟང་མོ་གང་ལྷུང་བཟེད་ལག་ན་ཐོགས་ཏེ་སྤྱོད་ལམ་རབ་ཏུ་ཞི་བས་འོང་བ་དེ་ཁྱོད་ཀྱི་སྟོན་པ་ཡིན་ནམ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-075-004-160"/>The master of the house asked, “Sumāgadhā, is this one who arrives in such a tranquil manner, holding an alms bowl, your teacher?”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-93">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-381</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེས་དེ་ལ་སྨྲས་པ། འདི་ནི་དགེ་སློང་རྟ་ཐུལ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་ཡིན་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-075-004-381"/>She replied, “This is the monk known as Aśvajit.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-94">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-381</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདིའི་སྤྱོད་ལམ་རབ་ཏུ་ཞི་བས་གླང་པོ་ཆེ་སྨྱོན་པ་བཏུལ་བ་དང་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>With his tranquil manner, he tamed a mad elephant.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-95">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-381</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདིའི་སྤྱོད་ལམ་རབ་ཏུ་ཞི་བ་མཐོང་བས་འཕགས་པ་ཤཱ་རིའི་བུས་བདེན་པ་མཐོང་བར་གྱུར་ཏེ། དེ་མངོན་པར་བྱུང་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱི་བསྟན་པ་ལ་རབ་ཏུ་བྱུང་ངོ་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Seeing his tranquil manner, the noble Śāriputra saw the truth, went forth and became a renunciant in the teaching of the Blessed One, and, having become a renunciant, attained arhathood.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-96">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-381</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རབ་ཏུ་བྱུང་ནས་ཀྱང་དགྲ་བཅོམ་པ་ཉིད་ཐོབ་པ་དེ་སྤྱོད་ལམ་རབ་<tei:ref folio="F.294.b"/>ཏུ་ཞི་བས་འོང་བ་འདི་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>It is he who arrives in a tranquil manner.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-97">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-162</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བར་སྐབས་དེར་ཚེ་དང་ལྡན་པ་ཉེ་བར་འཁོར་གྱིས་གསེར་གྱི་ཏ་ལའི་ནགས་མངོན་པར་སྤྲུལ་ཏེ། རྫུ་འཕྲུལ་གྱིས་སྟེང་གི་ནམ་མཁའ་ལས་འོང་ངོ་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-075-004-162"/>Then the venerable Upāli made his entrance from the sky above using his miraculous power, having magically created a forest of golden palm trees.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-98">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-163</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་ཁྱིམ་བདག་དེས་དེ་ལ་དྲིས་པ། མ་ག་དྷཱ་བཟང་མོ་གང་གསེར་གྱི་ཏ་ལའི་ནགས་ལ་རྟེན་ཅིང་འོང་བ་འདི་ཁྱོད་ཀྱི་སྟོན་པ་དེ་ཡིན་ནམ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-075-004-163"/>The master of the house asked, “Sumāgadhā, is this one who arrives in a forest of golden palm trees your teacher?”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-99">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-382</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེས་དེ་ལ་སྨྲས་པ། འདི་ནི་དགེ་སློང་ཉེ་བར་འཁོར་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་འདུལ་བ་འཛིན་པ་རྣམས་ཀྱི་མཆོག་ཏུ་བསྟན་པ་ཡིན་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-075-004-382"/>She replied, “This is the monk known as Upāli. The Blessed One pronounced him chief among the holders of the Vinaya.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-100">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-382</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདི་ལ་ཤཱཀྱ་ལྔ་བརྒྱ་ཙམ་རབ་ཏུ་བྱུང་བ་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་དོ་ཤལ་དང་། གདུ་བུ་དང་། དཔུང་རྒྱན་དང་། གསེར་གྱི་གདུགས་ལ་སོགས་པའི་རྒྱན་རྣམས་དང་། གོས་རྣམས་ཀྱི་ཕུང་པོ་ཆེན་པོ་མདུན་དུ་བཞག་པ་དང་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>As many as five hundred Śākya renunciants placed a great heap of ornaments such as necklaces, bracelets, armlets, golden parasols, and garments in front of him.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-101">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-382</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདིས་དེ་མཐོང་བ་དང་སྐྱོ་བ་ཆེན་པོ་སྐྱེས་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>When he saw them, he felt a great revulsion.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-102">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-382</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་དག་ཐམས་ཅད་མི་རྟག་པར་ཤེས་ནས། བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱི་བསྟན་པ་ལ་རབ་ཏུ་བྱུང་ངོ་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Understanding them all to be impermanent, he became a renunciant in the teaching of the Buddha, and, having become a renunciant, he realized the state of an arhat.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-103">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-382</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རབ་ཏུ་བྱུང་ནས་ཀྱང་དགྲ་བཅོམ་པ་ཉིད་མངོན་སུམ་དུ་བྱས་པ་དེ་གསེར་གྱི་ཏ་ལའི་ནགས་ལ་རྟེན་ནས་འོང་བ་འདི་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>It is he who arrives in a forest of golden palm trees.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-104">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-165</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་བར་སྐབས་དེར་ཚེ་དང་ལྡན་པ་ཀཱ་ཏྱཱ་ཡ་ནའི་བུ་ཆེན་པོས་བཻ་དཱུརྱའི་ཁང་པ་བརྩེགས་པ་མངོན་པར་སྤྲུལ་ཏེ། རྫུ་འཕྲུལ་གྱིས་ནམ་མཁའ་ལས་འོང་ངོ་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-075-004-165"/>Next, the venerable Mahākātyāyanaputra made his entrance from the sky using his miraculous power, having magically created a pinnacled temple made of beryl.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-105">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-166</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་ཁྱིམ་བདག་གིས་དྲིས་པ། མ་ག་དྷཱ་བཟང་མོ་བཻ་དཱུརྱའི་ཁང་པ་བརྩེགས་པ་ན་འདུག་སྟེ་འོང་བ་འདི་ཁྱོད་ཀྱི་སྟོན་པ་དེ་ཡིན་ནམ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-075-004-166"/>The master of the house asked, “Sumāgadhā, is this one who arrives seated in a pinnacled temple made of beryl your teacher?”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-106">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-383</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེས་དེ་ལ་སྨྲས་པ། འདི་ནི་དགེ་སློང་ཀཱ་ཏྱཱ་ཡ་ནའི་བུ་ཆེན་པོ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-075-004-383"/>She replied, “This is the monk known as Mahākātyāyanaputra.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-107">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-383</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་མདོ་སྡེ་པ་དང་བྱེ་བྲག་ཏུ་སྨྲ་བ་རྣམས་ཀྱི་མཆོག་ཏུ་བསྟན་པ་དེ་བཻ་དཱུརྱའི་ཁང་པ་བརྩེགས་པའི་ནང་དུ་འདུག་ནས་འོང་བ་འདི་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The Blessed One pronounced him chief among the Sautrāntika and Vaibhāṣika teachers. It is he who arrives seated in a pinnacled temple made of beryl.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-108">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-168</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བར་སྐབས་དེར་ཚེ་དང་ལྡན་པ་གསུས་པོ་ཆེས་ཁྱུ་མཆོག་གི་ཤིང་རྟ་མངོན་པར་སྤྲུལ་ནས། རྫུ་འཕྲུལ་གྱིས་སྟེང་གི་ནམ་མཁའ་ལས་འོང་ངོ་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-075-004-168"/>Next, the venerable Kauṣṭhila made his entrance from the sky above using his miraculous power, having magically created a bull chariot.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-109">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-169</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་ཁྱིམ་བདག་དེས་དྲིས་པ། མ་ག་དྷཱ་བཟང་མོ་གང་ཁྱུ་མཆོག་གི་ཤིང་རྟ་ལ་ཞོན་ཏེ་འོང་བ་འདི་ཁྱོད་ཀྱི་སྟོན་པ་དེ་ཡིན་ནམ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-075-004-169"/>The master of the house asked, “Sumāgadhā, is this one who arrives riding on a bull chariot your teacher?”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-110">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-384</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེས་དེ་ལ་སྨྲས་པ། འདི་ནི་དགེ་སློང་གསུས་པོ་ཆེ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-075-004-384"/>She replied, “This is the monk known as Kauṣṭhila.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-111">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-384</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་རིག་པ་ཐོབ་པ་རྣམས་ཀྱི་མཆོག་ཏུ་བསྟན་པ་དེ་ཁྱུ་མཆོག་གི་ཤིང་རྟས་འོང་བ་འདི་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The Blessed One pronounced him chief among those who have attained analytical knowledge. It is he who arrives seated on a bull chariot.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-112">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-171</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བར་སྐབས་དེར་ཚེ་དང་ལྡན་པ་སྲུང་དབང་གི་བུ་ངང་པའི་ཤིང་རྟས་སྟེང་གི་ནམ་མཁའ་ལས་རྫུ་འཕྲུལ་གྱིས་འོང་ངོ་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-075-004-171"/>Then the venerable Pilindavatsa, by means of a swan chariot, made his entrance from the sky above using his miraculous power.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-113">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-172</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་<tei:ref folio="F.295.a"/>ཁྱིམ་བདག་དེས་དྲིས་པ། མ་ག་དྷཱ་བཟང་མོ་གང་ངང་པའི་ཤིང་རྟས་འོང་བ་འདི་ཁྱོད་ཀྱི་སྟོན་པ་དེ་ཡིན་ནམ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-075-004-172"/>The master of the house asked, “Sumāgadhā, is this one who arrives riding a swan chariot your teacher?”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-114">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-385</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེས་དེ་ལ་སྨྲས་པ། འདི་ནི་དགེ་སློང་སྲུང་དབང་གི་བུ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-075-004-385"/>She replied, “This is the monk known as Pilindavatsa.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-115">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-385</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་སྙིང་རྗེ་ལ་གནས་པ་རྣམས་ཀྱི་མཆོག་ཏུ་བསྟན་པ་དེ་འདི་ཡིན་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The Blessed One pronounced him chief among those who abide in compassion.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-116">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-385</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདི་ཆུ་བོ་གང་གཱ་རྒལ་བར་འདོད་པ་ན་དམངས་མོ་འདུག་ཤིག་ཅེས་སྨྲས་པ་དང་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>When he wished to cross the Ganges River, he commanded, ‘Stay, servant woman!’</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-117">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-385</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཚིག་དེའི་རྗེས་ཐོགས་ཉིད་ལ་རི་བོ་བརྩེགས་པ་བཞིན་དུ་གནས་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>As soon as he spoke those words, she remained like a mountain peak, not flowing at all.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-118">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-385</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྣམ་པ་ཐམས་ཅད་དུ་མི་འབབ་པར་བྱེད་པ་དེ་ངང་པའི་ཤིང་རྟས་འོང་བ་འདི་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>It is he who arrives on a swan chariot.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-119">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-174</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བར་སྐབས་དེར་ཚེ་དང་ལྡན་པ་རྣ་བ་བྱེ་བ་ཉི་ཤུ་རི་ནགས་ཀྱི་ཚོགས་ལ་འཆག་ཅིང་འདུག་པ་དེ་འཆག་བཞིན་དུ་འོང་ངོ་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-075-004-174"/>Next, the venerable Koṭīviṃśakarṇa made his entrance on foot, walking in a mountain forest.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-120">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-175</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་ཁྱིམ་བདག་དེས་དྲིས་པ། མ་ག་དྷཱ་བཟང་མོ་གང་ནགས་ཤིང་བརྒྱ་དག་གིས་ཁྱབ་པའི་ནགས་འདི་ལ་འཆག་ཅིང་འོང་བ་འདི་ཁྱོད་ཀྱི་སྟོན་པ་དེ་ཡིན་ནམ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-075-004-175"/>The master of the house asked, “Sumāgadhā, is this one who arrives walking in a forest that is filled with hundreds of trees your teacher?”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-121">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-386</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེས་དེ་ལ་སྨྲས་པ། འདི་ནི་དགེ་སློང་རྣ་ཅན་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་བརྩོན་འགྲུས་རྩོམ་པ་རྣམས་ཀྱི་མཆོག་ཏུ་བསྟན་པ་ཡིན་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-075-004-386"/>She replied, “This is the monk known as Karṇika. The Blessed One pronounced him chief among those who exert themselves in diligence.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-122">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-386</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདི་སྐྱེས་པ་ཙམ་གྱིས་རྣ་བ་བྱེ་བ་ཉི་ཤུ་རི་བ་དང་བཅས་པར་སྐྱེས་པ་དང་། གང་གི་རྐང་མཐིལ་གྱི་འོག་ནས་སོར་བཞི་ཙམ་གྱི་གསེར་གྱི་སྤུ་ཡང་དག་པར་སྐྱེས་པ་དང་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>As soon as he was born, he possessed a worth of two hundred million chaffed grains, and from the soles of his feet sprouted golden hair four finger-breadths in length.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-123">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-386</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་འདི་དང་པོའི་ཟན་ལ་ཀཱར་ཥཱ་པ་ཎ་ལྔ་བརྒྱ་ཟད་པར་བྱས་པ་དང་། གང་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་སྙུང་བ་དང་། མཽད་གལ་གྱི་བུ་ཆེན་པོས་བཤོས་གཙང་ཉེ་བར་བླངས་པ་དང་། གང་གི་དྲིས་འོད་མའི་ཚལ་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀུན་དུ་གང་བ་ན། རྒྱལ་པོ་གཟུགས་ཅན་སྙིང་པོས་མནམས་ནས་མཆོག་ཏུ་ངོ་མཚར་སྐྱེས་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He is the one on whom five hundred karṣāpaṇa coins were spent for his first cooked meal, and when the Blessed One was ill and Mahāmaudgalyāyana brought it as a food offering for him, its aroma filled the whole of the Veṇuvana, so that King Bimbisāra smelled it and was greatly amazed.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-124">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-386</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་གི་རྐང་པ་གཉིས་བཞག་པ་ཙམ་གྱིས་ས་འདི་རབ་ཏུ་གཡོས་པ་དང་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He is the one who, merely setting down his two feet, caused this earth to quake.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-125">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-386</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་ཞིག་རབ་ཏུ་བྱུང་ནས་འཆག་སར་འཆག་པ་ན་དེའི་རྐང་པ་གཉིས་ལས་ཁྲག་བྱུང་བ་ཟགས་པ་ཁྭ་རྣམས་འཐུང་བ་དེ་འཆག་ཅིང་འོང་བ་འདི་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He is the one, after he became a renunciant and stepped onto the meditation walkway, from whose two feet blood flowed and was drunk by crows. It is he who arrives on foot.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-126">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-179</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བར་སྐབས་དེར་ཚེ་དང་ལྡན་པ་སྒྲ་གཅན་འཛིན་འཁོར་ལོས་སྒྱུར་བའི་ཆ་ལུགས་སུ་མངོན་པར་སྤྲུལ་ཏེ་འོང་བ་དང་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-075-004-179"/>Then the venerable Rāhula made his entrance, having magically created the appearance of a universal monarch.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-127">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-180</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་ཁྱིམ་བདག་དེས་དྲིས་པ། མ་ག་དྷཱ་བཟང་མོ་གང་འཁོར་ལོས་སྒྱུར་བའི་ཆ་བྱད་ཀྱིས་འོང་བ་འདི་ཁྱོད་ཀྱི་སྟོན་པ་དེ་ཡིན་ནམ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-075-004-180"/>The master of the house asked, “Sumāgadhā, is this one who arrives in the image of a universal monarch your teacher?”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-128">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-387</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེས་དེ་ལ་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-075-004-387"/>She replied, “This is the son of the Blessed One.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-129">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-387</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདི་ནི་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱི་སྲས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་བསླབ་པ་འཛིན་པ་རྣམས་ཀྱི་མཆོག་ཏུ་བསྟན་པ་ཡིན་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The Blessed One pronounced him chief among those who hold the precepts.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-130">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-387</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདིས་ཡབ་ཀྱིས་སྤངས་པའི་དཔལ་སྟོན་པར་བྱེད་ཅིང་འཁོར་ལོས་སྒྱུར་བའི་ཆ་ལུགས་ཀྱིས་རིན་པོ་ཆེ་སྣ་<tei:ref folio="F.295.b"/>བདུན་དང་ལྡན་པ་བུ་སྟོང་གིས་ཡོངས་སུ་བསྐོར་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He gloriously demonstrates what was relinquished by his father, and in the appearance of a universal monarch he is possessed of the seven treasures and surrounded by thousands of youths.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-131">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-387</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཟའ་དང་རྒྱུ་སྐར་དང་སྐར་མའི་ཚོགས་ཀྱིས་བསྐོར་བའི་ཟླ་བ་ལྟ་བུ་དང་། རྒྱལ་པོའི་ལམ་བཟུང་ནས་འགྲོ་བ་མིའི་བདག་པོ་ལྟ་བུ་དང་། ཆུ་བོ་སྟོང་ཕྲག་གི་ཆུ་འབབ་པས་ཀུན་ཏུ་འགེངས་པའི་རྒྱ་མཚོ་ལྟ་བུ་དང་། འཇིགས་པ་དང་ནད་དང་མྱ་ངན་སེལ་བའི་སྐྱེ་དགུ་སྐྱོང་བ་ཆེན་པོ་ལྟ་བུ་དང་། རི་དགས་ཀྱི་ནང་ན་སེང་གེ་ལྟ་བུ་དང་། བྱ་རྣམས་ཀྱི་ནང་ན་ནམ་མཁའ་ལྡིང་ལྟ་བུ་དང་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He is the one who arrives like the moon surrounded by a host of planets, constellations, and stars; like a lord of humans who has entered the royal road; like an ocean filled by the cascading of a thousand rivers; like a great protector of beings who dispels fear, illness, and misery; like a lion among beasts; like a garuḍa among birds; like the all-clearing sun; and like a universal monarch ruling the four continents.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-132">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-387</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཐམས་ཅད་སེལ་བའི་ཉི་མ་དང་། གླིང་བཞི་ལ་དབང་བའི་འཁོར་ལོས་སྒྱུར་བ་དང་། ཆོས་བཟང་ན་མིག་སྟོང་ལྡན་པ་ཆོས་སྐྱོང་བ་ལྟ་བུར་འོང་བ་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>It is he who arrives like the thousand-eyed protector of the Dharma in the assembly hall of Sudharma.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-133">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-183</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་བཞིན་དུ་ལ་ལ་ནི་འབར་བར་བྱེད་པ་དང་། ལ་ལ་ནི་ཆར་འབེབས་པ་དང་། དེ་བཞིན་དུ་ཆོ་འཕྲུལ་སྣ་ཚོགས་པ་སྟོན་ཅིང་འོང་བ་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-075-004-183"/>Likewise, the others made their entrances demonstrating a variety of miraculous displays—some displaying a blaze of fire, some a shower of rain.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-134">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-183</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལ་ལ་ས་ལས་འཕགས་པ་དང་། །ལ་ལ་ནམ་མཁའི་གཞི་ལ་གནས། །ལ་ལ་སྟན་ནི་སྤྲུལ་བྱེད་དེ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Some rose up from the earth, some rested on the foundation of the sky, and some created seats.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-135">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-183</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྫུ་འཕྲུལ་ལྡན་པའི་མཐུ་ལ་ལྟོས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Behold the might of those possessing miraculous power!</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-136">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-183</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ལྟར་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱི་སློབ་མ་རྣམས་ཡང་དག་པར་སོང་བ་དང་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>This is how the disciples of the Blessed One went.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-137">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-185</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་འོད་གང་གིས་འཛམ་བུའི་གླིང་ཐམས་ཅད་གསེར་བཙོ་མའི་མདོག་འདྲ་བའི་འོད་ཀྱིས་གང་བ་དེ་ལྟ་བུའི་འོད་བཀྱེ་ཞིང་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-075-004-185"/>Then the Blessed One emitted a light by which all of Jambudvīpa was filled with light the color of refined gold.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-138">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-185</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མཉན་ཡོད་ནས་བརྩམས་ཏེ་བུ་རམ་ཤིང་འཕེལ་གྱི་བར་འདིར་འོད་ཀྱི་དཀྱིལ་འཁོར་ཆེན་པོ་བཀྱེ་བས་གང་དུའང་མིག་གིས་མི་མཐོང་བ་མེད་པས་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱིས་མཐོང་བར་གྱུར་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>By sending forth a great mass of light from Śrāvastī all the way to Puṇḍravardhana, nowhere was there anything that could not be seen by the eyes; thus was there total visibility.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-139">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-185</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱང་ནམ་མཁའ་ལ་གཤེགས་པ་དང་། ལག་ན་རྡོ་རྗེ་ནི་སྣམ་ལོགས་ནས་འགྲེང་ངོ་། །གནས་གཙང་མ་པ་རྣམས་ནི་སྟེང་ནས་སོ། །འདོད་པ་ན་སྤྱོད་པའི་ལྷ་རྣམས་ནི་འོག་ནས་སོ། །གཡོན་ལོགས་ནས་ནི་བརྒྱ་བྱིན་ནོ། །གཡས་ནས་ནི་ཚངས་པའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The Blessed One too proceeded through the sky, with Vajrapāṇi following behind him, the residents of Śuddhāvāsa above, the gods of the desire realm below, Śakra on the left, and Brahmā on the right.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-140">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-187</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་བཞིན་དུ་གཙུག་ཕུད་ལྔ་པ་དང་། ཤིན་ཏུ་དགའ་དང་མིག་སྦྱིན་ལ་སོགས་པ་དྲི་ཟ་རྣམས་པི་བང་དང་གླིང་བུ་དང་རྔ་དང་རྫ་རྔ་ལ་སོགས་པ་རོལ་མོའི་བྱེ་བྲག་སྙན་པ་རྣམས་རྡུང་ཞིང་། མེ་ཏོག་དང་། བདུག་པ་དང་། དྲི་དང་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-075-004-187"/>Likewise, gandharvas such as Pañcaśikha, Supriya, and Eye Gift traveled in great numbers, playing pleasant, diverse melodies on lutes, flutes, paṇava drums, clay drums, and the like, and strewing flowers, incense, perfumes, and garlands.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-141">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-189</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཕྲེང་བ་རྣམས་ཀྱང་འཐོར་ཞིང་འབྱོར་པ་ཆེན་པོས་གཤེགས་ཏེ། བར་སྐབས་དེར་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་སྲོག་ཆགས་སྟོང་ཕྲག་བདུན་ཅུ་རྩ་བདུན་བདེན་པ་ལ་ཐོག་མར་རབ་ཏུ་བཀོད་པར་མཛད་ནས་དེའི་འོག་ཏུ་བུ་རམ་ཤིང་འཕེལ་གྱི་གྲོང་ཁྱེར་དུ་གཤེགས་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-075-004-189"/>Meanwhile, the Blessed One established seventy-seven thousand beings in the truth for the first time and, having done so, he arrived at the city of Puṇḍravardhana.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-142">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-189</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གྲོང་ཁྱེར་དེ་ན་ཡང་སྒོ་བཅྭ་བརྒྱད་ཡོད་པ་དང་། དེར་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་སངས་རྒྱས་བཅྭ་བརྒྱད་སྤྲུལ་པར་མཛད་ནས་སྒོ་<tei:ref folio="F.296.a"/>རེ་རེ་ཞིང་སངས་རྒྱས་སྣང་བར་གྱུར་པ་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་མ་ག་དྷཱ་བཟང་མོའི་ཁྱིམ་དུ་གཤེགས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The city had eighteen gates, at which the Blessed One emanated eighteen buddhas, a buddha appearing at each of the gates. Then the Blessed One arrived at Sumāgadhā’s house.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-143">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-190</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་སྐྱེ་བོའི་ཚོགས་ཆེན་པོ་དེ་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་སངས་རྒྱས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་མ་མཐོང་སྟེ། དེ་རྣམས་ཁྲོས་ནས་དེའི་ཁྱིམ་བཤིག་པར་བརྩམས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-075-004-190"/>Since they could not see the blessed Buddha, the great crowd of people became angry and started to break down the house.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-144">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-190</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་གྲོང་ཁྱེར་དེ་ཐམས་ཅད་ཤེལ་གྱི་རང་བཞིན་དུ་བྱིན་གྱིས་བརླབས་ཏེ། གང་ཁྱིམ་ཐམས་ཅད་དུའང་སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱི་སྐུ་བཞུགས་པར་མཐོང་བར་མཛད་དོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>So, the Blessed One used his intention to transform the entire city into crystal, so that the body of the Buddha could be seen seated within each and every house.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-145">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-191</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཇི་སྲིད་བུ་རམ་ཤིང་འཕེལ་དུ་མ་ག་དྷཱ་བཟང་མོ་ལ་སོགས་པའི་སྲོག་ཆགས་བརྒྱ་སྟོང་དུ་མ་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ལ་མེ་ཏོག་དང་དྲི་དང་། ཕྲེང་བ་དང་། སྤོས་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་མཆོད་པ་བྱས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-075-004-191"/>Sumāgadhā and many hundreds of thousands of other beings in Puṇḍravardhana then offered flowers, perfumes, garlands, and incense to the Blessed One.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-146">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-191</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་ཀྱང་མ་ག་དྷཱ་བཟང་མོ་ལ་སོགས་པའི་སྐྱེ་བོའི་ཚོགས་ཆེན་པོ་དེ་རྣམས་ལ་གང་ཞིག་ཐོས་ན་མ་ག་དྷཱ་བཟང་མོ་ལ་སོགས་པའི་སྲོག་ཆགས་བརྒྱ་སྟོང་དུ་མ་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་བདེན་པ་མངོན་དུ་མཐོང་བ་ཐོབ་པར་གྱུར་པ་དེ་ལྟ་བུའི་ཆོས་བསྟན་པ་མཛད་ཅིང་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The Blessed One taught the Dharma to Sumāgadhā and the rest of the great gathering of people in such a way that those who heard it—Sumāgadhā and the many hundreds and thousands of other beings—obtained the direct vision of the truth.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-147">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-191</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཁོར་དེ་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱང་སངས་རྒྱས་ལ་གཞོལ་བ་དང་། ཆོས་ལ་བབ་པ་དང་། དགེ་འདུན་ལ་འབབ་པར་གྱུར་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The entire assembly became inclined toward the Buddha, disposed to the Dharma, and favorable toward the Saṅgha.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-148">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-192</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡང་དགེ་སློང་རྣམས་ཐེ་ཙོམ་སྐྱེས་ཏེ། ཐེ་ཙོམ་ཐམས་ཅད་གཅོད་པར་མཛད་པ་སངས་རྒྱས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ལ་ཞུས་པ། བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཇི་སྲིད་དུ་མ་ག་དྷཱ་བཟང་མོ་མཆིས་ནས་སྲོག་ཆགས་བརྒྱ་སྟོང་དུ་མ་མཐོ་རིས་དང་ཐར་པ་ལ་གཞོལ་བར་གྱུར་པ་དང་། འདིས་སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱི་མཛད་པ་བགྱིས་པ་ནི་ངོ་མཚར་ཆེའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-075-004-192"/>Yet, the monks were perplexed, and to ease all their uncertainty, they addressed the Blessed One: “Blessed One, it is wondrous how by Sumāgadhā’s going to the other side, many hundreds of thousands of beings have become inclined toward the higher realms and toward liberation, and that by this she has accomplished buddha activity.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-149">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-193</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་བཀའ་སྩལ་པ། ད་ལྟ་འབའ་ཞིག་ཏུ་མ་ཟད་དེ། འདས་པའི་དུས་ན་འདིས་སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱི་བྱ་བ་བྱས་པ་དེ་ཉོན་ཅིག །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-075-004-193"/>The Blessed One replied, “Listen to how she accomplished buddha activity, not only at present but in the past, too.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-150">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-193</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དགེ་སློང་དག་སྔོན་བྱུང་བ་འདས་པའི་དུས་ན་སྐྱེ་དགུའི་ཚེ་ལོ་ཉི་ཁྲི་ཐུབ་པ་ན། ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་སངས་རྒྱས་འོད་སྲུང་ཞེས་བྱ་བ། རིག་པ་དང་ཞབས་སུ་ལྡན་པ། བདེ་བར་གཤེགས་པ། འཇིག་རྟེན་མཁྱེན་པ། སྐྱེས་བུ་འདུལ་བའི་ཁ་ལོ་སྒྱུར་བ་བླ་ན་མེད་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Monks, in ancient times, long ago, when the lifespan of humans was twenty thousand years, the perfectly complete buddha known as Kāśyapa, one endowed with perfect knowledge and conduct, a well-gone one, a knower of the world, an unsurpassed charioteer who tames beings, a teacher of gods and humans, a blessed buddha, emerged in the world.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-151">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-193</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལྷ་དང་མི་རྣམས་ཀྱི་སྟོན་པ། སངས་རྒྱས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་འཇིག་རྟེན་དུ་བྱུང་སྟེ། ཡང་དུས་དེའི་ཚེ་གྲོང་ཁྱེར་བཱ་རཱ་ཎ་སཱི་ན་རྒྱལ་པོ་ཀྲྀ་ཀཱི་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་རྒྱལ་པོ་བྱེད་དེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>At that time, a king known as Kṛkin ruled the city of Vārāṇasī.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-152">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-193</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེའི་བུ་མོ་གསེར་གྱི་ཕྲེང་བ་དང་ལྡན་པ་ཞིག་བཙས་ཏེ། དེའི་མིང་ཡང་གསེར་ཕྲེང་ཅན་ཞེས་བྱ་བར་བཏགས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>His daughter was born with a golden garland, and so they named her Kāñcanamālā.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-153">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-194</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཇི་སྲིད་ཅིག་ན་བུ་མོ་དེ་ཆེར་སྐྱེས་པར་གྱུར་པ་དང་ན་ཟླ་གཞོན་ནུ་མ་ལྔ་བརྒྱ་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱང་གཞོན་ནུ་མས་བསྐོར་ཅིང་ཐབས་ཅིག་ཏུ་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་<tei:ref folio="F.296.b"/>སངས་རྒྱས་འོད་སྲུང་ལ་བསྙེན་བཀུར་བྱེད་དེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-075-004-194"/>“Later, when the girl had grown up, she went together with a retinue of young ladies, in all five hundred young girls of the same age, to pay her respects to the perfectly complete Buddha Kāśyapa.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-154">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-194</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ལ་དད་པ་ཡང་དག་པར་ཐོབ་པས་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་སངས་རྒྱས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་འོད་སྲུང་ལ་ཇི་སྲིད་འཚོའི་བར་དུ་ཆོས་གོས་དང་། བསོད་སྙོམས་དང་གཟིམས་ཆ་དང་སྙུན་གྱི་རྐྱེན་སྨན་དང་། ཡོ་བྱད་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་བསྙེན་བཀུར་བྱེད་དོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Because they had faith in him, for as long as they lived they continued to serve that perfectly complete buddha, the blessed Kāśyapa, providing him with robes, alms, food, bedding, medicines for curing illness, and other necessities.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-155">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-195</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡང་དུས་དེའི་ཚེ་རྒྱལ་པོ་ཀྲྀ་ཀཱིས་མཚན་གཅིག་ལ་རྨི་ལམ་བཅུ་རྨིས་ཏེ། དེས་སྨྲས་པ། གླང་པོ་ཆེའི་རྒྱལ་པོ་སྐར་ཁུང་ནས་བྱུང་བ་ན་མཇུག་མ་ཕྲ་མོ་ཐོགས་པ་དང་། སྐོམ་པའི་ཕྱི་ནས་ཁྲོན་པ་སྙེགས་པར་རྨི་བ་དང་། ཕྱེ་བྲེ་གང་དང་མུ་ཏིག་བྲེ་གང་ཚོང་བྱེད་པ་དང་། ཙན་དན་དང་ཤིང་རིན་མཉམ་པར་བྱེད་པ་དང་། ཀུན་དགའ་ར་བ་མེ་ཏོག་དང་འབྲས་བུ་ཕུན་སུམ་ཚོགས་པ་མ་བྱིན་པར་ལེན་པ་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་ཕྲོགས་པ་དང་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-075-004-195"/>“During that time, one night, King Kṛkin dreamed ten dreams.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-156">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-195</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གླང་པོ་ཆེ་ཕྲུ་གུས་སྤོས་ཀྱི་གླང་པོ་འཇིགས་པར་བྱེད་པ་དང་། སྤྲེའུ་མི་གཙང་བས་གོས་པས་གཞན་ལ་སྐུད་པ་དང་། སྤྲེའུ་རྒྱལ་པོར་དབང་བསྐུར་བར་མཐོང་བ་དང་། རས་གཅིག་མི་བཅྭ་བརྒྱད་ཀྱིས་དྲས་ཀྱང་མ་རལ་བ་དང་། སྐྱེ་བོའི་ཚོགས་ཆེན་པོ་གཅིག་ཏུ་འདུས་ནས་འཐབ་པ་དང་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>As he recalled, ‘I dreamed of a king of elephants who, emerging from a window, was caught by its thin tail; I dreamed of hastening to a well when no longer thirsty; I saw the sale of a measure of pearls for a measure of flour; I saw sandalwood and ordinary wood being given equal value; I saw thieves stealing sumptuous fruits from a garden; I saw an elephant calf scaring a rutting elephant; I saw a dirty monkey smearing others with filth; I saw a monkey who was consecrated as king; I saw a piece of cloth not being torn though it was pulled by eighteen men; and I saw a great crowd of people assembled together who passed the time quarreling, arguing, fighting, and criticizing one another.’</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-157">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-198</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྩོད་པ་དང་གཡུལ་འགྱེད་པ་དང་མཚང་འདྲུ་བར་གྱུར་པས་འཇིགས་པ་མཐོང་ངོ་། །དེ་ནས་རྒྱལ་པོ་དེ་སད་པ་དང་འཇིགས་ཤིང་སྐྲག་ལ་སྐྱོ་བས་ངའི་འཚོ་བའི་སྲོག་གི་བར་ཆད་དུ་གྱུར་པའམ། རྒྱལ་སྲིད་ལས་ཉམས་པར་མི་འགྱུར་རམ་སྙམ་སྟེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-075-004-198"/>“Then the king awoke, distraught with fear and apprehension, thinking, ‘Has my life been threatened, or am I to fall from power?’</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-158">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-198</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེས་བྲམ་ཟེ་རྨི་ལྟས་ཀྱི་མཚན་མ་སྟོན་ཤེས་པ་རྣམས་བསྡུས་ནས་དེ་རྣམས་ལ་རྨི་ལམ་དེ་རྣམས་སྨྲས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>So he gathered some brahmins who were learned in the interpretation of dream signs, and he described his dreams to them.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-159">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-199</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་རྣམས་ཀྱང་གསེར་ཕྲེང་ཅན་ལ་ཞེ་སྡང་བ་ཡིན་པས་དེ་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་སྨྲས་པ། ལྷ་ཁྱེད་ལ་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱི་ནང་ན་ཐུགས་སུ་བྱོན་པ་དེའི་སྙིང་དང་མེ་ལ་སྦྱིན་སྲེག་གི་མཆོད་སྦྱིན་མཛོད་ཅིག །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-075-004-199"/>“However, because the brahmins despised Kāñcanamālā, they said, ‘Your Majesty, you must make a sacrificial offering to the fire with the heart of the one who is most dear to you of all.’</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-160">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-200</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་རྒྱལ་པོ་དེ་ཡི་མུག་པས་བསམས་པ། ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱི་ནང་ན་ང་ལ་སྡུག་པ་ནི་ངའི་གསེར་ཕྲེང་ཅན་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-075-004-200"/>“In despair, the king thought, ‘The one who is to me the sweetest of all is my Kāñcanamālā!’</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-161">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-201</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གསེར་ཕྲེང་ཅན་གྱིས་དེ་ཐོས་པ་དང་། དེ་ཡང་མཁས་པ་ཡིན་པས་རྒྱལ་པོ་དེའི་གན་དུ་སོང་སྟེ་ཕྱིན་ནས་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-075-004-201"/>“Kāñcanamālā heard about this, and since she was learned, she approached the king.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-162">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-201</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལྷ་ཉི་མ་ཤར་ན་སྒྲོན་མ་མེའི་འོད་དགོས་པ་ཅི་མཆིས།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>‘Your Majesty, when the sun is shining, what need is there for the flame of a lamp?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-163">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-201</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་སངས་རྒྱས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་འོད་སྲུང་འདི་དྲང་སྲོང་སྨྲ་བ་རི་དགས་རྒྱུ་བ་ན་བཞུགས་ཏེ་དེར་གཤེགས་ལ་ཞུས་ཤིག་དང་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The perfectly complete Buddha, the blessed Kāśyapa, is dwelling at the Ṛṣivadana in Deer Park—you should go there and ask him.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-164">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-201</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་དེས་ཁྱེད་ལ་ཇི་ལྟར་ལུང་བསྟན་པ་དེ་བཞིན་དུ་ཁྱེད་ཀྱིས་ཟུང་ཤིག །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>That blessed one will give you an accurate prophecy, to which you should adhere.’</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-165">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-202</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་རྒྱལ་པོ་ཀྲྀ་ཀཱིས་གྲོང་ཁྱེར་བཱ་རཱ་ཎ་སཱིར་ང་དེང་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་དེའི་དྲུང་དུ་འགྲོའོ་ཞེས་དྲིལ་ཆེན་པོ་བསྒྲགས་ནས་དེ་འཁོར་བརྒྱ་སྟོང་དུ་མ་དང་། གསེར་ཕྲེང་ཅན་དེ་དང་ཐབས་ཅིག་ཏུ་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་གང་ན་བ་དེར་སོང་སྟེ་ཕྱིན་ནས།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-075-004-202"/>“Then King Kṛkin sounded a great gong and announced, ‘Now I will go to the city of Vārāṇasī, to the presence of that blessed one,’ and together with Kāñcanamālā and a retinue of many hundreds of thousands, he went to where the Blessed One was.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-166">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-202</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱི་ཞབས་གཉིས་ལ་མགོ་<tei:ref folio="F.297.a"/>བོས་ཕྱག་བྱས་ཏེ་ཆོས་མཉན་པའི་ཕྱིར་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱི་སྤྱན་སྔར་འདུག་གོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>There, they bowed their heads to the feet of the Blessed One and sat before the Blessed One in order to listen to the Dharma.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-167">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-203</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཇི་སྲིད་ཅིག་ན་རྒྱལ་པོ་ཀྲྀ་ཀཱི་སྟན་ལས་ལངས་ཏེ་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་གང་ན་བ་དེར་ཐལ་མོ་སྦྱར་བ་བཏུད་ནས།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-075-004-203"/>“After some time, King Kṛkin rose from his seat and approached the Blessed One.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-168">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-203</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ལ་འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་གསོལ་ཏོ། །བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་འདིར་དགུང་གཅིག་ལ་བདག་གིས་རྨི་ལམ་བཅུ་ཁུམས་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He bowed with his hands folded and told the Blessed One, ‘O Blessed One, in a single night I witnessed ten dreams.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-169">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-203</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གླང་པོ་ཆེ་སྐར་ཁུང་ནས་བྱུང་བ་ན། དེའི་མཇུག་མ་ཐོགས་པ་ལ་སོགས་པ་སྔ་མ་བཞིན་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>An elephant, emerging from a window, was caught by its tail…’ and so forth as before.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-170">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-203</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་རྨི་ལམ་དེའི་འབྲས་བུ་འདིར་བདག་ལ་ལུང་བསྟན་དུ་གསོལ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>‘Please, Blessed One, tell me the portent of these dreams.’</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-171">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-205</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་བཀའ་སྩལ་པ། རྒྱལ་པོ་ཆེན་པོ་མ་འཇིགས་ཤིག །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-075-004-205"/>“The Blessed One replied, ‘Be not afraid, Great King.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-172">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-205</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཁྱོད་ཀྱི་ཡུལ་འཁོར་ཉམས་པར་མི་འགྱུར་ལ། སྲོག་གི་བར་ཆད་དུ་ཡང་མི་འགྱུར་གྱིས།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Your kingdom will not decline, and your life is not in danger.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-173">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-205</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྒྱལ་པོ་ཆེན་པོ་གཞན་དུ་ན་མ་འོངས་པའི་ཚེ་སྐྱེ་དགུའི་ཚེ་ལོ་བརྒྱ་ཐུབ་པ་ན་ཤཱཀྱ་ཐུབ་པ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་སངས་རྒྱས་འབྱུང་སྟེ། དེའི་ཕྱི་མའི་དུས་ན་ཉན་ཐོས་རྣམས་ལུས་མ་བསྡམས་པ། སེམས་མ་བསྡམས་པ། ཚུལ་ཁྲིམས་མ་བསྡམས་པ། ཤེས་རབ་མ་བསྡམས་པ་འབྱུང་བར་འགྱུར་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>On the contrary, Great King, in the future, when the lifespan of humans is one hundred years, a perfectly complete buddha known as Śākyamuni will appear, and in the latter part of that time there will emerge śrāvakas whose bodies are unrestrained, whose minds are unrestrained, whose moral discipline is unrestrained, and whose wisdom is unrestrained.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-174">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-205</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་རྣམས་གཉེན་གྱི་ཚོགས་སྤངས་ནས་རབ་ཏུ་འབྱུང་བར་འགྱུར་ཏེ། དེ་ནས་གཙུག་ལག་ཁང་རྣམས་སུ་ཁྱིམ་གྱི་འདུ་ཤེས་འཇོག་པས་ཆགས་པར་འགྱུར་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They will abandon their kin and become renunciants, yet by engaging the notion of the household while in monasteries, they will still be attached.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-175">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-205</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གླང་པོ་ཆེ་སྐར་ཁུང་ནས་བྱུང་བ་ན་དེའི་མཇུག་མ་ཐོགས་པ་ནི་དེའི་སྔ་ལྟས་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The elephant being caught by its tail when emerging from a window is a premonition of that.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-176">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-206</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྒྱལ་པོ་ཆེན་པོ་ཁྱོད་ཀྱིས་སྐོམ་པའི་ཕྱི་ནས་ཁྲོན་པ་སྙེགས་པར་རྨི་ལམ་དུ་མཐོང་བ་གང་ཡིན་པ་དེ་ནི་དེ་རྣམས་གཙུག་ལག་ཁང་གི་ནང་ན་ལྷན་ཅིག་གནས་པ་རྣམས་ལ་ཆོས་སྟོན་པར་འགྱུར་ཡང་དེ་རྣམས་ཉན་པར་འདོད་པར་མི་བྱེད་ཅིང་ཡིད་ལ་མི་འཇོག་སྟེ། དེའི་སྔ་ལྟས་ནི་འདི་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-075-004-206"/>“ ‘Great King, your dream of hastening to a well when no longer thirsty is a premonition that although the Dharma will be taught to those who assemble together in a monastery, they will not desire to listen, nor will they keep those teachings in mind.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-177">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-207</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྒྱལ་པོ་ཆེན་པོ་ཁྱོད་ཀྱིས་ཕྱེ་བྲེ་གང་དང་མུ་ཏིག་བྲེ་གང་ཚོང་བྱེད་པར་རྨི་ལམ་དུ་མཐོང་བ་གང་ཡིན་པ་དེ་ནི་དེ་ཉིད་ཀྱི་ཉན་ཐོས་རྣམས་ཏེ། གང་བཟའ་བ་ཙམ་གྱི་དོན་དུ་དབང་པོ་དང་སྟོབས་དང་བྱང་ཆུབ་ཀྱི་ཡན་ལག་རིན་པོ་ཆེ་རྣམས་ཡང་དག་པར་སྟོན་པར་འབྱུང་བར་འགྱུར་ཏེ་དེའི་སྔ་ལྟས་ནི་འདི་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-075-004-207"/>“ ‘Great King, your dream of the sale of a measure of pearls for a measure of flour is a premonition that there will emerge śrāvakas who will correctly teach the faculties, powers, and precious branches of awakening merely for the sake of food.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-178">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-208</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྒྱལ་པོ་ཆེན་པོ་ཁྱོད་ཀྱིས་ཙན་དན་དང་ཤིང་མཉམ་པོར་ཚོང་བྱེད་པར་རྨི་ལམ་དུ་མཐོང་བ་གང་ཡིན་པ་དེ་ནི་དེ་ཉིད་ཀྱི་ཉན་ཐོས་རྣམས་མུ་སྟེགས་ཀྱི་ཚིག་གང་ཡིན་པ་རྣམས་བཟུང་ནས་སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱི་བཀའ་དང་སྙོམས་པ་འབྱུང་བར་འགྱུར་ཏེ་དེའི་སྔ་ལྟས་ནི་འདི་ཡིན་ནོ། །རྒྱལ་པོ་ཆེན་པོ་ཁྱོད་ཀྱིས་ཀུན་དགའ་ར་བ་འབྲས་བུ་ཕུན་སུམ་ཚོགས་པ་མ་བྱིན་པར་ལེན་པ་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་ཕྲོགས་པར་རྨི་ལམ་དུ་མཐོང་བ་གང་ཡིན་པ་དེ་ནི་དེ་ཉིད་<tei:ref folio="F.297.b"/>ཀྱི་ཉན་ཐོས་ལུས་མ་བསྡམས་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-075-004-208"/>“ ‘Great King, your dream of sandalwood and ordinary wood being given equal value is a premonition that there will emerge śrāvakas who, apprehending the words of non-Buddhists, will equate them with the words of the Buddha.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-179">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-209</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སེམས་མ་བསྡམས་པ། ཚུལ་ཁྲིམས་མ་བསྡམས་པ། ཤེས་རབ་མ་བསྡམས་པ་རྣམས་འབྱུང་བར་འགྱུར་ཏེ། དེ་རྣམས་དགེ་འདུན་རྣམས་ཀྱི་མེ་ཏོག་གི་མཆོག་དང་། འབྲས་བུའི་མཆོག་རྣམས་འཚོ་བའི་ཕྱིར་དགེ་འདུན་ལས་བཅད་ནས་ཁྱིམ་པ་རྣམས་ལ་སྟེར་བར་འགྱུར་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-075-004-209"/>“ ‘Great King, your dream of thieves stealing sumptuous fruits from a garden is a premonition that there will emerge śrāvakas whose bodies are unrestrained, whose minds are unrestrained, whose moral discipline is unrestrained, and whose wisdom is unrestrained, and that they will take the best flowers and fruits of the saṅgha and give them to householders for the purpose of their livelihood.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-180">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-210</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེའི་སྔ་ལྟས་ནི་འདི་ཡིན་ནོ། །རྒྱལ་པོ་ཆེན་པོ་ཁྱོད་ཀྱིས་གླང་པོ་ཕྲུ་གུས་སྤོས་ཀྱི་གླང་པོ་འཇིགས་པར་བྱེད་པར་རྨི་ལམ་དུ་མཐོང་བ་གང་ཡིན་པ་འདི་ནི་དེ་ཉིད་ཀྱི་ཉན་ཐོས་རྣམས་ཚུལ་ཁྲིམས་འཆལ་བ། སྡིག་པའི་ཆོས་ཅན་དེ་རྣམས་གང་དགེ་སློང་ཚུལ་ཁྲིམས་དང་ལྡན་པ། དགེ་བའི་ཆོས་ཅན་རྣམས་ཟིལ་གྱིས་གནོན་པར་བྱེད་པར་འགྱུར་ཏེ་དེའི་སྔ་ལྟས་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-075-004-210"/>“ ‘Great King, your dream of an elephant calf scaring a rutting elephant is a premonition that śrāvakas who have faulty moral discipline and are possessed of sinful propensities will overpower monks who possess moral discipline and virtuous propensities.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-181">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-211</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྒྱལ་པོ་ཆེན་པོ་ཁྱོད་ཀྱིས་སྤྲེའུ་མི་གཙང་བས་གོས་པས་གཞན་ལ་སྐུད་པར་རྨི་ལམ་དུ་མཐོང་བ་གང་ཡིན་པ་འདི་ནི་དེ་ཉིད་ཀྱི་ཉན་ཐོས་ཚུལ་ཁྲིམས་འཆལ་བ། སྡིག་པའི་ཆོས་ཅན་རྣམས་འབྱུང་བར་འགྱུར་ཏེ། དེ་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་ཚུལ་ཁྲིམས་དང་ལྡན་པ་རྣམས་ལ་སྐུར་པ་འདེབས་པར་འགྱུར་ཏེ་དེའི་སྔ་ལྟས་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-075-004-211"/>“ ‘Great King, your dream of a dirty monkey smearing others with filth is a premonition that there will emerge śrāvakas who have faulty moral discipline and are possessed of sinful propensities and that they will deprecate those who possess moral discipline.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-182">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-212</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྒྱལ་པོ་ཆེན་པོ་ཁྱོད་ཀྱིས་སྤྲེའུ་རྒྱལ་པོར་དབང་བསྐུར་བར་མཐོང་བ་གང་ཡིན་པ་དེ་ནི་དུས་དེའི་ཚེ་རྨོངས་པ་རྣམས་རྒྱལ་པོར་དབང་བསྐུར་བར་འགྱུར་ཏེ་དེའི་སྔ་ལྟས་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-075-004-212"/>“ ‘Great King, your dream of a monkey who was consecrated as king is a premonition that at that time deluded ones will be consecrated as kings.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-183">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-213</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྒྱལ་པོ་ཆེན་པོ་ཁྱོད་ཀྱིས་རས་གཅིག་མི་བཅྭ་བརྒྱད་ཀྱིས་དྲས་ཀྱང་མ་རལ་བར་རྨི་ལམ་དུ་མཐོང་བ་གང་ཡིན་པ་དེ་ནི་དེ་ཉིད་ཀྱི་བསྟན་པ་སྡེ་བཅྭ་བརྒྱད་དུ་གྱེས་པར་གྱུར་ཀྱང་རྣམ་པར་གྲོལ་བའི་རས་ནི་རལ་བར་བྱ་བར་མི་ནུས་ཏེ་དེའི་སྔ་ལྟས་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-075-004-213"/>“ ‘Great King, your dream of a piece of cloth not being torn though it was pulled by eighteen men is a premonition that although the teaching on reality will be split into eighteen factions, the cloth of liberation cannot be torn.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-184">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-215</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྒྱལ་པོ་ཆེན་པོ་ཁྱོད་ཀྱིས་སྐྱེ་བོའི་ཚོགས་ཆེན་པོ་གཅིག་ཏུ་འདུས་ནས་འཐབ་པ་དང་རྩོད་པ་དང་གཡུལ་འགྱེད་པ་དང་། མཚང་འདྲུ་བར་རྨི་ལམ་དུ་མཐོང་བ་གང་ཡིན་པ་དེ་ནི་དེ་ཉིད་ཀྱི་བསྟན་པ་རྩོད་པས་ནུབ་པར་འགྱུར་ཏེ་དེའི་སྔ་ལྟས་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-075-004-215"/>“ ‘Great King, your dream of a great crowd of people assembled together quarreling, arguing, fighting, and criticizing one another other is a premonition that the teaching on reality will fade away through dispute.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-185">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-216</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྒྱལ་པོ་ཆེན་པོ་དེ་ལྟར་མི་བཟད་པ་རྣམས་མ་འོངས་པའི་དུས་ན་འབྱུང་བར་འགྱུར་རོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-075-004-216"/>“ ‘Great King, such unbearable things will come to pass in the future.’</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-186">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-216</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་བཀའ་སྩལ་པ། གང་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་སངས་རྒྱས་འོད་སྲུང་ལའང་རྒྱལ་པོ་ཀྲྀ་ཀཱི་དང་། གསེར་ཕྲེང་ཅན་གྱིས་ཐར་པའི་ཆ་དང་འཐུན་པའི་དགེ་བའི་རྩ་བ་རྣམས་བསྐྱེད་པ་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“And with these words, King Kṛkin and Kāñcanamālā generated roots of virtue toward the perfectly and completely awakened Buddha Kāśyapa that made them conducive to liberation.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-187">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-218</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དགེ་སློང་དག་འདི་ཇི་སྙམ་དུ་སེམས།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-075-004-218"/>“Monks, what do you think?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-188">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-218</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེའི་ཚེ་ན་གསེར་ཕྲེང་ཅན་གང་ཡིན་པ་དེ་ནི་མ་ག་དྷཱ་བཟང་མོ་འདི་ཉིད་ཡིན་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The one known at that time as Kāñcanamālā was this Sumāgadhā herself.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-189">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-218</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེའི་ཚེ་ཡང་འདིས་<tei:ref folio="F.298.a"/>སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱི་བྱ་བ་བྱས་ཏེ། ད་ལྟར་ཡང་འདི་འོངས་ནས་སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱི་བྱ་བ་བྱས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>At that time she performed buddha activity, and likewise she has come here and once again performed buddha activity.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-190">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-219</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡང་དགེ་སློང་རྣམས་ཐེ་ཙོམ་སྐྱེས་ནས། སངས་རྒྱས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ལ་ཞུས་པ། བཙུན་པ་གསེར་ཕྲེང་ཅན་གྱིས་ལས་ཅི་ཞིག་བགྱིས་ན་གསེར་གྱི་ཕྲེང་བ་བཏགས་པར་སྐྱེས།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-075-004-219"/>Then the monks, with doubts arising, inquired of the blessed Buddha, “Reverend One, due to what former action was Kāñcanamālā born tied with a golden garland?”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-191">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-220</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་བཀའ་སྩལ་པ། དགེ་སློང་དག་འདི་ཉིད་ཀྱིས་ལས་བྱས་པ་ཡོད་དེ། སྔོན་བྱུང་བ་ན་ཞིང་པ་གཞན་ཞིག་གི་ཆུང་མར་གྱུར་ཏེ། རང་སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱི་མཆོད་རྟེན་ལ་ཁ་དོག་སྣ་ཚོགས་པའི་མེ་ཏོག་རྣམས་ཀྱི་ཕྲེང་བ་བྱས་ནས་བཏགས་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-075-004-220"/>The Blessed One replied, “Monks, it was due to this action: Long ago, the wife of some farmer or other made garlands of variously colored flowers and tied them up at the caitya of a pratyekabuddha.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-192">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-220</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལས་དེའི་རྣམ་པར་སྨིན་པས་གསེར་གྱི་ཕྲེང་བ་བཏགས་པར་སྐྱེས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>By the ripening of that action, she was born tied with a golden garland.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-193">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-220</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་བས་ན་དགེ་སློང་དག་ལས་གཅིག་ཏུ་གནག་པ་རྣམས་ཀྱི་རྣམ་པར་སྨིན་པ་ནི་གཅིག་ཏུ་གནག་པ་ཡིན་ལ། གཅིག་ཏུ་དཀར་བ་རྣམས་ཀྱི་རྣམ་པར་སྨིན་པ་ནི་གཅིག་ཏུ་དཀར་བ་ཡིན་ཏེ། འདྲེན་མ་རྣམས་ཀྱི་རྣམ་པར་སྨིན་པ་ནི་འདྲེན་མའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Therefore, monks, the ripening of purely dark actions is purely dark, the ripening of those that are purely white is purely white, and the ripening of those that are mixed is mixed.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-194">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-220</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དགེ་སློང་དག་དེ་བས་ན་ལས་གཅིག་ཏུ་གནག་པ་རྣམས་དང་འདྲེན་མ་རྣམས་ནི་སྤངས་ལ། ལས་གཅིག་ཏུ་དཀར་བ་རྣམས་ལ་མངོན་པར་བརྩོན་པར་བྱ་སྟེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Therefore, monks, you should abandon purely dark and mixed actions and exert yourselves in purely white actions.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-195">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-220</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དགེ་སློང་དག་ཁྱེད་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་དེ་ལྟར་བསླབ་པར་བྱའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Monks, you should train in this way.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-196">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-221</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་དེ་སྐད་ཅེས་བཀའ་སྩལ་པ་དང་། དགེ་སློང་རྣམས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་གསུངས་པ་ལ་མངོན་པར་བསྟོད་དོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-075-004-221"/>Thus spoke the Blessed One, and the monks thoroughly praised the words of the Blessed One.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-197">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-222</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མ་ག་དྷཱ་བཟང་མོའི་རྟོགས་པ་བརྗོད་པ་རྫོགས་སོ།། །།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-075-004-222"/>This completes “The Exemplary Tale of Sumāgadhā.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-075-004-TU-198">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-075-004-223</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྒྱ་གར་གྱི་མཁན་པོ་དྷརྨ་ཤྲཱི་བྷ་དྲ་དང་། ཞུ་ཆེན་གྱི་ལོཙྪ་བ་དགེ་སློང་ཚུལ་ཁྲིམས་ཡོན་ཏན་གྱིས་བསྒྱུར་ཏེ། སྒྲ་སྒྱུར་གྱི་ལོཙྪ་བ་ཆེན་པོ་དགེ་སློང་རིན་ཆེན་བཟང་པོས་བཅོས་ཏེ་གཏན་ལ་ཕབ་པ།​། །​།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-075-004-223"/>Translated by the Indian preceptor Dharmaśrībhadra and the senior editor and translator, the monk Tsültrim Yönten. Corrected and finalized by the great translator, the monk Rinchen Sangpo.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>


</body>
</tmx>