<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tmx xmlns="http://www.lisa.org/tmx14" xmlns:eft="http://read.84000.co/ns/1.0" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<header creationtool="tibetan-aligner/84000" datatype="PlainText" segtype="block" adminlang="en-us" srclang="bo" o-tmf="TEI" eft:text-id="UT22084-083-015" eft:text-version="v-1.0.1-2023"/>
<body>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-1">
    <prop type="location-id">translation</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>
                    <tei:ref folio="F.134.b"/>༄༅༅། །རྒྱ་གར་སྐད་དུ། སརྦ་ཏ་ཐཱ་ག་ཏ་ཀཱ་ཡ་ཝཱཀྩིཏྟི་ཀྲྀཥྞ་ཡ་མཱ་རི་ནཱ་མ་ཏནྟྲ། བོད་སྐད་དུ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg/>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-2">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-85</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱི་སྐུ་གསུང་ཐུགས་གཤིན་རྗེ་གཤེད་ནག་པོ་ཞེས་བྱ་བའི་རྒྱུད། འཕགས་པ་འཇམ་དཔལ་གཤིན་རྗེའི་གཤེད་ལ་ཕྱག་འཚལ་ལོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-translation"/>The Tantra of Black Yamāri, the Body, Speech, and Mind of all Tathāgatas<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-85"/> Homage to Mañjuśrī-Yamāri!</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-3">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-88</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདི་སྐད་བདག་གིས་ཐོས་པ་དུས་གཅིག་ན།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-section-1-1"/>Chapter 1: The Practice Sequence<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-88"/> Thus did I hear at one time.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-4">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-88</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱི་སྐུ་དང་གསུང་དང་ཐུགས་རྡོ་རྗེའི་བཙུན་མོ་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱི་བྷ་ག་རྣམས་ལ་བཞུགས་ཏེ། གཏི་མུག་རྡོ་རྗེ་གཤིན་རྗེའི་གཤེད་དང་། ཕྲ་མོ་རྡོ་རྗེ་གཤིན་རྗེའི་གཤེད་དང་། འདོད་ཆགས་རྡོ་རྗེ་གཤིན་རྗེའི་གཤེད་དང་། ཕྲག་དོག་རྡོ་རྗེ་གཤིན་རྗེའི་གཤེད་དང་། ཞེ་སྡང་རྡོ་རྗེ་གཤིན་རྗེའི་གཤེད་དང་། ཐོ་བ་གཤིན་རྗེའི་གཤེད་དང་། དབྱུག་པ་གཤིན་རྗེའི་གཤེད་དང་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The Bhagavat was dwelling in the bhagas of all vajra women, who are the essence of the body, speech, and mind of all tathāgatas.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-5">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-88</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>པདྨ་གཤིན་རྗེའི་གཤེད་དང་། རལ་གྲི་གཤིན་རྗེའི་གཤེད་དང་། མཚམས་རྣམས་སུ་རྡོ་རྗེ་ཙ་རྩི་ཀཱ་དང་། རྡོ་རྗེ་ཕག་མོ་དང་། རྡོ་རྗེ་དབྱངས་ཅན་མ་དང་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He was there with Yamāri’s large assembly, which included Yamāri Mohavajra, Yamāri Piśunavajra, Yamāri Rāgavajra, Yamāri Īrṣyāvajra, Yamāri Dveṣavajra, Mudgara Yamāri, Daṇḍa Yamāri, Padma Yamāri, Khaḍga Yamāri, and, standing in the four intermediate directions, Vajracarcikā, Vajravārāhī, Vajrasarasvatī, and Vajragaurī.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-6">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-88</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྡོ་རྗེ་གཽ་རཱི་མ་རྣམས་མཚམས་སུའོ། །དེ་དག་ལ་སོགས་ཏེ་གཤིན་རྗེའི་གཤེད་ཀྱི་ཚོགས་ཆེན་པོ་དང་། ཐབས་ཅིག་ཏུ་བཞུགས་སོ། །དེ་ནས་ཕྱག་ན་རྡོ་རྗེས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་རྡོ་རྗེ་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱི་བདག་པོ་ལ་གསོལ་བ་བཏབ་པ་དང་། དེ་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱི་བདག་པོས་བདུད་ཐམས་ཅད་རྣམ་པར་འཇོམས་པའི་རྡོ་རྗེ་ཞེས་བྱ་བའི་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་འདི་ཉིད་ཀྱི་སྐུ་གསུང་ཐུགས་རྡོ་རྗེ་ལས་ངེས་པར་བཏོན་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Then, Vajrapāṇi supplicated the Bhagavat, the vajra-being, the lord of all tathāgatas, prompting the Bhagavat, the lord of all tathāgatas, to emerge from the meditative absorption called the vajra that conquers all māras, the state of his own vajra body, speech, and mind.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-7">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-91</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཟླ་བ་རྡོ་རྗེ་སྦྱོར་བ་ཡིས། །གཤིན་རྗེ་མཐར་བྱེད་བསྒོམ་པར་བྱ། །བདུད་རྣམས་ཞི་བར་བྱ་ཕྱིར་དང་། །ཞེ་སྡང་ཐམས་ཅད་བསལ་བའི་ཕྱིར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-91"/>“In order to pacify the māras And eliminate all hatred, One should visualize Yama’s Slayer By uniting the vajra and the moon.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-8">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-92</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འོད་ཟེར་ལྔ་ཡིས་འཁྲིགས་པ་ཡིས། །རྡོ་རྗེ་བསྲུང་བའི་དོན་དུ་བསྒོམ། །ཕྱི་མཚམས་རྡོ་རྗེ་ས་གཞི་དང་། །ར་བ་དྲ་བ་དེ་བཞིན་ནོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-92"/>“For protection, one should visualize a vajra Enveloped by five-colored rays of light And likewise the outer boundary, the vajra ground, The walls, and the canopy.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-9">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-94</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་སྐྱེད་པ་པོ་བདུད་འདུལ་བ་ཞེས་བྱ་བའི་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་ལ་སྙོམས་པར་ཞུགས་ནས་གཏི་མུག་རྡོ་རྗེ་གཤིན་རྗེའི་གཤེད་ལ་སོགས་པ་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱི་ས་བོན་འདི་ཉིད་ཀྱི་སྐུ་གསུང་ཐུགས་རྡོ་རྗེ་རྣམས་ལ་ངེས་པར་ཕྱུང་བ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-94"/>Then the Bhagavat, the father of tathāgatas, entered the meditative absorption known as the tamer of māras and emitted the seed-syllables of all the deities beginning with Yamāri Mohavajra from his own vajra body, speech, and mind.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-10">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-94</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དབུས་སུ་ཡ་དང་ཀྵེ་མ་མེད་ཡཙྪ་ནི་རཱ་ཛཱ་ས་དོ་རུ་ཎ་ཡོ་ནི་རའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>In the center is ya, and then kṣe, ma, me, da, ya, ca,ni, rā, jā, sa, do, ru, ṇa, yo, ni, and ra.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-11">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-98</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡ་སོགས་ཡི་གེ་དང་པོ་ལས། །གཤིན་རྗེའི་གཤེད་དུ་གྱུར་པ་ཡིན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-98"/>“The first among the syllables ya and the rest becomes Yama’s Slayer.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-12">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-98</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡི་གེ་ཀྵེ་ནི་གཏི་<tei:ref folio="F.135.a"/>མུག་བརྗོད། །ཡི་གེ་མ་ནི་ཕྲ་མར་གསུངས། །ཡི་གེ་མེ་ནི་འདོད་ཆགས་ཉིད། །ཡི་གེ་ད་ནི་ཕྲག་དོག་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The syllable kṣe expresses Moha, The syllable ma describes Piśuna, The syllable me becomes Rāga, And the syllable da is Īrṣyā.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-13">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-98</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཤིན་རྗེའི་གཤེད་སོགས་ལྔ་རུ་གྲགས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>These are known as the five Yamāris.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-14">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-102</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡི་གེ་ཡ་ལས་ཐོ་བར་འགྱུར། །ཡི་གེ་ཙྪ་ལས་དབྱུག་པའི་གཙོ། །ལག་ན་པདྨ་ནི་ཡིག་ལས། །ལག་ན་རལ་གྲི་རཱ་ལས་ཡིན། །ཛ་ལས་ཙརྩི་ཀཱ་ཞེས་བརྗོད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-102"/>“The syllable ya becomes Mudgara, From the syllable ca comes lord Daṇḍa, Padmapāṇi comes from the syllable ni, And Khaḍgapāṇi comes from the syllable rā.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-15">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-103</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡི་གེ་ས་ལས་ཕག་གདོང་མ། །ཡི་གེ་དོ་ལས་དབྱངས་ཅན་བསྒྲགས། །ཡི་གེ་རུ་ལས་གཽ་རཱི་དྲན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-103"/>“The syllable ja expresses Carcikā, From sa comes Vārāhī, Do is declared to be Sarasvatī, And ru recalls Gaurī.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-16">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-105</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཎ་ཡོ་ནི་ར་མཚམས་ཀྱི་བཞི། །ཐོད་པ་བཞི་རུ་འདོད་པ་ཡིན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-105"/>“Ṇa, yo, ni, ra, in the four corners Are held to be four skulls.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-17">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-105</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྣ་ཚོགས་རྡོ་རྗེ་འཇིགས་རུང་བ། །ནམ་མཁའ་རྡོ་རྗེའི་དཀྱིལ་དུ་བསམ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>A terrifying crossed vajra Should be imagined in the middle of the sky-vajra.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-18">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-106</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་དཀྱིལ་བཞུགས་པ་གཤིན་རྗེའི་གཤེད། །གནག་ཅིང་འབར་བ་བསྒོམ་པར་བྱ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-106"/>“One should visualize Yamāri, black and blazing, Standing in its center.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-19">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-106</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཤར་དུ་གཏི་མུག་རྡོ་རྗེ་སྟེ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>In the east is Mohavajra And, likewise, Piśuna is in the south.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-20">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-109</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལྷོ་རུ་དེ་བཞིན་ཕྲ་མ་ཡིན། །ནུབ་ཏུ་འདོད་ཆགས་རྡོ་རྗེ་སྟེ། །དེ་བཞིན་བྱང་དུ་ཕྲག་དོག་གོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-109"/>“Rāgavajra is in the west And, likewise, Īrṣyā is in the north.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-21">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-109</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མཚམས་ཀྱི་རྡོ་རྗེ་རྩེ་བཞི་ལ། །ཙརྩི་ཀཱ་སོགས་རྣམ་པར་བསྒོམ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>One should visualize Carcikā and the others On the four prongs of the vajra in the corners.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-22">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-110</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྒོ་ཡི་རྡོ་རྗེ་རྩེ་བཞི་ལ། །ཐོ་བ་ལ་སོགས་རྣམ་པར་བསྒོམ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-110"/>“On the four prongs of the vajra in the doors One should visualize Muḍgara and the rest.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-23">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-110</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྣ་ཚོགས་རྡོ་རྗེའི་མཚམས་བཞི་རུ། །མི་ཡི་མགོ་བོ་བཞི་དག་གོ། །དེ་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱི་བདག་པོས་གཤིན་རྗེའི་གཤེད་པོ་རྡོ་རྗེ་ཞེས་བྱ་བའི་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་ལ་སྙོམས་པར་ཞུགས་ནས་ཞེ་སྡང་ཆེན་པོའི་རིགས་ཀྱི་སྔགས་གསུངས་པ། ཨོཾ་ཧྲཱིཿཥྚྲཱིཿཝི་ཀྲྀཏཱ་ནན་ཧཱུྃ་ཧཱུྃ་ཕཊ་ཕཊ་སྭཱ་ཧཱ། དེ་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱི་བདག་པོས་གཏི་མུག་རྡོ་རྗེ་ཆེན་པོའི་སྔས་གསུངས་པ། ཨོཾ་ཛི་ནི་ཛཱི་ཀ །དེ་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱི་བདག་པོས་ཕྲ་མ་རྡོ་རྗེའི་སྔགས་གསུངས་པ། ཨོཾ་རནྟ་དྷྲཱྀཀ །དེ་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱི་བདག་པོས་འདོད་ཆགས་རྡོ་རྗེའི་སྔགས་གསུངས་པ། ཨོཾ་ཨཱ་རོ་ལཱི་ཀ །དེ་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱི་བདག་པོས་ཕྲག་དོག་རྡོ་རྗེའི་སྔགས་གསུངས་པ། ཨོཾ་པྲཛྙཱདྷྲཱྀཀ །དེ་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱི་བདག་པོས་རྡོ་རྗེ་ཐོ་བའི་སྔགས་གསུངས་པ། ཨོྃ་མུཌྒ་ར་དྷྲཱྀཀ །དེ་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱི་<tei:ref folio="F.135.b"/>བདག་པོས་རྡོ་རྗེ་དབྱུག་པའི་སྔགས་གསུངས་པ། ཨོཾ་དཎྜ་དྷྲཱྀཀ །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>In the four corners of the crossed vajra Are four human heads.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-24">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-111</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱི་བདག་པོས་རྡོ་རྗེ་པདྨའི་སྔགས་གསུངས་པ། ཨོཾ་པདྨ་དྷྲཱྀཀ །དེ་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱི་བདག་པོས་རྡོ་རྗེ་རལ་གྲིའི་སྔགས་གསུངས་པ། ཨོཾ་ཁཌྒ་དྷྲཱྀཀ །དེ་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱི་བདག་པོས་རྡོ་རྗེ་ཙརྩི་ཀཱའི་སྔགས་གསུངས་པ། ཨོཾ་མོ་ཧ་ར་ཏི། དེ་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱི་བདག་པོས་རྡོ་རྗེ་ཕག་མོའི་སྔགས་གསུངས་པ། ཨོཾ་དྭེ་ཥ་ར་ཏི། དེ་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱི་བདག་པོས་རྡོ་རྗེ་དབྱངས་ཅན་མའི་སྔགས་གསུངས་པ། ཨོཾ་རཱ་ག་ར་ཏི། དེ་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱི་བདག་པོས་རྡོ་རྗེ་གཽ་རཱི་མའི་སྔགས་གསུངས་པ། ཨོཾ་བཛྲ་ར་ཏི། དེ་ནས་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱི་བདག་པོས་སྐུ་གསུང་ཐུགས་བྱིན་གྱིས་བརླབ་པའི་སྔགས་གསུངས་པ། ཨོྃ་སརྦ་ཏ་ཐཱ་ག་ཏ་ཀཱ་ཡ་བཛྲ་སྭ་བྷཱ་པ་ཨཱཏྨ་ཀོ྅ཧཾ། ཨོཾ་སརྦ་ཏ་ཐཱ་ག་ཏ་ཝཱཀ་བཛྲ་སྭ་བྷཱ་བ་ཨཱཏྨ་ཀོ྅ཧཾ། ཨོཾ་སརྦ་ཏ་ཐཱ་ག་ཏ་ཙིཏྟ་བཛྲ་སྭ་བྷཱ་བ་ཨཱཏྨ་ཀོ྅ཧཾ། དེ་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱི་བདག་པོས་ཞེ་སྡང་ཆེན་པོའི་སྐུ་ངེས་པར་བསྟན་པ། ཞལ་གསུམ་ཕྱག་དྲུག་ཁྲོས་པ་ལ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-111"/>Then, the Bhagavat, the lord of all tathāgatas, entered the meditative absorption called yamāri vajra and pronounced the mantra of the family of great hatred: oṁ hrīḥ ṣṭrīḥ vikṛtānana hūṁ hūṁ phaṭ phaṭ svāhā |<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-113"/> The Bhagavat, the lord of all tathāgatas, next pronounced the mantra of the great Mohavajra: oṁ jinajīk |<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-115"/> The Bhagavat, the lord of all tathāgatas, next pronounced the mantra of Piśunavajra: oṁ ratnadhṛk |<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-117"/> The Bhagavat, the lord of all tathāgatas, next pronounced the mantra of Rāgavajra: oṁ ārolīk |<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-119"/> The Bhagavat, the lord of all tathāgatas, next pronounced the mantra of Īrṣyāvajra: oṁ prajñādhṝk |<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-121"/> The Bhagavat, the lord of all tathāgatas, next pronounced the mantra of Mudgaravajra: oṁ muḍgaradhṝk |<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-123"/> The Bhagavat, the lord of all tathāgatas, next pronounced the mantra of the Daṇḍavajra: oṁ daṇḍadhṝk |<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-125"/> The Bhagavat, the lord of all tathāgatas, next pronounced the mantra of Padmavajra: oṁ padmadhṝk |<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-127"/> The Bhagavat, the lord of all tathāgatas, next pronounced the mantra of Khaḍgavajra: oṁ khaḍgadhṝk |<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-129"/> The Bhagavat, the lord of all tathāgatas, next pronounced the mantra of Vajracarcikā: oṁ moharati |<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-131"/> The Bhagavat, the lord of all tathāgatas, next pronounced the mantra of Vajravārāhī: oṁ dveṣarati |<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-133"/> The Bhagavat, the lord of all tathāgatas, next pronounced the mantra of Vajrasarasvatī: oṁ rāgarati |<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-135"/> The Bhagavat, the lord of all tathāgatas, next pronounced the mantra of Vajragaurī: oṁ vajrarati |<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-137"/> The Bhagavat, the lord of all tathāgatas, next pronounced the mantra that empowers body, speech, and mind: oṁ sarva­tathāgata­kāyavajra­svabhāvātmako ’haṃ | oṁ sarva­tathāgata­vākvajra­svabhāvātmako ’haṃ | oṁ sarva­tathāgata­citta­vajra­svabhāvātmako ’haṃ |<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-141"/> Then, the Bhagavat, the Lord of all Tathāgatas, described the body of great wrath:<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-143"/> “An adept should visualize Yamāri As wrathful, with three faces and six arms.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-25">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-111</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཨིནྡྲ་ནཱི་ལ་འདྲ་བའི་མདོག །ཕྱག་ན་རྡོ་རྗེ་བསྣམས་པ་ཉིད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He is the color of a sapphire And holds a vajra in his hand.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-26">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-146</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཤིན་རྗེའི་གཤེད་ནི་བསྒོམ་པར་བྱ། །ཞལ་གསུམ་ཕྱག་དྲུག་ཞི་བ་ལ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-146"/>“Mohavajra should be visualized As peaceful, with three faces and six arms.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-27">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-146</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གསལ་བའི་གཟུགས་དང་འདྲ་བའི་འོད། །ཕྱག་ན་འཁོར་ལོ་བསྣམས་པ་ཉིད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He has a luminous, crystal-clear form, And holds a wheel in his hand.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-28">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-148</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཏི་མུག་རྡོ་རྗེ་རྣམ་བསྒོམ་བྱ། །ཞལ་གསུམ་ཕྱག་དྲུག་རྒྱས་གྱུར་པ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-148"/>“Piśunavajra should be visualized As enriching, with three faces and six arms.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-29">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-148</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གསེར་གྱི་རྣམ་པའི་འོད་དང་ལྡན། །ཕྱག་ན་རིན་ཆེན་བསྣམས་པ་ཉིད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He has a luster like that of gold And holds a jewel in his hand.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-30">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-151</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཕྲ་མ་རྡོ་རྗེ་རྣམ་བསྒོམ་བྱ། །ཞལ་གསུམ་ཕྱག་དྲུག་དབང་བྱེད་པ། །པདྨ་རཱ་ག་མཚུངས་པའི་འོད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-151"/>“Rāgavajra should be visualized As enthralling, with three faces and six arms.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-31">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-151</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཕྱག་ན་པདྨ་བསྣམས་པ་ཉིད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He shines like a ruby And holds a lotus in his hand.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-32">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-153</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདོད་ཆགས་རྡོ་རྗེ་རྣམ་བསྒོམ་བྱ། །ཞལ་གསུམ་ཕྱག་དྲུག་ཐམས་ཅད་ལ། །རིན་ཆེན་མ་རྒད་འོད་དང་ལྡན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-153"/>“Īrṣyāvajra should be visualized As universal, with three faces and six arms.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-33">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-153</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཕྱག་ན་ཤུབས་ཅན་བསྣམས་པ་ཉིད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He has a luster like that of an emerald And holds a sheathed sword in his hand.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-34">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-156</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཕྲག་དོག་རྡོ་རྗེ་རྣམ་བསྒོམ་<tei:ref folio="F.136.a"/>བྱ། །དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱི་སྐུ་གསུང་ཐུགས་གཤིན་རྗེའི་གཤེད་ནག་པོའི་རྒྱུད་ལས་མངོན་པར་རྟོགས་པའི་རིམ་པར་ཕྱེ་བ་སྟེ་ལེའུ་དང་པོའོ།། །།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-156"/>This was the first chapter, “The Practice Sequence,” from The Tantra of Black Yamāri, the Body, Speech, and Mind of All Tathāgatas.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-35">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-158</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱིས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་རྡོ་རྗེ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོ་ལ་བསྟོད་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-section-1-2"/>Chapter 2: The Great Maṇḍala<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-158"/> Then, all the blessed tathāgatas praised the blessed great vajra being: <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-159"/>“Homage to you, vajra body.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-36">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-158</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཤིན་རྗེའི་གཤེད་པོ་རབ་འཇིགས་པ། །གཏི་མུག་རྡོ་རྗེའི་ངོ་བོ་ཁྱོད། །སྟོན་པ་སངས་རྒྱས་ཀུན་རང་བཞིན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>You are the fearsome Yamāri, The essence of Mohavajra, The teacher with the nature of all buddhas.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-37">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-161</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྡོ་རྗེ་སྐུ་ལ་ཕྱག་འཚལ་བསྟོད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-161"/>“Homage to you, vajra jewel.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-38">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-161</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཤིན་རྗེའི་གཤེད་པོ་རབ་འཇིགས་པའི། །ཕྲ་མ་རྡོ་རྗེའི་ངོ་བོ་ཁྱོད། །རྡོ་རྗེ་ཐུགས་དང་རབ་མཚུངས་པ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>You are the fearsome Yamāri, The essence of Piśunavajra, Who is equal to the vajra mind.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-39">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-162</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྡོ་རྗེ་རིན་ཆེན་ཕྱག་འཚལ་བསྟོད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-162"/>“Homage to you, vajra speech.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-40">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-162</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདོད་ཆགས་རྡོ་རྗེའི་ངོ་བོ་ཁྱོད། །གཤིན་རྗེའི་གཤེད་པོ་རབ་འཇིགས་པ། །རྡོ་རྗེ་གསུང་དང་རབ་མཚུངས་པ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>You are the fearsome Yamāri, The essence of Rāgavajra, Who is equal to vajra speech.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-41">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-164</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྡོ་རྗེ་གསུང་ལ་ཕྱག་འཚལ་བསྟོད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-164"/>“Homage to you, with sword in hand.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-42">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-164</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཕྲག་དོག་ངོ་བོའི་རང་བཞིན་ཁྱོད། །གཤིན་རྗེའི་གཤེད་པོ་ལས་ཀུན་པ། །རྡོ་རྗེ་ཆགས་དང་རབ་ཏུ་མཚུངས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>You are Yamāri who serves all functions, The essence of Īrṣyāvajra, Who is equal to vajra desire.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-43">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-166</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཕྱག་ན་རལ་གྲི་ཕྱག་འཚལ་བསྟོད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-166"/>“Homage to you, lord of the maṇḍala.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-44">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-166</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སངས་རྒྱས་ཀུན་གྱི་དངོས་པོ་ཁྱོད། །སངས་རྒྱས་ཐམས་ཅད་གཅིག་བསྡུས་པས། །སངས་རྒྱས་ཀུན་མཆོག་གཙོ་བོའི་གཙོ། །དཀྱིལ་འཁོར་གཙོ་ལ་ཕྱག་འཚལ་བསྟོད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>You are the nature of all buddhas, The confluence of all buddhas, The most eminent of all buddhas.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-45">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-167</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྡོ་རྗེ་མིག་དང་། རྡོ་རྗེ་རྣ་བ་དང་། རྡོ་རྗེ་སྣ་དང་། རྡོ་རྗེ་ལྕེ་དང་། རྡོ་རྗེ་ལུས་དང་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-167"/>The Bhagavat then said, “Vajra eyes, vajra ears, vajra nose, vajra tongue, vajra body, and vajra mind.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-46">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-167</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྡོ་རྗེ་ཐུགས་ཞེས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་གསུངས་པ་ནི་མིག་ལ་སོགས་པ་བྱིན་གྱིས་བརླབ་པའི་ཆོ་གའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>This is the rite for empowering the eyes and the other senses.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-47">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-169</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་ཡང་དག་བཤད་བྱ་བ། །འདོད་པའི་དོན་གྲུབ་སྒྲུབ་བྱེད་པའི། །གཤིན་རྗེའི་གཤེད་པོ་ཉིད་མཚུངས་པ། །གཤིན་རྗེའི་འཇིགས་པའི་དཀྱིལ་འཁོར་ལོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-169"/>“Next, I will explain in detail The fearsome maṇḍala of Yamāri, Which appears just like Yamāri And fulfills every purpose.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-48">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-171</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྐུད་པ་གསར་པ་ལེགས་བསྒྲིམས་ལ། །ལེགས་པའི་ཚད་ལ་མཛེས་པ་ཡིས། །སྐུད་པ་བྱས་པས་ཐིག་གདབ་པོ། །གཤིན་རྗེའི་ཚོགས་ཀྱི་དཀྱིལ་འཁོར་ལོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-171"/>“The learned practitioner should tie The maṇḍala of Yamāri’s host With a new, tightly woven thread, One that is well measured and elegant.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-49">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-174</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མཚན་རྣམས་ཐམས་ཅད་རབ་རྫོགས་ཤིང་། །བར་ཆད་ཐམས་ཅད་རབ་ཉམས་པ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-174"/>“All of its features are complete And it eliminates all obstructive forces.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-50">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-174</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཞི་བ་ལ་སོགས་རབ་འཇུག་པའི། །དཀྱིལ་འཁོར་འཁོར་ལོའི་ཆ་བྱད་ལ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>This maṇḍala, shaped as a circle, Is used to pacify and so forth.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-51">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-176</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྩེ་མོ་ལྔ་དང་མཉམ་ལྡན་པའི། །ལས་ཀྱི་རྡོ་རྗེ་དེ་ལ་བྲི། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-176"/>“In that maṇḍala one should draw A karmavajra with five prongs on each end.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-52">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-176</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྡོ་རྗེ་འབར་བ་འཁྲིགས་པ་ཡི། །རྡོ་རྗེ་དེ་ཡི་དབུས་སུ་བྲི། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>A vajra engulfed in a blaze of vajras Should be drawn in its center.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-53">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-179</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རལ་གྲི་བྱང་གི་ཕྱོགས་སུ་བྲི། །འཁོར་ལོའི་འོད་ཀྱིས་བསྐོར་བ་ཡི། །འཁོར་ལོ་ཤར་གྱི་ཕྱོགས་སུ་<tei:ref folio="F.136.b"/>བྲི། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-179"/>“One should draw a sword in the north And in the east a wheel, Engulfed in wheel-shaped light.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-54">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-181</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འོད་ཀྱི་ཕྲེང་བ་མཉམ་འཕྲོ་བའི། །རིན་པོ་ཆེ་ནི་ལྷོ་རུ་བྲི། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-181"/>“One should draw a jewel in the south That emits halos of light.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-55">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-181</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>པདྨ་རཱ་གའི་མདངས་འདྲའི་འོད། །པདྨ་ནུབ་ཀྱི་ཕྱོགས་སུ་བྲི། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>One should draw a lotus in the west That shines with ruby-colored light.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-56">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-183</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འོད་ཟེར་ལྔ་དང་མཉམ་ལྡན་པའི། །ཤར་གྱི་མཚམས་སུ་འཁོར་ལོ་བྲི། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-183"/>“One should draw a wheel in the southeast That is engulfed in five-colored light.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-57">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-183</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལྷོ་རུ་རྡོ་རྗེ་བྲི་བར་བྱ། །ནུབ་ཏུ་པདྨའི་མེ་ཏོག་ནི། །ཡུ་བ་དང་བཅས་ཁ་བྱེ་གསལ། །འོད་ཀྱི་ཕྲེང་བ་མཉམ་འཕྲོ་བའི། །ཨུཏྤ་ལ་ནི་བྱང་ནུབ་བྲི། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>One should draw a vajra in the southwest, A lotus flower in the northwest Radiantly blossoming upon its stalk, And a water lily in the northeast That radiates halos of light.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-58">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-189</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཤར་གྱི་སྒོར་ནི་ཐོ་བ་སྟེ། །དབྱིག་པ་དེ་བཞིན་ལྷོ་ཡི་སྒོར། །འདམ་ལས་སྐྱེས་པ་ནུབ་ཀྱི་སྒོར། །བྱང་དུ་རྡོ་རྗེ་རལ་གྲིའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-189"/>“There should be a hammer in the eastern gate And, likewise, a cudgel in the southern gate, A lotus is in the western gate, And, in the north, a vajra-sword.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-59">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-190</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཤེས་པས་དཀྱིལ་འཁོར་རྫོགས་པ་ལ། །མཆོད་པ་ཁྱད་པར་འཕགས་པ་ནི། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-190"/>“Knowing the maṇḍala to be complete One should make special offerings.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-60">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-190</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདོད་པའི་ཡོན་ཏན་ལྔ་དག་གིས། །འཇིགས་པ་མེད་པར་མངོན་པར་མཆོད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>One should fearlessly worship Using the five sense pleasures.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-61">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-192</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱི་སྐུ་གསུང་ཐུགས་གཤིན་རྗེའི་གཤེད་ནག་པོའི་རྒྱུད་ལས་དཀྱིལ་འཁོར་ཆེན་པོའི་རིམ་པར་ཕྱེ་བ་སྟེ་ལེའུ་གཉིས་པའོ།། །།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-192"/>This was the second chapter, “The Great Maṇḍala,” from The Tantra of Black Yamāri, the Body, Speech, and Mind of All Tathāgatas.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-62">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-194</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱིས་བསྟོད་པའི་རྒྱལ་པོ་འདིས་བསྟོད་ནས་གསོལ་བ་བཏབ་པ། སྡིག་པ་ཐམས་ཅད་འཇོམས་པ་ཡི། །འཇིགས་པའི་གཤིན་རྗེ་འཇོམས་དཀྱིལ་འཁོར། །དཀྱིལ་འཁོར་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱི་གཙོ་བོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-section-1-3"/>Chapter 3: Ritual Activities<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-194"/> Then, all the blessed tathāgatas made a request using this king of praises:<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-196"/> “Protector, let the maṇḍala be drawn— The fearsome maṇḍala of Yama’s Slayer.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-63">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-194</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མགོན་པོ་དཀྱིལ་འཁོར་བྲི་བར་མཛོད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>It is the lord of all maṇḍalas That eradicates all misdeeds.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-64">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-197</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་རྡོ་རྗེ་འཛིན་ཆེན་པོས་ཉིད་ཀྱི་སྐུ་གསུང་ཐུགས་རྣམས་ལས་བདུད་རྩི་མྱང་བའི་ཆོ་ག་ངེས་པར་ཕྱུང་བ། ཨོཾ་ཨཱཿཧཱུྃ། རྡོ་རྗེ་མེ་ལྕེ་སྦྱོར་བ་ཡིས། །རྡོ་རྗེ་ཅན་ཀུན་མཉེས་པ་དང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-197"/>The great vajra bearer then issued the rite with the taste of nectar from his own body, speech, and mind: oṁ āḥ hūṁ |<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-200"/> The vajra holders are pleased By its contact with their vajra tongues.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-65">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-197</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྫོགས་པའི་སངས་རྒྱས་ཐམས་ཅད་བཞུགས། །ཡེ་ཤེས་འབྱུང་གནས་ངོ་བོ་ཉིད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>It then enters all the buddhas In their wisdom aspect, their intrinsic form.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-66">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-203</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དགུག་པ་དང་ནི་གཞུག་པ་དང་། །བཅིང་དང་དེ་བཞིན་དབང་བྱ་ཉིད། །ཐོ་བ་ལ་སོགས་སྔགས་བཞི་ཡིས། །མཉམ་པར་བཞག་པས་རྣམ་པར་བསྒོམ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-203"/>“One should then summon them, Draw them in, bind them and master them, And then remain in meditative absorption Using the four mantras of Muḍgara and the rest.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-67">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-205</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མ་ཧེ་རྡོ་རྗེ་རྣམ་བསྒོམས་ལ། །དཀྱིལ་འཁོར་གཙོ་བོ་རྣམ་བསྒོམ་བྱ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-205"/>“After visualizing the vajra buffalo, One should visualize the lord of the maṇḍala.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-68">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-205</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཟླ་བའི་དཀྱིལ་འཁོར་དབུས་གནས་པར། །གཏི་མུག་རྡོ་རྗེ་རྣམ་བསྒོམ་བྱ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Mohavajra should be visualized standing In the center of a moon disk.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-69">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-207</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྟ་བདུན་ལྡན་པའི་དབུས་གནས་པ། །ཕྲ་མ་ཞེས་བྱ་རྣམ་བསམ་བྱ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-207"/>“One should imagine the one named Piśuna Standing in the middle of the seven-horsed one.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-70">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-207</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དཀྱིལ་འཁོར་དམ་པའི་དབུས་གནས་པ། །འདོད་ཆགས་རྡོ་རྗེ་རྣམ་བསྒོམ་བྱ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Rāgavajra should be visualized Standing in the center of the sublime disk.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-71">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-207</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལས་ཀྱི་དཀྱིལ་འཁོར་དབུས་གནས་པ། །རྡོ་རྗེ་ལས་ནི་བསྒོམ་པར་བྱ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Karmavajrin should be visualized, Standing in the center of the karma disk.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-72">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-212</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཞི་བའི་གཏི་མུག་རྡོ་རྗེ་སྟེ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-212"/>“Mohavajra is for pacifying.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-73">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-212</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྒྱས་པ་དེ་<tei:ref folio="F.137.a"/>བཞིན་ཕྲ་མ་ཡིན། །འདོད་ཆགས་རྡོ་རྗེ་དབང་དུ་བྱས། །རྡོ་རྗེ་ལས་ཀྱིས་ཐམས་ཅད་དུའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Accordingly, Piśuna is for enriching, Rāgavajra is for enthralling, And Karmavajra is universal.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-74">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-213</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྡོ་རྗེ་ལས་ཀྱི་སྦྱོར་བ་ཡིས། །མི་ཚིལ་མི་ཡི་ཐོད་པར་བཞག །དེ་བཞིན་མི་སྐྲས་སྡོང་བུ་བྱ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-213"/>“Using the yoga of Karmavajra, One should put human fat in a human skull, Make a wick out of human hair, And collect the soot while in a charnel ground.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-75">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-215</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དུར་ཁྲོད་དག་ཏུ་དུ་བ་བསྒྲུབ། །མིག་སྨན་དག་ནི་དེ་བཞིན་དུ། །མིག་སྨན་ལས་ཀྱི་བསྒོམ་པ་དང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-215"/>“One should visualize Karmavajra In the collyrium and likewise on the collyrium.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-76">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-215</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལས་ཀྱི་བཟླས་པའི་སྦྱོར་བ་ཡིས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The collyrium siddhi will result When combined with Karmavajra’s recitation.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-77">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-218</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མིག་སྨན་འདི་ནི་འགྲུབ་པར་འགྱུར། །ཁྲག་དང་གུར་གུམ་གཟུང་བྱས་ནས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-218"/>“One produces the foot-salve Using saffron and blood.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-78">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-218</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྒྲུབ་པ་བྱུག་པ་བསྒྲུབ་པར་བྱ། །ལས་ཀྱི་རྡོ་རྗེ་སྦྱོར་བ་ཡིས། །རྐང་མགྱོགས་དག་ནི་འགྲུབ་པར་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>One produces the swift-feet siddhi By applying the practice of Karmavajra.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-79">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-220</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བདུད་རྩི་ལྔ་ནི་མཉམ་པ་ལ། །ཤ་ལྔ་དང་ནི་ལྡན་པ་ཡིས། །ལྕགས་གསུམ་དུ་ནི་བཅུག་བྱས་ན། །ལས་ཀྱི་སྦྱོར་བས་འགྲུབ་པར་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-220"/>“If one gathers the five nectars, Combines them with the five meats, And coats them with the three metals, The siddhi is gained through the practice of Karmavajra.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-80">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-221</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཀན་ཏའི་ལྕགས་ཀྱི་རལ་གྲི་ནི། །ལས་ཀྱི་སྦྱོར་བ་བསྒྲུབ་པར་བྱ། །ལས་ཀྱི་རྡོ་རྗེ་སྦྱོར་བ་ཡིས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-221"/>“The magnetic iron sword siddhi, Can be accomplished with the yoga of Karmavajra.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-81">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-221</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལས་ཀྱི་རལ་གྲི་རབ་འགྲུབ་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>While applying the practice of Karmavajra, One can accomplish Karmavajra’s sword.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-82">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-222</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱི་སྐུ་གསུང་ཐུགས་གཤིན་རྗེའི་གཤེད་ནག་པོའི་རྒྱུད་ལས་ལས་ཀྱི་རིམ་པར་ཕྱེ་བ་སྟེ་ལེའུ་གསུམ་པའོ།། །།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-222"/>This was the third chapter, “Ritual Activities,” from The Tantra of Black Yamāri, the Body, Speech, and Mind of All Tathāgatas.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-83">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-225</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱིས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་རྡོ་རྗེ་འཛིན་པ་ཆེན་པོ་ལ་བསྟོད་པའི་རྒྱལ་པོ་འདིས་བསྟོད་ནས་གསོལ་བ་བཏབ་པ། ལས་ཀྱི་དབྱེ་བའི་དབྱེ་བ་ལས། །སེམས་ཅན་འཇུག་པ་ཇི་ལྟར་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-section-1-4"/>Chapter 4: The Rites for Killing and so forth using the Yantras, Mantras, and Medicines Related to the Procedure for Vajra Killing<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-225"/> Then, all the blessed tathāgatas made a request to the blessed great vajra bearer using this king of praises:<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-227"/> “How should beings proceed, Through the different categories of ritual action?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-84">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-225</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྡོ་རྗེ་ཆེན་པོས་བཤད་དུ་གསོལ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Great Vajra, please explain!</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-85">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-225</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡོན་ཏན་རྒྱ་མཚོ་རྣམས་ཉན་ལགས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>May the oceans of qualities listen!”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-86">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-229</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་རྡོ་རྗེ་འཛིན་རྒྱལ་པོས། །ལས་ནི་ཐམས་ཅད་རབ་སྒྲུབ་པ། །ཉེས་ཀུན་གསོ་བའི་བདག་ཉིད་ཀྱིས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-229"/>Then, the vajra-bearing king Who has accomplished all ritual actions, And has himself remedied all faults, Spoke the following words.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-87">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-230</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདི་སྐད་ཀྱི་ནི་ཚིག་གསུངས་སོ། །བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་ཐམས་ཅད་ཐུགས་རྡོ་རྗེ་ཉིད་ཀྱི་མཐུས་ཕྱག་འཚལ་ཞིང་མཆོད་པ་བྱས་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ལ་ལན་གསུམ་བསྐོར་བ་བྱས་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-230"/>The blessed tathāgatas, through the power of their vajra minds, bowed to, worshiped, made offerings to, and circled the Bhagavat three times.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-88">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-230</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡང་དང་ཡང་དུ་ཕྱག་བྱས་ནས། །བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱི་གསུང་ཉན་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They bowed to him, again and again, and listened to what the Bhagavat said.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-89">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-231</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་རྡོ་རྗེ་འཛིན་རྒྱལ་པོས། །དབང་དུ་བྱ་བའི་འཁྲུལ་འཁོར་བསྟན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-231"/>The vajra-bearing king Taught the yantra for enthralling.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-90">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-231</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཤིན་རྗེའི་གཤེད་ལས་འཁོར་ལོ་མཆོག །མ་བྱུང་འབྱུང་བར་མི་འགྱུར་རོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“The supreme circles of Yamāri Have not appeared, nor will they appear.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-91">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-234</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བུད་མེད་དབང་དུ་བྱ་བ་དང་། །བསྲུང་བའི་དོན་དང་དེ་བཞིན་དུ། །ཞི་བ་རོ་ཙ་ནས་བཟུང་སྟེ། །གྲོ་གའམ་དེ་བཞིན་སྨྱུག་ཤུན་ལ། །འཁོར་ལོ་གཉིས་<tei:ref folio="F.137.b"/>ནི་མཉམ་བྲིས་ནས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-234"/>“In order to enthrall women, And likewise for protection, In the pacifying rite use bovine bezoar To draw a double circle On birch or bamboo bark.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-92">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-237</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ན་མཿམིང་གིས་རྣམ་བསྟེན་ལ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-237"/>“Append the target’s name with namaḥ.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-93">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-237</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ནག་དང་ཡུ་ཅན་མ་ཡིན་པའི། །ཁམ་ཕོར་གཉིས་ནི་ཁ་སྦྱར་ཏེ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>And place it in two conjoined bowls That are not black and lack a base.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-94">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-237</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མར་དང་སྦྲང་རྩིས་བཀང་བར་གཞུག །སྐུད་པ་དཀར་པོས་ཁམ་ཕོར་བཅིང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The bowls should be filled with ghee and honey And wrapped with a white thread.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-95">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-238</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཤར་དུ་མངོན་པར་ཕྱོགས་པ་ཡིས། །མེ་ཏོག་དཀར་པོས་དུས་གསུམ་གཏོར། །གཤིན་རྗེ་མཐར་བྱེད་ཆུ་ཤེལ་འདྲར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-238"/>“At the three junctures, facing east, One should scatter white flowers, And focus on being Yamāntaka Appearing like a candrakānta.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-96">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-238</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བདག་ཉིད་བསྒོམས་ནས་མདུན་བཀོད་ལ། །ཟླ་བའི་དཀྱིལ་འཁོར་ལ་གནས་ནས། །བསྒྲུབ་བྱ་བ་ལྟས་ནས་དབང་བསྐུར་བྱ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>One should visualize the target on a moon disk before oneself And confer the initiation.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-97">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-240</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བདུད་རྩི་ལྔ་ཡིས་གང་བ་ཡི། །བུམ་པ་དཀར་པོ་ཟླ་བ་འདྲས། །རྫོགས་སངས་དུ་མས་ཁྲུས་བྱས་ཏེ། །བལྟས་ནས་སྔགས་ཀྱི་བཟླས་པ་བརྩམ། ཨོྃ་ན་མཿཧྲཱིཿཥྚྲིཿཝི་ཀྲྀ་ཏཱ་ན་ན་ཧཱུྃ་ཧཱུྃ་ཕཊ་ཕཊ་དེ་བ་དཏྟཱ་ཡ་ཤཱནྟིཾ་ཀུ་རུ་ན་མཿསྭཱ་ཧཱ། ཞི་བའི་ཆོ་ག་གསུངས་པའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-240"/>“Imagine a multitude of perfect buddhas Washing the target with a moon-white vase Filled with the five nectars, While reciting this mantra: <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-241"/>oṁ namaḥ hrīḥ ṣṭrīḥ vikṛtānana hūṁ hūṁ phaṭ phaṭ devadattāya śāntiṃ kuru namaḥ svāhā |<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-244"/> This is the rite for pacification.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-98">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-245</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྐྱེས་པ་ཞི་ལ་གུར་ཀུམ་གྱིས། །བྲི་བྱ་དེ་བཞིན་རྒྱས་པ་ཡང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-245"/>“One should write with red saffron When pacifying a man or when enriching.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-99">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-245</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཁོར་ལོ་གཉིས་ནི་ཁ་ཆེ་ཡི། །སྭཱ་ཧཱས་མིང་ནི་བརྒྱན་པ་ཡི། །བསྒྲུབ་བྱའི་མིང་ནི་བྲིས་བྱས་ལ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The double circle is drawn with Kashmiri saffron With the target’s name appended to svāhā.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-100">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-247</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མར་དང་སྦྲང་རྩིས་བཀང་ནས་ནི། །ཁམ་ཕོར་ཁ་སྦྱར་ནང་དུ་གཞུག །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-247"/>“It should be placed inside conjoined bowls That have been filled with ghee and honey.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-101">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-247</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྐུད་པ་སེར་པོས་བཅིངས་ནས་ནི། །མེ་ཏོག་སེར་པོ་དུས་གསུམ་གཏོར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They should be wrapped with yellow thread And strewn with yellow flowers at the three junctures.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-102">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-248</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱང་དུ་ཁ་བལྟས་མདོག་སེར་བའི། །གཤིན་རྗེའི་གཤེད་དུ་བདག་ཉིད་བསམ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-248"/>“One should imagine themselves as Yama’s Slayer, Yellow in color and facing north.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-103">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-248</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བསྒྲུབ་བྱ་ཟླ་བ་སེར་ནག་ལ། །བུམ་པ་སེར་པོས་བཀྲུ་བྱ་ཞིང་། །དབང་བསྐུར་བ་ནི་བསྒོམ་བྱས་ལ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The target, standing on a dark-yellow moon disk, Should be cleansed using a yellow vase.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-104">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-250</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྤྲོས་ལ་རྒྱས་པའི་བཟླས་པ་བྱ། །ཨོྃ་ཧྲཱིཿཥྚྲིཿཝི་ཀྲྀ་ཏཱ་ན་ན་ཧཱུྃ་ཧཱུྃ་ཕཊ་ཕཊ་སྭཱ་ཧཱ། དེ་བ་དཏྟ་པུཥྚིཾ་ཀུ་རུ་སྭཱ་ཧཱ། ཨོྃ་ཧྲཱིཿཥྚྲཱི་ཝིཀྲྀ་ཏཱ་ན་ན་ཧཱུྃ་ཧཱུྃ་ཕཊ་ཕཊ། བཽ་ཥ་ཊ་དེ་བ་དཏྟ་སྱ་པུཥྚིཾ་ཀུ་རུ་བཽ་ཥ་ཊ་སྭཱ་ཧཱ། འདི་ནི་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་རྒྱས་པའི་ཆོ་ག་གསུངས་པའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-250"/>“Once the target has been initiated, One should recite the enriching mantra while radiating light: oṁ hrīḥ ṣṭrīḥ vikṛtānana hūṁ hūṁ phaṭ phaṭ svāhā | devadatta puṣṭiṃ kuru svāhā | oṁ hrīḥ ṣṭrīḥ vikṛtānana hūṁ hūṁ phaṭ phaṭ vauṣaṭ devadattasya puṣṭiṃ kuru vauṣaṭ svāhā |<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-256"/> This is the enriching rite taught by the Bhagavat.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-105">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-257</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གྲོག་འམ་རས་ལ་རྒྱ་སྐྱེགས་ཀྱི། །ཁུ་བའམ་ཙནྡན་དམར་པོའམ། །སྲིན་ལག་གི་ནི་ཁྲག་ཀྱང་རུང་། །ཡི་གེ་ཧོཿཡིས་བརྟེན་པ་ཡི། །འཁོར་ལོ་གཉིས་ནི་མཉམ་པར་བྲི། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-257"/>“On birch bark or a rag, One should use lac fluid, red sandalwood, Or blood from their own ring finger, as available, To draw a double circle With the syllable hoḥ appended.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-106">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-260</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཁོར་ལོ་ནག་པོ་སོགས་བྲལ་བའི། །ཁམ་ཕོར་གཉིས་ནི་ཁ་སྦྱར་དུ། །མར་དང་སྦྲང་རྩིས་བཀང་བ་གཞག །སྐུད་པ་དམར་པོས་བཅིངས་བྱས་ལ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-260"/>“The circle should be placed in conjoined bowls, That are not black and so forth, And that are filled with ghee and honey, Then wrapped with a red thread.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-107">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-260</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ནུབ་ཕྱོགས་སུ་ནི་ཁ་བལྟས་ནས། །མེ་ཏོག་དམར་པོས་མཆོད་པར་བྱ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Facing west one should make Offerings of red flowers.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-108">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-262</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བདག་ཉིད་གཤིན་རྗེ་མཐར་བྱེད་པ། །ཁ་དོག་དམར་པོ་ཆེར་འབར་བ། །ཟླ་བ་དམར་པོ་ལ་གནས་པའོ། །བསྒྲུབ་བྱ་ཡང་ནི་རྣམ་བསམ་བྱ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-262"/>“One should imagine themselves as Yama’s Slayer, Red in color and blazing fiercely, And that the target stands On a red moon disk.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-109">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-263</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རང་གི་ལུས་ལས་བྱུང་བ་ཡི། །འོད་ཟེར་<tei:ref folio="F.138.a"/>དམར་པོ་ལྕགས་ཀྱུ་ཡིས། །བསྒྲུབ་བྱ་དགུག་པར་བྱ་བར་བསམ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-263"/>“One should visualize the target being drawn in With hooks of red light rays That emerge from one’s body, And recite the mantra ten thousand times as they spread.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-110">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-264</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྔགས་ནི་སྤྲོ་ཞིང་ཁྲི་བཟླས་བྱ། །དེས་ནི་བསྒྲུབ་བྱ་ཉམས་གྱུར་ནས། །རྐང་པ་གཉིས་སུ་ལྷགས་གྱུར་ནས། །གོས་བྲལ་སྐྲ་ནི་བཤིག་གྱུར་པ། །རྣམ་པར་བསམས་ལ་བཟླས་པ་བརྩམ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-264"/>“Imagining that the target is distressed, Their legs are crippled, And they are naked with their hair loose, Begin the recitation.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-111">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-265</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གལ་ཏེ་དབང་དུ་མ་གྱུར་ན། །མར་ལ་སོགས་པ་བྲལ་བྱས་ལ། །དུ་བ་མེད་པའི་སེང་ལྡེང་མེས། །འཁོར་ལོ་དེ་ནི་སྒྲུབ་པོས་བསྲོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-265"/>“If the target is not enthralled, The practitioner should heat the circle Over a smokeless fire of acacia wood, Omitting the ghee and the rest.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-112">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-268</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཨོཾ་ཧྲཱིཿཥྚྲཱིཿཝི་ཀྲྀ་ཏཱ་ན་ན་ཧཱུྃ་ཧཱུྃ་ཕཊ་ཕཊ་སྭཱ་ཧཱ། ཧོ་དེ་བ་དཏྟ་ཝ་ཤཾ་ཀུ་རུ་ཧོཿ ཨོཾ་ཧྲཱིཿཥྚྲཱི་ཝིཀྲྀ་ཏཱ་ན་ན་ཧཱུྃ་ཧཱུྃ་ཕཊ་ཕཊ་སྭཱ་ཧཱ། བཽ་ཥཊ་དེ་བ་དཏྟ་སྱ་ཝ་ཤ་མ་ན་ཡ་བཽཥཊ། འདི་ནི་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་དབང་དུ་བྱ་བའི་ཆོ་ག་གསུངས་པའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-268"/>oṁ hrīḥ ṣṭrīḥ vikṛtānana hūṁ hūṁ phaṭ phaṭ svāhā | ho devadatta vaśaṃ kuru hoḥ |<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-270"/> oṁ hrīḥ ṣṭrīḥ vikṛtānana hūṁ hūṁ phaṭ phaṭ svāhā | vauṣaṭ devadattasya vaśamānaya vauṣaṭ |<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-272"/> This is the enthralling rite taught by the Bhagavat.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-113">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-273</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དུར་ཁྲོད་གོས་སམ་ཡང་ན་ནི། །རང་བྱུང་གིས་བསྐུས་རས་ལ་ནི། །ཁྲག་དང་རྒྱ་སྐྱེགས་བསྲེས་པ་ཡིས། །འཁོར་ལོ་གཉིས་ནི་མཉམ་བྲིས་ལ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-273"/>“On cloth from a charnel ground Or a rag smeared with menstrual blood, One should draw a double circle With a mixture of blood and lac.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-114">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-274</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡི་གེ་ཛཿདང་ཡི་གེ་ཧྲཱིཿས། །མིང་ནི་རྣམ་པར་བརྟེན་བྱས་ལ། །བཙུན་མོ་ཡི་ནི་པདྨའི་སྣོད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-274"/>“The target’s name should be framed With the syllables jaḥ and hrīḥ, And the circle placed in conjoined skull cups Made from the skulls of women.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-115">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-274</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཁ་སྦྱོར་ནང་དུ་བཙུད་བྱས་ཏེ། །སྐུད་པ་དམར་པོས་བཅིངས་བྱས་ལ། །མེ་ཏོག་དམར་པོས་མཆོད་པར་བྱ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>This should be wrapped with red thread And presented with offerings of red flowers.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-116">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-275</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བདག་ཉིད་གཤིན་རྗེ་མཐར་བྱེད་པ། །ནུབ་ཀའི་ཉི་མ་དང་འདྲ་དམར། །ལྕགས་ཀྱུ་དམར་པོས་བཀུག་པ་ཡི། །བསྒྲུབ་བྱ་དག་ནི་རྣམ་བསྒོམ་བྱ། །སྙིང་ལ་ལྕགས་ཀྱུས་བརྒྱ་བ་ནས་ནི། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-275"/>“Imagining themselves as Yama’s Slayer, Red like the setting sun, One should imagine Seizing the target with red iron hooks.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-117">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-276</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྐེ་ནས་ཞགས་པས་བཅིངས་བྱས་ཏེ། །གཅེར་བུ་སྐྲ་ནི་མ་བཅིངས་པར། །རླུང་གི་དཀྱིལ་འཁོར་སྦྱོར་བ་ཡི། །སེང་གེ་དམར་པོའི་སྟེང་འདུག་ལ། །རྫས་ལྔ་ཡིས་ནི་བཀྲུ་བྱ་ཞིང་། །འོངས་པ་རུ་ནི་བསམ་པར་བྱ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-276"/>“After hooks strike their heart And a noose binds their neck, One should imagine they arrive, Naked, hair loose, Seated on a red lion, Accompanied by circle of wind, And are cleansed with the five substances.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-118">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-278</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གལ་ཏེ་བསྒྲུབ་བྱ་མི་འོང་ན། །སེང་ལྡེང་གི་ནི་མེ་མདག་ལ། །དེར་ནི་བཟླས་པ་བརྩམ་པར་བྱ། །བརྟུལ་ཞུགས་ཅན་གྱིས་འཁོར་ལོ་བསྲོ། །ཨོྃ་ཧྲཱིཿཥྚྲཱིཿཝི་ཀྲྀ་ཏཱ་ན་ན་ཧཱུྃ་ཧཱུྃ་ཕཊ་ཕཊ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-278"/>“If the target does not arrive, The vow-holder should recite the mantra While heating the circle In a fire of acacia wood.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-119">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-279</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཧྲཱིཿཨ་མུ་ཀཾ་ཨཱ་ཀརྵ་ཡ་ཧྲཱིཿ ཨོྃ་ཧྲཱིཿཥྚྲཱི་ཝི་ཀྲྀ་ཏཱ་ན་ན་ཧཱུྃ་ཧཱུྃ་ཕཊ་ཕཊ་ཛཿདེ་བ་དཏྟ་ཨཱ་ཀརྵ་ཡ་ཛཿ། འདི་ནི་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་དགུག་པའི་ཆོ་ག་གསུངས་པའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-279"/>oṁ hrīḥ ṣṭrīḥ vikṛtānana hūṁ hūṁ phaṭ phaṭ | hrīḥ amukam ākarṣaya hrīḥ |<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-281"/> oṁ hrīḥ ṣṭrīḥ vikṛtānana hūṁ hūṁ phaṭ phaṭ jaḥ devadatta ākarṣaya jaḥ |<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-283"/> This is the summoning rite taught by the Bhagavat.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-120">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-284</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དུར་ཁྲོད་གོས་ལ་མཁས་པས་ནི། །ཡུང་བ་ཡི་ནི་ཁུ་བ་ཡིས། །འཁོར་ལོ་གཉིས་ནི་མཉམ་པར་བྲི། །ཡི་གེ་ལྃ་གྱིས་བརྟེན་པ་ཡི། །བསྒྲུབ་བྱའི་མིང་ཡང་བྲི་བར་བྱ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-284"/>“The adept should draw a double circle On cloth from a charnel ground, Using a decoction of turmeric, And write the target’s name Appended to the syllable laṁ.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-121">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-285</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཁམ་ཕོར་ཁ་སྦྱོར་ནང་དུ་སྟེ། །ཁམ་ཕོར་སེར་པོའི་སྟེང་དུ་བཞག །དེ་ལ་མཁས་པས་རེ་ཁཱ་བྲི། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-285"/>“The adept should place it Inside conjoined bowls, Place this on top of a yellow bowl, And draw lines on it.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-122">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-286</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རེ་ཁཱ་བདུན་ནམ་ཡང་ན་<tei:ref folio="F.138.b"/>བཞི། །མཉམ་པར་བཞག་པས་བྲི་བར་བྱ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-286"/>“The adept, in a state of meditative focus, Should draw seven or four lines.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-123">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-286</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རི་རབ་ལྕོག་བརྒྱད་ཅེས་གྲགས་པ། །དེ་ཡི་སྟེང་དུ་མཉམ་པར་བྲི། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Above that they should draw The eight-peaked Mount Sumeru.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-124">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-287</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡི་གེ་ཧཱུྃ་དང་ཡི་གེ་བྃ། རི་རབ་དེ་ནི་བརྟན་པར་བྱ། །དེ་ཡི་སྟེང་དུ་ལྃ་ཡིག་ལས། །དབང་ཆེན་དཀྱིལ་འཁོར་དགོད་པར་བྱ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-287"/>“The syllables hūṁ and vaṃ Frame Mount Meru, And, above that, Indra’s maṇḍala Should be drawn with the syllable laṃ.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-125">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-290</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྣ་ཚོགས་རྡོ་རྗེས་མནན་པ་ལ། །སྐུད་པ་སེར་པོས་བཅིངས་ནས་ནི། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-290"/>“It should be stamped with a crossed vajra And wrapped with a yellow thread.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-126">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-290</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཤིན་རྗེའི་གཤེད་པོ་མདོག་སེར་པོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>One should imagine themselves As the yellow Yama’s Slayer.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-127">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-292</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དབང་ཆེན་དཀྱིལ་འཁོར་ལ་གནས་པ། །བསྒྲུབ་བྱ་སེར་པོ་རྣམ་བསམས་ལ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-292"/>“One should imagine the target to be yellow And standing on Indra’s maṇḍala.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-128">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-292</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རི་རབ་ཀྱིས་ནི་མནན་བྱས་པ། །ཕྱག་ན་རྡོ་རྗེས་མནན་བྱས་པ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They are being crushed by Mount Sumeru And crushed by Vajrapāṇi as well.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-129">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-295</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དབང་ཆེན་དཀྱིལ་འཁོར་གྱི་འོག་ཏུ། །མན་དཱ་ར་སོགས་རི་བོ་དང་། །སྣ་ཚོགས་རི་བོ་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་ཀྱང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-295"/>“One should imagine the target is crushed By Mandara and the like, And other various mountains That are beneath Indra’s maṇḍala.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-130">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-296</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བསྒྲུབ་བྱ་མནན་པར་བསྒོམ་པར་བྱ། །དེ་ལ་གནས་ནས་བཟླས་པར་བྱ། །ཨོྃ་ཧྲཱིཿཥྚྲཱིཿལྦི་ཀྲྀ་ཏཱ་ན་ན་ཧཱུྃ་ཧཱུྃ་ཕཊ་ཕཊ་ལྃ་དེ་བ་དཏྟ་སྠཱ་ནེ་སྟམྦྷ་ཡ་ཀུ་རུ་ལཾ། འདི་ནི་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་རེངས་པར་བྱེད་པའི་གསུངས་པའོ། །ངག་ནི་རེངས་པར་འདོད་པ་ཡིས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-296"/>“While maintaining this visualization, recite the mantra:<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-298"/> oṁ hrīḥ ṣṭrīḥ vikṛtānana hūṁ hūṁ phaṭ phaṭ laṁ devadatta sthāne stambhaya kuru laṁ |<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-300"/> This is the paralyzing rite taught by the Bhagavat.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-131">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-301</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་བཞིན་འཁོར་ལོ་གཉིས་བྲིས་ལ། །བསྒྲུབ་བྱའི་མིང་ཡང་བྲི་བར་བྱ། །དེར་ནི་སྔགས་ཀྱང་སྤྲོས་ལ་བཟླས། །ཨོྃ་ཧྲཱིཿཥྚྲཱི་ཝིཀྲྀ་ཏཱ་ན་ན་ཧཱུྃ་ཧཱུྃ་ཕཊ་ཕཊ་ལྃ་དེ་བ་དཏྟསྱ་ཡ་ཐཱསྲ་རཐཱ། ཀར་ཀྲིཏ་ཏེ་ནན་ཏི་བི་ར་ཡ་ཐཱ་ཨ་བི་རཱུ་པ་ཀཾ་དེ་བ་དཏྟ་ཡ་ཛྙཱ་དཏྟ་ཡ་སྱ་ཝཱ་ཀཝཀ་སྟམྦྷ་ན་ཀུ་རུ་ལཾ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-301"/>“One who wishes to paralyze speech Should draw a similar double circle, Add the target’s name, And recite the pulsating mantra:<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-303"/> oṁ hrīḥ ṣṭrīḥ vikṛtānana hūṁ hūṁ phaṭ phaṭ laṁ devadattasya yathāprārabdha­kāryakṛte tannivārayato virūpakaṃ vadato yajñādattasya vākstambhanaṃ kuru laṃ huṃ phaṭ |<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-305"/> This paralyzing rite was taught by the Bhagavat.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-132">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-306</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་རེངས་པར་བྱེད་པའི་ཆོ་ག་དེ་སྐད་གསུངས་སོ། །ཤིན་ཏུ་ལེགས་པར་སྦས་པ་ཡིས། །འདི་ལས་གསུངས་བཞིན་དགོས་པ་དག །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-306"/>“This must be performed exactly as taught And with the utmost secrecy.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-133">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-306</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཤིན་རྗེའི་གཤེད་ནག་སྦྱོར་བ་ཡིས། །ཉི་མ་གཅིག་གིས་འགྲུབ་པར་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Using the practice of Black Yamāri One will gain accomplishment in a single day.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-134">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-307</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྔར་བཞིན་དུར་ཁྲོད་ཀྱི་རས་ལ། །འཁོར་ལོ་གཉིས་བྲིས་བརྟུལ་ཞུགས་ཅན། །སྐེ་ཚེ་དང་ནི་ཚྭ་དང་ནི། །དུག་དང་གཞན་ཡང་ནིམ་པ་དང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-307"/>“As before, the vow holder should draw A double circle on a charnel ground rag.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-135">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-308</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཚ་བ་གསུམ་དང་ཚ་བའི་མར། །དུར་ཁྲོད་ཀྱི་ནི་སོལ་བ་དང་། །དྷ་དུར་ལོ་མའི་ཁུ་བ་དང་། །ཙན་ད་ལི་འབྲས་མཛུབ་མོ་ཁྲག །ཚ་སྒོ་ཅན་གྱི་ས་བླངས་ཏེ། །གདོལ་བའི་རྫ་མའི་དྲེག་པ་དང་། །རབ་ཏུ་ལྟོགས་པའི་སྨྱུ་གུ་ཡིས། །བཅུ་བཞི་ལ་བྲིས་བརྟུལ་ཞུགས་ཅན། །ཁྲོས་པའི་སེམས་ཀྱིས་ཉིན་ཕྱེད་ན། །གདུག་པ་ཅན་རྣམས་གསད་པའི་ཕྱིར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Taking black mustard seeds, salt, Poison, as well as neem, <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-308"/>“The three hot spices, white mustard oil, Charcoal from a charnel ground, Juice from datura leaves, And likewise datura seeds, saline soil,<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-309"/> “Blood from the index finger, And soot from a caṇḍāḷa’s pot, And using a quill from a starved bird, The vow holder should draw it on the fourteenth day, At midday, with a wrathful mind, In order to slay evil beings.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-136">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-314</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སེམས་ཅན་གནོད་པ་བྱེད་པའི་མིང་། །ཡི་གེ་ཧཱུྃ་གིས་བརྟེན་བྱས་ལ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-314"/>“To the syllable hūṁ one should append The name of the person to be slain.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-137">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-314</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བདག་ཉིད་གཤིན་རྗེ་མཐར་བྱེད་པའི། །སྦྱོར་བས་ལྷོ་ཕྱོགས་<tei:ref folio="F.139.a"/>ཁ་བལྟས་ཏེ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The yogin, facing south, Should embody Yama’s Slayer.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-138">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-315</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཁྲོ་ཆེན་རབ་ཏུ་དྲག་པོའི་གཟུགས། །རུས་པས་མགོ་བོ་རྣམ་བརྒྱན་ལ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-315"/>“Of wrathful form and intensely fierce, He is adorned with severed heads.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-139">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-315</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མ་ཧེ་ལ་བཞུགས་ལྕེ་ཕྱུང་འདྲིལ། །གསུས་པ་ཆེ་ལ་རབ་འཇིགས་པ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He stands on a buffalo, his tongue lolls, He has a large belly, and is terrifying.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-140">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-317</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྐྲག་བྱེད་སྐྲ་འབར་གྱེན་དུ་འགྲེང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-317"/>“He is frightening, his blazing hair rises upward.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-141">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-317</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྨ་ར་སྨིན་མ་དེ་བཞིན་སེར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>His beard and eyebrows are similarly yellow.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-142">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-317</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཡས་ན་རྡོ་རྗེ་ཆེན་པོ་དང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>His first right hand holds a large vajra.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-143">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-317</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཉིས་པ་ན་ནི་རལ་གྲི་དང་། །གསུམ་པའི་ཕྱག་ན་གྲི་གུག་གོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>In his second is a sword, And, in the third, a knife.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-144">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-317</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ད་ནི་གཡོན་པའི་བྲི་བར་བྱ། །འཁོར་ལོ་དང་ནི་པདྨ་ཆེ། །ཐོད་པ་ཉིད་ནི་གཡོན་ནའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Now, to draw the left hands: A wheel, a large lotus, And a skull cup, are in his left hands.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-145">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-319</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྩ་བའི་ཞལ་ནི་ཤིན་ཏུ་གནག །གཡས་པའི་ཟླ་འོད་བཟང་པོ་འདྲ། །གཡོན་པའི་དམར་པོ་ཡིན་པར་བརྟག །རྡོ་རྗེ་རྒྱན་གྱིས་རབ་ཏུ་བརྒྱན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-319"/>“His main face is deep black, His right like fine moonlight, His left face is declared to be red, And he is adorned with vajra ornaments.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-146">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-321</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བ་སྤུ་ཁུང་ནས་འཇིགས་ཆེན་པོ། །རང་རིགས་བདག་པོ་རབ་འཕྲོ་བ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-321"/>“From his pores emanate The fearsome one, lord of his own family.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-147">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-321</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཉི་མའི་དཀྱིལ་འཁོར་སྟེང་ན་ནི། །ཞབས་ནི་གཡོན་པ་བརྐྱང་བས་གནས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He stands on a sun disk With his left leg extended.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-148">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-321</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མཆེ་བ་གཙིགས་ཤིང་རྒྱགས་པ་ཡིས། །བསྐལ་པའི་འབར་བ་མེ་དང་མཚུངས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He haughtily bares his fangs And resembles the apocalyptic fire.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-149">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-323</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདི་ལྟ་བུ་ཡི་བདག་ཉིད་ཀྱིས། །བསྒྲུབ་པར་བྱ་བ་མདུན་དུ་དགོད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-323"/>“Embodying this oneself, One should imagine the target placed in front.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-150">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-323</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གདུག་པའི་མཚོན་གྱིས་བརྒྱབ་པ་ཡིས། །དྲི་མ་ཅན་ལ་ནད་ཀྱིས་གཟིར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>By striking with a poisoned blade, The target becomes filthy and diseased.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-151">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-326</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གོས་མེད་འདར་ཞིང་ཉམ་ཆུང་བས། །དོན་འདོད་པ་ཡི་ཚིག་སྨྲ་ཞིང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-326"/>“They become naked, shake, grow depressed, And speak pleading words.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-152">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-326</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མཚོན་གྱིས་གཟིར་བར་བྱས་པ་ཡི། །རྣག་གི་ཐུམ་པོས་ལུས་གང་བ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Their body is covered with pus-filled sores— The result of being sliced with a blade.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-153">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-328</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གྲང་བའི་རླུང་གིས་གཙེས་གྱུར་ཞིང་། །མེ་ཡི་ནང་དུ་ཞུགས་པ་ལ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-328"/>“After being tormented by frigid wind, They find themselves in the midst of fire.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-154">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-328</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མ་ཧེ་དང་ནི་སྟག་དག་དང་། །ཁྱི་དང་མཆུ་རིངས་ཅན་དག་གིས། །སངས་རྒྱས་སྡེ་ནི་མངོན་འཇིགས་པའི། །སྡིག་པོ་ཆེ་ནི་བཟའ་བར་བྱེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The wicked one, fearful of the host of buddhas, Will be consumed by buffaloes, Tigers, dogs, and crows.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-155">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-330</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མཐར་བྱེད་པ་ཡི་ལྷོར་གནས་པ། །ཚེར་མས་ལུས་ནི་བཀང་བ་དང་། །རྐང་པ་ཤིང་ལྕགས་སྒྲོག་གིས་བསྡམས། །དེ་བཞིན་དུམ་བུ་དུམ་བུར་བྱས། །པགས་པ་དག་ནི་བཤུས་བྱས་ནས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-330"/>“The target stands in Yama’s stomach, Their body rife with thorns, And their feet clasped in wooden stocks.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-156">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-334</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ལ་ཚྭ་དང་སྐེ་ཚེ་བསྐུས། །ཧཱུྃ་ཞེས་ཟེར་བ་བསྒོམ་པར་བྱ། །དེ་ཡི་ལུས་བསྲུང་ལ་སོགས་པ། །གཅད་པ་དག་ནི་མདུན་དུ་དགོད། །དེ་ཡི་གོ་ཆའང་མེད་བྱས་ནས། །སྟོང་པའི་ལུས་ནི་མདུན་དུ་བསམ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They are chopped into pieces, Their skin is flayed, They are smeared with salt and mustard, And utter the syllable hūṁ<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-334"/> “Imagine them in one’s presence, Their physical protections gone, Stripped of their armor, Their body completely vacant.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-157">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-337</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རང་གི་ལུས་བྱུང་ཁྲོ་བོ་ནི། །གཤིན་རྗེའི་གཤེད་སོགས་བདག་ཉིད་འདྲས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-337"/>“Wrathful deities emanate from one’s own body Similar in form to oneself as Yamāri.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-158">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-337</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ཡི་ལུས་ལ་བརྒྱབ་ནས་ནི། །ཚིལ་བུ་རྐང་དག་འཐུང་བར་བྱེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They strike the target’s body And suck their fat and marrow.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-159">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-338</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ཡི་མདུན་དུ་གཤིན་རྗེ་བསྒོམ། །ལག་ན་དབྱིག་པ་སྟོབས་པོ་ཆེ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-338"/>“One should imagine Yama in front of them, Powerful, with a cudgel in hand.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-160">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-338</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གདུག་པ་ཅན་དེས་རྡེག་པར་བྱེད། །<tei:ref folio="F.139.b"/>དེ་ཡི་རྒྱུ་མའི་ཕྲེང་བ་སོགས། །བྱ་རྒོད་ཀྱིས་ཁྱེར་མཁའ་ལ་འགྲོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The cruel one strikes them, As vultures take to the sky Carrying off their entrails and the like.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-161">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-338</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ས་ཡི་འོག་ནས་ཀླུ་དང་ནི། །ལྷ་མ་ཡིན་ལ་སོགས་པས་རྡེག །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>From below the ground, Nāgas and asuras strike at them.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-162">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-340</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདི་ལྟར་བསྒྲུབ་བྱ་ཉམས་བྱ་བ། །སྙིང་རྗེ་ལ་གནས་སེམས་ཀྱིས་ནི། །བྱེད་པས་འཁོར་བའི་གནས་བཏོན་ནས། །སངས་རྒྱས་ཞིང་དུ་འགྲོ་བར་བྱེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-340"/>“Experiencing the target in this way, One should, while steeped in compassion, Lift them from their saṃsaric state, And lead them to a buddhafield.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-163">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-341</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་ཐམས་ཅད་ཁྱད་པར་ཅན་གྱི་ཐུགས་ཀྱིས་འདི་ལྟ་བུའི་གསུང་ཕྱུང་བར་མཛད་དོ། །ཨེ་མའོ་གསད་པའི་ཡང་དག་གསད། །བསད་པ་མ་ཡིན་སྡིག་ལས་བཀྲོལ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-341"/>Then, all the blessed tathāgatas uttered these words with a particular intention in mind:<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-343"/> “How amazing indeed is this killing— Killing that is not killing Because it frees from evil.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-164">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-341</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཇི་སྲིད་བསད་ཀྱང་མ་བསད་དོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The one who was killed was not truly killed.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-165">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-345</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྡིག་པ་སྟོང་ཕྲག་བྱས་པ་ཡི། །མནར་མེད་ལ་སོགས་མི་སྐྱེ་བ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-345"/>“One who has committed a thousand evil deeds Will not be born in the Avīci Hell or others.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-166">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-345</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཨེ་མའོ་སངས་རྒྱས་ཆེ་བའི་བདག །བསད་པས་བྱང་ཆུབ་ཐོབ་པར་བྱེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>How amazing is the greatness of the Buddha, That being killed leads to awakening.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-167">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-346</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སེམས་ཅན་གསོད་པ་བསད་པ་ཉིད། །སྙིང་རྗེ་ཆེན་པོ་ཉིད་ཀྱིས་བྱས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-346"/>“The killing of the murderous being Is done by cultivating great compassion.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-168">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-346</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཨེ་མའོ་སྙིང་རྗེ་སྟོབས་ཀྱི་མཆོག །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>How amazing is supreme compassion.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-169">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-346</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྙིང་རྗེ་དམན་པས་འགྲུབ་མི་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Success will not come through weak compassion.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-170">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-349</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཨོཾ་ཧྲཱིཿཥྚྲཱིཿཝི་ཀྲྀ་ཏཱ་ན་ན་ཧཱུྃ་ཧཱུྃ་ཕཊ་ཕཊ། ཧཱུྃ་དེ་བ་དཏྟ་མཱ་ར་ཡ་ཧཱུྃ་ཕཊ། ཨོཾ་ཧྲཱིཿཥྚྲཱིཿཝིཀྲྀ་ཏཱ་ན་ན་ཧཱུྃ་ཧཱུྃ་ཕཊ་ཕཊ། དེ་བ་དཏྟ་མཱ་ར་ཡ་ཕཊ། དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱི་སྐུ་གསུང་ཐུགས་གཤིན་རྗེའི་གཤེད་ནག་པོའི་རྒྱུད་ལས་རྣམ་པར་རྟོག་པ་གསོད་པའི་རྡོ་རྗེའི་འཁྲུལ་འཁོར་དང་སྔགས་དང་སྨན་གྱིས་གསད་པ་ལ་སོགས་པའི་ཆོ་ག་སྟེ་རིམ་པར་ཕྱེ་བ་བཞི་པའོ།། །།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-349"/>oṁ hrīḥ ṣṭrīḥ vikṛtānana hūṁ hūṁ phaṭ phaṭ | hūṁ devadatta māraya hūṁ phaṭ | oṁ hrīḥ ṣṭrīḥ vikṛtānana hūṁ hūṁ phaṭ phaṭ | devadatta māraya phaṭ |<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-351"/> This was the fourth chapter, “The Rites for Killing and so forth using Yantras, Mantras, Medicines, Related to the Procedure for Vajra Killing,” from The Tantra of Black Yamāri, the Body, Speech, and Mind of All Tathāgatas.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-171">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-354</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་འཁོར་ལོ་གཉིས་བྲིས་ལ། །ཡི་གེ་ཕཊ་ཀྱིས་བརྟེན་པ་ཡི། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-section-1-5"/>Chapter 5: The Procedure for Drawing Yantras<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-354"/> “Next, one should draw a double circle And append the syllable phaṭ.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-172">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-354</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བསྒྲུབ་བྱའི་མིང་ནི་བྲི་བྱས་ལ། །ཐོད་པ་ཁ་སྦྱར་ནང་དུ་གཞུག །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>One should write the target’s name And put it into conjoined skull cups.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-173">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-355</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྐུད་པ་སྔོན་པོས་བཅིངས་བྱས་ཏེ། །ཉི་མ་ཕྱེད་ཀྱི་དུས་སུ་ནི། །དུར་ཁྲོད་ས་ཡི་ནང་དུ་སྦ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-355"/>“This should be wrapped with a blue thread And buried in a charnel ground at midday.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-174">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-356</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཤིན་རྗེའི་གཤེད་ཀྱི་སྦྱོར་བ་ཡི། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-356"/>“While focused on being Yamāri, One should place the target before themselves.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-175">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-356</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྟ་དང་མ་ཧེ་ཞོན་པ་ཡི། །ལག་ན་མཚོན་ཐོགས་བསྒྲུབ་བྱ་གཉིས། །མདུན་དུ་བསྒྲུབ་བྱ་དགོད་པར་བྱ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>There are two targets, weapons in hand, Mounted on a horse and a buffalo.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-176">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-358</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཁྲོས་པའི་ལུས་ལ་སྤྲུལ་བའི་ཚོགས། །གཉིས་ཀའི་ཕྱོགས་སུ་བསམ་པར་བྱ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-358"/>“One should imagine that, on both sides, Are emanated hordes of wrathful beings.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-177">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-358</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཉིས་ཀས་འཐབ་མོ་མང་པོ་བྱེད། །ཁྲོས་ཤིང་གདུག་པའི་སེམས་ལྡན་པའི། །སྟོབས་ལྡན་ཁྲོས་པ་བསྒོམ་པར་བྱ། །བསྒོམས་པས་བཟླས་པ་བརྩམ་པར་བྱ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>With a mind steeped in wrath, One should recite the mantra while visualizing The two, powerful and fierce, in protracted battle.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-178">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-360</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཨོཾ་ཧྲཱིཿཥྚྲཱིཿཝིཀྲྀ་ཏཱ་ན་ན་ཧཱུྃ་ཧཱུྃ་ཕཊ་ཕཊ། དེ་བ་དཏྟ་ཡ་ཛྙཱ་དཏྟེ་བི་དྭེཥཱ་ཡ་ཧཱུྃ་ཕཊ། འདི་ནི་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་དབྱེ་བའི་ཆོ་ག་གསུངས་<tei:ref folio="F.140.a"/>པའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-360"/>oṁ hrīḥ ṣṭrīḥ vikṛtānana hūṁ hūṁ phaṭ phaṭ | devadatta yajñādatte vidveṣāya hūṁ phaṭ |<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-362"/> This is the rite for sowing discord taught by the Bhagavat.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-179">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-363</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཆོ་ག་དག་ནི་སྔ་མ་བཞིན། །འཁོར་ལོ་གཉིས་ནི་བྲི་བྱས་ལ། །ཡི་གེ་ཧཱུྃ་ཕཊ་ཀྱིས་བརྟེན་པ། །ཐོད་པ་ཁ་སྦྱར་ནང་དུ་གཞུག །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-363"/>“Following the same rite as before, One should draw a double circle, Augment it with the syllables hūṁ and phaṭ, And put it inside conjoined skull cups.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-180">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-364</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྐུད་པ་ནག་པོས་བཅིངས་བྱས་ལ། །ཤ་ཟའི་ཚུལ་དུ་སྦ་བར་བྱ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-364"/>“It should be wrapped with a black cord And buried in an ancestor’s grove.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-181">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-364</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཤིན་རྗེའི་སྦྱོར་བ་ལ་གནས་པས། །མདུན་དུ་བསྒྲུབ་བྱ་བ་སྒོམ་པར་བྱ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Maintaining the practice of Yamāri, One should imagine the target before oneself.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-182">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-366</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡྃ་བྱུང་གཞུ་ཡི་དབྱིབས་འདྲ་བའི། །རླུང་གི་དཀྱིལ་འཁོར་ནག་པོ་ལ། །དེ་སྟེང་མདོག་སྔོན་རྔ་མོ་བསྒོམ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-366"/>“Visualize a black wind maṇḍala, Born from yaṁ and shaped as a bow, With a blue camel on it.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-183">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-366</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ལ་གདུག་པ་ཅན་བསྐྱོན་ལ། །ལྷོ་ཡི་ཕྱོགས་སུ་ཁ་བསྟན་ཏེ། །ཁྲོ་བོའི་ཚོགས་ཀྱིས་དེ་བརྡེག་པ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>On it is the evildoer, facing south, Being beaten by a furious horde.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-184">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-366</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སངས་རྒྱས་ཡིན་ཡང་བཟློག་པ་དཀའ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Even a buddha would find this hard to reverse.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-185">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-367</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཨོཾ་ཧྲཱིཿཥྚྲཱི་ཝིཀྲྀ་ཏཱ་ན་ན་ཧཱུྃ་ཧཱུྃ་ཕཊ་ཕཊ། ཧཱུྃ་ཕཊ་དེ་བ་དཏྟ་ཨུཙྪ་ཊ་ཡ་ནྃ་ཧཱུྃ་ཕཊ། འདི་ནི་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་བསྐྲད་པའི་ཆོ་ག་གསུངས་པའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-367"/>oṁ hrīḥ ṣṭrīḥ vikṛtānana hūṁ hūṁ phaṭ phaṭ devadattam ucchāṭaya hūṁ phaṭ |<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-369"/> This is the expelling rite taught by the Bhagavat.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-186">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-370</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཁྲོས་པས་རྣལ་འབྱོར་ལྷོར་བལྟས་ལ། །ར་ཁྲག་རོ་བསྲེགས་ཐལ་བ་དང་། །དུག་གི་ཚྭ་དང་སྐེ་ཚེ་དང་། །མར་ཁུ་སྨྱོན་པའི་ཁུ་བ་ཡིས། །དུར་ཁྲོད་རས་ལ་འཁོར་ལོ་གཉིས། །རིམ་པ་འདི་བཞིན་བྲི་བར་བྱ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-370"/>“The fierce yogin, facing south, Should draw a double circle on charnel ground cloth Using a decoction of goat blood, corpse ash, Poison, salt, black mustard, and datura, Following the ritual sequence.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-187">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-373</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བསད་པ་གཤིན་རྗེའི་ལུས་ལ་གནས། །དབྱེ་བ་རྟ་དང་མ་ཧེ་ཡིས། །བསྐྲད་པ་རྔ་མོའི་ལུས་ལ་གནས། །ཞི་བ་ཟླ་བའི་དཀྱིལ་འཁོར་གྱིས། །རྒྱས་པ་ཟླ་བ་སེར་པོ་ལ། །བཙུན་མོ་སྙིང་གར་དབང་དུ་བྱ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-373"/>“To kill, one should place the target on Yama’s body; To sow dissent, on a horse and a buffalo; To expel, standing on a camel; To pacify, on a moon disk; To enrich, on a yellow moon disk; To enthrall, in a woman’s heart; To summon, mounted on a goat; To paralyze, in a ring of mountains; And to summon, on a śarabha lion.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-188">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-373</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ར་ལ་བསྐྱོན་པས་འགུགས་པར་བྱེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The other rites are defined in a similar manner.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-189">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-377</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རི་བོའི་དཀྱིལ་དུ་རེངས་བྱ་གཞག །ཤ་ར་བྷ་འམ་སེང་གེས་དགུག །དེ་བཞིན་གཞན་ཡང་མཚོན་པར་བྱ། །རོ་ཙ་ན་དང་རྒྱ་སྐྱེགས་དང་། །ཁ་ཆེ་ཡི་ནི་ཁྱད་པར་གྱི། །དབང་དུ་བྱ་བ་གྲོ་གར་བྲི། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-377"/>“One should draw with bovine bezoar, Lac, or Kashmiri saffron, as specified, On birch bark in order to enthrall.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-190">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-377</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དགེ་བའི་སེམས་ཀྱིས་བཟུང་བྱས་ན། །འགྲུབ་པར་འགྱུར་ཏེ་ཐེ་ཚོམ་མེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>If one’s mind is focused on virtue, There is no doubt it will be successful.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-191">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-382</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཁམ་ཕོར་ཁ་སྦྱར་ནང་དུ་གཞུག །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-382"/>“The circles should be placed in conjoined bowls.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-192">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-382</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཁྭ་ཡི་སྒྲོ་ཡི་སྨྱུ་གུ་ཡིས། །ཉི་མ་ཕྱེད་ནས་བྲི་བར་བྱ། །པདྨའི་ཁ་སྦྱོར་རོ་བསྲེགས་སར། །གཤིན་རྗེའི་རྣལ་འབྱོར་བདག་ཉིད་ཀྱིས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>After midday, one should write with a raven feather On a cremation pyre or conjoined skull cups.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-193">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-382</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཨོཾ་ཧྲཱིཿཥྚྲཱིཿལ་སོགས་གསང་སྔགས་བཟླས། །ལྷོ་ཕྱོགས་གནས་ཏེ་ཚར་གཅད་བྱ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>While focused on being Yamāri, One should recite the mantra oṁ hrīḥ ṣṭrīḥ…, With the target of suppression facing south.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-194">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-385</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མཐའ་ཡི་ཡ་བོར་ཞི་བ་ལ། །ཡི་གེ་ནི་དེ་གཉིས་ཀ་དང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-385"/>“For pacifying, the syllable ya at the edge is effaced, As well as both the ni syllables.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-195">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-385</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཕྱི་ནས་དཀྱིལ་གྱི་ཡ་སྤངས་ཏེ། །ཡི་གེ་ལྷག་མ་ཇི་བདེ་བར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Next, efface the syllable ya in the center, And the remaining syllables as desired.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-196">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-387</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྔོན་དུ་བསྙེན་པ་ཁྲི་ཙམ་བྱ། །འདིས་ནི་ལས་རྣམས་རབ་སྒྲུབ་པ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-387"/>“One should do ten thousand preparatory recitations, Which results in successful ritual action.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-197">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-387</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡེ་ཤེས་རྡོ་རྗེ་བྱ་བ་སྟེ། །གཤིན་རྗེའི་གཤེད་ཀྱི་རྣལ་འབྱོར་པས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>This is to be done with vajra wisdom While focused on being Yamāri.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-198">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-389</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རབ་ཏུ་གྲགས་པའི་འཁོར་<tei:ref folio="F.140.b"/>ལོ་འདི། །ཡི་གེར་བྲིས་ནས་གནས་པ་དང་། །འཁོར་ལོ་བྲིས་ནས་གནས་པ་ཡི། །ཁྱིམ་དེར་འཐབ་མོ་རྟག་ཏུ་འབྱུང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-389"/>“There will be continuous strife In a house where this terrifying circle remains After it has been drawn, With all the syllables still written.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-199">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-391</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱི་སྐུ་གསུང་ཐུགས་གཤིན་རྗེའི་གཤེད་ནག་པོའི་རྒྱུད་ལས་འཁྲུལ་འཁོར་གྱི་གོ་རིམས་བྲི་བ་ཞེས་བྱ་སྟེ་རིམ་པར་ཕྱེ་བ་ལྔ་པའོ།། །།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-391"/>This was the fifth chapter, “The Sequence for Drawing Yantras,” from The Tantra of Black Yamāri, the Body, Speech, and Mind of All Tathāgatas.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-200">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-394</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱི་བདག་པོས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་རྡོ་རྗེ་འཆང་ཆེན་པོ་ལ་བསྟོད་པའི་རྒྱལ་པོ་འདིས་གསོལ་བ་བཏབ་པ། གང་གིས་རྡོ་རྗེ་ཅན་མཉེས་པ། །ཞེ་སྡང་ཕྱག་རྒྱའི་རྣལ་འབྱོར་གྱིས། །རྡོ་རྗེའི་ཕྱག་རྒྱས་རྒྱས་བཏབ་པས། །དངོས་གྲུབ་རྒྱ་ཆེན་ཐོབ་པར་བྱེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-section-1-6"/>Chapter 6: Drawing the Circle<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-394"/> Then, the lord of all the blessed tathāgatas supplicated the Bhagavat, the great vajra holder, using this king of praises:<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-396"/> “By applying the mudrā of anger, Which delights the vajra holders, And then sealing it with the vajra mudrā, A vast array of siddhis are attained.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-201">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-398</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་རྡོ་རྗེ་འཆང་རྒྱལ་པོས། །འདི་ལྟ་བུ་ཡི་གསུང་བསྒྲགས་སོ། །དཀྱིལ་འཁོར་གྱི་ནི་ལྷ་ཀུན་གྱི། །དབུ་ལ་གཤིན་རྗེའི་གཤེད་པོ་བསྒོམ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-398"/>The vajra holder, the king, Then made this statement: “Visualize Yama’s Slayer On the heads of all the maṇḍala deities.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-202">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-399</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྟག་ཏུ་དཀྱིལ་འཁོར་བྲི་བར་བྱ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-399"/>“Continually draw the maṇḍala.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-203">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-399</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྟག་ཏུ་སྦྱིན་སྲེག་གིས་ཀྱང་དགང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Continually satisfy with fire offerings.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-204">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-399</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྟག་ཏུ་དམ་ཚིག་དག་ཀྱང་གཟུང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Continually uphold the samayas.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-205">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-399</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྡོམ་པ་དག་ཀྱང་ཡང་དག་གཟུང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Continually maintain the vows.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-206">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-400</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དང་པོ་ལ་ནི་ཅོད་པན་དབང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-400"/>“First is the crown initiation.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-207">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-400</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཉིས་པ་རལ་གྲི་སྦྱིན་པར་བྱ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Second, the sword initiation should be given.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-208">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-400</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གསུམ་པ་རྡོ་རྗེ་དྲིལ་བུ་དང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Third, the vajra and bell initiation.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-209">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-400</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཟླ་བ་བཟའ་བ་བཞི་པ་སྟེ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The eating of the moon is fourth.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-210">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-403</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཞི་པོ་འདི་ནི་དབང་ཆེན་པོ། །ནག་པོའི་ཞལ་ནས་བྱུང་བ་ཡི། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-403"/>“These are the four great initiations, Sprung from the Black One’s mouth.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-211">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-403</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དབང་འདི་དག་གི་བྱེ་བྲག་གིས། །རྒྱལ་བའི་སྲས་ཀྱིས་བྱང་ཆུབ་ཐོབ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Through the uniqueness of these four initiations, The children of the jinas attain awakening.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-212">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-405</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འབྱུང་པོ་ཀུན་གྱི་གཏོར་མའི་ལུགས། །སྔགས་འདི་དེ་ནས་རབ་བཤད་བྱ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-405"/>“Next, I will explain the mantra, The means for offering bali to all spirits.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-213">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-405</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྔགས་ཆེན་བཟླས་པ་ཙམ་གྱིས་ནི། །འབྱུང་པོ་ཐམས་ཅད་འདར་འགྱུར་བ། །ཨོཾ་ཨིནྡྲཱ་ཡ་ཧྲཱིཿ། ཡ་མཱ་ཡ་ཥྚྲཱིཿ། བ་རུ་ཎཱ་ཡ་ཝི། ཀུ་བེ་རཱ་ཡ་ཀྲྀ། ཨཱི་ཤྭ་ནཱ་ཡ་ཏ། ཨགྷ་ཨེ་ཨཱ། ནཻ་རི་ཏྱཱ་ཡ་ན། བཱ་ཡ་བེ་ན། ཙནྡྲཱ་ཡ་ཧཱུྃ། ཨཱ་ཀརྵ་ཡ་ཧཱུྃ། བྲཧྨ་ཎཱེ་ཡ་ཕཊ། བ་སུ་དྷ་རཱི་ནྱཻ་ཕཊ། བཻ་མ་ཙེ་ཏྲི་ཎྃ་སྭཱ། སརྦ་བྷཱུ་ཏིཾ་བྷྱོ། ཧཱ་ཧ་ཧ་ཧི་ཧི།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>By merely reciting the great mantra All spirits will tremble.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-214">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-406</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཧཱུྃ་ཧཱུྃ། ཕཱོཾ་ཕོཾ་ཕཊ་ཕཊ་སྭཱ་ཧཱ། བཌྜི་མཱུ་ཏྲ་ཆུ་བསྲེས་པས། དཀྱིལ་འཁོར་གྲུ་གསུམ་བྱས་ནས་ནི། །ལྷ་རྣམས་ཀྱང་ནི་ཚིམ་པར་བྱ། །ཧ་ཧ་ཞེས་ཀྱང་དྲན་པར་བྱ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-406"/>oṁ indrāya hrīḥ | yamāya ṣṭrīḥ | varuṇāya viḥ | kuberāya kṛ | īśvanāya taḥ | agnaye ā | nairṛtyāya na | vāyave na | candrāya hūṁ | arkāya hūṁ | brahmaṇe phaṭ | vasudhārāyai phaṭ | vemacitriṇe svā | sarva­bhūtebhyo hā | ha ha hi hi hūṁ hūṁ pheṁ pheṁ svāhā |<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-409"/> “Once the triangular maṇḍala is made, Using a mixture of urine, feces, and water, The yogin should satisfy the deities, And should call to mind the syllables hā hā.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-215">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-412</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དཀྱིལ་འཁོར་རིམ་གསུམ་བྱ་བ་ནི། །བརྒྱད་དང་བཅུ་གཉིས་བཅུ་དྲུག་པའི། །དཀྱིལ་འཁོར་མཁས་པས་བྲིས་པ་ལ། །སྔགས་ནི་ཀུན་ཏུ་དགོད་པར་བྱ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-412"/>“The adept should draw Three concentric circles, With eight, twelve, and sixteen cells And place the mantra syllables throughout.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-216">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-415</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བརྟུལ་ཞུགས་ཅན་གྱིས་བཅུ་གཉིས་པར། །གྲུབ་པའི་སྔགས་རྣམས་དགོད་པར་བྱ། །རྒྱུ་དང་མི་རྒྱུའི་<tei:ref folio="F.141.a"/>འཇིག་རྟེན་གསུམ། །མ་ལུས་ལུས་པ་མེད་པར་འགྲུབ། །ཡ་མ་རཱ་ཛཱ་ས་དོ་མེ་ཡ། ཡ་མེ་དོ་རུ། ཎ་ཡོད་ཡ། ཡ་ད་ཡོ་ནི། ར་ཡ་ཀྵེ་ཡ། ཡ་ཀྵེ་ཡཙྪ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-415"/>“The vow-holder should place The perfected syllables in the twelve cells The vow-holder will be victorious in every way Over the three worlds, the animate and inanimate.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-217">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-417</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ནི་རཱ་མ་ཡ། དཀྱིལ་དུ་ཡ་བྱས་ཤར་དུ་ཀྵེ། །ལྷོ་རུ་འཇམ་པའི་རྡོ་རྗེ་སྟེ། །ཡི་གེ་མེ་ནི་ནུབ་དུ་བྲི། །བྱང་དུ་ད་སྟེ་ད་མ་ནཱ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-417"/>ya ma rā jā sa do me ya ya me do ru ṇa yo da ya | ya da yo ni ra ya kṣe ya ya kṣe ya ccha ni rā ma ya<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-418"/> “Ya is to be placed in the center, kṣe to the east, In the south, Mañjuvajra, The syllable me is drawn in the west, And in the north, dantadhāvanam.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-218">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-421</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བསྒྲུབ་བྱའི་མིང་ནི་སྦྱིན་བྱ་བ། །མཚམས་ཀྱི་སྟོད་པ་དག་ཏུའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-421"/>“The target’s name should be added In the empty intermediate directions.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-219">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-421</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཧཱུྃ་གཉིས་ཀྱིས་ནི་བརྟེན་བྱས་པས། །དགོས་པ་ཐམས་ཅད་སྒྲུབ་པར་བྱེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>By framing it with two hūṁs, All ritual actions will be successful.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-220">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-423</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡཙྪ་ནི་རཱ་ཛཱ་ས་དོ་རུ། །ཎ་ཡོ་ནི་རལ་སོགས་པ། །ཕྱི་རོལ་རིམ་པར་གཡོན་བརྩམས་བྲི། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-423"/>“The syllables ya, ccha, ni, rā, jā, Sa, do, ru, ṇa, yo, ni, ra, and the rest, Should be drawn outside, from the left.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-221">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-423</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དོན་ཀུན་རབ་ཏུ་བསྒྲུབ་པའི་ཕྱིར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>This will fulfill all aims.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-222">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-425</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རིམ་པ་གསུམ་པ་དེ་ལ་ནི། །ཀུན་དུ་ཆ་རེ་བོར་བ་ལ། །ཤར་ནས་བརྩམས་ནས་བྲི་བར་བྱ། །ཨོཾ་ཧྲཱིཿཥྚྲཱིཿལ་སོགས་པའི་སྔགས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-425"/>“In the third ring, from the east, One should draw the syllables Of the mantra beginning oṁ hrīḥ ṣṭrīḥ In every other cell.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-223">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-429</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ཡི་བར་དག་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱི། །ཆ་བརྒྱད་པོར་བ་དག་ལ་བྲི། །ཨ་མུ་ཀཾ་ཀུ་རུ། ཨུཙྪ་ཊ་ཡ། ཝ་ཤཾ་ཀུ་རུ། བི་དྭ་ཥ་ཡ། ཤནྟིཾ་ཀུ་རུ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-429"/>“In each of the eight intermediate cells, One should write, from the left Mūkaṃ kuru,uccāṭaya,vaśīkuru, vidveṣaya, śāntiṃ kuru, or puṣṭiṃ kuru, Depending on the specific rite.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-224">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-433</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>པུཥྚིཾ་ཀུ་རུ། འདི་ལྟར་གཡོན་ནས་བརྩམས་ནས་ནི། །ལས་དང་རྗེས་སུ་མཐུན་པར་ནི། །མིང་དང་ན་མཿཐ་མའི་བར། །ཐ་མ་རུ་བཽ་ཥ་ཊ་དང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-433"/>“Oṁ is at the beginning and then namaḥ after that, And then, after that, vauṣaṭ.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-225">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-433</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཧཱུྃ་ཕཊ་དང་ལྡན་ས་བོན་གྱིས། །ཞི་དང་རྒྱས་དང་མཐར་དབང་བྱེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Furnishing these seeds with hūṃ and phaṭ Effects the pacifying, enriching, and enthralling rites.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-226">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-436</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱི་སྐུ་གསུང་ཐུགས་གཤིན་རྗེའི་གཤེད་ནག་པོའི་རྒྱུད་ལས་འཁོར་ལོ་རྣམ་པར་བྲི་བ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་སྟེ་རིམ་པར་ཕྱེ་བ་དྲུག་པའོ།། །།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-436"/>This was the sixth chapter, “Drawing the Circle,” from The Tantra of Black Yamāri, the Body, Speech, and Mind of All Tathāgatas.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-227">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-438</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཁྲག་དགུག་པ་ཡི་སྦྱོར་བ་ནི། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-section-1-7"/>Chapter 7: The Procedures for Extraction and So Forth<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-438"/> “For the procedure to extract blood The adept should meditate on Carcikā.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-228">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-438</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཞལ་གསུམ་ཕྱག་དྲུག་སྐེམ་པ་ཡི། །ཕྱག་ན་འཁོར་ལོ་ཟླ་འོད་འདྲའི། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>She has three faces, six arms, is emaciated, Holds a wheel in her hand, and shines like the light of the moon.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-229">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-440</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མཁས་པས་ཙརྩི་ཀཱ་བསྒོམ་བྱ། །ཆང་དག་དགུག་པའི་སྦྱོར་བ་ནི། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-440"/>“For the procedure to extract alcohol The adept should meditate on Vārāhī.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-230">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-440</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཞལ་གསུམ་ཕྱག་དྲུག་ཕག་གདོང་མ། །རབ་སྔོ་ཕྱག་ན་རྡོ་རྗེ་བསྣམས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>She has three faces, six arms, the face of a sow, Is dark blue, and holds a vajra in her hand.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-231">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-441</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མཁས་པས་ཕག་མོ་བསྒོམ་པར་བྱ། །ཤེས་རབ་བསྐྱེད་པར་བྱ་བའི་ཕྱིར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-441"/>“To increase knowledge The vow-holder should meditate on Sarasvatī.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-232">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-441</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཞལ་གསུམ་ཕྱག་དྲུག་དམར་བ་ལ། །ཞི་བ་ཕྱག་ན་པདྨ་བསྣམས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>She has three faces, six arms, is red, Peaceful, and holds a lotus in her hand.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-233">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-442</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དབྱངས་ཅན་བརྟུལ་ཞུགས་ཅན་གྱིས་བསྒོམ། །ཁུ་བ་དགུག་པའི་སྦྱོར་བ་ནི། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-442"/>“For the procedure to draw semen The adept should meditate on Gaurī.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-234">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-442</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཞལ་གསུམ་ཕྱག་དྲུག་རལ་གྲི་བསྣམས། །ནོར་བུ་མརྒད་འདྲ་བ་ནི། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>She has three faces, six arms, wields a sword, And appears like an emerald.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-235">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-444</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཽ་རཱི་མཁས་པས་བསྒོམ་པར་བྱ། །དེ་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་རྡོ་རྗེ་གཤེན་རྗེའི་གཤེད་པོ་གསད་པ་དང་དགུག་པ་ཞེས་བྱ་བའི་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་ལ་སྙོམས་པར་ཞུགས་ནས་རྡོ་རྗེ་ཙརྩི་ཀཱའི་སྔགས་འདི་<tei:ref folio="F.141.b"/>གསུངས་སོ། །ཨོཾ་ཙརྩི་ཀཱ་སིདྡྷེ་ན་དྲ་ནཱི་ལ་ཧཱ་རི་ཎི་རཏྣ་ཏྲ་ཡ་ཨ་པ་ཀཱ་རི་ཎོ་རུ་དི་ར་ཨཱ་ཀརྵ་ཡ་ཛཿ། སྔགས་འདི་དག་ནི་དྲན་བྱས་ན། །ཁ་གདངས་པ་དག་བྱས་པ་ཡིན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-444"/>Then, the blessed Vajra Yama’s Destroyer entered the meditative absorption called killing and extracting and spoke the mantra of Carcikā: <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-447"/>oṁ carcike siddhendranī­lahāriṇi ratna­trayāpakāriṇo rudiram ākarṣaya jaḥ |<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-448"/> “One should open their mouth And then call this mantra to mind.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-236">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-444</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇིག་རྟེན་གསུམ་གྱི་ཁྲག་ཆེན་པོ། །འགུགས་པ་འདི་ལ་ཐེ་ཚོམ་མེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The great blood from the three worlds Will be extracted, there is no doubt.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-237">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-451</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་རྡོ་རྗེ་གཤིན་རྗེའི་གཤེད་ཆེན་པོ་ཆང་འགུགས་པ་ཞེས་བྱ་བའི་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་ལ་སྙོམས་པར་ཞུགས་ཏེ། རྡོ་རྗེ་ཕག་མོའི་ཆང་འགུགས་པའི་སྔགས་གསུངས་པ། ཨོཾ་བཛྲ་གྷོ་ཎེ་སུགྷོ་ཎེ་བཛྲ་མཱ་མ་ཀཱི་བྷ་ར་བྷ་ར། སམྦྷ་ར་སམྦྷ་ར། ཏྲཻ་དྷཱ་ཏུ་ཀཱརྱཾ། ཨཱ་ཀརྵ་ཡ་ཛཿ། རྫ་མཁན་ལག་པ་ཕྱིས་པའི་སས། །བུམ་པ་ཁ་མཛེས་ཉེར་བྱས་ལ། །རྐུན་མའི་སྐྲ་ནི་རྟེན་བཞག་སྟེ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-451"/>Then, the blessed great Vajra Yamāri entered the meditative absorption called extracting alcohol and spoke Vajravārāhī’s mantra for extracting alcohol:<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-454"/> oṁ vajra­ghoṇe sughoṇe vajra­māmakī bhara bhara sambhara sambhara traidhātu­kāryam ākarṣaya jaḥ |<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-456"/> “One should make a pot with a beautiful mouth Using clay from a potter’s hand, Place it on a base of thief’s hair, And call the mantra to mind.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-238">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-459</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྔགས་ནི་རྗེས་སུ་དྲན་པར་བྱ། །སྔགས་འདི་ཆེ་བའི་བདག་ཉིད་འདི། །བ་ཏ་མཆོད་རྟེན་དག་ཏུ་བསྟན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-459"/>“The great quality of this mantra Was demonstrated at Caityapattana.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-239">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-459</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དལ་གྱིས་དམིགས་ནས་འབད་པར་བྱ། །ཆང་ནི་འགུགས་པར་རབ་ཏུ་གྲགས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>One should exert effort with gentle persistence And the alcohol extraction will be successful.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-240">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-462</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་དམ་ཚིག་ཆེན་པོའི་གཤིན་རྗེའི་གཤེད་རྡོ་རྗེ་ཤེས་རབ་ཀྱི་ཕ་རོལ་ཏུ་ཕྱིན་པ་ཞེས་བྱ་བའི་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་ལ་སྙོམས་པར་ཞུགས་ནས་རྡོ་རྗེ་དབྱངས་ཅན་མའི་སྔགས་གསུངས་པ། ཨོཾ་པི་ཙུ་པི་ཙུ་པྲཛྙཱ་བརྡྷ་ནི་ཛྭཱ་ལ་ཛྭཱ་ལ་མེ་དྷཱ་བརྡྷ་ནི། དྷི་ནི་དྷི་ནི། བུདྡྷི་བརྡྷ་ནི་སྭཱ་ཧཱ། ཚེས་ཀྱི་དང་པོ་ནས་བཟུང་སྟེ། །ཀུན་ཏུ་ཟླ་བ་ཉ་ཡི་བར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-462"/>Then the blessed Vajra Yama’s Slayer, the great samaya, entered the meditative absorption called the vajra perfection of wisdom and spoke the mantra of Sarasvatī: <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-464"/>oṁ picu picu prajñāvardhani jvala jvala medhā­vardhani dhiri dhiri buddhi­vardhani svāhā |<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-465"/> “Beginning on the first day And every day until the full moon, One should speak Sanskrit, And continue, following the phases of the moon.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-241">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-466</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྦྱར་བའི་སྐད་ནི་སྨྲ་བར་བྱ། །ཇི་སྲིད་ཟླ་བའི་རྗེས་འཇུག་པས། །རྟག་ཏུ་ཚིགས་བཅད་བརྒྱ་ཟིན་འདི། །ངག་གི་དབང་ཕྱུག་འགྲུབ་པར་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-466"/>“With the regular completion of one hundred ślokas One will succeed in becoming a lord of speech.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-242">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-466</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཁམས་གསུམ་མ་ལུས་པ་དག་ནི། །མ་ལུས་ལུས་པ་མེད་པར་འགྲུབ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>One will find success throughout the three worlds, Entirely and in every way.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-243">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-469</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་གཤིན་རྗེའི་གཤེད་རྡོ་རྗེས་ཁུ་བ་འགུགས་པ་ཞེས་བྱ་བའི་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་ལ་སྙོམས་པར་ཞུགས་ནས། ཁུ་བ་འགུགས་པར་བྱེད་པའི་གཽ་རཱིའི་སྔགས་འདི་གསུངས་སོ། །ཨོཾ་ཨཱཾ་ཀརྵ་ཎི་ཨཱ་ཀརྵ་ཎི་གོ་རཱི་ཧྲཱིཿདུཥྚཱ་ཡ། དུཥྚཱ་ཡ། ཤུ་ཀྲ་མ། ཨཱ་ཀརྵ་ཡ་ཛཿཛཿཛཿཧཱུཾ་ཧཱུཾ་ཧཱུཾ་སྭཱ་ཧཱ། པདྨ་ཁ་དང་རྡོ་རྗེ་དང་། །དྲིལ་བུ་ལྕགས་ཀྱུའི་རླུང་སྦྱོར་གྱིས། །བཟླས་དང་བསྒོམ་པའི་སྦྱོར་བ་ནི། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-469"/>Then, the blessed Vajra Yama’s Destroyer entered the meditative absorption called the extraction of semen and spoke Gaurī’s mantra for the extraction of semen:<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-473"/> oṁ ākarṣaṇi ākarṣaṇi gaurī hrīḥ duṣṭāya duṣṭāya śukram ākarṣaya jaḥ jaḥ jaḥ hūṁ hūṁ hūṁ svāhā |<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-475"/> “From the mouth of the lotus and from the vajra, Through the application of the bell, hook, and wind, An abundance of semen is extracted By employing mantra and meditation.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-244">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-477</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཁུ་བའི་ཚོགས་ནི་འགུགས་པར་བྱེད། །ནགས་ཀྱི་ནང་ངམ་དབེན་པ་རུ། །ལས་འདི་དག་ནི་བསྐུལ་བྱས་ནས། །ནུབ་བདུན་ཙམ་དུ་སྦྱོར་བ་ཡིས། །འགྲུབ་འགྱུར་འདི་ལ་ཐེ་ཚོམ་མེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-477"/>“These rites, eagerly employed Over the course of seven nights In a forest or isolated place, Bring success, of this there is no doubt.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-245">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-478</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་རྡོ་རྗེ་གཤིན་<tei:ref folio="F.142.a"/>རྗེའི་གཤེད་ཆེན་པོ། རྡོ་རྗེ་ནག་པོ་འཇིགས་པ་ཞེས་བྱ་བའི་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་ལ་སྙོམས་པར་ཞུགས་ནས་དབང་བསྐུར་བ་མཆོག་གི་དམ་ཚིག་འདི་ཉིད་ཀྱི་སྐུ་གསུང་ཐུགས་རྡོ་རྗེ་རྣམས་ལས་ཕྱུང་བར་མཛད་དོ། །ཨུ་དུམ་བཱ་ར་མ་ན་དཱ་ར། །པ་རི་ཛ་ཏ་ཀ་ཕྲེང་དང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-478"/>Then the blessed great Vajra Yamāri entered the meditative absorption called the vajra that terrifies death and set forth the samaya of the supreme initiation from his vajra body, speech, and mind.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-246">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-480</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཀར་ཎི་ཀ་ཡི་ཕྲེང་བ་ནི། །བུ་ཁྱོད་ཟུང་ལ་བྱིན་གྱིས་རློབ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-480"/>“Dear child, take garlands Of udumbara, mandāra, pārijāta, And karṇīkāra flowers, And be consecrated.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-247">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-482</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རལ་གྲི་ཆེན་པོ་ཁམས་གསུམ་པའི། །སངས་རྒྱས་ཀུན་གྱིས་ཕྱག་བྱས་པ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-482"/>“Take the great sword of the triple world That is venerated by all buddhas And summons all spirits.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-248">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-482</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འབྱུང་པོ་ཐམས་ཅད་འགུགས་པར་བྱེད། །ལས་ཀྱི་རལ་གྲི་དམ་པ་འདི། །བཟུང་ན་བདུད་ལས་རྒྱལ་བར་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>This sublime sword of activity Is victorious over all māras.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-249">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-484</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཤེས་རབ་ཐབས་ཀྱི་ངོ་བོ་ཉིད། །རྡོ་རྗེ་དྲིལ་བུ་བསྒྲུབས་པ་འདི། །ལོང་ལ་སློབ་མ་ཡང་དག་ཟུང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-484"/>“Take the perfected vajra and bell, The nature of insight and method, And accept the disciple.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-250">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-486</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཏུང་བ་རིན་པོ་ཆེ་འདིས་ནི། །རྡོ་རྗེ་ལུས་ནི་རབ་ཏུ་སྒྲུབ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-486"/>“This most precious of drinks Perfects the vajra body.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-251">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-486</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཀུན་ཏུ་ཡེ་ཤེས་བུ་ཁྱོད་ཀྱིས། །འཐུང་ཤིག་ཡེ་ཤེས་ལས་བྱུང་བ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Dear child of omniscient wisdom, Drink it so wisdom may arise.’</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-252">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-488</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སློབ་མའི་ཁར་ཡང་བླུག་བྱ་བ། །གཤིན་རྗེའི་གཤེད་ཀྱིས་བསྒྲགས་པ་ཡིན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-488"/>“It should then be poured into the disciple’s mouth, In order to accomplish Yamāri.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-253">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-488</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྡོ་རྗེ་སློབ་མ་བདག་ཉིད་ཆེས། །ཤིན་ཏུ་དགའ་བའི་སེམས་སུ་བྱ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The eminent vajra disciple Should cultivate feeling of great joy.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-254">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-491</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱི་སྐུ་གསུང་ཐུགས་གཤིན་རྗེའི་གཤེད་ནག་པོའི་རྒྱུད་ལས་དགུག་པ་ལ་སོགས་པའི་སྦྱོར་བའི་རིམ་པར་ཕྱེ་བ་སྟེ་བདུན་པའོ།། །།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-491"/>This was the seventh chapter, “The Procedures for Extraction and So Forth,” from The Tantra of Black Yamāri, the Body, Speech, and Mind of All Tathāgatas.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-255">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-493</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་རྡོ་རྗེ་འཛིན་རྒྱལ་པོ། །སྲུང་བའི་འཁོར་ལོ་སྦྱོར་བར་བྱེད། །བགེགས་དང་ལོག་པར་འདྲེན་པ་དང་། །གདུག་པ་ཅན་དག་བསལ་ཕྱིར་གསུངས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-section-1-8"/>Chapter 8: The Fire Offering Rite<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-493"/> Then, the vajra-bearing king Employed the protection circle procedure And spoke in order to expel Vighnas, vināyakas, and wicked beings.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-256">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-494</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དཔལ་ལྡན་རལ་གྲི་འཆང་བའི་བདག །སྲུང་བའི་འཁོར་ལོ་སྦྱོར་བར་བྱེད། །རལ་གྲི་འབར་བའི་བདག་ཉིད་ཀྱིས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-494"/>“I, the glorious sword bearer, Employ the protection circle procedure Using the naturally blazing sword.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-257">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-494</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རིག་པ་གསུམ་ལས་མཆོད་པར་བྱེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>I offer worship through the three knowledges.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-258">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-496</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སེམས་ཅན་ཐམས་ཅད་སྐྱོབ་པ་ཡི། །སྤྱོད་པའི་ཚུལ་དང་ཁྱད་པར་གྱིས། །ས་དང་ཕ་རོལ་ཕྱིན་པ་ལ། །ལྷ་མོ་ཁྱོད་ནི་དཔང་དུ་གྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-496"/>“Devī, you serve as witness To the mode of conduct That protects all beings, Especially to the bhūmis and perfections.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-259">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-498</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཤིན་རྗེའི་གཤེད་ཀྱི་དཀྱིལ་འཁོར་ནི། །སློབ་དཔོན་བདག་གིས་དཀྱིལ་འཁོར་བྲི། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-498"/>“I, the master, will draw The maṇḍala of Yamāri.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-260">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-499</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གོས་ཀྱིས་གདོང་ནི་བཅིངས་བྱས་ལ། །དཀྱིལ་འཁོར་གྱི་ནི་མདུན་སྐོར་བཞག །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-499"/>“After covering the disciple’s face with cloth, They should enter the door of the maṇḍala.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-261">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-499</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཁྱོད་སུ་ཞེས་ཀྱང་འདི་སྐད་དྲི། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They should be asked, ‘Who are you?’</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-262">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-499</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྐལ་བཟང་བདག་ཅེས་ཚིག་ཏུ་བརྗོད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>To which they reply, ‘I am a fortunate one.’</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-263">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-501</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གསོལ་བཏབ་པ་ཡི་བློ་བཟང་ལ། །ཡོལ་བའི་ནང་དུ་སྦྱིན་པར་བྱ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-501"/>“The keen disciple who makes the request Should be given access behind the curtain.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-264">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-502</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དབང་བསྐུར་དོན་དུ་གུས་ཆེན་པོས། །དེ་ནས་ལན་གསུམ་ཆེད་དུ་བརྗོད། །ཇི་ལྟར་སངས་རྒྱས་ཆོས་ཆེན་པོས། །རྡོ་རྗེ་སེམས་དཔའ་དབང་བསྐུར་ལྟར། །བདག་<tei:ref folio="F.142.b"/>ཀྱང་མགོན་པོས་དབང་བསྐུར་ཞིང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>In order to receive initiation they should Make this request devotedly three times: <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-502"/>“ ‘Just as the Buddha initiated the vajra-being By means of the great Dharma, I ask the protector to also initiate me, And grant me a boon.’</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-265">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-504</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མཆོག་ཀྱང་བདག་ལ་སྩལ་དུ་གསོལ། །དེ་བཞིན་གླུ་དང་རོལ་མོས་མཆོད། །དེ་བཞིན་ཁྲུས་དང་བྱུག་པས་ཀྱང་། །སློབ་མ་དང་བས་བླུག་པར་བྱ། །དེ་ལ་བསྟོད་པ་ཀུན་ཀྱང་བྱ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-504"/>“The disciple should offer song and music, As well as respectfully anoint With bathing water and unguents, And sing praises at that time.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-266">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-506</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་རྡོ་རྗེ་འཆང་གི་རྒྱལ་པོས་སྟོང་པའི་སྔགས་གསུངས་པ། །ཨོྃ་ཤཱུ་ནྱཏཱ་ཛྙཱ་ན་བཛྲ་སྭ་བྷཱ་ཝ་ཨཱཏྨ་ཀོ྅ཧྃ། ཨོྃ་པཱུ་ཛ་བཛྲ་སྭབྷཱ་བ་ཨཱཏྨ་ཀོ྅ཧཾ། ཨོྃ་དྷརྨ་དྷཱ་ཏུ་བཛྲ་སྭབྷཱ་བ་ཨཱཏྨ་ཀོ྅ཧཾ། ཞི་བ་ལ་སོགས་དབྱེ་བ་ཡི། །སྦྱིན་སྲེག་དེ་ནས་བཤད་པར་བྱ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-506"/>Then, the vajra-bearing king spoke the mantra of emptiness:<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-507"/> oṁ śūnyatājñāna­vajra­svabhāvātmako ’ham |<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-508"/> oṁ pūja­vajra­svabhāvātmako ’ham |<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-510"/> oṁ dharma­dhātu­vajra­svabhāvātmako ’ham |<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-511"/> “Next, I will explain the fire offering, Based on its use in pacifying and other rites.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-267">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-506</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྦྱིན་སྲེག་གང་གིས་གྲུབ་པ་ཡི། །ལས་རྣམས་ཐམས་ཅད་རབ་སྒྲུབ་པ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>It is through fire offering that one gains the siddhi That accomplishes all rites.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-268">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-512</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཞི་བ་ཞི་བའི་སེམས་ཀྱིས་ཏེ། །རྒྱས་པ་རྒྱས་པའི་སེམས་ཀྱིས་སོ། །དབང་ཡང་དེར་གཏང་སེམས་ཀྱིས་ཏེ། །བསད་དང་བསྐྲད་པ་ལ་ཡང་ངོ་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-512"/>“Pacifying rites require a peaceful mind, Enriching rites, an expansive mind, Enthralling rites, a mind that has let go, And this too for killing and expelling.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-269">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-515</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཞི་བའི་དཀྱིལ་འཁོར་ཟླུམ་པོ་སྟེ། །རྒྱས་པ་ཡི་ནི་རྫིང་བུ་འདྲ། །དབང་དུ་བྱ་བ་ཟླ་གམ་ལྟར། །ནམ་མཁའི་ཁམས་འདྲ་བས་ནི་བསད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-515"/>“For the pacifying, the fire pit is circular, For enriching, like a water tank, For enthralling, crescent-shaped, And like the space element for killing.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-270">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-519</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཞི་བ་ཁྲུ་གང་ཚད་དུ་སྟེ། །དེ་བཞིན་རྒྱས་པའི་ཁྲུ་དོ་པ། །ཇི་ལྟར་རྒྱས་པ་དེ་ལྟར་དབང་། །བསད་པ་ལ་ནི་སོར་ཉི་ཤུ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-519"/>“For pacifying, it should measure one cubit, For enriching, two cubits, As for enriching, so for enthralling, And for killing, twenty finger-widths.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-271">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-521</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཞི་བ་སྟེང་དུ་ཁྲུ་ཕྱེད་ཚད། །རྒྱུས་པ་ལ་ནི་ཁྲུ་ཙམ་སྟེ། །སོར་ལྔ་གཉིས་ནི་བསད་པ་ལ། །དབང་ལ་ཇི་ལྟར་དེ་བཞིན་དགུག །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-521"/>“For pacifying, half a cubit up, For enriching, one cubit, Ten finger-widths for killing, And for enthralling, the same as summoning.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-272">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-525</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཚེས་གཅིག་ལ་ནི་ཞི་བ་བྱ། །ཟླ་བ་ཉ་ལ་རྒྱས་པ་སྟེ། །བཅུ་བཞི་ལ་ནི་མངོན་སྤྱོད་དོ། །དབང་གི་ལས་ནི་ཚེས་བརྒྱད་ལའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-525"/>“Pacifying should be performed on the first day, Enriching on the full moon, The fourteenth day for hostile rites, And enthralling rites on the eighth day.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-273">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-526</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱི་སྐུ་གསུང་ཐུགས་གཤིན་རྗེའི་གཤེད་ནག་པོའི་རྒྱུད་ལས་སྦྱིན་སྲེག་གི་ཆོ་ག་རིམ་པར་ཕྱེ་བ་སྟེ་བརྒྱད་པའོ།། །།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-526"/>This was the eighth chapter, “The Fire Offering Rite,” from The Tantra of Black Yamāri, the Body, Speech, and Mind of All Tathāgatas.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-274">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-528</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྒྱ་མཚོའི་ས་ནི་བླངས་བྱས་ལ། །ཀླུ་ཡི་གཟུགས་གཅིག་བརྩམས་བྱས་ཏེ། །ཡི་གེ་ཧཱུྃ་ཕུཿསྙིང་གར་ནི། །ཧྲཱིཿཥྚྲཱིཿལ་སོགས་བཟླས་པ་བྱ། །ཆར་ནི་མི་འབབ་དུས་དག་ཏུ། །བཟླས་པ་ཁྲི་བྱས་འབབ་པར་འགྱུར། །སྦྲུལ་ནག་པོ་ཡི་ཤ་དང་ནི། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-section-1-9"/>Chapter 9: Fearsome Yamāri<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-528"/> “One should take soil from the ocean, Make an image of a single nāga, Place the syllables hūṁ puḥ at its heart, And recite the mantra that begins hrīḥ ṣṭrīḥ.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-275">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-531</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ནིམ་པའི་ལོ་མ་དང་བསྲེས་ལ། །དེ་ལ་རིལ་བུ་བྱས་ནས་ནི། །བརྟུལ་ཞུགས་ཅན་གྱིས་རྒྱ་མཚོར་གཞུག །སྔགས་ཀྱི་བཟླས་པ་ཁྲི་བྱས་ན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Rain will fall at times of drought By reciting the mantra ten thousand times, <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-531"/>“The vow-holder should mix cobra meat With leaves of the neem tree, Roll the mixture into a pill, Throw it into the ocean, And recite the mantra ten thousand times.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-276">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-531</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མཚོ་རླབས་རེངས་བྱེད་མཆོག་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>This is the supreme means for arresting waves.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-277">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-532</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཙནྡན་འབྲས་བུ་བརྒྱ་བླངས་ལ། །འབྲས་དང་མར་ཤས་བསྲེས་བྱས་ཏེ། །འབུམ་ཕྲག་བརྒྱ་ནི་རབ་བཟླས་ལ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-532"/>“One should take one hundred datura seeds, Mixed with beans and rice grains, And perform a fire offering with 800,000 recitations.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-278">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-532</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྦྱིན་སྲེག་བྱས་ན་ལྷ་མཐོང་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>One will then behold the deity.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-279">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-1318</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དུར་ཁྲོད་རོ་བསྲེགས་ཡོག་པའི་ཤིང་། །བརྟུལ་<tei:ref folio="F.143.a"/>ཞུགས་ཅན་གྱི་གཟུགས་སུ་བྲི། །སྨྱོན་པའི་ཁུ་བས་བསྐུ་བྱས་ལ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-1318"/>“The vow-holder should draw an effigy With charred stick from a cremation pyre And smear it with datura fluid.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-280">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-1318</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྔགས་ཁྲི་བཟླས་པས་མཛེས་ཐེབས་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>After reciting the mantra 10,000 times the target will develop leprosy.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-281">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-537</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གྲུབ་པའི་ཡུངས་ཀར་བླངས་བྱས་ལ། །འབུམ་ཕྲག་བཞི་ནི་བཟླས་བྱས་ན། །སྦྲུལ་གྱིས་བཟུང་ནས་འགྱེལ་བ་ལ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-537"/>“One should take white mustard seeds, Recite the mantra 400,000 times, And scatter them over a person collapsed from snake bite.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-282">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-537</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཏོར་ན་འཚོ་བར་ཐེ་ཚོམ་མེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>That person will recover—there is no doubt.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-283">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-539</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རི་གཤོང་ཆུ་ཡི་ས་བླངས་ལ། །སྔགས་ཀྱི་བཟླས་པ་འབུམ་བྱས་ནས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-539"/>“One should take clay from a gulch And recite the mantra 100,000 times.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-284">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-539</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མགོ་ལ་བསྐུས་པ་ཙམ་གྱིས་ནི། །མགོ་ཡི་ནད་ནི་ཉམས་པར་བྱེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Any headache will be cured By smearing this on one’s head.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-285">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-540</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྔགས་ནི་ལན་བདུན་མངོན་བཟླས་པའི། །ལག་པས་མགོ་བོ་མཉེས་ན་ནི། །མགོ་ནི་ཟུག་གཟེར་འབྱུང་མི་འགྱུར། །དེ་ནི་འདི་ལྟར་ཐེ་ཚོམ་མེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-540"/>“When one incants their hand seven times And uses it to rub their head, There will be no head pain— About this there is no doubt.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-286">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-541</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྲམ་ཟེ་ཡི་ནི་ཤ་དག་ལ། །དུར་ཁྲོད་ས་དང་ཐལ་བ་ལས། །གཤིན་རྗེའི་གཤེད་ཀྱི་གཟུགས་བྱས་ཏེ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-541"/>“One should make an effigy of Yamāri From the flesh of a brahmin And ash and soil from a charnel ground.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-287">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-541</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཕྱག་གཉིས་ཞལ་ནི་གཅིག་པ་ལ། །རྡོ་རྗེ་ཆེན་པོ་གཡས་པ་ན། །དེ་བཞིན་མི་མགོ་གཡོན་པ་ནའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He should have two arms and one face, Hold a large vajra in his right hand, And a human head in his left.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-288">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-541</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མདོག་ནི་དཀར་པོ་ཆེར་འཇིགས་པ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He should be white and very frightening.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-289">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-541</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ཡིས་གདུག་པ་འཇོམས་པར་བྱེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>All wicked beings can be destroyed with this.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-290">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-543</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བདུད་རྩི་ལྔ་དང་ཤ་ལྔ་ཡིས། །ཉིན་རེ་བཞིན་དུ་གཏོར་མ་སྦྱིན། །བདག་གི་དགྲ་བོ་ཆོམས་ཤིག་ཅེས། །རྣལ་འབྱོར་པས་བདག་གསོལ་བ་གདབ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-543"/>“The yogin should offer bali daily, Using the five meats and the five nectars, And the make the request, ‘Annihilate my enemies!’</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-291">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-544</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ནུབ་མོ་དེ་སྐད་བརྗོད་པས་ཉལ། །དགྲ་ནི་ཐོ་རངས་འཆི་བར་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-544"/>“When this is said at night, before sleep, The enemy will be dead at dawn.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-292">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-544</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཆུ་འགགས་ལ་སོགས་པས་གཟིར་ཞིང་། །ཡང་ན་ནད་ཀྱིས་ཐེབས་པར་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Or they will suffer from urinary blockage Or fall sick with another illness.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-293">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-546</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དགྲ་ཡི་བཻ་རོ་ཙ་ན་བླང་། །མི་ཡི་རྐང་སྦུབས་ཡོངས་བཀང་སྟེ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-546"/>“One should take the enemy’s vairocanā And fill a human bone with it.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-294">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-546</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རབ་ཏུ་བཀང་ནས་འབུམ་བཟླས་ན། །ཤིང་རྩེར་རྒྱུ་བའི་ཡི་དགས་མཚུངས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Once full, and once the mantra is recited 100,000 times, One will be like a preta moving through treetops.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-295">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-546</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལྷ་རྫས་དངོས་གྲུབ་ཀུན་བྱེད་ཅིང་། །དགོས་པ་སྣ་ཚོགས་རབ་སྒྲུབ་བོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>One will attain every excellent siddhi And achieve the various goals.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-296">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-549</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱི་སྐུ་གསུང་ཐུགས་གཤིན་རྗེའི་གཤེད་ནག་པོའི་རྒྱུད་ལས་འཇིགས་བྱེད་གཤིན་རྗེའི་གཤེད་ཅེས་བྱ་བའི་རིམ་པར་ཕྱེ་པ་སྟེ་དགུ་བའོ།། །།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-549"/>This was the ninth chapter, “Fearsome Yamāri,” from The Tantra of Black Yamāri, the Body, Speech, and Mind of All Tathāgatas.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-297">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-552</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རོ་ལངས་ཆེན་པོའི་སྒྲུབ་ཐབས་ནི། །དེ་ནས་ཡང་དག་བཤད་པར་བྱ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-section-1-10"/>Chapter 10: Cultivating the Recollection for Mastering Vetālas<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-552"/> “Next, I will perfectly explain The sādhana of the great vetāla.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-298">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-552</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྒྲུབ་པ་བཟང་པོ་ཀུན་བྱེད་ཅིང་། །དགོས་པ་སྣ་ཚོགས་རབ་སྒྲུབ་པའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>It effects every excellent siddhi And leads to the achievement of the various goals.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-299">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-554</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཟང་པོ་མ་གོད་རྨ་མེད་པ། །ཤིང་ལ་སྦྱངས་པས་བསྡུས་བྱས་ལ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-554"/>“The vow-holder should find a corpse hanging from a tree— A corpse that is clean, unspoiled, and without wounds.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-300">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-554</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཕབ་ལ་ལེགས་པར་བཀྲུ་བྱ་སྟེ། །དེར་འདུག་སྔགས་བཟླས་བརྟུལ་ཞུགས་ཅན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They should take it down, wash it well, And incant it with mantra where it lays.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-301">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-556</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཨེ་མའོ་ངོ་མཚར་སྔགས་ཀྱི་མཐུ། །བསམ་པ་མེད་པའི་འོ་དོད་འབོད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-556"/>“Amazing, the power of mantra Whereby the insensate cries out!</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-302">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-556</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཤིན་རྗེའི་རྣལ་འབྱོར་ལྡན་པ་ཡི། །ཡིད་ཀྱིས་ཅུང་ཟད་འཇིགས་མི་བྱ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The one who practices the yoga of Yamāri Should be entirely without fear.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-303">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-556</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྣལ་འབྱོར་<tei:ref folio="F.143.b"/>ལམ་ནི་གང་འདོར་པ། །དེ་ཀུན་ཐམས་ཅད་སྟེར་བར་བྱེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Whatever it is the yogin seeks Will be bestowed in full.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-304">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-559</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྟག་དང་དེ་ལས་གཞན་པ་དང་། །དོམ་དང་སྤྲེའུ་དག་ལ་ནི། །ཁྱི་དག་གི་ནི་ཁྱད་པར་དང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-559"/>“One should craft an effigy Of Yamāri’s terrifying form, From the flesh, of a buffalo and crocodile, As well as a tiger, A bear, a monkey, And specifically, a dog.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-305">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-559</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དུག་དག་སྐེ་ཚེ་ཚྭ་དང་ནི། །དེ་བཞིན་ཚྭ་གསུམ་སོ་པཉྫ། །འདི་དག་ལེགས་པར་སྦྱར་གཟུགས་བྱ། །གཤིན་རྗེའི་གཤེད་པོ་འཇིགས་པའི་གཟུགས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>One should also use poison, black mustard seeds, salt, The three hot spices, and the moringa tree.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-306">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-562</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ལ་རྣལ་འབྱོར་པས་གསོལ་གདབ། །ཧྲཱིཿཥྚྲཱིཿལ་སོགས་སྔགས་ཀྱིས་ནི། །ཆེ་གེ་མོ་དེ་བདག་ལ་སྩོལ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-562"/>“The yogi should make a request of this effigy Using the mantra beginning hrīḥ ṣṭrīḥ And saying, ‘I seek so-and-so.’</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-307">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-562</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ཡི་ཕ་ཡིས་སྟེར་བར་བྱེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Her father will then present her.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-308">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-563</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གལ་ཏེ་རྣལ་འབྱོར་པ་མ་ཕྱིན། །རྨི་ལམ་གཤིན་རྗེའི་གཤེད་བརྡེག་ཅིང་། །ལྷོ་ཡི་ཕྱོགས་སུ་ཁྱེར་མཐོང་ནས། །སད་ན་དེ་ཡི་ཕ་ཡིས་སྟེར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-563"/>“If this does not come to pass, If the yogin sees Yamāri strike her in a dream, And carry her off to the south, Her father will present her when the yogin wakes.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-309">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-564</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཞལ་གསུམ་ཕྱག་དྲུག་འཇིགས་པ་ལ། །ཨིནྡྲ་ནཱི་ལ་འདྲ་བའི་མདོག །ཐོ་བ་འཛིན་པའི་བརྟུལ་ཞུགས་ཅན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-564"/>“The vow-holder should visualize Mudgara Yamāri As fearsome, with three faces and six arms.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-310">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-564</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཕྱག་ཏུ་ཐོ་བ་དགོད་པར་བྱ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He has the appearance of a sapphire And has a hammer in his hand.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-311">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-567</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཞལ་གསུམ་ཕྱག་དྲུག་ཁྲོས་པ་ལ། །མདོག་དམར་པོ་སྟེ་ཁྲོས་པར་འཇིགས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-567"/>“Daṇḍa Yamāri has three faces and six arms, And is red, wrathful, and terrifying.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-312">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-567</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇིགས་པ་ཡང་ནི་འཇིགས་པར་མཛད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Terrifying even to the terrifying.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-313">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-567</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མཁས་པས་ཕྱག་ཏུ་དབྱིག་པ་དགོད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The adept should place a cudgel in his hand.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-314">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-568</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཞལ་གསུམ་ཕྱག་དྲུག་དམར་བ་ལ། །འཇིགས་པ་ཆེན་པོ་བསྡིགས་པ་ཡི། །ཕྱག་ན་པདྨ་དམར་པོ་བསྣམས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-568"/>“The adept should visualize the one called Padma Yamāri. He has three faces, six arms, and is red in color; He is extremely frightening, terrifying, And holds a red lotus in his hand.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-315">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-570</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>པདྨ་ཞེས་བྱ་མཁས་པས་བསྒོམ། །ཞལ་གསུམ་ཕྱག་དྲུག་ལྗང་གུ་སྟེ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-570"/>“One should visualize the one called Khaḍga Yamāri, Who has three faces, six arms, and is green.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-316">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-570</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཕྱག་ན་རལ་གྲི་བསྣམས་པ་ཡི། །ལས་ཀུན་བྱེད་པར་གྱུར་པའོ། །རལ་གྲི་ཞེས་བྱ་རྣམ་བསྒོམ་བྱ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He accomplishes all activities And holds a sword in his hand.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-317">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-571</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྷ་གར་ལིང་ག་རྣམ་བསྒོམ་ཉིད། །དཀྱིལ་འཁོར་བདག་པོ་རྣམ་པར་བསྒོམ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-571"/>“With one’s liṅga in the bhaga, One should visualize the lord of the maṇḍala.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-318">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-571</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཞེ་སྡང་རྗེས་དྲན་རྣལ་འབྱོར་གྱིས། །གཏི་མུག་རྗེས་དྲན་རྣམ་བསྒོམ་བྱ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The yogin who has brought anger to mind Should cultivate the recollection of ignorance.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-319">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-574</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཏི་མུག་རྗེས་དྲན་ལ་དམིགས་ནས། །ཕྲ་མ་རྗེས་དྲན་བསྒོམ་པར་བྱ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-574"/>“After making ignorance the object of recollection, One should cultivate the recollection of miserliness.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-320">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-574</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཕྲ་མ་རྗེས་དྲན་རྣལ་འབྱོར་གྱིས། །འདོད་ཆགས་རྗེས་དྲན་བསྒོམ་པར་བྱ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The one absorbed in recollecting miserliness Should next cultivate the recollection of desire.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-321">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-575</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདོད་ཆགས་རྗེས་དྲན་རྣལ་འབྱོར་གྱིས། །ཕྲག་དོག་དྲན་བྱ་བརྟུལ་ཞུགས་ཅན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-575"/>“The vow-holder immersed in recollecting desire Should recollect the one called jealousy.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-322">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-575</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སོ་སོའི་རིགས་ཀྱི་སྤྲིན་རྣམས་ནི། །བ་སྤུའི་ཁུང་ནས་སྤྲོ་བར་བྱ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Clouds of deities from each of their families Emanate from their pores.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-323">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-577</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཉི་མའི་དཀྱིལ་འཁོར་དབུས་སུ་ནི། །གཏུམ་པོའི་ཁྲོ་བོ་བསྒོམ་པར་བྱ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-577"/>“The four wrathful ones should be visualized Standing in the center of sun disks.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-324">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-577</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཟླ་བའི་དཀྱིལ་འཁོར་དབུས་སུ་ནི། །ལྷ་མོ་བཞི་པོ་རབ་བསྒོམ་བྱ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The four goddesses should be visualized Standing on moon disks.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-325">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-580</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱི་སྐུ་གསུང་ཐུགས་གཤིན་རྗེའི་གཤེད་ནག་པོའི་རྒྱུད་ལས་རྗེས་སུ་དྲན་པ་རིམ་པར་ཕྱེ་བ་སྟེ་བཅུ་བའོ།། །།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-580"/>This was the tenth chapter, “Cultivating the Recollection for Mastering Vetālas,” from The Tantra of Black Yamāri, the Body, Speech, and Mind of All Tathāgatas.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-326">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-583</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཞེ་སྡང་གིས་མནན་འགྲོ་མཐོང་ནས། །ཞེ་སྡང་གཤིན་རྗེའི་<tei:ref folio="F.144.a"/>གཤེད་གཟུགས་སུ། །བཅོམ་ལྡན་གཤིན་རྗེའི་དབང་དུ་མཛད། །ཞེ་སྡང་ཐམས་ཅད་ཟད་པར་བྱེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-section-1-11"/>Chapter 11: Revealing the Conduct<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-583"/> “Seeing that beings are overcome with hatred, The Bhagavat, taking the form of Dveṣa Yamāri, Brings Yama under control And lays waste to all hatred.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-327">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-585</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཏི་མུག་གིས་མནན་འགྲོ་མཐོང་ནས། །གཏི་མུག་གཤིན་རྗེའི་གཤེད་གཟུགས་སུ། །བཅོམ་ལྡན་གཤིན་རྗེའི་དབང་མཛད་ནས། །གཏི་མུག་ཐམས་ཅད་ཟད་པར་མཛད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-585"/>“Seeing that beings are overcome with ignorance, The Bhagavat, taking the form of Moha Yamāri, Brings Yama under control And lays waste to all ignorance.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-328">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-587</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འགྲོ་བ་ཕྲ་མས་མནན་མཐོང་ནས། །ཕྲ་མ་གཤིན་རྗེའི་གཤེད་གཟུགས་སུ། །བཅོམ་ལྡན་སྙིང་རྗེ་ཅན་གྱིས་མཛད། །ཕྲ་མ་ཐམས་ཅད་ཟད་པར་མཛད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-587"/>“Seeing that beings are overcome with miserliness, The Bhagavat, moved by compassion, Takes the form of Piśuna Yamāri And lays waste to all miserliness.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-329">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-588</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདོད་ཆགས་ཀྱིས་མནན་འགྲོ་མཐོང་ནས། །འདོད་ཆགས་གཤིན་རྗེའི་གཤེད་གཟུགས་སུ། །བཅོམ་ལྡན་སྙིང་རྗེ་ཅན་མཛད་ནས། །འདོད་ཆགས་ཐམས་ཅད་ཟད་པར་མཛད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-588"/>“Seeing that beings are overcome with desire, The Bhagavat, moved by compassion, Takes the form of Rāga Yamāri And lays waste to all desire.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-330">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-589</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཕྲག་དོག་གིས་མནན་འགྲོ་མཐོང་ནས། །ཕྲག་དོག་གཤིན་རྗེའི་གཤེད་གཟུགས་སུ། །བཅོམ་ལྡན་སྙིང་རྗེ་ཅན་མཛད་ནས། །ཕྲག་དོག་ཐམས་ཅད་ཟད་པར་མཛད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-589"/>“Seeing that beings are overcome with jealousy, The Bhagavat, moved by compassion, Takes the form of Īrṣyā Yamāri And lays waste to all jealousy.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-331">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-590</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱམས་པ་ཙརྩི་ཀཱར་གསུངས་ཏེ། །སྙིང་རྗེ་དེ་བཞིན་ཕག་མོའོ། །དབྱངས་ཅན་མ་ནི་དགའ་བ་སྟེ། །བཏང་སྙོམས་གཽ་རཱིའི་གཟུགས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-590"/>“Carcikā is said to be love, Vārāhī is compassion, Sarasvatī is joy, While Gaurī embodies equanimity.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-332">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-591</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བདག་ཉིད་དངོས་པོ་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱིས། །རྫོགས་པར་བྱས་ནས་དཀྱིལ་འཁོར་གྱི། །རྣལ་འབྱོར་སྙིང་གའི་ས་བོན་སྤྲོ། །འགྲུབ་པར་འདི་ལ་ཐེ་ཚོམ་མེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-591"/>“The yogin, themselves perfected As all those present in the maṇḍala, Radiates from the seed syllable and their hearts; Success ensues, there is no doubt.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-333">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-594</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་ད་ནི་བཤད་བྱ་བ། །སྤྱོད་པ་ཡི་ནི་མཚན་ཉིད་མཆོག །གཤིན་རྗེའི་གཤེད་པོ་འཇིགས་གཟུགས་ཀྱིས། །སྐུ་དང་གསུང་དང་ཐུགས་སུ་འགྲུབ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-594"/>“I will now explain The supreme qualities of the conduct That perfects body, speech, and mind Through Yamāri’s terrifying form.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-334">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-596</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དགོན་པ་ཆེན་པོའི་ས་ཕྱོགས་སུ། །མ་ཧེ་མཆོག་ནི་བཀུག་ལ་ཞོན། །སྦྲུལ་དག་གིས་ནི་བརྒྱན་པར་བྱ། །ལྕགས་ཀྱི་རྡོ་རྗེ་གཟུགས་པར་བྱ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-596"/>“In a vastly forested area, One should call and mount a supreme buffalo, Adorn themselves with snakes, And take up an iron vajra.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-335">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-598</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྐྲ་ཡང་སེར་པོ་དག་ཏུ་བྱ། །གྱེན་བརྫེས་པ་ཡི་ཁྱད་པར་གྱིས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-598"/>“One should also turn their hair yellow, Which should specifically flow upwards.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-336">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-598</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མགོ་ལ་ཐོད་པས་ཡང་དག་བསྐོར། །སྨ་ར་ལྐོག་སྤུ་སེར་པོར་བྱ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Skulls should ring their head And their beard should be turned yellow.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-337">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-600</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཧྲཱིཿཥྚྲཱིཿལ་སོགས་སྔགས་བརྗོད་ཅིང་། །ལྕགས་ཀྱི་རྡོ་རྗེ་མཁའ་ལ་གསོར། །རྡོ་རྗེ་གཤིན་རྗེའི་གཤེད་སྦྱོར་བས། །སེང་གེའི་སྒྲ་ཡང་དེ་ལ་བྱ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-600"/>“While brandishing the iron vajra, One should recite the mantra beginning hrīḥ ṣṭrīḥ And roar a lion’s roar, While applying the practice of Vajra Yamāri.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-338">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-601</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ནུས་པ་ཅུང་ཟད་སྐྱེས་པ་ན། །རོལ་ཅིང་གྲོང་དུ་འཇུག་པར་བྱ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-601"/>“Once a little power develops, One should playfully enter a village.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-339">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-601</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གར་དང་བདེ་བའི་ཆ་ཀུན་གྱིས། །དྲུག་ལས་སྐྱེད་སོགས་གླུ་བླང་བྱ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>One should dance and ecstatically sing Songs using ṣāḍava and other scales.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-340">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-603</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་རྒྱལ་མཚན་ཁྱམས་མཐོང་ན། །དེར་ནི་འོ་མ་རབ་བསྒྲུབ་བྱ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-603"/>“Seeing a row of banners, One should perfect the milk there.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-341">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-603</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འོ་མ་ལ་སེམས་གཅིག་གོམས་པས། །ཕྱག་རྒྱ་ཆེན་པོ་རབ་བསྒྲུབ་བྱ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>By focusing one-pointedly on the milk, One will attain mahāmudrā.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-342">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-606</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཕག་མོ་ཡི་ནི་གཟུགས་བཟུང་བའི། །<tei:ref folio="F.144.b"/>བཙུན་མོ་ཀུན་ལ་འཁྱུད་པ་ཡིས། །དཔའ་མོ་སེང་གེ་བཞིན་དུ་སྤྱད། །འདོད་པའི་དོན་ཀུན་རབ་ཏུ་འགྲུབ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-606"/>“By embracing any woman Who has taken the form of Vārāhī, The courageous one acts like a lion And accomplishes all desired aims.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-343">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-609</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་ད་ནི་བཤད་བྱ་བ། །ཕྱག་རྒྱ་མ་ནི་རབ་སྒྲུབ་ཐབས། །གསང་སྔགས་ཆེན་པོ་ཡི་གེ་གཅིག །དེ་ཡི་བཟླས་པ་མངོན་པར་བཤད་བྱ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-609"/>“Next, I will explain The method for the Hundred-Armed One And will describe the recitation Of the great one-syllable mantra.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-344">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-611</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡི་གེ་ཧྲཱིཿལས་བྱུང་བ་ཡི། །མ་ཧེ་ཡང་དག་བསྒོམ་བྱ་སྟེ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-611"/>“One should visualize the Buffalo-Faced One Manifesting from the syllable hrīḥ.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-345">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-611</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྡོ་རྗེ་དཀྱིལ་འཁོར་ལ་གནས་པ། །མ་ཧེ་སྟེང་དུ་བསྒོམ་པར་བྱ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He stands on a vajra maṇḍala And is mounted on a buffalo.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-346">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-1319</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་ཡང་ཅུང་ཟད་གཅོད་ཅིང་འབིགས། །མཚོན་ཆ་སྣ་ཚོགས་གཟུགས་དེ་ནི། །མ་ཧེ་སྣ་ཚོགས་བསྒྲུབ་པ་ཡི། །བློ་དང་ལྡན་པའི་ཕྱག་ན་བསྣམས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-1319"/>“The adept who practices The mantra of the Buffalo-Faced One Should imagine him holding various weapons— Those that cut and those that pierce.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-347">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-616</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་ཡང་དག་བཤད་བྱ་བ། །དབྱིག་པ་གཤིན་རྗེའི་གཤེད་སྒྲུབ་ཐབས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-616"/>“Next, I will explain, The practice of Daṇḍa Yamāri.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-348">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-616</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡི་གེ་ཧྲཱིཿནི་གསང་སྔགས་ཆེ། །མ་ཧེ་ཆེན་པོ་ལ་བཅིབས་པ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The syllable hrīḥ is his great mantra And he has a buffalo as his mount.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-349">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-617</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཕྱག་ནི་འབུམ་ཕྲག་རྫོགས་པའི་ཕྱག །སྐུ་ནི་མི་རོའི་ཐལ་བས་བསྐུས། །རི་རབ་དང་ནི་མཉམ་པའི་ལུས། །གསེར་གྱི་ས་གཞི་ཐུག་པར་མནན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-617"/>“He is arrayed with two-hundred-thousand arms And his body, smeared with human ashes, Is as high as Mount Sumeru And reaches down to the golden ground.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-350">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-619</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་ཡང་དག་བཤད་བྱ་བ། །བྱེ་བའི་ཕྱག་ཅན་སྒྲུབ་པའི་ཐབས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-619"/>“Next, I will explain The method for the Ten-Million-Armed One.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-351">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-619</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡི་གེ་ཧཱུྃ་ལས་བྱུང་བའི་གཙོ། །ཝིཀྲྀ་ཏཱ་ན་གསང་སྔགས་ཆེ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He is the lord arisen from the syllable hūṁ And vikṛtānana is his great mantra.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-352">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-620</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཨོྃ་ཧྲཱིཿཥྚྲཱིཿཝིཀྲྀ་ཏཱ་ནན་ཧཱུྃ་ཧཱུྃ་ཕཊ་ཕཊ་ཧ་ཧཱ་ཧི་ཧཱི་ཧུ་ཧཱུ་ཧེ་ཧཻ་ཧཽ་ཧྃ་ཧཿཕཊ་སྭཱ་ཧཱ། དགོས་པ་ཐམས་ཅད་བསྒྲུབ་པ་ཡི། །དམ་ཚིག་སྒྲུབ་ཐབས་བཤད་པར་བྱ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-620"/>oṁ hrīḥ ṣṭrīḥ vikṛtānana hūṁ hūṁ phaṭ phaṭ ha hā hi hī hu hū he hai ho hau haṁ haḥ phaṭ svāhā |<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-621"/> “I will explain the samaya practice That accomplishes all aims.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-353">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-620</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྔགས་ཀྱིས་དུབ་པས་ཁ་ཟས་བཟའ། །ངན་པ་དང་བྲལ་རྙེད་དཀའ་མིན། །ཤ་ཆེན་དག་ནི་རྟ་དང་ནི། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The food for those exhausted by the mantra Is easy to obtain and beyond reproach.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-354">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-622</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གླང་པོ་ཆེ་ཡི་ཁྱད་པར་དང་། །བ་ལང་གི་དང་ཁྱི་དང་ནི། །བོང་བུ་རྔ་མོ་ཅེ་སྤྱང་ངོ་། །སྔོན་པོ་དང་ནི་བསྲེས་པ་ཡི། །སྣུམ་ཆེན་གྱིས་ནི་ལུས་བྱུགས་ན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-622"/>“One should mix great flesh, With horse and especially elephant, As well as cow and dog, Donkey, camel, jackal, <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-624"/>“And the indigo plant, And then rub it on one’s body with great oil.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-355">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-622</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལུས་ལ་བྱུགས་པ་ཙམ་གྱིས་ནི། །འགྲོ་བ་ཐམས་ཅད་དབང་དུ་འགྱུར། །སྣང་མཛད་སི་དུ་བ་ར་དང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>One can enthrall the world Simply by rubbing it on one’s body.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-356">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-627</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་བཞིན་བིལ་བའི་ལོ་མ་དང་། །སོ་ཕག་ཕྱེ་མ་བསྲེས་པ་དང་། །གསེར་ཤིང་ལོ་མའི་ཁུ་བ་རྣམས། །འདི་ཡིས་དྲིལ་ཕྱིས་བྱས་གྱུར་ན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-627"/>“One should mix vairocana and sinduvāra, As well as bilva leaves, A mixture of powdered brick, And the juice of kanaka leaves.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-357">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-630</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཁམས་གསུམ་པོ་ནི་དབང་དུ་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-630"/>“Simply by rubbing this on their limbs One will enthrall the three worlds.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-358">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-630</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དུག་དང་ཆུ་བུར་དེ་བཞིན་མཛེ། །དྲིལ་ཕྱིས་བྱས་པས་ཉམས་པར་བྱེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Poison, blisters, as well as leprosy Are cured when one is smeared with it.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-359">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-632</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཅི་བ་ཆེན་པོ་བཏུང་བར་བྱ། །རྡོ་རྗེ་བདུད་རྩི་དེ་བཞིན་དུ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-632"/>“One should drink the great urine As well as vajra nectar.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-360">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-632</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདི་ནི་རྣལ་འབྱོར་མཆོག་གཙོ་བོ། །རང་འབྱུང་མེ་ཏོག་བཏུང་བ་བཞིན།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>This is the highest, best yoga, As is drinking the self-arisen flower.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-361">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-634</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱི་སྐུ་གསུང་ཐུགས་གཤིན་རྗེའི་གཤེད་ནག་པོའི་རྒྱུད་ལས་སྤྱོད་པ་སྟོན་པ་ཞེས་<tei:ref folio="F.145.a"/>བྱ་བའི་རྒྱུད་རིམ་པར་ཕྱེ་བ་སྟེ་བཅུ་གཅིག་པའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-634"/>This was the eleventh chapter, “Revealing the Conduct,” from The Tantra of Black Yamāri, the Body, Speech, and Mind of All Tathāgatas.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-362">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-637</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་སྐྱེས་བུ་ཆེན་པོའི་དམ་ཚིག་རྡོ་རྗེ་སེམས་དཔའི་ངོ་བོ་ཙརྩི་ཀཱའི་རྣམ་པའི་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་ལ་ཡང་སྙོམས་པར་ཞུགས་ཤིང་། ཕག་མོའི་རྣམ་པའི་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་ལ་ཡང་སྙོམས་པར་ཞུགས་སོ། །དབྱངས་ཅན་གྱི་རྣམ་པའི་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་ལ་ཡང་སྙོམས་པར་ཞུགས་སོ། །གཽ་རི་མའི་རྣམ་པའི་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་ལ་སྙོམས་པར་ཞུགས་ཏེ། མཆོད་པའི་གླུ་འདི་དག་རྗོད་པར་མཛད་དོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-section-1-12"/>Chapter 12: All the Unique Ancillary Rites<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-637"/> Then, the blessed Mahāpuruṣasamaya, Vajrasattva in essence, entered the meditative absorption of Carcikā’s form, then Vārāhī’s form, then Sarasvatī’s form, then Gaurī’s form, and performed these songs of offering: <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-640"/>“Hey, Black Yamāri!</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-363">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-637</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཨ་ཀྱེ་ཀྱེ་གཤིན་རྗེའི་གཤེད་ནག་བླ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Master!</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-364">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-637</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྲིན་པོའི་གཟུགས་ཅན་རང་བཞིན་ཁྱོད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>You have the nature and form of a rākṣasa.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-365">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-637</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བདག་གིས་ཁྱོད་མཐོང་ཤིན་ཏུ་འཇིགས། །ཁྲོ་བའི་རང་བཞིན་འདི་ཐོང་མཛོད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>I am terrified when I look at you, Please cast off this wrathful nature!</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-366">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-641</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མཐོ་རིས་ས་སྟེངས་ས་འོག་བཅས། །ཁྱོད་ཀྱི་གར་གྱིས་གཡོས་པར་མཛད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-641"/>“The heavens, earth, and underworld Quake from your dance.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-367">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-641</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཨཉྫ་ནག་པོ་བཅག་འདྲ་བའི། །ཁྲོ་ཁྱོད་རོ་ལངས་ཞི་གར་མཛོད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Wrathful one, black as collyrium, You dance to appease the vetālas.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-368">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-643</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྣམ་པ་སྣ་ཚོགས་གཟུགས་སྤྲུལ་ཞིང་། །མདངས་ནག་ཚད་ནི་ཐུང་བ་ལ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-643"/>“Of dark, complex, and dwarfish stature, You emanate a variety of different forms.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-369">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-643</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བདེ་ཆེན་ངོ་བོ་ཁྲོ་གར་གྱིས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Essence of great bliss, dance!</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-370">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-643</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྡོ་རྗེ་དབྱངས་ཅན་མ་གསོལ་འདེབས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>I, Vajrasarasvatī, supplicate you.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-371">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-645</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཧྲཱིཿཥྚྲཱི་སྔགས་དང་གར་གྱིས་ཁྱོད། །སྲིད་པ་གསུམ་གྱི་འཁྲུལ་པ་ཆོད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-645"/>“With the hrīḥ ṣṭrīḥ mantra and your dance, You cut through the confusion of the three existences.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-372">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-645</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྙིང་རྗེ་ཁྲོས་པའི་དང་སྒྲོལ་གར། །འགྲོ་བས་དད་ནི་ངོ་མཚར་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Your liberating dance of compassionate wrath Fills the world with faith and wonder.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-373">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-647</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་ཡང་དག་བཤད་བྱ་བ། །བཟླས་པ་ཡི་ནི་མཚན་ཉིད་མཆོག །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-647"/>“Next, I will explain The supreme characteristics of mantra recitation.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-374">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-647</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཟླས་པ་གང་ཞིག་རབ་བཟླས་ན། །དངོས་གྲུབ་ཡངས་པ་ཐོབ་པ་ནི། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Those who apply this mantra recitation Will attain vast siddhis.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-375">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-649</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མྱུར་བར་མ་ཡིན་དལ་བར་མིན། །རིང་དུ་མ་ཡིན་ཐུང་ངུ་མིན། །སྔགས་ནི་ཅུང་ཟད་ཐོས་པར་བཟླས། །གཤིན་རྗེ་སློབ་དཔོན་མི་མཆོག་གི། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-649"/>“Neither too quickly nor too leisurely, Neither too long nor too short, For the master of Yama, the supreme person, The recitation should be barely audible.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-376">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-651</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མ་ཧེ་མི་དང་སོ་གཉིས་དང་། །བ་ལང་དང་ནི་རྟ་དག་དང་། །བོང་བུ་རྔ་མོའི་རུས་པ་ལས། །བཟླས་པའི་ཕྲེང་བ་རབ་བསྒྲུབ་བྱ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-651"/>“The recitation mālā should be made From buffalo or human bones, Or those of an elephant, cow, horse, Donkey, or camel.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-377">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-652</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཟླ་ངོ་གཅིག་གི་བཅུ་བཞི་ལ། །བདུད་རྩི་ལྔ་དང་ལྡན་པ་ཡིས། །ཤ་ལྔ་དག་ནི་བསྡུ་བྱས་ནས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-652"/>“On the fourteenth day of the first month, One should gather the five meats Mixed with the five nectars.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-378">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-652</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཟླས་ན་དངོས་གྲུབ་འགྲུབ་པའི་མཆོག །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Recitation then leads to the supreme siddhi.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-379">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-654</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རིལ་བུ་དག་ནི་སོ་སོ་ལ། །རྣལ་འབྱོར་པ་ཡིས་གཤིན་གཤེད་བསྒོམ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-654"/>“The yogi should visualize Yamāri inside each bead.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-380">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-654</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མཁས་པས་ནི་ཡང་མི་མགོ་སྟེ། །ཁྲག་གིས་བཀང་བའི་མགོ་བསྒོམ་བྱ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Or, the adept can visualize them As human heads covered in blood.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-381">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-655</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཁྲི་ཙམ་གྱིས་ནི་འབྱུང་པོ་རྣམས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-655"/>“When applying the practice of Vajra Yamāri, Bhūtas will die after 10,000 recitations.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-382">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-655</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མཁའ་འགྲོ་མ་རྣམས་སྟོང་ཕྲག་གིས། །བདུད་དང་ཡི་དགས་ཚོགས་ཀྱང་འཆི། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Ḍākinīs will die after one thousand, As will the hosts of māras and pretas.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-383">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-657</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཤིན་གཤེད་རྡོ་རྗེའི་སྦྱོར་བ་ཡིས། །རྣལ་འབྱོར་བདག་ཉིད་འབུམ་བཟླས་ནས། །དེས་ནི་<tei:ref folio="F.145.b"/>ལས་ཀུན་བྱེད་པ་ཡིན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-657"/>“After 100,000 recitations, the one immersed in yoga Can perform any of the ritual activities.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-384">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-657</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱེ་བ་བཟླས་ནས་དངོས་གྲུབ་སྟེར། །བྱེ་བ་ལྔ་བཟླས་སྨོས་ཅི་དགོས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>After ten million repetitions, they will be granted siddhis, To say nothing of fifty million.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-385">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-659</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཉིན་རེའམ་ཡང་ན་ཟླ་རེ་འམ། །དེ་བཞིན་ལོ་ནི་རེ་རེ་ལ། །གཏོར་མ་དྲུག་ཅུ་རྩ་བཞི་སྦྱིན། །དབྱུག་གུ་དྲུག་ཅུ་རྩ་བཞིར་ཤེས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-659"/>“Every day, every month, Or even every year, The adept should make sixty-four bali offerings At the sixty-four daṇḍas.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-386">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-663</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྟག་ཏུ་ཅུང་ཟད་ཅི་ཟ་དང་། །དེ་བཞིན་ཅུང་ཟད་འཐུང་བ་དང་། །གཞན་ཡང་བཟའ་བ་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱི། །ཕུད་ནི་གཤིན་རྗེའི་གཤེད་ལ་དབུལ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-663"/>“Whenever one has a little something to eat, When they have little something to drink, Or when they enjoy a full meal, The best part should be offered to Yamāri.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-387">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-664</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་ཡང་དག་བཤད་བྱ་བ། །བླ་མ་ལ་ནི་ཡོན་དབུལ་བའོ། །ལས་ནི་ཐམས་ཅད་བསྒྲུབ་པ་དང་། །བདག་ཉིད་ཞི་བར་བྱ་བའི་ཕྱིར། །བདག་ཉིད་ཀྱང་ནི་དབུལ་བ་དང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-664"/>“Now, I will explain the gifts That are to be offered to the master In order to accomplish all activities And to pacify oneself.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-388">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-665</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྟ་དང་བ་དང་གླང་པོ་དང་། །གསེར་དང་དེ་ལས་གཞན་པ་དང་། །རང་གི་ཆུང་མ་དེ་བཞིན་བུ། །མ་དང་སྲིང་མོ་ཚ་མོ་དང་། །དེ་བཞིན་དུ་ནི་སྤུན་ཟླ་དང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-665"/>“The vow-holder should offer themselves, As well as a horse, cow, or elephant, Or gold, and beyond that, Their own spouse and children, Their mother, sisters, and nieces, As well as their brothers.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-389">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-669</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ན་བཟའ་སྣ་ཚོགས་དག་དང་ནི། །གདུགས་དང་རྡུལ་ཡབ་མཛེས་པ་དང་། །ཁྱིམ་དང་གདན་དང་དྲི་ཞིམ་དང་། །དེ་བཞིན་གླུ་དང་རོལ་མོ་དང་། །རལ་གྲི་དང་ནི་རྒྱན་དག་དང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-669"/>“One should offer different articles of clothing, A parasol and elegant tail whisk, A home, a seat, and fragrances, As well as songs and music, A sword and jewelry.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-390">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-670</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བརྟུལ་ཞུགས་ཅན་གྱིས་བླ་མར་དབུལ། །དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱི་སྐུ་གསུང་ཐུགས་གཤིན་རྗེའི་གཤེད་ནག་པོའི་རྒྱུད་ལས་ཉེ་བར་མཁོ་བའི་ལས་ཀྱི་ཁྱད་པར་ཐམས་ཅད་ཞེས་བྱ་སྟེ་རིམ་པར་ཕྱེ་བ་བཅུ་གཉིས་པའོ།། །།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-670"/>This was the twelfth chapter, “All Unique Ancillary Rites,” from The Tantra of Black Yamāri, the Body, Speech, and Mind of All Tathāgatas.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-391">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-672</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་སེམས་ཅན་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱི། །སྡིག་པ་དག་ནི་ཇི་སྙེད་པ། །དེ་དག་གཅོད་པའི་གྲི་གུག་སྟེ། །ཞེ་སྡང་གཅོད་པའི་ཤུབས་ཅན་ནོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-section-1-13"/>Chapter 13: Identifying the Siddhis<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-672"/> “Now, the knife that severs The evil deeds of beings, However many there are, Is the sword that cuts through anger.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-392">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-674</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་ཡང་དག་བཤད་བྱ་བ། །རིང་བའི་ཐོས་པ་བསྒྲུབ་པའི་ཕྱིར། །རྡོ་རྗེ་མཁའ་འགྲོ་མ་སྒྲུབ་ཐབས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-674"/>“Next, I will explain The practice of Vajraḍākinī, In order to accomplish remote hearing.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-393">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-676</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ནམ་མཁའི་ཁམས་ཀྱི་དབུས་གཏོགས་པར། །ཉི་མའི་དཀྱིལ་འཁོར་མཆོག་བསམ་བྱ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-676"/>“One should imagine a sublime sun disk Located in the center of the sky.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-394">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-676</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གནས་དེར་རྩེ་ལྔ་པ་ཡང་བསྒོམ། །དེ་ཡི་སྟེང་དུ་གནས་དགོད་བྱ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>A five-pronged vajra should be visualized there, And a palace placed on top of that.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-395">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-679</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མཐིང་མདོག་ནག་པོ་འཇིགས་ཚུལ་ལ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-679"/>“One should visualize her In a dark-blue, terrifying form.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-396">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-679</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཕྱག་དྲུག་འཇིགས་སུ་རུང་བ་སྟེ། །ཕྱག་ན་རྡོ་རྗེ་རྣམ་བསྒོམ་བྱ། །ཕྱག་གཞན་དག་ལ་གཞན་དག་དགོད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>She is six-armed and fearsome, With a vajra in one hand and the others in the rest.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-397">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-682</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཤར་དུ་སངས་རྒྱས་མཁའ་འགྲོ་མ། །ཕྱག་དྲུག་གཏི་མུག་རྡོ་རྗེ་མཚུངས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-682"/>“In the east is Buddhaḍākinī, Six-armed and resembling Mohavajra.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-398">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-682</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལག་ན་འཁོར་ལོ་འཇིགས་པར་བྱེད། །བསྒོམ་བྱ་སྦྱོར་བའི་དཀྱིལ་འཁོར་དུ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Terrifying with a wheel in hand, She is visualized in the center of a yoga-maṇḍala.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-399">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-684</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལྷོ་རུ་རིན་ཆེན་མཁའ་འགྲོ་མ། །ཕྱག་དྲུག་ཕྲ་མ་དང་མཚུངས་པ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-684"/>“In the south is Ratnaḍākinī, Six-armed and resembling Piśuna.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-400">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-684</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཕྱག་ན་རིན་ཆེན་རབ་འབར་བ། །ཉི་མའི་དཀྱིལ་འཁོར་བསྒོམ་པར་བྱ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Blazing brightly with a jewel in hand, She is visualized on the disk of the sun.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-401">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-686</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ནུབ་ཏུ་<tei:ref folio="F.146.a"/>པདྨའི་མཁའ་འགྲོ་མ། །ཕྱག་དྲུག་པདྨ་འཛིན་པའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-686"/>“In the west is Padmadākinī, Six-armed and holding a lotus.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-402">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-686</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱང་དུ་ལས་ཀྱི་མཁའ་འགྲོ་མ། །རལ་གྲི་འཛིན་པའི་དཀྱིལ་འཁོར་རིམ་པའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>In the north is Karmaḍākinī, On a bhaga maṇḍala holding a sword.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-403">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-688</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མེ་ལ་སོགས་པ་མཚམས་བཞི་རུ། །ལྷ་མོ་བསྒོམ་བྱ་བརྟུལ་ཞུགས་ཅན། །ལཱ་སྱེ་མཱ་ལེ་དེ་བཞིན་གར། །གླུ་མ་ཡི་ནི་ཁྱད་པར་རོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-688"/>“In the four corners, beginning in the west, The vow-holder should visualize the goddesses, Specifically Lāsyā and Mālyā, As well as Nṛtyā and Geyā.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-404">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-689</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལས་ཀྱི་ཆོ་ག་མཐོང་བ་ཡིས། །དེར་ནི་སྒོ་སྐྱོང་བསྒོམ་པར་བྱ། །ཐོ་བ་དབྱིག་པ་དང་པདྨ། །དེ་བཞིན་གཞན་ནི་རལ་གྲིའོ། །ཨོྃ་བཛྲ་ཌཱ་ཀི་ནཱི།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-689"/>“They should then focus on the door guardians By following the prescribed method: Mudgara, Daṇḍa, Padma, And the other one, Khaḍga.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-405">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-691</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཨོྃ་བུདྡྷ་ཌཱ་ཀི་ནཱི། ཨོྃ་རཏྣ་ཌཱ་ཀི་ནཱི། ཨོྃ་པདྨ་ཌཱ་ཀི་ནཱི། ཨོྃ་ཀརྨྨ་ཌཱ་ཀི་ནཱི། ལྃ་ནྃ་གྃ་མྃ། མཚམས་སུའོ། །ཨོྃ་མུདྒར་ཛཿཨོཾ་དཎྜ་ཧཱུྃ། ཨོྃ་པདྨ་བྃ། ཨོྃ་ཁངྒ་ཧོཿ །འདི་ནི་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་རྡོ་རྗེ་ཅན་གྱིས་རྡོ་རྗེ་མཁའ་འགྲོ་མའི་སྒྲུབ་ཐབས་གསུངས་པའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-691"/>oṁ vajraḍākinī | oṁ buddhaḍākinī | oṁ ratnaḍākinī | oṁ padmaḍākinī | oṁ karmaḍākinī |<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-692"/> And for the corners: laṁ naṁ gaṁ maṁ |<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-693"/> oṁ mudgara jaḥ | oṁ daṇḍa hūṁ | oṁ padma vaṁ | oṁ khadga hoḥ |<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-694"/> This is the practice of Vajraḍākinī taught by the blessed vajra bearer.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-406">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-695</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རིང་པོའི་ཐོས་པ་བསྒྲུབ་དོན་དུ། །རྡོ་རྗེ་མཁའ་འགྲོ་མ་བསྒོམ་བྱ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-695"/>“To accomplish remote hearing One should visualize Vajraḍākinī.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-407">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-695</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེར་ནི་གསང་སྔགས་ཀྱི་དངོས་གྲུབ་འགྲུབ་པར་འགྱུར་ཏེ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>In that way the mantra siddhi is attained.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-408">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-697</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཨོྃ་ཨཱ་ཀི་ཤ་ཙ་ར་བཛྲ་ཌཱ་ཀི་ནཱི་སྭཱ་ཧཱ། དེ་ནས་ཡང་དག་བཤད་བྱ་བ། །རྡོ་རྗེས་འོག་སྒྲུབ་ཐབས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-697"/>oṁ ākāśacara ḍākinīye hūṁ hūṁ phaṭ phaṭ svāhā |<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-699"/> “Next, I will explain The practice of Vajrapātāla.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-409">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-697</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ས་འོག་རྣམ་པར་བསྒྲུབ་དོན་དུ། །གནོད་མཛེས་རྡོ་རྗེ་བསྒོམ་པར་བྱ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>To attain the siddhi of moving underground One should visualize Śumbhavajra.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-410">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-700</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཕྱག་དྲུག་མདོག་སྔོན་འཇིགས་པ་ཡི། །ཕྱག་ཏུ་གཏུན་ཤིང་དགོད་པར་བྱ། །དཀྱིལ་འཁོར་གྱི་ནི་དཀྱིལ་དག་ཏུ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-700"/>“He has six arms, is blue and fearsome, Holds a pestle aloft in his hand, And is in the middle of the garbhamaṇḍala.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-411">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-700</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདི་ནི་རབ་ཏུ་དགོད་པར་བྱ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>This is how he is to be arranged.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-412">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-703</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཤར་དུ་སྤྱན་མ་དགོད་པར་བྱ། །དེ་བཞིན་ལྷོ་རུ་མཱ་མ་ཀཱི། །ནུབ་ཏུ་ལྷ་མོ་གོས་དཀར་མོ། །སྒྲོལ་མ་བྱང་གི་ཕྱོགས་སུ་དགོད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-703"/>“Locanā should be placed in the east, Māmakī in the south, The goddess Pāṇdarā in the west, And Tārā in the north.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-413">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-704</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མེ་ཏོག་སྤོས་དང་དེ་བཞིན་དྲི། །མར་མེ་ལ་སོགས་མཚམས་སུ་དགོད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-704"/>“Puṣpā, Dhūpā, Gandhā, and Dīpā Should be placed in the east and so forth.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-414">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-704</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཐོབ་ལ་སོགས་སྒོ་དྲུང་སྟེ། །སྦྲུལ་གྱིས་བརྒྱན་པའི་སྐ་རགས་བྱས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Mudgara and the rest stand in the doors, All wearing snakes as belts.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-415">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-705</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལས་ཀྱི་ཆོ་ག་མཐོང་ནས་ནི། །དཀྱིལ་འཁོར་འདི་ལྟར་བསྒོམ་པར་བྱ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-705"/>“One should visualize the maṇḍala in this way, Following the prescribed method.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-416">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-705</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྡོ་རྗེ་ས་འོག་སྦྱོར་ལྡན་པས། །རྨི་ལམ་དུ་ནི་ལམ་མཐོང་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Those who train in Vajrapātāla Will see a path in their dreams.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-417">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-706</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་ཡང་དག་བཤད་བྱ་བ། །བདུན་པའི་རྒྱལ་པོའི་དཀྱིལ་འཁོར་ཏེ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-706"/>“Next, I will explain The maṇḍala of the King of the Seven.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-418">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-706</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མཁའ་སྤྱོད་ཉིད་ནི་རབ་བསྒྲུབ་ཕྱིར། །རྟ་ཡི་མཆོག་ནི་རབ་ཏུ་བསྒྲུབ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>In order to attain the power of flight, One should perfect Paramāśva.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-419">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-708</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཕྱག་གཉིས་པ་ལ་ཞལ་གཅིག་པ། །སྐུ་མདོག་ལྗང་གུ་འཇིགས་པར་བྱེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-708"/>“He has two arms, one face, A dark-colored body, and is terrifying.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-420">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-708</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཉི་མའི་དཀྱིལ་འཁོར་སྟེང་དུ་གཞག །རྟ་ཡི་གདོང་པ་རབ་མཛེས་པས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He stands on a sun disk And is beautiful, with face of a horse.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-421">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-708</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཡས་པ་སྲད་བུ་ཁུ་ཚུར་བཅས། །ཕྱག་གཡོན་པ་ནི་ཐོད་པའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>His right hand holds bean pods in a fist, And his left, a skull cup.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-422">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-711</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཨོྃ་ཕུྃཤ་ཕུྃ་ཕུྃ་ཧི་ཧི་ཧི། གསང་<tei:ref folio="F.146.b"/>སྔགས་འདི་ནི་མཁས་པས་བཟླ། །རྟ་ཡི་མཆོག་ཏུ་གྱུར་པར་གྲགས། །ཤར་དུ་བ་ཌ་བིཾ་བསྒོམ་བྱ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-711"/>oṁ phuṁ phuṁ phuṁ hi hi hi |<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-713"/> “The adept should recite this mantra For the renowned Paramāśva.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-423">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-715</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལྷོ་ཕྱོགས་སུ་ནི་རིམ་གྲོ་མ། །ནུབ་ཏུ་བདུན་པའི་རྒྱལ་པོ་སྟེ། །རྟ་མཆོག་མ་ནི་བྱང་ཕྱོགས་དགོད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-715"/>“In the east, visualize Vaḍavā, In the south Turaṅgamā, In the west Saptarājñī, And in the northern space, Paramāśvā.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-424">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-717</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བདག་པོའི་ཞལ་ཕྱག་ཇི་ལྟ་བར། །ཐམས་ཅད་དེ་དང་འདྲ་བར་བསྒོམ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-717"/>“One should visualize their faces and arms To be like those of the central deity.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-425">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-717</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྔགས་འདི་ཡིས་ནི་ཐམས་ཅད་དུ། །གཤེགས་སུ་གསོལ་བར་རབ་ཏུ་གྲགས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The request for them to arrive Resounds everywhere through this mantra.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-426">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-718</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྨྱུག་མའི་གླིང་བུ་པི་བང་དང་། །རྔ་ཟླུམ་རྔ་བྲན་མཚམས་སུ་གཞག །བན་གླང་སྣ་དང་གླང་པོའི་སྣ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-718"/>“In each of the corners one should place Bamboo and reed flutes, a lute, drum, and tabor.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-427">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-720</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་བཞིན་གདོང་བཟང་གདོང་ངན་ཏེ། །གཏུན་ཤིང་དང་ནི་སྟ་རེ་དང་། །ལྕགས་ཀྱུ་དང་ནི་ཞགས་པ་དང་། །གར་ལ་སོགས་པའི་རྣལ་འབྱོར་གྱིས། །སྒོ་བཞི་རུ་ནི་རྟག་ཏུ་བསྒོམ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-720"/>“Gokarṇa, Hastikarṇa, Sumukha, Durmukha, Muśāla, Paraśu, Aṅkuśa, and Pāśa Should be continuously visualized in the four doors, Engaged in dance and other dramatic acts.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-428">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-720</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྔོ་ཆགས་གཡོན་པར་བསྒོམ་པར་བྱ། །རང་གི་ཕྱག་མཚན་དེ་བཞིན་གཡས། །ཇི་ལྟར་རྟ་མཆོག་སྔགས་ཀྱིས་ནི། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Green shoots should be visualized in their left hands And, similarly, their emblems in their right.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-429">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-720</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྡོ་རྗེ་ས་འོག་གི་ཡང་གཏེར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The mantra of Paramāśva Is the same as Vajrapātāla’s.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-430">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-720</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྟ་མཆོག་རྣལ་འབྱོར་ཉིད་ཀྱིས་ནི། །ཁམས་གསུམ་ནམ་མཁའི་ཁམས་སུ་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>By cultivating the practice of Paramāśva One becomes the space of the three worlds.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-431">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-723</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱི་སྐུ་གསུང་ཐུགས་གཤིན་རྗེའི་གཤེད་ནག་པོའི་རྒྱུད་ལས་དངོས་གྲུབ་ངེས་པར་བསྟན་པ་སྟེ་རིམ་པར་ཕྱེ་བ་བཅུ་གསུམ་པའོ།། །།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-723"/>This was the thirteenth chapter, “Identifying the Siddhis,” from The Tantra of Black Yamāri, the Body, Speech, and Mind of All Tathāgatas.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-432">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-725</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ལ་འདི་ནི་སྲད་བུ་བརྐྱང་བའི་དམ་ཚིག་གི་མཆོག་སྟེ། ཨ་ཀཱ་རོ་མུ་ཁྃ་སརྦཱ་དྷརྨཱཏྟཱུཾ། ཨཱདྱཱ་ནུད་པན་ན་ཏྭཱད། །དཔལ་ལྡན་གཤིན་རྗེའི་གཤེད་བསྒོམས་ལ། །སློབ་མ་རྣམ་སྣང་མཛད་དུ་བསྒོམ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-section-1-14"/>Chapter 14: The Practice of Mañjuvajra<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-725"/> “This is the supreme rite for the measuring cord:<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-726"/> oṁ akāro mukhaṃ sarva­dharmāṇām ādyanutpannatvāt oṁ āḥ hūṁ phaṭ svāhā |<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-728"/> “One should visualize themselves as glorious Yamāntaka And the disciple as Vairocana.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-433">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-725</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡེ་ཤེས་ཐིག་མཆོག་རྩེ་མོ་རྩེ། །ཤིན་ཏུ་མཉམ་པར་བཞག་ནས་བཏབ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Then, while meditatively composed, Set the supreme, preeminent wisdom cord.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-434">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-729</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ལ་འདི་ནི་དཀྱིལ་འཁོར་ཆེན་པོའི་དམ་ཚིག་མཆོག །ཨོྃ་ཨཱཿཧཱུྃ་དཀྱིལ་འཁོར་ཉིས་འགྱུར་རིམ་པར་བྱ། །དེ་ཡི་སྤོ་ཡི་ཉི་ཤུའི་ཚད། །བ་ཡི་རྣམ་ལྔ་མཉམ་བྱུགས་པའི། །སྐུད་པ་སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱིས་རབ་བརྟགས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-729"/>“This is the supreme samaya of the great maṇḍala:oṁ āḥ hūṁ |<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-731"/> “The adept should prepare a cord That is smeared with the five cow products And is twice as long as the maṇḍala, With the doors being a twentieth of that.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-435">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-733</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ལ་འདི་ནི་རྡོ་རྗེ་ཆེན་པོ་གསོལ་བ་གདབ་པའི་དམ་ཚིག་གོ། །ཨེ་མའོ་སངས་རྒྱས་སློབ་དཔོན་ཆེ། །ཨེ་མའོ་ཆོས་དང་ཚོགས་ཀྱི་གཙོ། །དམ་ཚིག་དེ་ཉིད་བདག་ལ་སྩོལ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-733"/>“This is the rite for the great vajra request:<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-734"/> “O great master, a buddha, Lord of the Dharma assembly, Grant me the true samaya!</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-436">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-733</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་ཀྱང་བདག་ལ་སྩོལ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Grant me the bodhicitta!</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-437">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-736</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ལ་འདི་ནི་ས་ཆེན་པོ་ཡོངས་སུ་གཟུང་བའི་ཆོ་ག་སྟེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-736"/>“This is the rite for the erecting the great site.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-438">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-737</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྡོ་རྗེ་སའི་ལྷ་མོ་བཀུག་ལ། །ལྷ་མོ་ཁྱོད་ནི་དཔང་དུ་འགྱུར། །སྐྱོབ་པ་སངས་རྒྱས་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱི། །སྤྱོད་པ་ཡི་ནི་ཁྱད་པར་<tei:ref folio="F.147.a"/>དང་། །ས་དང་ཕ་རོལ་ཕྱིན་པ་ལའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Once the earth goddess has been summoned, one should say:<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-737"/> ‘Devi, you bear witness To the unique conduct Of all the buddhas, the protectors, And to their perfections and levels.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-439">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-738</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྒོ་ནི་དཀྱིལ་འཁོར་ཆ་བརྒྱད་དེ། །ཁྱམས་ཆེན་དག་ནི་བོར་བ་ལ། །བདག་ཉིད་ཆེན་པོས་ཤེས་པར་བྱ། །ཡིད་དུ་འོང་ཞིང་ལེགས་སྤྲས་པའི། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-738"/>“Supreme beings should know The doors to be an eighth of the maṇḍala, Excluding the great main hall, Which is pleasing and lavishly decorated.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-440">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-1320</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མུ་ཁྱུད་སྒོ་ཙམ་ཤེས་པར་བྲི། །ལྷ་ཡི་སྣམ་བུའང་དེ་ཙམ་མོ། །རྡོ་རྗེ་ལྷ་མོ་ལྡན་པ་ཡིས། །གླུ་དང་རོལ་མོ་གར་ཡང་དགོད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-1320"/>“The crests should be known to be like the doors, As are the celestial moldings, Which are affixed with vajra apsarases Who are singing, playing instruments, and dancing.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-441">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-743</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མཆོད་སྣམ་སྒོ་ཡི་ཕྱེད་ཉིད་དེ། །འགྲམ་དང་ངོས་ཀྱང་དེ་ཙམ་མོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-743"/>“The altar is half the measure of the doors, As are the cheek moldings and the sides.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-442">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-743</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དོ་ཤལ་སེ་མོ་དོ་དང་ནི། །ཉི་མ་ཟླ་བ་མེ་ཏོག་ཕྲེང་། །དེ་ལ་གོས་དང་འཕན་དག་གོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>It also has long and short pearl strands, Moons, suns, flower garlands, Cloth hangings, and ribbons.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-443">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-746</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྩ་བ་ས་ཡི་ཐིག་རྒྱབ་ཏུ། །ཚོན་རྩེའི་སྣམ་བུ་དེ་ཡི་ཕྱེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-746"/>“The colored ground is half of that And the base line is outside the grounds.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-444">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-749</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ལ་སྙིང་པོ་ཆེན་པོ་འདིས། །བདག་ཉིད་འཁོར་ལོ་རྣམ་པར་དགོད། །དེར་ནི་རང་གི་ཕྱག་རྒྱའང་བསྟེན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-749"/>“Now, the great essence:<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-751"/> “One’s own circle should be set And one should embrace their mudrā.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-445">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-749</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དམ་ཚིག་ཡེ་ཤེས་གཞུག་པ་སྟེ། །དེ་ལྟར་དཀྱིལ་འཁོར་བསྒྲུབ་པར་བྱ། །ཤར་དུ་དཀར་པོ་ཆེན་པོ་སྟེ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The wisdom enters the samaya— Thus should the maṇḍala be established.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-446">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-754</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལྷོར་ནི་སེར་པོ་དང་ལྡན་པས། །ནུབ་ཀྱི་ཆར་ནི་དམར་པོའོ། །བྱང་དུ་ལྗང་གུ་དང་ལྡན་པར། །ཨིནྡྲ་ནཱི་ལའི་འོད་འདྲ་བའི། །དབུས་ཀྱི་ཆར་ནི་ཡང་དག་བྲི། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-754"/>“The east should be colored bright white, The south, yellow, The western portion, red, The north green in color, And the central space like the light of a sapphire.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-447">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-756</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ལ་ཕྱག་རྒྱ་དགོད་པར་བྱ། །ལས་ཀྱི་ཆོ་ག་མཐོང་ནས་ནི། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-756"/>“Then the implements should be placed In accordance with the prescribed rite.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-448">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-756</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྟག་ཏུ་ཕྱག་རྒྱ་མཁའ་མཉམ་པ། །ཕྱག་རྒྱ་དེ་ཉིད་རྟག་ཏུ་བྲི། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The implements are always sky-like And are always drawn in this way.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-449">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-758</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ཡི་དཀྱིལ་དུ་རྡོ་རྗེ་བྲི། །ཤར་དུ་འཁོར་ལོ་ཡང་དག་བྲི། །དེ་ལྟ་བུ་ལ་སོགས་པ་བལྟ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-758"/>In the center one should draw a vajra, In the east, a wheel should be drawn, And so forth for the other directions.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-450">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-758</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཕྱག་མཚན་ཀུན་ཏུ་ཞལ་དང་མཚུངས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The implements should always resemble the main face.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-451">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-760</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ལ་འདི་ཡི་དགང་གཟར་ནི། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-760"/>Now, for the ladle:<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-762"/> “One should fashion a stick That it is one cubit in length.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-452">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-760</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ཡི་ཡུ་བའི་ཚད་དུ་བྱ། །ཁྲུ་གང་དང་ནི་ལྡན་པར་བྱ། །དེ་ཡི་དཀྱིལ་འཁོར་རྩེ་མོ་ནི། །སོར་བཞི་པོ་ལ་ཟླུམ་པོར་བྱ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Its end should be rounded And measure four finger-widths around.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-453">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-760</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཏིང་དུ་སོར་གཉིས་ཟབ་པ་ལ། །དེ་ལ་སོར་ཕྱེད་མཆུར་བྱས་པའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The bottom should be two finger-widths deep And fashioned with a spout half a finger-width wide.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-454">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-764</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བླུགས་གཟར་པདྨའི་འདབ་འདྲ་བའི། །ཁ་ནི་མཐེ་བོའི་ལྟོ་གང་ལ། །དེ་ལ་སོར་གཅིག་ཙམ་ཟབ་པ། །རྒྱུད་འདི་རུ་ནི་རབ་ཏུ་བསྔགས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-764"/>“A spoon, shaped like a lotus petal, With a bowl one thumb-width high And one finger-width deep, Is praised in this tantra.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-455">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-766</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དཀྱིལ་འཁོར་དུ་ནི་མ་ཞུགས་དང་། །མཚམས་མེད་ལྔ་ནི་བྱས་པ་དང་། །སེམས་ཅན་སྲོག་ནི་གཅོད་པ་དང་། །ཉ་དང་ཤ་ནི་མངོན་ཟ་དང་། །ཆང་ལ་མངོན་པར་དད་པ་དང་། །ཆད་ལྟའི་བརྟུལ་ཞུགས་འཛིན་པ་དང་། །མངོན་པར་དབང་ནི་མ་བསྐུར་དང་། །ཀུན་ཏུ་འཁྱམ་ཞིང་ལྡོམ་བུ་དང་། །གྲོང་གི་གླ་མི་བྱེད་པས་ཀྱང་། །གཤིན་རྗེའི་གཤེད་རྒྱུད་མངོན་<tei:ref folio="F.147.b"/>གཞོལ་ན། །ནག་པོའི་ཚིག་ནི་ཇི་ལྟ་བར། །གྲུབ་པར་འདི་ལ་ཐེ་ཚོམ་མེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-766"/>“People who have not entered the maṇḍala, Who have committed the five acts with immediate retribution, Who have taken a life, Who eat fish and other meats,<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-767"/> “Who indulge in wine, Who uphold the ways of nihilists, Who have not been initiated, Who wander about begging,<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-770"/> “And who delight in country ways, And yet devote themselves to Yamāri’s tantra, Will doubtlessly become accomplished, According to words of the Dark One.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-456">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-773</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་བྱམས་པ་ལ་སོགས་ཀྱིས། །རྡོ་རྗེ་ངེས་པ་འདི་མཐོང་ནས། །རྡོ་རྗེ་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཀུན། །མི་སྨྲ་བར་ནི་སྡོད་པར་གྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-773"/>Once all the buddhas and the bodhisattvas, headed by Maitreya, heard this vajra statement, they fell silent and remained seated.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-457">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-776</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ལ་འདི་ནི་རྡོ་རྗེ་དབབ་པའི་ཆོ་གའོ། །འབྱུང་བཞིའི་ས་བོན་ཆེན་པོ་ཡིས། །འཁོར་ལོ་བཞི་ནི་རབ་བསྒྲུབ་བྱ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-776"/>This is the rite for vajra entry: <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-777"/>“The four circles should be formed From the great seed syllables of the four elements.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-458">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-776</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གནས་བཞིར་རབ་ཏུ་སྦྱོར་བ་བསམ། །ནམ་མཁའ་ལ་ནི་གཡོ་བར་བྱེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>By connecting them to the four places, One can move through the sky.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-459">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-780</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྐང་པ་དག་གི་འོག་ཏུ་ཡྃ། །ལྟེ་བར་རྃ་སྟེ་སྙིང་གར་ལྃ། །མགོ་བོ་ལ་ནི་ཡི་གེ་བྃ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-780"/>“The syllable yaṁ is on the bottom of the feet, the syllable raṃ is at the navel, the syllable laṃ is at the heart, and the syllable vaṃ is at the head.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-460">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-781</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡི་གེ་ཡ་ནི་ནག་ཆེན་པོ། །དྲག་ལ་རྔམ་པ་རབ་འགྱུར་བའི། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-781"/>“The wind maṇḍala is bow-shaped, pitch-black, The form of fierce and fearsome wind.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-461">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-781</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གྲུ་གསུམ་སྲེག་པའི་མེ་ལྟར་འབར། །ཉི་མའི་དཀྱིལ་འཁོར་ལྟ་བུར་དམར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The fire maṇḍala is triangular, blazes like fire, And appears as red as the sun.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-462">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-784</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྡོ་རྗེ་ས་གཞི་འཛིན་བཟོད་པའི། །སེར་པོ་ཆེན་པོ་གྲུ་བཞི་པ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-784"/>“The earth maṇḍala is a bright yellow square, The imperishable base of the vajra ground.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-463">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-784</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རི་རབ་རི་ཡིས་མནན་པ་ཡི། །ནོར་འཛིན་དེ་ནི་བསྒོམ་པར་བྱ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>It should be imagined as the very earth Upon which stand Sumeru and its mountain range.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-464">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-785</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དཀར་པོ་ཟླུམ་པོ་བསིལ་ཆེན་པོ། །སྤྲིན་བཞིན་དུ་ནི་ཆར་བ་འཛིན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-785"/>“The water maṇḍala is white, round, intensely cold, And carries water like a bank of clouds.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-465">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-785</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྒྱ་མཚོ་དུ་མ་ཆུས་གང་བའི། །གངས་ཀྱི་རི་བོ་ལྟར་བསིལ་བའི། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>It is like the ocean filled by a thousand streams And cool like snow-covered mountains.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-466">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-786</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གནས་བཞི་རུ་ནི་སྦྱོར་བས་ན། །ཁར་ནི་སྣང་བ་མཐའ་ཡས་ཏེ། །སློབ་མ་རྡོ་རྗེ་བསྒོམ་པར་བྱ། །མྱུར་བ་རུ་ནི་འབེབས་པར་བྱེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-786"/>“One should visualize the vajra-holding disciple, Using the method of these four places, And with Amitābha in their mouth, And then bring them quickly into the maṇḍala.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-467">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-789</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ལ་འདི་ནི་སྤྲོ་བའི་ཆོ་གའོ། །རྡོ་རྗེ་ཆོས་ནི་མགོན་ཆེན་པོ། །སྣང་བ་མཐའ་ཡས་བདེ་བ་ཆེ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-789"/>“This is the rite for the request:<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-791"/> “ ‘Vajradharma, Great Protector, Amitābha, Great Bliss!</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-468">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-789</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གསུངས་ཤིག་འདོད་ཆགས་ཆོས་ཆེན་པོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Please speak, you who have great desire for the Dharma.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-469">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-789</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དགེ་དང་མི་དགེ་ལེགས་པར་དྲི། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>I ask about virtue and nonvirtue.’</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-470">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-792</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཁྲུ་གང་ནས་ནི་བརྩམས་ནས་ནི། །ཇི་སྲིད་ཁྲུ་ནི་སྟོང་གི་བར། །སློབ་མ་ཆེན་པོ་འཕར་བར་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-792"/>“Great disciples rise up From just one cubit, Up to one thousand cubits.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-471">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-792</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནི་དབབ་པའི་ཆོ་གའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>This is based on the rite of entering.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-472">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-794</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇིགས་གཟུགས་རི་མོའི་མཚན་ཉིད་ནི། །དེ་ནས་ཡང་དག་བཤད་པར་བྱ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-794"/>“Now I will explain The features of the plaster image.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-473">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-794</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ས་ནི་འཇམ་པོ་བླངས་བྱས་ལ། །བརྟུལ་ཞུགས་ཅན་གྱིས་བཟླས་པ་བྱ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The vow holder should take wet clay And perform the mantra recitation.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-474">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-796</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྲན་གྲེའུ་འོ་མ་དེ་བཞིན་ཤ །བུ་རམ་ཏིན་ནི་ནི་ལ་སོགས། །སྣུམ་དང་ནིམ་པའི་འོ་མ་དང་། །ན་ཏི་དེ་བཞིན་ཛ་གེ་སར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-796"/>“Beans, milk, meat, and molasses, Should be mixed with tamarind and the like, With oil, neem leaves, As well as nāḍīka seeds.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-475">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-798</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དང་པོར་དཀར་པོར་བྲི་བར་བྱ། །ཁ་དོག་གཞན་གྱིས་དེ་ནས་བསྒོམ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-798"/>“One should first apply a white layer And then decorate it with other colors.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-476">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-798</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྡོ་རྒྱུས་དང་ནི་བཙག་དག་ལས། །རྒྱ་སྐྱེགས་ལྟ་བུའི་མདོག་ཏུ་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Using chalk and red ocher Results in a color similar to lac.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-477">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-800</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡུང་བ་དེ་དང་རམས་དག་ལས། །དེ་བཞིན་ཁ་དོག་ལྗང་གུར་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-800"/>“Turmeric and indigo Similarly yield dark green.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-478">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-800</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྔོན་པོ་དག་ནི་རམས་ཀྱིས་བྱ། །དེ་བཞིན་དུ་བས་ནག་པོའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Blue mixed with indigo, Or with eye black, yields black.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-479">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-801</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལྡོང་རོས་ཀྱིས་ནི་སེར་པོ་སྟེ། །དམར་པོ་དེ་བཞིན་<tei:ref folio="F.148.a"/>མཚལ་གྱིས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-801"/>“Mixing pale yellow with realgar, Or vermillion, yields red.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-480">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-801</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ལ་བིལ་བའི་སྙིང་པོ་བཞག །ཧ་ཅང་ཉུང་དང་མང་བ་མིན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Add to that a drop of bilva, But just a little, not too much.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-481">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-802</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མང་ན་ནག་པོར་འགྱུར་བ་སྟེ། །ཉུང་ན་དེ་བཞིན་འཐུལ་བར་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-802"/>“If one adds too much it turns black, If too little, it becomes grey.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-482">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-802</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཟུགས་ནི་ཁྲོ་དང་ཞི་བའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The image can be either wrathful or peaceful.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-483">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-802</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མཚན་ཉིད་དག་ནི་བཤད་པར་བྱ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The characteristics of both will now be described.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-484">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-803</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རོལ་བ་ཞི་བར་གསུངས་པ་སྟེ། །ཁྲོ་བོ་སྦོམ་ལ་ཐུང་བར་བཤད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-803"/>“The peaceful is described as playful, The wrathful as rotund and short.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-485">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-803</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྣ་ནི་སོར་བཞི་བྱ་བ་སྟེ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Its nose should measure four finger-widths.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-486">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-805</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དཔྲལ་བ་ཀོས་ཀོ་མཆུ་དེ་བཞིན། །མགྲིན་པ་འགྲམ་པ་དེ་བཞིན་མཚན། །སོར་བཞི་དག་ཏུ་བྱ་བ་ཡིན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Its forehead, chin, jaws, throat, and neck,<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-805"/> Should also be four finger-widths.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-487">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-805</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཉི་ཤུ་རྩ་བཞི་ལག་པ་ལ། །གྱེན་དུ་སོར་ནི་ཉི་ཤུ་ཡིན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The image should be twenty-four cubits and twenty finger-widths tall.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-488">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-805</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལག་པ་རྐང་པ་གདོང་ཇི་ལྟར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Its hands, feet and mouth are all the same size.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-489">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-805</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མིག་ནི་མཐེ་བོང་གང་ཙམ་སྟེ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>And its eyes are a single thumb width.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-490">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-806</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྣ་བ་གཉིས་ལ་སོར་གཉིས་བསྒྲགས། །འབྲས་བུ་གཉིས་ལ་དེ་བཞིན་བཞི། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-806"/>“Its ears are described as two finger-widths And its two testicles each four.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-491">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-806</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མཆུ་ནི་སོར་གཉིས་བསྡོམས་པའོ། །ལྟེ་བ་སོར་གཅིག་ཟབ་པ་ཡིན། །ལུས་ནི་མགྲིན་པ་བོར་བ་ཡི། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Its lips together are two finger-widths And its navel one finger-width.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-492">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-807</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གདོང་ནི་གསུམ་འགྱུར་ལུས་ལ་དགོད། །རལ་པ་ཅོད་པན་དེ་ཡི་ཚད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-807"/>“Its face is one of third its body And has no neck.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-493">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-807</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རིན་ཆེན་ཅོད་པན་སོར་དྲུག་པའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Its crown of matted hair is the length of its face And bears a crown that is six finger-widths.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-494">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-810</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རལ་པ་གཅིག་མ་རབ་སྒྲུབ་ཐབས། །དེ་ནས་ཡང་དག་བཤད་བྱ་བ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-810"/>“Now I will explain The practice of Ekajaṭā.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-495">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-810</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གནོད་སྦྱིན་མོ་ནི་སྒྲུབ་འདོད་པས། །རལ་པ་གཅིག་མ་རབ་སྒྲུབ་ཐབས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>One who seeks the siddhis of a yakṣiṇī Should train in Ekajaṭā.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-496">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-811</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཕྱག་གཉིས་པ་ལ་ཞལ་གཅིག་སྟེ། །གྲི་གུག་དང་ནི་ཐོད་པ་ལ། །ཤིན་ཏུ་སྦོམ་ལ་མདོག་སྔོ་བ། །དཀྱིལ་འཁོར་དབུས་སུ་བསྒོམ་པར་བྱ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-811"/>“One should visualize her in the maṇḍala’s center, With one face and two arms, Holding a knife and a skull cup, Her body stout and blue.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-497">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-813</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཛམྦྷ་ལ་ནི་ཤར་དུ་བསྒོམ། །བ་སུ་དྷ་ར་ལྷོ་ཕྱོགས་སུ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-813"/>“Jambhalā should be imagined in the east And Vasudhārā in the south.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-498">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-813</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཆུ་དབང་ནུབ་ཏུ་དགོད་པར་བྱ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Jalendrā is to be placed in the west And Cibikuṇḍalī in the north.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-499">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-815</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱང་དུ་རྣ་ཆ་ཀོས་ཀོ་འཕྱང་། །མེ་ལ་སོགས་པའི་མཚམས་དག་ཏུ། །གནོད་སྦྱིན་མོ་བཞི་རབ་བསྒོམ་བྱ། །ཀུ་ཏལ་ཀྱེ་ཧེ་ནི་གྱི་ཧྃ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-815"/>“In the four corners, the southeast first, One should visualize the four yakṣiṇīs— Kuntalā, Dehinī, Gehā, and Vasundarī, And arrange them according to the rite.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-500">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-817</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བ་སུ་དྷ་རི་ཆོ་ག་བཞིན་དགོད། །དེར་ནི་སྒོ་བ་རྣམ་བསྒོམས་ཏེ། །ཐོ་བ་ལ་སོགས་མཉམ་པར་རོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-817"/>“One should then visualize the doors, With Mudgara and the rest all around.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-501">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-817</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཁོར་ལོ་སྔ་མ་མཐོང་བ་བཞིན། །དེ་བཞིན་མདོག་ནི་རབ་སྦྱར་བྱ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>One should use the same colors As in the previous maṇḍala.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-502">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-820</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཕྱག་མཚན་བདག་ནི་ལྟར་འཛིན་པ། །མཁས་པས་ཕྱི་ནས་སྔགས་བཟླས་ཏེ། །ཨོཾ་ཨེ་ཀ་ཛཊཱི་བ་སུདྷཱ་རི་ཎི་སྭཱ་ཧཱ། །པུཀྐ་སཱི་ནི་རབ་སྒྲུབ་ཐབས། །དེ་ནས་ཡང་དག་བཤད་པར་བྱ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-820"/>“Seeing themselves as the maṇḍala deity, bearing emblems, The adept should then recite her mantra:<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-822"/> oṁ ekajaṭi vasudhāriṇi svāhā |<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-824"/> “Next, I will explain The practice of Pukkasī.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-503">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-820</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་ཞིག་བསྒོམས་པ་ཙམ་གྱིས་ནི། །འཇིག་རྟེན་གསུམ་ལ་འཚེ་ནུས་པ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>By merely visualizing her One is able to harm the three worlds.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-504">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-826</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྐུ་མདོག་སེར་པོ་ཞལ་བཞི་པ། །ཕྱག་བཞི་བོང་བུ་ལ་བཅིབས་པ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-826"/>“One should imagine her As yellow, with four faces and arms, And riding on a donkey.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-505">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-826</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>པུཀྐ་སཱི་ཡི་ལུས་བསྒོམ་བྱ། །<tei:ref folio="F.148.b"/>ཞགས་པ་ཐོ་བ་མདའ་དག་དང་། །བརྟུལ་ཞུགས་ཅན་གྱིས་གཞུ་བཅས་བསྒོམ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>She should be visualized holding a bow, Noose, hammer, and arrow.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-506">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-827</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཨོཾ་པུཀྐ་སཱི་ཨཾ་ཞེས་སྔགས་བརྗོད་དོ། །འཇམ་པའི་རྡོ་རྗེའི་དཀྱིལ་འཁོར་ནི། །དེ་ནས་ཡང་དག་བཤད་བྱ་བ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-827"/>“The mantra to recite is: oṁ pukkasī aṃ |<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-829"/> “Now I will explain The maṇḍala of Mañjuvajra.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-507">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-827</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ཡི་མོད་ལ་མི་སྣང་བར། །འཇམ་པའི་རྡོ་རྗེ་གྲགས་འགྱུར་བ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Once Mañjuvajra is accomplished, Invisibility instantly ensues.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-508">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-831</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འབར་བའི་གསེར་འོད་འདྲ་བ་ཡི། །སེར་པོ་ཞལ་གསུམ་ཕྱག་དྲུག་པ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-831"/>“He has three faces and six arms, And is yellow, like the luster of gold.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-509">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-831</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཞོན་ནུའི་གཟུགས་ནི་འཛིན་པའི་མགོན། །མི་མཐོང་བྱ་བའི་དོན་དུ་བསྒོམ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>One should train in this protector with a youthful form In order to make oneself invisible.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-510">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-832</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཤར་དུ་མཛེས་མ་དགོད་པར་བྱ། །དེ་བཞིན་ལྷོ་རུ་སྐྲ་ཅན་མ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-832"/>“Sundarī should be placed in the east And Keśinī in the south.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-511">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-832</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ནུབ་ཏུ་སེར་པོ་བསྒོམ་པར་བྱ། །བྱང་དུ་ཉེ་བའི་སྐྲ་ཅན་མ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Vihvalā should be imagined in the west And Upakeśinī in the north.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-512">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-834</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཐམས་ཅད་ཕྱག་ན་རལ་གྲི་དང་། །འཁོར་ལོ་ལ་སོགས་གཞན་ལ་དགོད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-834"/>“A sword should be placed in their right hands And a wheel and the rest in all the others.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-513">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-834</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཐམས་ཅད་ཞལ་གསུམ་ཕྱག་དྲུག་པ། །སྣ་ཚོགས་རྒྱན་གྱིས་བརྒྱན་པའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They all have three faces and six arms And are adorned with various ornaments.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-514">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-836</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ས་བོན་ཡི་གེ་མཾ་ལས་བྱུང་། །དཀྱིལ་འཁོར་གྱི་ནི་དབུས་ན་བཞུགས། །ཐམས་ཅད་ཞབས་ནི་གཡོན་བརྐྱང་བས། །རི་བོང་ཅན་གྱི་གདན་ལ་བཞུགས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-836"/>“Arising from the seed syllable maṁ, They stand in the maṇḍala’s core, All standing on moon disks With their left legs extended.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-515">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-838</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འོད་ཟེར་ཅན་དང་རི་ཁྲོད་མ། །དེ་བཞིན་ནོར་འཛིན་སྐུལ་བྱེད་མ། །མེ་ལ་སོགས་པའི་མཚམས་བཞི་རུ། །བསྡུས་པ་དགོད་བྱ་སྙིང་པོ་ལའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-838"/>“Mārīcī, Parṇaśabarī, Vasudhārā, and Cundrikā Are placed in the four corners, southeast first, As a gathering of the essence.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-516">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-840</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མྱ་ངན་མེད་དང་ཡལ་འདབ་དང་། །འབྲས་ཀྱི་སྙེ་མ་དབྱིག་པའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-840"/>“They are visualized holding aśoka leaves and branches, As well as the stalks of clusters of grain.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-517">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-840</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སེར་དང་ལྗང་དང་ཡང་སེར་པོ། །དཀར་པོའི་ལུས་ནི་བསྒོམ་པར་བྱ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Their bodies are yellow and green, Yellow again, and white.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-518">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-841</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཀུན་ཀྱང་ཞལ་གསུམ་ཕྱག་དྲུག་པ། །དཀྱིལ་འཁོར་དག་ཏུ་གདབ་པར་བྱ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-841"/>“They all have three faces and six arms, And are known as the maṇḍala deities.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-519">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-841</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཐོ་བ་ལ་སོགས་སྒོ་བ་བཞི། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Mudga and the rest are visualized in the doors.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-520">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-841</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བསྒོམས་ན་མཐོང་བར་མི་འགྱུར་རོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Thus will one become invisible.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-521">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-843</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱི་སྐུ་གསུང་ཐུགས་གཤིན་རྗེའི་གཤེད་ནག་པོའི་རྒྱུད་ལས་འཇམ་པའི་རྡོ་རྗེ་སྒྲུབ་པའི་ཐབས་ཞེས་བྱ་སྟེ་རིམ་པར་ཕྱེ་བ་བཅུ་བཞི་པའོ།། །།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-843"/>This was the fourteenth chapter, “The Practice of Mañjuvajra,” from The Tantra of Black Yamāri, the Body, Speech, and Mind of All Tathāgatas.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-522">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-845</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཕགས་པ་ཛི་གུ་ལིའི་སྒྲུབ་ཐབས། །དེ་ནས་ཡང་དག་བཤད་པར་བྱ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-section-1-15"/>Chapter 15: The Practice of Vajrānaṅga<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-845"/> “Next, I will explain The practice of the noble Jāṅgulī.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-523">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-845</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་ཞིག་བསྒོམ་པ་ཙམ་གྱིས་ནི། །ཆུ་ཡི་སྟེང་ནས་འགྲོ་འགྱུར་བ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>One can walk on water Merely by visualizing her.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-524">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-846</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སེར་པོ་ཞལ་གསུམ་ཕྱག་དྲུག་པ། །ས་བོན་ཕུཿལས་ཡང་དག་བྱུང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-846"/>“Born from the seed syllable phuḥ, She is yellow, with three faces and six arms.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-525">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-846</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྐུ་ཆེན་ཕྱག་ན་སྦྲུལ་བསྣམས་པ། །རྨ་བྱ་ལ་ནི་ཞོན་པ་དགོད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Mighty in form, she holds a snake in her hand And rides a peacock as her mount.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-526">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-847</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཤར་དུ་རྨ་བྱ་དགོད་པར་བྱ། །དེ་བཞིན་ལྷོ་རུ་ཁྲོ་གཉེར་ཅན། །ནུབ་ཏུ་རི་ཁྲོད་ལོ་མ་ཅན། །བྱང་དུ་རྡོ་རྗེ་ལྕགས་སྒྲོག་མ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-847"/>“One should place Māyūrī in the east, Bhṛkuṭī in the south, Parṇaśabarī in the west, And Vajraśṛṅkhalā in the north.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-527">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-848</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྨ་བྱའི་སྒྲོ་དང་སྤྱི་བླུགས་དང་། །ལོ་མ་དང་ནི་ལྕགས་<tei:ref folio="F.149.a"/>སྒྲོག་མ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-848"/>“They should be visualized with peacock feathers, Water pitchers, sprigs, and vajra chains.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-528">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-848</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་དག་རྣམ་པར་བསྒོམ་པར་བྱ། །སེར་དང་དམར་དང་དེ་བཞིན་ལྗང་། །ཁ་དོག་སྔོན་པོ་དབྱེ་བ་ཉིད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Their colors are yellow, red, Green, and blue, respectively.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-529">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-850</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མཁས་པས་འདི་ལྟར་བསྒོམ་པར་བྱ། །དེ་བཞིན་སྔགས་འདི་དག་ཀྱང་བཟླས། །ཨོཾ་ཕུཿཛཿ། ཐོ་བ་ལ་སོགས་སྒོ་རུ་དགོད། །མེ་ཏོག་ལ་སོགས་མཚམས་སུ་དགོད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-850"/>“The adept should visualize in this way And then recite her mantra:<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-851"/> oṁ phuḥ jaḥ |<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-852"/> “Mudgara and the others are placed in the doors, And Puṣpā and the others in the corners.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-530">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-850</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཛྃ་གུ་ལི་ཡི་སྦྱོར་བ་ཡིས། །ཆུ་ཡི་སྟེང་ནས་རྟག་ཏུ་འགྲོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Through the yoga of Jāṅgulī, One will always walk on water.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-531">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-853</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཀུ་རུ་ཀུལླེ་རབ་སྒྲུབ་ཐབས། །དེ་ནས་ཡང་དག་བཤད་པར་བྱ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-853"/>“Next, I will explain The practice of Kurukullā.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-532">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-853</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་གིས་བསྒོམས་པ་ཙམ་གྱིས་ནི། །ཀླུ་ཡི་བུ་མོ་རབ་འགུགས་པ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Merely by visualizing her One can summon a female nāga.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-533">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-854</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཁ་དོག་དམར་པོ་ཞལ་བཞི་པ། །ཕྱག་བརྒྱད་དང་ནི་རབ་ཏུ་ལྡན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-854"/>“She is red, has four faces, And is arrayed with eight arms.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-534">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-854</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཧྲཱིཿཡི་ས་བོན་ལས་བྱུང་བས། །ཀླུ་ནི་འགུགས་པར་བྱེད་པ་ཡིན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>She arises from the syllable hrīḥ And is capable of summoning nāgas.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-535">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-855</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཕྱག་བརྒྱད་དུ་ནི་ཀླུ་དགོད་དེ། །མཐའ་ཡས་ལ་སོགས་ཀླུ་རིགས་བརྒྱད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-855"/>“Nāgas from the eight families, Ananta first, Should be placed in her eight hands.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-536">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-855</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལུས་ནི་སྦྲུལ་གྱིས་རབ་ཏུ་བརྒྱན། །བརྟུལ་ཞུགས་ཅན་གྱིས་མཛེས་མ་བསྒོམ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The vow holder should imagine her graceful body To be beautifully adorned with snakes.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-537">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-857</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྔགས་ནི་ཨོཾ་ཀུ་རུ་ཀུལླེ་ཧྲཱིཿཕུཿསྭཱ་ཧཱ། དེ་ནས་གསང་བ་བཤད་པར་བྱ། །བསྡུས་ནས་ཡིན་གྱི་རྒྱས་པ་མིན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-857"/>“The mantra is:<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-858"/> oṁ kurukulle hrīḥ phuḥ svāhā |<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-859"/> “Now I will relate the secret, In brief, not extensively.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-538">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-857</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་ཞིག་ཤེས་པ་ཙམ་གྱིས་ནི། །ལྷ་ཡི་བུ་མོ་འགུགས་བྱེད་པ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Merely knowing it enables one To summon Apsarases.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-539">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-860</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཕྱག་གཉིས་པ་ལ་ཞལ་གཅིག་སྟེ། །ཕྱག་ན་མདའ་དང་གཞུ་བསྣམས་པ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-860"/>“One should visualize Vajrānaṅga With two arms and one face, And an arrow and a bow in hand.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-540">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-860</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལུས་ནི་སེར་པོ་ཆེན་པོ་ཡི། །རྡོ་རྗེ་ལུས་མེད་བསྒོམ་པར་བྱ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>His mighty body is yellow in color.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-541">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-862</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཤར་དུ་དགའ་མ་བསྒོམ་པར་བྱ། །ལྷོ་རུ་འདོད་པས་མཛེས་མ་བསྒོམ། །ནུབ་ཏུ་འདོད་པའི་ལྷ་མོ་བསྒོམ། །བྱང་དུ་འདོད་པའི་ལྕགས་ཀྱུའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-862"/>“Rati should be visualized in the east, Madanasundarī in the south, Kāmadevī in the west, And Madanotsukā in the north.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-542">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-864</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདོད་པའི་ལྷ་མོ་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱི། །ཕྱག་ཏུ་མདའ་དང་གཞུ་བསྒོམ་བྱ། །སེར་དང་དམར་དང་དེ་བཞིན་ལྗང་། །དམར་སྐྱ་དག་ནི་བསྒོམ་པར་བྱ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-864"/>“All of these love goddesses Should be imagined holding a bow and arrow And visualized as yellow, Red, green, and pink.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-543">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-866</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མཚམས་རྣམས་སུ་ནི་རྟག་དགོད་པ། །མི་འགག་དེ་བཞིན་མཚམས་ཀྱི་བདག །གཡི་དང་སྤྲེའུའི་རྒྱལ་མཚན་ནི། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-866"/>“Aniruddha and Uṣāpati Are always placed in the corners.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-544">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-866</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྒོ་ཡི་ཕྱོགས་ཀྱི་བཤད་པར་བྱ། །འདོད་པ་འགྱིང་དང་འགྱིང་བག་ཅན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Vasanta and Makaraketu Are said to be in the doors.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-545">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-868</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དྲན་དང་དེ་བཞིན་མདའ་གྲི་ཅན། །ལྷ་རྣམས་དེ་དག་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱི། །དབུ་ལ་གཤིན་རྗེའི་གཤེད་པོ་བསྒོམ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-868"/>“Yama’s slayer should be visualized On the heads of all the deities Kandarpa and Darpaka, Smara, and Bāṇāyudha.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-546">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-870</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བུད་མེད་ཀྱི་ནི་པདྨ་རུ། །རྡོ་རྗེ་ལུས་མེད་བསྒོམ་པར་བྱ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-870"/>“Vajrānaṅga should be visualized Standing inside a woman’s lotus.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-547">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-870</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡི་གེ་ཧྲཱིཿལས་ཡང་དག་བྱུང་། །ཀུན་ཏུ་འཁོར་བར་རྣམ་པར་འཕྲོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Arisen from the syllable śīt He emits light in all directions.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-548">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-873</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བསླུས་ཤིང་གཡེངས་པ་བསྒོམ་པར་བྱ། །མྱོས་<tei:ref folio="F.149.b"/>ནས་བདེ་བའི་འདོད་ཡིད་ཀྱིས། །དམར་པོའི་གོས་ཀྱིས་ཡོངས་དཀྲིས་ཏེ། །རྐང་པའི་དྲུང་དུ་ལྷུང་བར་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-873"/>“One should imagine the desired woman Trembling, beside herself with anxious desire, She has fallen at one’s feet, Wrapped in a red garment.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-549">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-875</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེར་ནི་སྔགས་ཀྱང་བཟླས་པར་བྱ། །ཡི་གེ་ཨོཾ་ནི་རིང་པོར་དྲང་། །ཡི་གེ་སྭཱ་ཧཱ་མཐའ་མར་སྦྱིན། །ཡི་གེ་སི་ཏིའི་སྔགས་བཟླས་བྱ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-875"/>“This is the moment to recite the mantra, Pronouncing the mantra-syllable śīt Extending from the syllable oṁ, With svāhā placed at the end.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-550">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-877</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཆེ་གེ་མོ་ཞིག་བདག་དབང་འགྱུར། །ཐམས་ཅད་དུ་ནི་བསྒོམས་བྱས་ན། །ནག་པོའི་ཚིག་ནི་ཇི་བཞིན་གྱིས། །རྣལ་འབྱོར་འདོད་པས་དེ་འཐོབ་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-877"/>“If one continuously meditates, ‘May the woman so-and-so be enthralled,’ The yogin will obtain her through desire, Just as the Dark One declared.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-551">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-879</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱི་སྐུ་གསུང་ཐུགས་གཤིན་རྗེའི་གཤེད་ནག་པོའི་རྒྱུད་ལས་ལུས་མེད་རྡོ་རྗེའི་སྒྲུབ་ཐབས་རིམ་པར་ཕྱེ་བ་སྟེ་བཅྭ་ལྔ་པའོ།། །།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-879"/>This was the fifteenth chapter, “The Practice of Vajrānaṅga,” from The Tantra of Black Yamāri, the Body, Speech, and Mind of All Tathāgatas.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-552">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-881</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཧེ་རུ་ཀ་ཆེན་སྒྲུབ་པའི་ཐབས། །དེ་ནས་ཡང་དག་བཤད་པར་བྱ། །རྣལ་འབྱོར་འཁོར་བར་བཅིངས་པ་ལ། །གང་ཞིག་ཤེས་པས་མྱུར་གྲོལ་བ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-section-1-16"/>Chapter 16: The Practice of Heruka<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-881"/> “Next, I will explain The practice of the great Heruka, Knowing which, the yogin Will quickly be liberated from saṃsāra’s fetters.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-553">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-882</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཕྱག་གཉིས་པ་ལ་ཞལ་གཅིག་སྟེ། །ཁ་དོག་སྔོན་པོ་ཕྱེད་གར་ཅན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-882"/>“One should visualize him with two arms and one face, Blue in color, and in the half-dancing posture.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-554">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-882</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྡོ་རྗེ་ཕྱག་ཏུ་བསྒོམ་པར་བྱ། །གཞན་ཡང་ཐོད་པ་བསྒོམ་པར་བྱ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He should be visualized with a vajra in one hand And a skull cup in the other.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-555">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-884</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྤྱན་གསུམ་སྐྲ་ནི་གྱེན་དུ་འགྲེང་། །ཕྱག་རྒྱ་ལྔ་ཡིས་རྣམ་པར་བརྒྱན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-884"/>“He has three eyes, his hair flows upward, And he is adorned with the five mudrās.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-556">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-884</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཁ་ཊྭཱྃ་ག་ནི་གཡོན་ཕྱོགས་སུ། །ཕྲེང་བ་དག་གིས་རྐང་པ་བརྒྱན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He has a khaṭvāṅga at his left side And his feet are adorned with anklets.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-557">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-886</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ས་བོན་ཧཱུྃ་ལས་ཡང་དག་བྱུང་། །ཡི་དགས་ལ་གནས་རྟག་ཏུ་དགོད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-886"/>“He has emerged from the syllable hūṁ And should always be placed standing on a preta.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-558">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-886</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སངས་རྒྱས་ལྔ་རུ་རབ་སྦྱོར་བ། །ཐོད་པ་ལྔ་ནི་དབུ་ལའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The five skulls on his head Are related to the five buddhas.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-559">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-886</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཅོད་པན་ལ་ནི་མི་བསྐྱོད་བསྒོམ། །ཧེ་རུ་ཀར་གྲགས་བསྒོམ་པར་བྱ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>One should visualize Akṣobhya on their crown— This is how one visualizes the one called Heruka.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-560">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-888</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཤར་དུ་ཆོས་ཀྱི་འཁོར་ལོ་མ། །སངས་རྒྱས་བྱང་ཆུབ་ལྷོ་རུའོ། །འདོད་པ་ཀུན་གྱི་འཁྲིས་མ་ནུབ། །བྱང་དུ་ཧེ་རུ་ཀ་ཉིད་འདྲ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-888"/>“In the east is Dharmacakrā, In the south, Buddhabodhi, In the west, Sarvakāmalatā, And in the north, the one resembling Heruka.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-561">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-890</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྒྱན་ཀུན་གྱིས་ནི་རྣམ་བརྒྱན་པའི། །ཁ་དོག་སྣ་ཚོགས་རྣམ་པར་དགོད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-890"/>“They are adorned with every ornament And are arrayed in their respective colors.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-562">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-890</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཟུགས་མཛེས་ཡི་དགས་ལ་བཞུགས་པ། །གཏི་མུག་ཐམས་ཅད་ཉེར་འཇོམས་བྱེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They are alluring, stand on pretas, And destroy all delusion.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-563">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-892</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཆོས་འཁོར་ཨ་ཤྭཏྠའི་དབྱུག་པ། །དེ་བཞིན་ཡིད་བཞིན་ནོར་བུའི་ཤིང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-892"/>“They are to be drawn in the midst of a Dharma wheel, An aśvattha sprig, and a wish-fulfilling tree.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-564">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-892</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལྷ་མོ་རྣམས་ཀྱི་ཕྱག་གཡས་སུ། །རྡོ་རྗེ་ཡང་ནི་བསྒོམ་པར་བྱ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>A vajra should be visualized In the goddesses’ right hands.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-565">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-892</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཆོས་ཀྱི་འཁོར་ལོ་ཐམས་ཅད་ལ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They should be visualized on a circular disk, With a human skull in their other hand.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-566">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-895</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཐོད་པའི་སྣོད་ནི་གཡོན་པ་ལ། །སྤྱན་མ་མཱ་མ་ཀཱི་སྒྲོལ་མ། །གོས་དཀར་ཡིད་དུ་འོང་བ་རྣམས། །མེ་ལ་སོགས་པའི་མཚམས་བཞི་རུ། །འཁོར་ལོ་ཕྱི་རོལ་གཤིན་གཤེད་དོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-895"/>“The enchanting Locanā, Māmakī, Tārā, and Pāṇḍarā Are in the four corners, beginning in the southeast, And Yamāntaka is in the outer circle.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-567">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-896</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཤེས་རབ་མཐར་བྱེད་རྟ་མགྲིན་དང་། །འཁྱིལ་བར་བཅས་པ་བསྒོམ་<tei:ref folio="F.150.a"/>པར་བྱ། །འཁོར་ལོ་ཡི་ནི་སྒོ་སྲུངས་ཏེ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-896"/>One should visualize Prajñāntaka, Hayagrīva, Sarvakuṇḍali, And the maṇḍala’s door guardians as well, Imagining them following the proper rite.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-568">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-897</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཆོ་གའི་ལས་ནི་མཐོང་བས་སོ། །གཤིན་རྗེའི་གཤེད་ནག་པོའི་རྒྱུད་ལས་ཧེ་རུ་ཀ་བསྒྲུབ་པའི་རིམ་པར་ཕྱེ་བ་སྟེ་བཅུ་དྲུག་པའོ།། །།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-897"/>This was the sixteenth chapter, “The Practice of Heruka,” from The Tantra of Black Yamāri, the Body, Speech, and Mind of All Tathāgatas.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-569">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-899</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྣམ་པ་ལྔ་ནི་བསྒོམས་བྱས་ལ། །སངས་རྒྱས་གཟུགས་ནི་བསྒོམ་པར་བྱ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-section-1-17"/>Chapter 17: Bodhicitta<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-899"/> “After visualizing the five aspects, The adept should visualize an image of the Buddha.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-570">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-899</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སངས་རྒྱས་གཟུགས་ནི་བསྒོམ་པ་ཡིས། །མཁས་པས་འཁོར་ལོ་བསྒོམ་པར་བྱ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>After visualizing the image of the Buddha, They should visualize the wheel bearer.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-571">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-903</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གྲུ་བཞི་ཡི་ནི་སྦྱོར་བ་ཡིས། །འཁོར་ལོ་བསྐྱེད་པར་བྱ་བ་སྟེ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-903"/>“The performance of the four songs Initiates the emergence of the wheel bearer.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-572">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-903</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཙརྩི་ཀཱ་སོགས་གླུ་དང་ནི། །དྲུག་པ་སྐྱེས་སོགས་ལེན་པར་བྱེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Cārcikā and the others offer songs In the ṣāḍava and other scales.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-573">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-905</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྙིང་རྗེ་ཁྲོས་པའི་དད་སྒྲོལ་བཞེངས། །ཁམས་གསུམ་ཀུན་གྱི་གཏི་མུག་སོལ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-905"/>“ ‘Rise, lord of compassionate wrath, And remove the ignorance of the three worlds!’</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-574">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-907</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དད་སྒྲོལ་གསོལ་བས་མ་བཞུགས་བཞེངས། །བདུད་འདི་དག་ལས་རྒྱལ་བར་མཛོད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-907"/>“ ‘I beg you, Lord, do not linger but rise, Be victorious over the māras!’</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-575">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-909</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇིག་རྟེན་མགོན་པོ་སྟོང་ཉིད་ཇི་སྟེ་བཞུགས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-909"/>“ ‘World protector, how can you dwell in emptiness?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-576">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-910</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དད་སྒྲོལ་འཇིག་རྟེན་བསོད་ནམས་ཀྱིས་བཞེངས་ཤིག །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Arise, Lord, through the power of the world’s merit!’<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-910"/> “ ‘Why do you remain in emptiness?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-577">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-910</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱང་ཆུབ་འདོད་པའི་འཇིག་རྟེན་མགྲོན་བོས་ནས། །ཁྱོད་ནི་སྟོང་པ་ཉིད་ལ་སེམས་པར་བྱེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The world moves toward the nature of awakening.’</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-578">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-912</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཇི་ལྟར་སྐར་མདའ་འཕོ་བ་བཞིན། །བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་ལ་ཞུགས་པར་གྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-912"/>“Bodhicitta should be reached, Like the trajectory of a shooting star.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-579">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-912</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྡོ་རྗེ་འཆང་རང་ངོ་བོ་ཉིད། །སྙིང་རྗེ་དང་ནི་འདོད་ཆགས་སེམས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The vajra holder himself has melted, Through a mind suffused with compassion.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-580">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-914</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དང་པོར་བསྒོམ་པ་རྣལ་འབྱོར་ཏེ། །གཉིས་པ་རྗེས་ཀྱི་རྣལ་འབྱོར་ཡིན། །གསུམ་པ་ཤིན་ཏུ་རྣལ་འབྱོར་ཏེ། །བཞི་པ་རྣལ་འབྱོར་ཆེན་པོའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-914"/>“First one should cultivate yoga, Second, anuyoga, Third, atiyoga, And fourth, mahāyoga.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-581">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-915</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྡོ་རྗེ་སེམས་དཔའ་རྫོགས་པ་ཡིན། །རྣལ་འབྱོར་ཡིན་པར་འདི་ལྟར་འདོད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-915"/>“The completion of Vajrasattva Is what is meant by yoga.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-582">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-915</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནི་རྒྱུ་མཐུན་ལྷ་ཡི་སྐུ། །རྗེས་ཀྱི་རྣལ་འབྱོར་ཡིན་པར་གྲགས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The melting of the deity’s body Is known as anuyoga.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-583">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-918</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཁོར་ལོ་ཐམས་ཅད་ཡོངས་རྫོགས་པ། །ཤིན་ཏུ་རྣལ་འབྱོར་ཡིན་པར་གྲགས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-918"/>“The completion of the entire circle Is called atiyoga.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-584">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-919</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྐུ་དང་གསུང་དང་ཐུགས་རྣམས་དང་། །ལྷ་ཡི་མིག་སོགས་བྱིན་རླབས་དང་། །ཡེ་ཤེས་འཁོར་ལོ་གཞུག་པ་དང་། །བདུད་རྩི་མྱང་བ་དག་དང་ནི། །མཆོད་དང་བསྟོད་པ་ཆེན་པོ་དག །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-919"/>“The empowerment of the divine eyes, As well as body, speech, and mind, Entry into the wisdom circle, The tasting of the nectar, And the extensive offerings and praises, Are known as mahāyoga.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-585">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-922</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྣལ་འབྱོར་ཆེན་པོ་ཞེས་བྱའོ། །སློབ་དཔོན་ལ་ནི་བརྙས་མི་བྱ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-922"/>“The teacher should not be disparaged.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-586">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-922</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བདེ་གཤེགས་བཀའ་ལས་འདའ་མི་བྱ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The sugatas commands should not be transgressed.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-587">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-922</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་བཞིན་སྤུན་ལ་ཁྲོ་བ་དང་། །ཉེས་པ་བསྒྲག་པར་མི་བྱའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Likewise, one should not grow angry with their brethren And should not reveal their faults.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-588">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-924</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་ཀྱང་གཏང་མི་བྱ། །བདག་གཞན་ཆོས་ལ་སྨད་མི་བྱ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-924"/>“One should never abandon bodhicitta Or dishonor their own or others’ Dharma.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-589">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-924</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སེམས་ཅན་ལ་ནི་བྱམས་པ་དག །ནམ་ཡང་གཏང་བར་མི་བྱའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>One should never relinquish Their love for other beings.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-590">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-925</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡོངས་སུ་མ་སྨིན་སེམས་ཅན་ལ། །གསང་<tei:ref folio="F.150.b"/>བ་དག་ནི་བསྟན་མི་བྱ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-925"/>“One should not teach secrets To those who are not yet ripened.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-591">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-925</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བདག་སོགས་ཕུང་པོ་བརྙས་མི་བྱ། །གྲོང་པའི་ཆོས་ནི་སུན་མི་གདོན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>One should not revile their own aggregates Nor disparage village ways.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-592">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-927</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གདུག་ལ་བྱམས་པ་རྟག་ཏུ་སྤང་། །ཆོས་ལ་ཚད་གཞལ་བར་མི་བྱ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-927"/>“One should always avoid those enamored with wickedness And not take the measure of meritorious acts.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-593">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-927</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སེམས་ཅན་དད་པ་ཅན་མི་བསླུ། །རྟག་ཏུ་དམ་ཚིག་བསྟེན་པར་བྱ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>One should not deceive beings who have faith And should always honor their samaya.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-594">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-930</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བུད་མེད་ཤེས་རབ་རང་བཞིན་ལ། །སྨོད་པ་ཉེས་པ་དེ་བཞིན་ནོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-930"/>“Deprecating women, the nature of wisdom, Is considered an offence.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-595">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-930</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྣལ་འབྱོར་སློང་མོས་རྒྱུ་མི་བྱ། །རྣལ་འབྱོར་སྤང་བར་མི་བྱ་སྟེ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Yogins should never go out for alms, Nor should they forsake their yoga.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-596">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-931</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྟག་པར་རྒྱུན་དུ་གསང་སྔགས་བཟླ། །རྟག་ཏུ་དམ་ཚིག་ལ་སོགས་བསྟེན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-931"/>“They should always and continuously recite mantra And always honor their samayas.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-597">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-931</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གལ་ཏེ་བག་མེད་བྱུང་གྱུར་ན། །བླ་མ་དམ་ཚིག་ལ་གནོད་ན། །དེས་ནི་དཀྱིལ་འཁོར་བྲི་བྱས་ལ། །བདེ་གཤེགས་རྣམས་ལ་ཉེས་པ་བཤགས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>If, in a moment of carelessness, One damages the samaya with their teacher, They should draw a maṇḍala And confess their faults to the sugatas.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-598">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-932</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྙིང་རྗེ་ཅན་གྱིས་མི་བརྟག་པར། །དད་པས་བླ་མའི་དམ་ཚིག་བསྲུང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-932"/>“The compassionate should, without rationalization, Faithfully guard the samaya with their master.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-599">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-932</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཉེས་པ་མ་ལུས་རྣམ་སྤངས་སེམས་ཀྱིས་ནི། །བསམ་གཏན་ལ་སོགས་བཟླས་པ་མཆོག་གཞོལ་བར། །བྱས་ལ་རྟག་ཏུ་བླ་མ་བླ་མར་བྱ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They should continuously venerate their master Through great effort in meditation, recitation, and the rest, All with a mind that has relinquished its faults.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-600">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-935</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བརྟན་ཞིང་དུལ་ལ་སྙིང་རྗེ་གཅིག་ཏུ་སེམས། །དད་དང་ལྷག་པའི་བསམ་པས་བཟོད་པ་འཛིན། །སློབ་མ་བླ་མ་ལ་ནི་གུས་པ་དང་། །དད་པས་གཤིན་རྗེའི་གཤེད་ལ་གུས་པ་ལ། །བརྟུལ་ཞུགས་ལྡན་པས་དེ་ནི་ཡོངས་སྦྱིན་བྱ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-935"/>“The vow holder should ripen the disciple Who is steadfast, disciplined, singularly compassionate, Who endures with faith and determination, Who is devoted to their master, And is faithfully devoted to Yamāri.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-601">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-937</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱི་མཆོག་ཏུ་དགའ་བ་ཆེན་པོའི་ངོ་བོ་རྡོ་རྗེ་འཆང་གི་གསུང་ཉེ་བར་ཐོས་ནས་ཅང་མི་སྨྲ་བར་གྱུར་ཏེ། འདི་ལྟ་བུའི་ཆེད་དུ་བརྗོད་པས་ཆེད་དུ་བརྗོད་དོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-937"/>Once all the blessed tathāgatas heard the words of the vajra bearer, the embodiment of supremely great bliss, they fell silent.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-602">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-940</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བརྟུལ་ཞུགས་མཐར་ཐུག་ཐོད་པ་ཆེན་པོ་ལྟར། །འཁྲུལ་འཁོར་མཐར་ཐུག་གཤིན་རྗེའི་གཤེད་ཀྱི་རྒྱུད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Then, they spoke this praise:<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-940"/> “Just as the great skull cup is the ultimate expression of the vow, The yantras are the ultimate expression of Yamāri’s tantras.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-603">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-940</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྒྱུད་ཀྱི་མཐར་ཐུག་པ་ནི་འདུས་པ་སྟེ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The ultimate expression of the tantras is the assembly.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-604">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-940</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱུང་བར་མ་གྱུར་འབྱུང་བར་མི་འགྱུར་རོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Nothing else has been or will be.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-605">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-1317</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཨེ་མའོ་ཞི་བ་ཆེན་པོའི་ཆོས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-1317"/>“How amazing, the Dharma of great peace!</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-606">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-1317</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཨེ་མའོ་ཁྲོ་བོ་འཇིགས་མཛད་པ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>How amazing, the wrathful terrifier!</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-607">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-1317</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཨེ་མའོ་མྱ་ངན་འདས་པའི་མཆོག །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>How amazing, the supreme nirvāṇa!</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-608">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-1317</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཨེ་མའོ་འཁོར་བ་ཞི་བ་ཉིད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>How amazing, the pacifier of saṃsāra!</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-609">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-942</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཨེ་མའོ་འདི་ནི་རབ་ཏུ་མཚར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-942"/>“How amazing! This is truly marvelous!</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-610">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-942</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཉེས་པ་གང་དེ་ཡོན་ཏན་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Faults become qualities.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-611">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-942</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱང་ཆུབ་མེད་ཅིང་མངོན་རྟོགས་མེད། །དངོས་པོ་མ་ཡིན་བསྒོམ་བྱ་མིན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>There is no awakening, no realization, No being and no becoming.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-612">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-944</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཁམས་མ་ཡིན་ཞིང་རྣམ་ཤེས་མིན། །ནམ་མཁའི་ཁམས་དང་མཚུངས་པ་ཉིད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-944"/>“There are no elements and no consciousness, All is equal to the element of space.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-613">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-944</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ནམ་མཁའ་ལྟ་བུར་བདག་མེད་པ། །ཆོས་འདི་<tei:ref folio="F.151.a"/>བདེ་བ་ཆེན་པོ་སྟེ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Devoid of self, just like the sky, This Dharma is great bliss.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-614">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-945</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ས་ཡང་མ་ཡིན་ཆུ་མིན་ཏེ། །མེ་མིན་རླུང་མིན་ནམ་མཁའ་མིན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-945"/>“There is no earth, no water, No fire, no wind, and no space.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-615">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-945</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྡོ་རྗེ་སེམས་དཔའི་སྦྱོར་བ་ཡིས། །བསྐྱེད་པ་ཡང་ནི་རབ་གནས་ནས། །དངོས་པོ་ཐམས་ཅད་དངོས་མེད་བཤད། །དངོས་པོ་མེད་ཅེས་མ་བསྒྲགས་པ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Once generated and consecrated, Through the method of the vajra-being, All that exists is said to not exist And no claim is made about the nonexistent.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-616">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-947</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྣལ་འབྱོར་སྦྱོར་བ་དང་འབྲེལ་ཕྱིར། །ཆད་པ་མ་ཡིན་རྟག་པ་མིན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-947"/>“Through the connection between yoga and being a yogin, There is neither cessation nor permanence.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-617">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-947</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡན་ལག་མེད་ཅིང་ཁ་དོག་མེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>There are no arms and no colors.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-618">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-947</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཐོག་མ་བར་དང་མཐའ་སྤངས་པ། །དངོས་པོ་ཐམས་ཅད་མེད་པར་འགྱུར། །མཆོག་ཏུ་དགའ་བའི་མཚན་ཉིད་དོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Beginning, middle, and end are abandoned, And all existents disappear— This is the quality of supreme joy.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-619">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-950</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཙརྩི་ཀཱ་ཆེན་པོ་ལ་སོགས་པས་ཆེད་དུ་བརྗོད་པས་ཆེད་དུ་བརྗོད་དོ། །བསོད་ནམས་སྡིག་པ་དག་དང་མ་འབྲེལ་བས། །མཆོག་ཏུ་དགའ་བ་དྲི་མེད་དག་པའི་མགོན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-950"/>Then, the blessed great Carcikā and the others spoke this praise:<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-952"/> “Unrelated to both merit and evil, Supreme joy is the stainless, pure protector.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-620">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-950</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་བཞིན་ཉིད་ཀྱི་གཏེར་ཆེན་གཅིག་པུ་དང་། །ཀུན་ཀྱང་སྙིང་རྗེའི་སེམས་ཀྱིས་མགོན་འདི་ཡོད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>It is the singular great treasure of thusness, A protector as the universal compassionate mind.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-621">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-953</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཆོས་རྣམས་ངོ་བོ་བདེ་བ་ཆེན་པོའི་དངོས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-953"/>“All phenomena have the nature of great bliss.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-622">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-953</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མཆོག་ཏུ་དགའ་བ་འདི་ཡི་ངོ་བོ་ཉིད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Supreme joy is its intrinsic nature.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-623">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-953</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ལ་གཟུགས་མེད་བསོད་ནམས་མེད་ཅིང་སྡིག་པ་མེད། །སྐྱེ་བ་དང་ནི་འགག་པ་དག་ནི་ཡོད་མ་ཡིན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>It has no form, merit, or evil, Nor does it undergo arising and ceasing.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-624">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-955</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱི་སྐུ་གསུང་ཐུགས་གཤིན་རྗེའི་གཤེད་ནག་པོའི་རྒྱུད་ལས་བྱང་ཆུབ་ཀྱི་སེམས་ཀྱི་རིམ་པར་ཕྱེ་བ་སྟེ་བཅུ་བདུན་པའོ།། །།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-955"/>This was the seventeenth chapter, “Bodhicitta,” from The Tantra of Black Yamāri, the Body, Speech, and Mind of All Tathāgatas.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-625">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-958</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་གཏམ་རྒྱུད་བཤད་པར་བྱ་སྟེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-section-1-18"/>Chapter 18<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-958"/> “Now I will relate the history of this tantra.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-626">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-959</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་མངོན་པར་བྱང་ཆུབ་པའི་དུས་སུ་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཐུབ་པ་ཆེན་པོ་ལ་བྱང་ཆུབ་ཀྱི་བར་དུ་གཅོད་པའི་ཕྱིར་ཤིན་ཏུ་འཇིགས་སུ་རུང་བའི་འཇིགས་པ་ཆེན་པོ་སྟོན་ཅིང་། བདུད་ཀྱི་དཔུང་ཆེན་པོ་ལྷགས་ཏེ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-959"/>“When the Bhagavat was about to attain awakening, a great army of māras approached, displaying fearsome terrors in order to interfere with the awakening of the blessed Great Sage.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-627">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-959</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེའི་དུས་ན་བདུད་ཆེན་པོ་ལས་རྣམ་པར་རྒྱལ་བ་ཞེས་བྱ་བའི་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་ལ་སྙོམས་པར་ཞུགས་ཏེ། བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཉིད་ཀྱི་སྐུ་གསུང་ཐུགས་རྡོ་རྗེ་རྣམས་ལས་གཤིན་རྗེའི་གཤེད་ཀྱི་ཁྲོ་བོ་ངེས་པར་ཕྱུང་སྟེ། ངེས་པར་ཕྱུང་ནས་ཀྱང་ལག་ན་རྡོ་རྗེ་ཐུབ་པ་ཆེན་པོའི་བཀའ་བཞིན་བྱེད་པ་ལ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>At that time, the Bhagavat entered the meditative absorption called victory over great māras and emanated the wrathful great Yamāri from the vajras of his body, speech, and mind.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-628">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-961</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཕྱག་ན་རྡོ་རྗེ་ཁྱོད་འདི་ལྟ་བུའི་གཤིན་རྗེའི་གཤེད་ཀྱི་ཁྲོ་བོའི་གཟུགས་སུ་བསྒྱུར་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Once emanated, the King of Sages gave this command to Vajrapāṇi:<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-961"/> “Vajrapāṇi!</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-629">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-961</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བདུད་དང་། ཀླུ་དང་། གནོད་སྦྱིན་དང་། ལྷ་མ་ཡིན་དང་། ལྷ་རྣམས་ཀྱང་ཆོམས་ཤིག །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Assume this form of the wrathful Yamāri and destroy, bind, and kill the māras, nāgas, yakṣas, asuras, and devas!”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-630">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-965</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཆིངས་ཤིག །རྟོགས་ཤིག་ཅེས་གསུངས་སོ། །དེའི་དུས་ན་<tei:ref folio="F.151.b"/>ཇི་ལྟར་བདག་གིས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་གསུངས་པ་ཐོས་ཏེ། སྐད་ཅིག་ལ་བཟུང་ཞིང་དོན་བཟུང་སྟེ་བསྡུས་ནས་རབ་ཏུ་ཡིད་ལ་བྱས་སོ། །ཞེས་གསང་བ་ཆེན་པོའི་བདག་པོ་ཆེན་པོ་རྡོ་རྗེ་རིགས་ཀྱི་གཙོ་བོ་ནཱ་ད་ཀུ་བེ་རའི་ཡབ་ཀྱིས་དེ་སྐད་ཅེས་གསུངས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-965"/>The great Lord of the Guhyakas, the head of the vajra family, and father of Nalakūbera, then said:<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-967"/> “At that time, I heard the words of the Bhagavat, instantly grasped and understood the meaning, compiled it, and took it to heart.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-631">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-969</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཨཽཌྱན་གྱི་ཡུལ་ནས་ཡང་དག་པར་བྱུང་བ་དངོས་གྲུབ་ཐམས་ཅད་སྐྱེད་པར་བྱེད་པ་རྒྱུད་ཀྱི་རྒྱལ་པོ་འབུམ་ཕྲག་བདུན་པ་ལས་ཕྱུང་བ་གཤིན་རྗེའི་གཤེད་ནག་པོའི་རྒྱུད་ལས་ལེའུ་བཅྭ་བརྒྱད་པའོ།། །།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-969"/>This was the eighteenth chapter of the Tantra of Black Yamāri, which was extracted from the King of Tantras in seven hundred thousand lines and revealed in the land of Oḍḍiyāna, and which produces all siddhis.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-632">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-970</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱི་སྐུ་གསུང་ཐུགས་གཤིན་རྗེའི་གཤེད་ནག་པོའི་རྒྱུད་རྫོགས་སོ།། །།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-970"/>The Tantra of Black Yamāri, the Body, Speech, and Mind of all Tathāgatas, is complete.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-633">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-971</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྒྱ་གར་གྱི་མཁན་པོ་ཆེན་པོ་མཁས་པ་དཱི་པཾ་ཀར་ཤྲཱིཛྙཱ་ན་དང་། བོད་ཀྱི་ལོཙྪ་བ་དགེ་སློང་ཚུལ་ཁྲིམས་རྒྱལ་བས་བསྒྱུར་ཅིང་ཞུས་ཏེ་གཏན་ལ་ཕབ་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-083-015-971"/>This was translated, edited, and finalized by the great Indian preceptor Dīpaṅkaraśrījñāna and the Tibetan translator, the monk Tsültrim Gyalwa.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-083-015-TU-634">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-083-015-971</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སླད་ཀྱིས་ལོཙྪ་བ་དགེ་སློང་དར་མ་གྲགས་ཀྱིས་བཅོས་ལ། དེ་ལས་ཀྱང་དགེ་སློང་རྡོ་རྗེ་གྲགས་ཀྱིས་བཅོས་སོ།། །།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Later, the translation was revised by the monk and translator Darma Drak, and then again by the monk Dorjé Drak.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>

</body>
</tmx>