<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tmx xmlns="http://www.lisa.org/tmx14" xmlns:eft="http://read.84000.co/ns/1.0" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" version="1.4b">
<header creationtool="InterText" creationtoolversion="1.0" datatype="PlainText" segtype="block" adminlang="en-us" srclang="bo" o-tmf="TEI" eft:text-id="UT22084-040-005" eft:text-version="v-1.0.7-2021"/>
<body>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-1">
            <prop type="folio">F.185.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-369</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཕགས་པ་ཀུན་ནས་སྒོའི་ལེའུ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་ཐེག་པ་<tei:ref folio="F.185.a"/>ཆེན་པོའི་མདོ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The Noble Mahāyāna Sūtra The Exposition on the Universal Gateway</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-2">
            <prop type="folio">F.185.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-15</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སངས་རྒྱས་དང་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཐམས་ཅད་ལ་ཕྱག་འཚལ་ལོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Homage to all buddhas and bodhisattvas.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-3">
            <prop type="folio">F.185.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-15</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདི་སྐད་བདག་གིས་ཐོས་པ་དུས་གཅིག་ན།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Thus did I hear at one time.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-4">
            <prop type="folio">F.185.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-369</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་རྒྱལ་པོའི་ཁབ་ན་བྱ་རྒོད་ཀྱི་ཕུང་པོའི་རི་ལ་དགེ་སློང་བརྒྱད་བརྒྱའི་དགེ་སློང་གི་དགེ་འདུན་ཆེན་པོ་དང་། བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་བཞི་ཁྲི་ཉིས་སྟོང་དང་ཐབས་ཅིག་ཏུ་བཞུགས་ཏེ</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The Blessed One was staying at Vulture Peak Mountain by Rājagṛha, together with a great saṅgha of eight hundred monks, and with forty-two thousand bodhisattvas.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-5">
            <prop type="folio">F.185.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-369</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེའི་ཚེ་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོ་དྲི་མ་མེད་པའི་སྙིང་པོ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་དགུ་ཁྲི་ཉིས་སྟོང་དང་ལྷན་ཅིག་ཏུ་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་དགྲ་བཅོམ་པ་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་སངས་རྒྱས་མེ་ཏོག་ཀུན་དུ་རྒྱས་པའི་སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱི་ཞིང་འཇིག་རྟེན་གྱི་ཁམས་སྤྱོད་པ་ཡོངས་སུ་དག་པ་དང་ལྡན་པ་ནས་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>At that time, a bodhisattva great being by the name Amalagarbha, accompanied by ninety-two thousand other bodhisattvas, set out from the world known as Immaculate Conduct—the buddhafield of the thus-gone, worthy, perfect buddha Saṃkusumita.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-6">
            <prop type="folio">F.185.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-369</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇིག་རྟེན་གྱི་ཁམས་མི་མཇེད་འདིའི་བྱ་རྒོད་ཀྱི་ཕུང་པོའི་རི་ག་ལ་བ་དང་། བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་དགྲ་བཅོམ་པ་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་སངས་རྒྱས་ཤཱཀྱ་ཐུབ་པ་ག་ལ་བ་དེར་སོང་ངོ་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They traveled to Vulture Peak Mountain, here in this Sahā world, where the blessed, thus-gone, worthy, perfect buddha Śākyamuni dwelled.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-7">
            <prop type="folio">F.185.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-369</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོ་དྲི་མ་མེད་པའི་སྙིང་པོ་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའི་ཚོགས་ཆེན་པོས་ཡོངས་སུ་བསྐོར་ཅིང་། བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའི་ཚོགས་ཀྱིས་མདུན་དུ་བདར་ནས་ནམ་མཁའ་ལས་འོང་བར་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་གཟིགས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-19"/>As the bodhisattva great being Amalagarbha arrived in the sky, surrounded and attended by a great assembly of bodhisattvas, the Blessed One noticed him.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-8">
            <prop type="folio">F.185.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-369</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཟིགས་ནས་ཀྱང་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་འདི་སྙམ་དུ་དགོངས་ཏེ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>As he caught sight of him, the Blessed One thought,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-9">
            <prop type="folio">F.185.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-369</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོ་དྲི་མ་མེད་པའི་སྙིང་པོ་འདི་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་དགྲ་བཅོམ་པ་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་སངས་རྒྱས་མེ་ཏོག་ཀུན་དུ་རྒྱས་པས་ཀུན་ནས་སྒོའི་ལེའུའི་ཆོས་ཀྱི་རྣམ་གྲངས་འདི་ཡང་དག་པར་ཡོངས་སུ་གཟུང་བའི་ཕྱིར་འདིར་འོང་བར་གནང་སྟེ་བཏང་གིས། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“The bodhisattva great being Amalagarbha has been dispatched here by the thus-gone, worthy, perfect buddha Saṃkusumita in order to receive the Dharma teaching called The Exposition on the Universal Gateway.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-10">
            <prop type="folio">F.185.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-369</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ངས་ཀྱང་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་དག་བསྡུ་བར་བྱ་བར་ངེས་སོ་སྙམ་དུ་དགོངས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Therefore, I, for my part, should gather the bodhisattvas.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-11">
            <prop type="folio">F.185.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-369</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་དགོངས་པ་དེ་ལྟ་བུ་དགོངས་ནས་དེས་འཇིག་རྟེན་གྱི་ཁམས་མཐའ་ཡས་མུ་མེད་པ་དག་ན་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོ་གང་དག་འཁོད་པ་དེ་དག་འཇིག་རྟེན་གྱི་ཁམས་མི་མཇེད་འདིའི་བྱ་རྒོད་ཀྱི་ཕུང་པོའི་རི་ག་ལ་བ་དང་། བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ག་ལ་བ་དེར་ལྷགས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Then, because the Blessed One formed this intent, all bodhisattva great beings residing in boundless, infinite worlds<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="UT22084-040-005-20"/> arrived at Vulture Peak Mountain here in this Sahā world to meet the Blessed One.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-12">
            <prop type="folio">F.185.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-369</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལྷགས་ནས་ཀྱང་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱི་ཞབས་ལ་མགོ་བོས་ཕྱག་འཚལ་ཏེ་ཕྱོགས་གཅིག་ཏུ་འཁོད་དོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-21"/>Upon arrival, they bowed their heads to the Blessed One’s feet and sat down to one side. </seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-13">
            <prop type="folio">F.185.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-370</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་<tei:ref folio="F.185.b"/>དཔའ་ཆེན་པོ་གང་དག་བྱ་རྒོད་ཀྱི་ཕུང་པོའི་རི་ལ་ནང་དུ་ཡང་དག་འཇོག་ལ་ཞུགས་པ་དེ་དག་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱང་འདུས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>All the bodhisattva great beings at Vulture Peak Mountain who had retired for meditation<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="UT22084-040-005-22"/> also gathered.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-14">
            <prop type="folio">F.185.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-370</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོ་དྲི་མ་མེད་པའི་སྙིང་པོ་རིན་པོ་ཆེ་སྣ་བདུན་ལས་བྱས་པའི་པད་མ་འདབ་མ་སྟོང་དང་ལྡན་པ་ཐོགས་ནས་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་དགྲ་བཅོམ་པ་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་སངས་རྒྱས་ཤཱཀྱ་ཐུབ་པ་ག་ལ་བ་དེར་སོང་སྟེ་ཕྱིན་པ་དང་། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The bodhisattva great being Amalagarbha then went before the thus-gone, worthy, perfect buddha Śākyamuni, holding a thousand-petaled lotus flower made of the seven precious substances.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-15">
            <prop type="folio">F.185.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-370</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱི་ཞབས་ལ་མགོ་བོས་ཕྱག་འཚལ་ཏེ</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He bowed his head to the Blessed One’s feet and</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-16">
            <prop type="folio">F.185.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-370</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>པད་མ་འདབ་མ་སྟོང་དང་ལྡན་པ་དེ་ཕུལ་ནས། བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ལ་འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་གསོལ་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>offered him the thousand-petaled lotus. <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-23"/>Amalagarbha then said to the Blessed One,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-17">
            <prop type="folio">F.185.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-370</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་འཇིག་རྟེན་གྱི་ཁམས་སྤྱོད་པ། ཡོངས་སུ་དག་པ་དང་ལྡན་པ་ནས་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་དགྲ་བཅོམ་པ་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་སངས་རྒྱས་མེ་ཏོག་ཀུན་དུ་རྒྱས་པ་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ལ་སྙུན་གསོལ་ཏེ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Blessed One, the thus-gone, worthy, perfect buddha Saṃkusumita from the world Immaculate Conduct inquiries about the Blessed One’s health.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-18">
            <prop type="folio">F.185.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-370</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གནོད་པ་ཆུང་ངམ། ཉམ་ང་བ་ཉུང་ངམ། བསྐྱོད་པ་ཡང་ངམ། འཚོ་འམ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Does the Blessed One have but little trouble, grief, and agitation?<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="UT22084-040-005-24"/>
                </seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-19">
            <prop type="folio">F.185.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-370</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྟོབས་དང་ལྡན་པར་བདེ་བ་ལ་རེག་པར་གནས་སམ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Is he in good health, strong, and at ease?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-20">
            <prop type="folio">F.185.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-370</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ལ་སྙུན་མི་མངའ་འམ། གནོད་པ་ཆུང་ངམ་ཞེས་སྙུན་གསོལ་ཞིང་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Is the Blessed One free of illness and does he have but few troubles?”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-21">
            <prop type="folio">F.185.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-370</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་དགྲ་བཅོམ་པ་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་སངས་རྒྱས་ཤཱཀྱ་ཐུབ་པ་ཀུན་ནས་སྒོའི་ལེའུ་བསམ་གྱིས་མི་ཁྱབ་པ་ལ་འཇུག་པའི་ཆོས་ཀྱི་རྣམ་གྲངས་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོ་རྣམས་ལ་སྟོན་ཏམ་ཞེས་ཀྱང་གསུང་ངོ་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>When he had thus inquired after the Blessed One’s health, he added, “Might the blessed, thus-gone, worthy, perfect buddha Śākyamuni deliver the Dharma teaching pertaining to the inconceivable Exposition on the Universal Gateway to the bodhisattva great beings?”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-22">
            <prop type="folio">F.185.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-370</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོ་དྲི་མ་མེད་པའི་སྙིང་པོས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ལ་རྣམ་པ་དེ་དག་གསོལ་ནས་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་དེ་དག་དང་ལྷན་ཅིག་ཏུ་འཁོར་དང་བཅས་ཏེ་ནམ་མཁའ་ལ་སྐྱིལ་མོ་ཀྲུང་བཅས་ནས་འདུག་གོ །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Then, having asked the Blessed One in this way, the bodhisattva great being Amalagarbha sat down cross-legged in the sky in the midst of his retinue of bodhisattvas.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-23">
            <prop type="folio">F.185.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-370</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡང་དེའི་ཚེ་ན་འཇམ་དཔལ་གཞོན་ནུར་གྱུར་པ་འཁོར་དེ་ཉིད་དུ་འདུས་པར་གྱུར་ཏེ་འདུག་གོ །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-25"/>At that time, Prince Mañjuśrī was also present within that assembly.<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="UT22084-040-005-26"/>
                </seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-24">
            <prop type="folio">F.185.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-370</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་འཇམ་དཔལ་གཞོན་ནུར་གྱུར་པ་སྟན་ལས་ལངས་ཏེ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He rose from his seat,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-25">
            <prop type="folio">F.185.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-370</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བླ་གོས་ཕྲག་པ་གཅིག་ཏུ་གཟར་ནས་པུས་མོ་གཡས་པའི་ལྷ་ང་ས་ལ་བཙུགས་ཏེ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>draped his shawl over one shoulder, and knelt on his right knee.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-26">
            <prop type="folio">F.185.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-370</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ག་ལ་བ་དེ་ལོགས་སུ་ཐལ་མོ་སྦྱར་བ་བཏུད་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ལ་འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་གསོལ་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Joining his palms, he bowed toward the Blessed One and said,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-27">
            <prop type="folio">F.185.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-370</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་རྣམས་རྗེས་སུ་བཟུང་བའི་སླད་དུ་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པས་ཀུན་ནས་སྒོའི་ལེའུ་བསམ་གྱིས་མི་ཁྱབ་པ་ལ་འཇུག་པའི་ཆོས་ཀྱི་རྣམ་གྲངས་ལེགས་པར་བཤད་དུ་གསོལ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“In order to foster the bodhisattvas, I request the Blessed One, the Thus-Gone One, to thoroughly expound the Dharma teaching pertaining to the inconceivable Exposition on the Universal Gateway.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-28">
            <prop type="folio">F.186.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-371</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་བདག་གིས་<tei:ref folio="F.186.a"/>མངོན་པར་འཚལ་ཏེ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Blessed One, I beseech you.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-29">
            <prop type="folio">F.186.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-371</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདས་པའི་དུས་ན་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་དགྲ་བཅོམ་པ་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་སངས་རྒྱས་ཀུན་དུ་སྣང་བའི་སྒྲོན་མ་ལས་ཆོས་ཀྱི་རྣམ་གྲངས་འདི་ཐོས་ནས་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་བྱེ་བ་ཁྲག་ཁྲིག་བརྒྱ་སྟོང་ཕྲག་བརྒྱད་ཅུ་རྩ་བཞི་བསྐྱེད་པར་གྱུར། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>In the past, I received this teaching from the thus-gone, worthy, perfect buddha Bright Lamp and thereby developed eighty-four sextillion absorptions.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-30">
            <prop type="folio">F.186.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-371</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཟུངས་སྒྲུབ་པའི་སྒོ་བྱེ་བ་ཁྲག་ཁྲིག་བརྒྱ་སྟོང་ཕྲག་བདུན་ཅུ་རྩ་བདུན་ཡང་རྟོགས་པར་གྱུར་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>I also understood seventy-seven sextillion approaches to accomplishing dhāraṇīs.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-31">
            <prop type="folio">F.186.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-371</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ལྟ་ལགས་པས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་ཀྱང་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་རྣམས་རྗེས་སུ་གཟུང་བའི་སླད་དུ་ལེགས་པར་བཤད་དུ་གསོལ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>That being the case, may the Blessed One also teach this thoroughly in order to foster these bodhisattvas.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-32">
            <prop type="folio">F.186.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-371</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་སྐད་ཅེས་གསོལ་པ་དང་། བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་འཇམ་དཔལ་གཞོན་ནུར་གྱུར་པ་ལ་འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་བཀའ་སྩལ་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-27"/>In response, the Blessed One said the following to Prince Mañjuśrī:</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-33">
            <prop type="folio">F.186.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-371</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེའི་ཕྱིར་འཇམ་དཔལ་ཁྱོད་ལེགས་པར་རབ་ཏུ་ཉོན་ལ་ཡིད་ལ་ཟུང་ཤིག་དང་བཤད་དོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“To this effect, Mañjuśrī, listen carefully and keep in mind what I explain.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-34">
            <prop type="folio">F.186.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-371</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་གཞོན་ནུར་གྱུར་པས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་དེ་བཞིན་ནོ། །ཞེས་གསོལ་ཏེ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Prince Mañjuśrī answered, “Blessed One, so be it.”<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="UT22084-040-005-29"/>
                </seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-35">
            <prop type="folio">F.186.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-371</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱི་ལྟར་ཉན་པ་དང་། བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་དེ་ལ་འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་བཀའ་སྩལ་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-30"/>He listened closely as the Blessed One said,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-36">
            <prop type="folio">F.186.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-371</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་འདི་ལ་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོས་གཟུགས་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་དུ་རྟོགས་པར་བྱའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Mañjuśrī, bodhisattva great beings should understand form to be absorption.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-37">
            <prop type="folio">F.186.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-371</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྒྲ་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་དུ་རྟོགས་པར་བྱའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They should understand sound to be absorption.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-38">
            <prop type="folio">F.186.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-371</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དྲི་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་དུ་རྟོགས་པར་བྱའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They should understand scent to be absorption.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-39">
            <prop type="folio">F.186.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-371</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རོ་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་དུ་རྟོགས་པར་བྱའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They should understand taste to be absorption.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-40">
            <prop type="folio">F.186.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-371</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རེག་བྱ་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་དུ་རྟོགས་པར་བྱའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They should understand tactile objects to be absorption.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-41">
            <prop type="folio">F.186.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-371</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡིད་ཀྱི་ཁམས་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་དུ་རྟོགས་པར་བྱའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They should understand the objects of the mind to be absorption.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-42">
            <prop type="folio">F.186.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-371</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བུད་མེད་ཀྱི་གཟུགས་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་དུ་རྟོགས་པར་བྱའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-31"/>“They should understand women’s figures<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="UT22084-040-005-32"/> to be absorption.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-43">
            <prop type="folio">F.186.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-371</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྐྱེས་པའི་གཟུགས་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་དུ་རྟོགས་པར་བྱའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They should understand men’s figures<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="UT22084-040-005-33"/> to be absorption.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-44">
            <prop type="folio">F.186.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-371</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཁྱེའུའི་གཟུགས་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་དུ་རྟོགས་པར་བྱའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They should understand boys’ figures to be absorption.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-45">
            <prop type="folio">F.186.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-371</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བུ་མོའི་གཟུགས་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་དུ་རྟོགས་པར་བྱའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They should understand girls’ figures to be absorption.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-46">
            <prop type="folio">F.186.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-371</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལྷའི་གཟུགས་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་དུ་རྟོགས་པར་བྱའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They should understand the gods’ figures to be absorption.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-47">
            <prop type="folio">F.186.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-371</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཀླུའི་གཟུགས་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་དུ་རྟོགས་པར་བྱའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They should understand the nāgas’ figures to be absorption.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-48">
            <prop type="folio">F.186.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-371</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གནོད་སྦྱིན་གྱི་གཟུགས་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་དུ་རྟོགས་པར་བྱའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They should understand the yakṣas’ figures to be absorption.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-49">
            <prop type="folio">F.186.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-371</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དྲི་ཟའི་གཟུགས་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་དུ་རྟོགས་པར་བྱའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They should understand the gandharvas’ figures to be absorption.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-50">
            <prop type="folio">F.186.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-371</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལྷ་མ་ཡིན་གྱི་གཟུགས་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་དུ་རྟོགས་པར་བྱའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They should understand the asuras’ figures to be absorption.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-51">
            <prop type="folio">F.186.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-371</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ནམ་མཁའ་ལྡིང་གི་གཟུགས་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་དུ་རྟོགས་པར་བྱའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They should understand the garuḍas’ figures to be absorption.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-52">
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མི་འམ་ཅིའི་གཟུགས་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་དུ་རྟོགས་པར་བྱའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They should understand the kinnaras’ figures to be absorption.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-53">
            <prop type="folio">F.186.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-371</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལྟོ་འཕྱེ་ཆེན་པོའི་གཟུགས་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་དུ་རྟོགས་པར་བྱའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They should understand the mahoragas’ figures to be absorption.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-54">
            <prop type="folio">F.186.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-371</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སེམས་ཅན་དམྱལ་བའི་གཟུགས་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་དུ་རྟོགས་པར་བྱའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They should understand the hell beings’ figures to be absorption.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-55">
            <prop type="folio">F.186.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-372</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དུད་འགྲོའི་སྐྱེ་གནས་ཀྱི་གཟུགས་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་<tei:ref folio="F.186.b"/>དུ་རྟོགས་པར་བྱའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They should understand animals’ figures to be absorption. </seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-56">
            <prop type="folio">F.186.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-372</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཤིན་རྗེའི་འཇིག་རྟེན་གྱི་གཟུགས་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་དུ་རྟོགས་པར་བྱའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They should understand the figures of beings in the world of the Lord of Death to be absorption.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-57">
            <prop type="folio">F.186.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-372</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདོད་ཆགས་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་དུ་རྟོགས་པར་བྱའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-34"/>“They should understand attachment to be absorption.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-58">
            <prop type="folio">F.186.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-372</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཞེ་སྡང་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་དུ་རྟོགས་པར་བྱའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They should understand anger to be absorption.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-59">
            <prop type="folio">F.186.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-372</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཏི་མུག་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་དུ་རྟོགས་པར་བྱའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They should understand ignorance to be absorption.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-60">
            <prop type="folio">F.186.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-372</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དགེ་བ་ཐམས་ཅད་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་དུ་རྟོགས་པར་བྱའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They should understand all virtues to be absorption.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-61">
            <prop type="folio">F.186.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-372</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མི་དགེ་བ་ཐམས་ཅད་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་དུ་རྟོགས་པར་བྱའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They should understand all nonvirtues to be absorption.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-62">
            <prop type="folio">F.186.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-372</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདུས་བྱས་ཐམས་ཅད་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་དུ་རྟོགས་པར་བྱའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They should understand all conditioned phenomena to be absorption.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-63">
            <prop type="folio">F.186.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-372</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདུས་མ་བྱས་ཐམས་ཅད་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་དུ་རྟོགས་པར་བྱའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They should understand all unconditioned phenomena to be absorption.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-64">
            <prop type="folio">F.186.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-372</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ལྟར་ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་དུ་རྟོགས་པར་བྱ་སྟེ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>In this manner, they should understand all phenomena to be absorption.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-65">
            <prop type="folio">F.186.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-372</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་དེ་ལྟ་བུའི་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་ཐམས་ཅད་དང་ལྡན་པའི་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོ་ནི་ཐམས་ཅད་དུ་འགྲོ་བའི་བློ་དང་ལྡན་པ་ཡིན་ལ་ཀུན་ནས་སྒོའི་ལེའུའི་ཆོས་ཀྱི་རྣམ་གྲངས་འདི་ཉིད་ལ་ཡང་བསླབས་པ་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Mañjuśrī, bodhisattva great beings who obtain all such absorptions have omnipresent minds and are trained in the Dharma teaching of The Exposition on the Universal Gateway.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-66">
            <prop type="folio">F.186.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-372</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་དེ་ལ་ཇི་ལྟར་ན་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔས་གཟུགས་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་དུ་རྟོགས་པར་བྱ་ཞེ་ན། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-35"/>“Mañjuśrī, in this regard, how should bodhisattvas understand form to be absorption?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-67">
            <prop type="folio">F.186.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-372</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཟུགས་ནི་དབུ་བ་ལྟ་བུར་གསུངས། དེ་ལ་སྙིང་པོ་མི་རྙེད་དོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Form is said to be like a bubble: Its essence cannot be found.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-68">
            <prop type="folio">F.186.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-372</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྙིང་པོ་མེད་ཕྱིར་གཟུང་མེད་ཕྱིར། །དེས་ན་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་ཅེས་བསྟན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Since it is essenceless and cannot be grasped, I have taught it to be absorption.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-69">
            <prop type="folio">F.186.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-372</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་དེ་ལྟར་ན་གཟུགས་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་དུ་རྟོགས་པར་བྱའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Mañjuśrī, this is how one should understand form to be absorption.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-70">
            <prop type="folio">F.186.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-372</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་དེ་ལ་ཇི་ལྟར་ན་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔས་སྒྲ་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་དུ་རྟོགས་པར་བྱ་ཞེ་ན། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-38"/>“Mañjuśrī, in this regard, how should bodhisattvas understand sound to be absorption?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-71">
            <prop type="folio">F.186.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-372</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྒྲ་ནི་བྲག་ཆ་ལྟ་བུ་སྟེ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Sound is like an echo:</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-72">
            <prop type="folio">F.186.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-372</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ལ་དངོས་པོ་ཡོད་མ་ཡིན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>It has no substance.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-73">
            <prop type="folio">F.186.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-372</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཐ་དད་དབྱེ་བ་མེད་ཤེས་ཤིང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>I know it to have no distinguishable parts</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-74">
            <prop type="folio">F.186.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-372</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མཚན་ཉིད་མེད་པར་བྱེ་བྲག་མེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>And to be devoid of characteristics, with no particularities.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-75">
            <prop type="folio">F.186.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-372</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མཚན་ཉིད་མེད་ཅིང་བྱུང་བ་མེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-40"/>“It has no characteristics or origin,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-76">
            <prop type="folio">F.186.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-372</prop>
            <prop type="alternative-source"/>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡ་མ་བརླ་དང་འདུས་མ་བྱས། །བྲག་ཆ་ལྟ་བུར་ཤེས་པ་ན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>And is hollow and unconditioned. Knowing it<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="UT22084-040-005-41"/> to be like an echo,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-77">
            <prop type="folio">F.186.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-372</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེས་ན་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་ཅེས་བསྟན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>I have taught it to be absorption.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-78">
            <prop type="folio">F.186.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-372</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་དེ་ལྟར་ན་སྒྲ་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་དུ་རྟོགས་པར་བྱའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Mañjuśrī, that is how you should understand sound to be absorption.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-79">
            <prop type="folio">F.186.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-372</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་དེ་ལ་ཇི་ལྟར་ན་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔས་དྲི་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་དུ་རྟོགས་པར་བྱ་ཞེ་ན། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-43"/>“Mañjuśrī, how should bodhisattvas understand scent to be absorption?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-80">
            <prop type="folio">F.186.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-372</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཇི་ལྟར་རྒྱ་མཚོའི་གཏིང་དག་ནི། །ནམ་ཡང་ཅིས་ཀྱང་གང་མེད་ལྟར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Just as the bottom of the ocean Can never be reached in any way,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-81">
            <prop type="folio">F.186.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-372</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བསྐལ་པ་བྱེ་བར་བསྣམས་བྱས་ཀྱང་། །སྣ་ནི་ཚིམ་པར་འགྱུར་བ་མེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>You could smell for ten million eons, But there would still be no satisfying the nose.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-82">
            <prop type="folio">F.186.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-372</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྣ་ཡི་རྣམ་རིག་གཟུང་མེད་དེ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-45"/>“The olfactory cognition cannot be apprehended;</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-83">
            <prop type="folio">F.186.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-372</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སླུ་བའི་ཆོས་དེ་ཡོད་མ་ཡིན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>It is deceiving and nonexistent.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-84">
            <prop type="folio">F.186.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-372</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གལ་ཏེ་ཡང་དག་ཡིན་གྱུར་ན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Were it to be real,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-85">
            <prop type="folio">F.186.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-372</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ལས་མྱུར་དུ་ཚིམ་པར་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>It could rapidly be contented.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-86">
            <prop type="folio">F.186.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-372</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཟུང་བ་མེད་ཅིང་ཡང་དག་མིན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-46"/>“Since it is imperceptible and unreal,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-87">
            <prop type="folio">F.186.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-372</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྣ་ཡང་ཡོད་མིན་གསོག་ཏུ་ཤེས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The nose is known to be nonexistent and hollow.<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="UT22084-040-005-47"/>
                </seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-88">
            <prop type="folio">F.186.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-372</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གསོབ་དང་སྟོང་བར་ཤེས་པས་ན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Knowing it to be void and empty, </seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-89">
            <prop type="folio">F.187.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-373</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེས་ན་<tei:ref folio="F.187.a"/>ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་ཅེས་བསྟན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>I have taught it to be absorption.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-90">
            <prop type="folio">F.187.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-373</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་དེ་ལྟར་ན་དྲི་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་དུ་རྟོགས་པར་བྱའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Mañjuśrī, this is how you should understand scent to be absorption.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-91">
            <prop type="folio">F.187.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-373</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་དེ་ལ་ཇི་ལྟར་ན་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔས་རོ་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་དུ་རྟོགས་པར་བྱ་ཞེ་ན། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-49"/>“Mañjuśrī, how should bodhisattvas understand taste to be absorption?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-92">
            <prop type="folio">F.187.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-373</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལྕེ་ནི་ཚ་དང་ཁ་བའང་མིན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“The tongue is neither pungent nor bitter;</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-93">
            <prop type="folio">F.187.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-373</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྐྱུར་དང་ལན་ཚྭ་འང་མ་ཡིན་ཏེ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>It is neither sour nor salty.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-94">
            <prop type="folio">F.187.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-373</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཅི་འདྲའི་རྐྱེན་དང་ལྡན་པ་ལས། །ལྕེ་ཡང་དེ་དང་འདྲ་བར་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The tongue just changes in accordance With the conditions it encounters.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-95">
            <prop type="folio">F.187.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-373</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རོ་འདི་རྒྱུ་ལས་བྱུང་བ་དང་། །རྐྱེན་ལས་རག་ལས་ཤེས་གྱུར་ཅིང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-51"/>Taste is known to arise through causes<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="UT22084-040-005-52"/> And in dependence on conditions.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-96">
            <prop type="folio">F.187.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-373</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བསམ་གྱིས་མི་ཁྱབ་ཤེས་པས་ན། །དེས་ན་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་ཅེས་བསྟན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Knowing it to be inconceivable, I have taught it to be absorption.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-97">
            <prop type="folio">F.187.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-373</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་དེ་ལྟར་ན་རོ་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་དུ་རྟོགས་པར་བྱའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Mañjuśrī, this is how you should understand taste to be absorption.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-98">
            <prop type="folio">F.187.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-373</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་དེ་ལ་ཇི་ལྟར་ན་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔས་རེག་བྱ་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་དུ་རྟོགས་པར་བྱ་ཞེ་ན། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-54"/>“Mañjuśrī, how should bodhisattvas understand tactile objects to be absorption?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-99">
            <prop type="folio">F.187.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-373</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྣམ་རིག་ལས་བྱུང་རེག་བྱ་ནི། །ངོ་བོ་ཉིད་ཀྱིས་ཡོད་མ་ཡིན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Tactile objects, which arise out of cognition, Are not inherently existent.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-100">
            <prop type="folio">F.187.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-373</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་པ་དང་ནི་རྩུབ་པ་ཉིད། །རྐྱེན་རྣམས་ལས་ནི་བྱུང་བ་ཡིན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Softness<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="UT22084-040-005-56"/> and roughness Are created by conditions.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-101">
            <prop type="folio">F.187.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-373</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རེག་བྱ་གནས་པ་མེད་པ་སྟེ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-57"/>“Tactile objects are baseless;</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-102">
            <prop type="folio">F.187.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-373</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བདག་མེད་ཉེ་བར་གནས་པ་ཡིན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Their way of abiding is devoid of self.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-103">
            <prop type="folio">F.187.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-373</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཚོགས་རྣམས་སྦྱོར་བར་ཤེས་པས་ན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Knowing them to be a combination of composite factors,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-104">
            <prop type="folio">F.187.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-373</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེས་ན་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་ཅེས་བསྟན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>I have taught them to be absorption.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-105">
            <prop type="folio">F.187.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-373</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་དེ་ལྟར་ན་རེག་བྱ་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་དུ་རྟོགས་པར་བྱའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Mañjuśrī, this is how you should understand tactile objects to be absorption.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-106">
            <prop type="folio">F.187.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-373</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་དེ་ལ་ཇི་ལྟར་ན་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔས་ཡིད་ཀྱི་ཁམས་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་དུ་རྟོགས་པར་བྱ་ཞེ་ན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-59"/>“Mañjuśrī, how should bodhisattvas understand objects of the mind to be absorption?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-107">
            <prop type="folio">F.187.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-373</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་དག་སྟོང་གསུམ་སེམས་ཅན་རྣམས། །དེ་དག་གནས་གཅིག་གནས་གྱུར་ཏེ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Beings of the trichiliocosm All dwell in the same condition.<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="UT22084-040-005-61"/>
                </seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-108">
            <prop type="folio">F.187.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-373</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡིད་ཁམས་རྣམ་པར་ཤེས་བྱེད་ཀྱང་། །དེ་ཡི་དངོས་པོ་རྙེད་མི་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Though they cognize the range of mental objects, They cannot find their substance.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-109">
            <prop type="folio">F.187.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-373</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བསགས་པ་དང་ནི་གོང་བུ་ཡང་། །རྣམ་པར་རིག་ལ་གནས་པ་མེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-62"/>“That which is aggregated and amassed Has no basis in cognition.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-110">
            <prop type="folio">F.187.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-373</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཁ་དོག་སྣ་ཚོགས་རྣམས་སྟོན་ཀྱང་། །ཕྱི་དང་ནང་ན་གནས་མ་ཡིན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Though cognition displays various colors, These exist neither outside nor inside.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-111">
            <prop type="folio">F.187.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-373</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གནས་པ་མེད་ཅིང་གནས་ཀྱང་མེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-63"/>“Mental objects do not abide and have no basis.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-112">
            <prop type="folio">F.187.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-373</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྒྱུ་མ་ལྟ་བུར་དངོས་པོ་མེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Like an illusion, they are insubstantial.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-113">
            <prop type="folio">F.187.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-373</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མེད་ཅིང་ཡ་མ་བརླར་ཤེས་པས། །དེས་ན་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་ཅེས་བསྟན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Knowing them to be nonexistent and hollow, I have taught them to be absorption.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-114">
            <prop type="folio">F.187.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-373</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་དེ་ལྟར་ན་ཡིད་ཀྱི་ཁམས་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་དུ་རྟོགས་པར་བྱའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Mañjuśrī, that is how you should understand mental objects to be absorption.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-115">
            <prop type="folio">F.187.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-373</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་དེ་ལ་ཇི་ལྟར་ན་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔས་བུད་མེད་ཀྱི་གཟུགས་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་དུ་རྟོགས་པར་བྱ་ཞེ་ན། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-65"/>“Mañjuśrī, how should bodhisattvas understand the female figure to be absorption?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-116">
            <prop type="folio">F.187.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-373</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འབྱུང་བ་ཆེན་པོ་བཞི་པོ་དག །དེ་ལ་བུད་མེད་ཡོད་མིན་ཡང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Though women do not exist Within the four major elements,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-117">
            <prop type="folio">F.187.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-373</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱིས་པ་རྣམས་ནི་རྨོངས་པའི་བློས། །འདོད་པའི་གསོག་ལ་སྤྱོད་པར་བྱེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The immature, with their confused minds, Engage in trifling desires.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-118">
            <prop type="folio">F.187.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-373</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྒྱུ་མའི་བུད་མེད་མཚན་མེད་ཀྱང་། །བུད་མེད་གཟུགས་སུ་སྣང་བ་ལ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-67"/>“Though illusory women are without marks, They appear as the female figure.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-119">
            <prop type="folio">F.187.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-374</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་དག་མུན་པས་བསྒྲིབས་པའི་མི། །<tei:ref folio="F.187.b"/>དེ་ལ་ཀུན་དུ་ཆགས་པ་སྐྱེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Those men who are enclosed in darkness Give rise to strong attachment toward them.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-120">
            <prop type="folio">F.187.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-374</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཇི་ལྟར་སྒྱུ་མའི་བུད་མེད་ལ། །འདོད་ཆགས་ལྡན་པའི་སེམས་བསྐྱེད་ཀྱང་། །དེ་ལ་བུད་མེད་ཡོད་མ་ཡིན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-68"/>“While they give rise to desirous thoughts Regarding illusory women, These women are nonexistent.<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="UT22084-040-005-69"/>
                </seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-121">
            <prop type="folio">F.187.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-374</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཕྱིན་ཅི་ལོག་གི་སེམས་ཀྱིས་ནི། །བསྐལ་པ་བྱེ་བ་གྲངས་མེད་དུ། །བློ་གྲོས་ཆུང་རྣམས་འཁོར་བར་བྱེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-70"/>“It is this mistaken mind That has made the simple-minded Circle around for countless eons.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-122">
            <prop type="folio">F.187.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-374</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་དངོས་པོ་མེད་ཤེས་ན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-71"/>“Therefore, if you know insubstantiality,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-123">
            <prop type="folio">F.187.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-374</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བུད་མེད་ཐམས་ཅད་མཚན་ཉིད་མེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>All women are without characteristics.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-124">
            <prop type="folio">F.187.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-374</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཏིང་འཛིན་ཞི་བ་བརྗོད་པ་ནི། །བུད་མེད་གཟུགས་ཀྱིས་རབ་ཏུ་བསྟན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>This statement on the peace of absorption I have made with reference to the female figure.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-125">
            <prop type="folio">F.187.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-374</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་དེ་ལྟར་ན་བུད་མེད་ཀྱི་གཟུགས་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་དུ་རྟོགས་པར་བྱའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Mañjuśrī, that is how you should understand the female figure to be absorption.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-126">
            <prop type="folio">F.187.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-374</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་དེ་ལ་ཇི་ལྟར་ན་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔས་སྐྱེས་པའི་གཟུགས་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་དུ་རྟོགས་པར་བྱ་ཞེ་ན། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-73"/>“Mañjuśrī, how should bodhisattvas understand the male figure to be absorption?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-127">
            <prop type="folio">F.187.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-374</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདི་ནི་བུད་མེད་བདག་སྐྱེས་པར། །ཇི་ལྟར་སྐྱེས་པས་བརྗོད་པ་ལས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“When men declare: ‘This is a woman and I am a man,’</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-128">
            <prop type="folio">F.187.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-374</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ཡི་ཚེ་ན་དེ་ཡི་སེམས། །འདོད་ཆགས་ལྡན་པ་བརྫུན་པ་འབྱུང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>In that instant, their minds Become desirous and mistaken.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-129">
            <prop type="folio">F.187.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-374</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སེམས་ནི་གཟུགས་མེད་གཟུང་བ་མེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-75"/>“Yet mind is formless<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="UT22084-040-005-76"/> and imperceptible.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-130">
            <prop type="folio">F.187.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-374</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བུད་མེད་སྐྱེས་པར་བསྟན་པ་མེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>It is indemonstrable as woman or man.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-131">
            <prop type="folio">F.187.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-374</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཀུན་ཏུ་རྟོག་པས་སྒྲོ་བཏགས་ནས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>It is conceptual superimpositions</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-132">
            <prop type="folio">F.187.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-374</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྐྱེས་པའི་འདུ་ཤེས་འབྱུང་བར་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>That give rise to the perception of man.<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="UT22084-040-005-77"/>
                </seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-133">
            <prop type="folio">F.187.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-374</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདི་ནི་བུད་མེད་བདག་དཔའ་ཞེས། །འདུ་ཤེས་གང་གིས་རྣམ་བརྟགས་པ། །དེ་ངས་སྨིག་རྒྱུ་འདྲར་གསུངས་ཏེ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-78"/>“Men declare: ‘This is a woman and I am a man.’ Yet all such imputed notions I have taught to be like a mirage,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-134">
            <prop type="folio">F.187.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-374</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ལ་སྐྱེས་པ་ཡོད་མ་ཡིན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>And no man exists therein.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-135">
            <prop type="folio">F.187.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-374</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྐྱེས་པ་ཉིད་ནི་བརྫུན་པས་ན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-79"/>“Since the nature of man is illusory,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-136">
            <prop type="folio">F.187.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-374</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནི་མེད་ལས་བྱུང་བ་ཡིན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He has arisen out of nonexistence.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-137">
            <prop type="folio">F.187.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-374</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཏིང་འཛིན་ཞི་བ་བརྗོད་པ་ནི། །དཔའ་བོའི་གཟུགས་ཀྱིས་རབ་ཏུ་བསྟན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>This statement on the peace of absorption I have made with reference to the male figure.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-138">
            <prop type="folio">F.187.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-374</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་དེ་ལྟར་ན་སྐྱེས་པའི་གཟུགས་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་དུ་རྟོགས་པར་བྱའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Mañjuśrī, this is how you should understand the male figure to be absorption.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-139">
            <prop type="folio">F.187.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-374</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་དེ་ལ་ཇི་ལྟར་ན་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔས་ཁྱེའུའི་གཟུགས་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་དུ་རྟོགས་པར་བྱ་ཞེ་ན། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-81"/>“Mañjuśrī, how should bodhisattvas understand boys’ figures to be absorption?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-140">
            <prop type="folio">F.187.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-374</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལྗོན་པའི་མྱུ་གུ་ཡོད་མིན་ན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“If there is no sapling,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-141">
            <prop type="folio">F.187.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-374</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མེ་ཏོག་འབྱུང་བར་ག་ལ་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>How can a flower appear?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-142">
            <prop type="folio">F.187.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-374</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མེ་ཏོག་ཡོད་པ་མ་ཡིན་ན། །འབྲས་བུ་འཐོབ་པའང་མེད་པ་ལྟར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>If there is no flower, The fruit cannot grow either.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-143">
            <prop type="folio">F.187.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-374</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བུད་མེད་ཡོད་པ་མ་ཡིན་པས། །ཁྱེའུ་ཡང་དམིགས་པར་མི་འགྱུར་ཏེ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-83"/>“Likewise, since women are nonexistent, Boys cannot be apprehended either.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-144">
            <prop type="folio">F.187.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-374</prop>
            <prop type="alternative-source"/>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བརྟགས་པའི་དབང་དུ་སོང་རྣམས་ཀྱིས། །ཁྱེའུ་ཞེས་བྱ་བར་བཏགས་པ་ཡིན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Those who are under the sway of their imaginations, Falsely conceive<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="UT22084-040-005-84"/> what they call boy.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-145">
            <prop type="folio">F.187.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-374</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བུད་མེད་སྐྱེ་བ་མེད་ཤེས་ན། །ཁྱེའུ་ཡང་འབྱུང་བ་ཡོད་མིན་ཏེ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-85"/>“If you know woman to be unborn, Boys have no origin either.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-146">
            <prop type="folio">F.187.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-374</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དངོས་པོ་ཐམས་ཅད་མེད་རྟོགས་པས། །དེས་ན་ཁྱེའུ་ནི་ཏིང་འཛིན་བསྟན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Realizing all entities to be nonexistent, I have taught boys to be absorption.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-147">
            <prop type="folio">F.187.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-374</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་དེ་ལྟར་ན་ཁྱེའུའི་གཟུགས་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་དུ་རྟོགས་པར་བྱའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Mañjuśrī, this is how you should understand boys’ figures to be absorption.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-148">
            <prop type="folio">F.188.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-375</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་དེ་ལ་ཇི་ལྟར་ན་བྱང་ཆུབ་<tei:ref folio="F.188.a"/>སེམས་དཔས་བུ་མོའི་གཟུགས་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་དུ་རྟོགས་པར་བྱ་ཞེ་ན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-87"/>“Mañjuśrī, how should bodhisattvas understand girls’ figures to be absorption?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-149">
            <prop type="folio">F.188.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-375</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཇི་ལྟར་ཏ་ལའི་མགོ་བཅད་པ། །དེ་ནི་ནམ་ཡང་མི་སྐྱེ་སྟེ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“If a palm tree’s crown is cut off, It can never grow again.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-150">
            <prop type="folio">F.188.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-375</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མཁས་པས་ཤེས་ནས་དེ་ལ་ནི། །འབྲས་བུ་ཐོབ་པར་འདོད་པ་མེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Knowing this, the wise Will not wish for any fruits to appear.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-151">
            <prop type="folio">F.188.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-375</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་བཞིན་མཁས་པས་བུད་མེད་ཀྱང་། །རྣམ་ཀུན་སྐྱེ་བ་མེད་ཤེས་པས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-89"/>“Likewise, once the wise know that women Have also never been born,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-152">
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བརྟན་པ་བུ་མོ་སྐྱེས་སོ་ཞེས། །ཕྱིན་ཅད་རྟོག་པར་མི་བྱེད་དོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They no longer wrongly think, ‘Their basis, a girl, has been born.’</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-153">
            <prop type="folio">F.188.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-375</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ས་བོན་སྐམས་པར་གྱུར་པ་ལ། །རྣམ་ཀུན་སྐྱེ་བ་མེད་ཤེས་པས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-91"/>“Knowing that when a seed is parched It can no longer grow,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-154">
            <prop type="folio">F.188.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-375</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཏིང་འཛིན་ཞི་བ་བརྗོད་པ་ནི། །བུ་མོའི་གཟུགས་ཀྱིས་རབ་ཏུ་བསྟན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>This statement on the peace of absorption I have made with reference to girls’ figures.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-155">
            <prop type="folio">F.188.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-375</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་དེ་ལྟར་ན་བུ་མོའི་གཟུགས་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་དུ་རྟོགས་པར་བྱའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Mañjuśrī, this is how you should understand girls’ figures to be absorption.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-156">
            <prop type="folio">F.188.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-375</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་དེ་ལ་ཇི་ལྟར་ན་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔས་ལྷའི་གཟུགས་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་དུ་རྟོགས་པར་བྱ་ཞེ་ན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-93"/>“Mañjuśrī, how should bodhisattvas understand gods’ figures to be absorption?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-157">
            <prop type="folio">F.188.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-375</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྣམ་རྟོག་དགེ་ལས་བྱུང་བ་ཡི། །ལས་དགེའི་འབྲས་བུ་ལྷ་རྣམས་ཏེ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Gods are the result of virtuous action Produced by virtuous thoughts.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-158">
            <prop type="folio">F.188.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-375</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རབ་ཏུ་དང་བའི་ཡིད་ཀྱིས་ནི། །མཛེས་པའི་ལྷ་རྣམས་མངོན་པར་གྲུབ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Pure minds cause The manifestation of beautiful gods.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-159">
            <prop type="folio">F.188.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-375</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཞལ་མེད་ཁང་པ་ཉམས་དགའ་བ། །དེ་དག་གཞན་སུས་བྱས་པ་མིན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-95"/>“Their delightful palaces Are not created by anyone else.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-160">
            <prop type="folio">F.188.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-375</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མེ་ཏོག་མན་དཱ་ར་བ་ཡང་། །དེ་དག་གཞན་སུས་བསྐྱེད་པ་མིན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The mandārava flower too Is not made by anyone else.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-161">
            <prop type="folio">F.188.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-375</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྒྱུ་མའི་ལས་ལས་ཀུན་བྱུང་བས། །བྱུང་བ་རྣམས་ཀྱང་བསམ་དུ་མེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-96"/>“Produced by illusory action, These appearances are inconceivable.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-162">
            <prop type="folio">F.188.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-375</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཟང་པོར་སྣང་བའི་བཻ་དཱུརྱ། །ལོག་པས་གྲུབ་པ་རྣམས་ཀྱང་བརྫུན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The beautiful glitter of beryl gems Is also false and untrue.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-163">
            <prop type="folio">F.188.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-375</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡང་དག་མིན་པས་ཀུན་བསྐྱེད་པས། །ལྷ་རྣམས་བརྫུན་པར་ཤེས་པས་ན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-97"/>“Knowing that gods manifest in an unreal manner And are therefore unreal,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-164">
            <prop type="folio">F.188.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-375</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཏིང་འཛིན་ཞི་བ་བརྗོད་པ་ནི། །ལྷ་ཡི་གཟུགས་ཀྱིས་བསྟན་པ་ཡིན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>This statement on the peace of absorption I have made with reference to the gods’ figures.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-165">
            <prop type="folio">F.188.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-375</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་དེ་ལྟར་ན་ལྷའི་གཟུགས་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་དུ་རྟོགས་པར་བྱའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Mañjuśrī, this is how you should understand gods’ figures to be absorption.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-166">
            <prop type="folio">F.188.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-375</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་དེ་ལ་ཇི་ལྟར་ན་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔས་ཀླུའི་གཟུགས་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་དུ་རྟོགས་པར་བྱ་ཞེ་ན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-99"/>“Mañjuśrī, how should bodhisattvas understand nāgas’ figures to be absorption?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-167">
            <prop type="folio">F.188.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-375</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མི་བཟོད་བསྐྱེད་པ་བྱས་ནས་ནི། །ཡོད་མིན་སྤྲིན་གྱི་གཟུགས་བསྟན་ཅིང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“By becoming intolerant, They manifest the forms of nonexistent clouds. Although they do not remain in those clouds,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-168">
            <prop type="folio">F.188.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-375</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཆར་པའི་རྒྱུན་དག་རབ་འབེབས་པ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They bring down heavy rainfall.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-169">
            <prop type="folio">F.188.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-375</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་དག་ནང་ན་མི་གནས་ཀྱང་། །འཛམ་བུའི་གླིང་འདིར་རྒྱ་མཚོ་དང་། །ཀླུང་དང་དུག་ཅན་ཡོངས་སུ་འགེངས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-101"/>“They fill up the seas, Rivers,<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="UT22084-040-005-102"/> and oceans here in Jambudvīpa.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-170">
            <prop type="folio">F.188.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-375</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྔོན་གྱི་མཐའ་འམ་ཕྱི་མའི་མཐར། །ཆུ་ནི་འབྱུང་བ་ཡོད་མ་ཡིན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Yet, whether in the beginning or the end, This water is devoid of origin.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-171">
            <prop type="folio">F.188.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-375</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་དང་མཚུངས་པའི་སེམས་ཅན་ཀུན། །རྩོམ་པ་སྣ་ཚོགས་བསླབས་པ་རྣམས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-103"/>“All beings are similar to that water— They are skilled in various undertakings</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-172">
            <prop type="folio">F.188.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-375</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལས་རྣམས་སྣ་ཚོགས་སྟོན་བྱེད་ཀྱང་། །ལས་དེ་འབྱུང་བ་ཡོད་མ་ཡིན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>And display various karmic actions, But these karmic actions have no origin.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-173">
            <prop type="folio">F.188.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-376</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མཁས་པས་བྱིས་པ་རྨོངས་བྱེད་པའི། །སྒྱུ་འདི་<tei:ref folio="F.188.b"/>མ་བྱུང་ཤེས་པས་ན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-104"/>“The wise know these illusions, Which delude the immature, to be unarisen.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-174">
            <prop type="folio">F.188.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-376</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བདེན་པ་མ་ཡིན་བདེན་སྣང་བས། །ཀླུ་ནི་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་དུ་བསྟན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Thus, since the untrue appears as true, I have taught nāgas to be absorption.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-175">
            <prop type="folio">F.188.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-376</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་དེ་ལྟར་ན་ཀླུའི་གཟུགས་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་དུ་རྟོགས་པར་བྱའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Mañjuśrī, that is how you should understand nāgas’ figures to be absorption.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-176">
            <prop type="folio">F.188.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-376</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་དེ་ལ་ཇི་ལྟར་ན་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔས་གནོད་སྦྱིན་གྱི་གཟུགས་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་དུ་རྟོགས་པར་བྱ་ཞེ་ན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-106"/>“Mañjuśrī, how should bodhisattvas understand yakṣas’ figures to be absorption?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-177">
            <prop type="folio">F.188.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-376</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སེམས་ནི་རྣམ་པར་གྱུར་པ་ལས། །འཇིགས་པའི་གཟུགས་ནི་མངོན་གྲུབ་པ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“From the transformation of the mind Manifests a terrifying figure.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-178">
            <prop type="folio">F.188.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-376</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལུས་ཀྱི་བོང་ཚོད་ཆེ་བ་ཡང་། །སེམས་གཅིག་གིས་ནི་ཀུན་དུ་བསྐྱེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Though its body may be great, It was created by a single mind.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-179">
            <prop type="folio">F.188.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-376</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སེམས་ལ་འཇིགས་པ་ཡོད་མིན་ཏེ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-108"/>“Fear does not exist within the mind;</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-180">
            <prop type="folio">F.188.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-376</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཚོགས་པ་དག་ལས་འཇིགས་པ་སྐྱེ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>It appears from a combination of factors.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-181">
            <prop type="folio">F.188.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-376</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡོད་པ་མིན་པའི་ལས་རྣམས་ལས། །མི་སྡུག་རྣམ་པ་བསམ་ཡས་ལྟོས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Look at the inconceivable array of hideous forms<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="UT22084-040-005-109"/> Arising out of nonexistent action!</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-182">
            <prop type="folio">F.188.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-376</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མི་སྡུག་རྣམ་པ་བསམ་ཡས་པ། །ཤིན་ཏུ་སྟོང་པར་ཤེས་པས་ན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-110"/>“Knowing this inconceivable array of hideous forms To be utterly empty,<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="UT22084-040-005-111"/>
                </seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-183">
            <prop type="folio">F.188.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-376</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཏིང་འཛིན་ཞི་བ་བརྗོད་པ་ནི། །གནོད་སྦྱིན་གཟུགས་ཀྱིས་བསྟན་པ་ཡིན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>This statement on the peace of absorption I have made with reference to the yakṣas’ figures.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-184">
            <prop type="folio">F.188.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-376</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་དེ་ལྟར་ན་གནོད་སྦྱིན་གྱི་གཟུགས་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་དུ་རྟོགས་པར་བྱའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Mañjuśrī, that is how you should understand yakṣas’ figures to be absorption.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-185">
            <prop type="folio">F.188.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-376</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་དེ་ལ་ཇི་ལྟར་ན་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔས་དྲི་ཟའི་གཟུགས་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་དུ་རྟོགས་པར་བྱ་ཞེ་ན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-113"/>“Mañjuśrī, how should bodhisattvas understand gandharvas’ figures to be absorption?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-186">
            <prop type="folio">F.188.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-376</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཆོས་དེ་ཤིན་དུ་འགྲོ་མེད་ཀྱང་། །འགྲོ་བའི་སྒྲར་ནི་བརྗོད་པས་ན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Though these phenomena are devoid of any going, They are given the name of wanderers.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-187">
            <prop type="folio">F.188.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-376</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འགྲོ་བས་འགྲོ་བ་མེད་ཤེས་པས། །དྲི་ཟས་ཏིང་འཛིན་བསྟན་པ་ཡིན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Knowing wanderers to go nowhere, I have taught absorption with reference to gandharvas.<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="UT22084-040-005-115"/>
                </seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-188">
            <prop type="folio">F.188.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-376</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་དེ་ལྟར་ན་དྲི་ཟའི་གཟུགས་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་དུ་རྟོགས་པར་བྱའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Mañjuśrī, this is how you should understand gandharvas’ figures to be absorption.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-189">
            <prop type="folio">F.188.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-376</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་དེ་ལ་ཇི་ལྟར་ན་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔས་ལྷ་མ་ཡིན་གྱི་གཟུགས་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་དུ་རྟོགས་པར་བྱ་ཞེ་ན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-117"/>“Mañjuśrī, how should bodhisattvas understand asuras’ figures to be absorption?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-190">
            <prop type="folio">F.188.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-376</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཨ་ཡི་རྒྱས་བཏབ་ལྷ་མིན་ཏེ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“The asura, sealed with the letter a,<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="UT22084-040-005-119"/>
                </seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-191">
            <prop type="folio">F.188.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-376</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྐྱེ་བ་མེད་ལས་ཡང་དག་བྱུང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Truly arises from the unborn.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-192">
            <prop type="folio">F.188.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-376</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འགག་མེད་འབྱུང་བ་ཡོད་མིན་པས། །ལྷ་མ་ཡིན་གྱིས་ཏིང་འཛིན་བསྟན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Since they are unceasing and non-arising, Absorption is taught with reference to the asuras.<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="UT22084-040-005-120"/>
                </seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-193">
            <prop type="folio">F.188.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-376</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་དེ་ལྟར་ན་ལྷ་མ་ཡིན་གྱི་གཟུགས་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་དུ་རྟོགས་པར་བྱའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Mañjuśrī, this is how you should understand asuras’ figures to be absorption.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-194">
            <prop type="folio">F.188.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-376</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་དེ་ལ་ཇི་ལྟར་ན་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔས་ནམ་མཁའ་ལྡིང་གི་གཟུགས་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་དུ་རྟོགས་པར་བྱ་ཞེ་ན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-122"/>“Mañjuśrī, how should bodhisattvas understand garuḍas’ figures to be absorption?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-195">
            <prop type="folio">F.188.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-376</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཛིན་པ་མེད་ལ་འཛིན་བྱས་ནས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Grasping onto the ungraspable,<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="UT22084-040-005-124"/>
                </seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-196">
            <prop type="folio">F.188.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-376</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བརྗོད་པས་མིང་དུ་བཏགས་པས་ན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>We apply labels as we speak.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-197">
            <prop type="folio">F.188.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-376</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མིང་དང་གཟུགས་ནི་ཡོད་མིན་པས། །ནམ་མཁའ་ལྡིང་གིས་ཏིང་འཛིན་བསྟན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Since neither name nor form are existent, I have taught absorption with reference to the garuḍas.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-198">
            <prop type="folio">F.188.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-376</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་དེ་ལྟར་ན་ནམ་མཁའ་ལྡིང་གི་གཟུགས་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་དུ་རྟོགས་པར་བྱའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Mañjuśrī, this is how you should understand garuḍas’ figures to be absorption.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-199">
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་དེ་ལ་ཇི་ལྟར་ན་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔས་མི་འམ་ཅིའི་གཟུགས་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་དུ་རྟོགས་པར་བྱ་ཞེ་ན།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Mañjuśrī, how should bodhisattvas understand kinnaras’ figures to be absorption?</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-200">
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱས་མིན་བྱས་པའི་ལས་རྣམས་ཀྱིས། །མི་འམ་ཅི་ཉིད་ཀུན་དུ་བསྐྱེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“It is by uncreated, created actions That the kinnaras are produced.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-201">
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདི་དག་སྐྱེ་བ་མེད་ཤེས་པས། །མི་འམ་ཅི་ཡིས་ཏིང་འཛིན་བསྟན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Knowing them to be unborn, I have taught absorption with reference to the kinnaras.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-202">
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་དེ་ལྟར་ན་མི་འམ་ཅིའི་གཟུགས་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་དུ་རྟོགས་པར་བྱའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Mañjuśrī, this is how you should understand the kinnaras’ figures to be absorption.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-203">
            <prop type="folio">F.189.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-377</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་དེ་ལ་ཇི་ལྟར་ན་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔས་ལྟོ་འཕྱེ་ཆེན་པོའི་གཟུགས་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་དུ་རྟོགས་པར་བྱ་ཞེ་ན། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-130"/>“Mañjuśrī, how should bodhisattvas understand mahoragas’ figures to be absorption?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-204">
            <prop type="folio">F.189.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-377</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མིང་གང་གིས་ནི་ཆོས་འདི་དག །འཇིག་རྟེན་དག་ཏུ་སྣ་ཚོགས་བཞག །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“By whatever names these phenomena Are variously posited<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="UT22084-040-005-132"/> in the worlds,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-205">
            <prop type="folio">F.189.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-377</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཆོས་དེ་འདི་ལ་ཡོད་མ་ཡིན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The phenomena do not exist there;</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-206">
            <prop type="folio">F.189.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-377</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མེད་ལས་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀུན་དུ་བརྟགས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Everything is imagined out of nonexistence.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-207">
            <prop type="folio">F.189.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-377</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཀུན་དུ་བརྟགས་པར་ཀུན་ཤེས་ན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-133"/>“If you know everything to be fabricated,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-208">
            <prop type="folio">F.189.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-377</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ངོ་བོ་ཉིད་ཀྱིས་ཀུན་རྟོག་མེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>There are naturally no concepts.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-209">
            <prop type="folio">F.189.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-377</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཏིང་འཛིན་ཞི་བ་བརྗོད་པ་ནི། །ལྟོ་འཕྱེ་ཆེན་པོའི་གཟུགས་ཀྱིས་བསྟན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>This statement on the peace of absorption I have made with reference to the mahoragas’ figures.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-210">
            <prop type="folio">F.189.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-377</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་དེ་ལྟར་ན་ལྟོ་འཕྱེ་ཆེན་པོའི་གཟུགས་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་དུ་རྟོགས་པར་བྱའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Mañjuśrī, this is how you should understand mahoragas’ figures to be absorption.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-211">
            <prop type="folio">F.189.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-377</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་དེ་ལ་ཇི་ལྟར་ན་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔས་སེམས་ཅན་དམྱལ་བའི་གཟུགས་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་དུ་རྟོགས་པར་བྱ་ཞེ་ན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-135"/>“Mañjuśrī, how should bodhisattvas understand the hell beings’ figures to be absorption?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-212">
            <prop type="folio">F.189.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-377</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྡུལ་དང་བྲལ་ཞིང་རྡུལ་མེད་གསོག །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Stainless, pure, and hollow,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-213">
            <prop type="folio">F.189.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-377</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ལ་བྱེད་པོ་འགའ་ཡང་མེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They have no maker whatsoever.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-214">
            <prop type="folio">F.189.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-377</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རང་གི་རྟོག་པས་ཀུན་བསྐྱེད་དེ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They are produced by their own thoughts,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-215">
            <prop type="folio">F.189.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-377</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྟོག་པ་དེ་ཡང་ཡོད་མ་ཡིན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Which have no existence either.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-216">
            <prop type="folio">F.189.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-377</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དམྱལ་བ་དྲི་མེད་དྲི་བྲལ་ཞིང་། །དག་དང་ཡང་དག་འོད་གསལ་དང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-137"/>“Hell is clean, immaculate, Pure, true, and luminous.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-217">
            <prop type="folio">F.189.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-377</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མཚན་ཉིད་མེད་ཅིང་མཚན་མེད་པར། །བྱང་ཆུབ་སྙིང་པོར་ངས་ཤེས་ཏེ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>It is beyond all characteristics and marks, Like the seat of awakening—thus I know.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-218">
            <prop type="folio">F.189.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-377</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མཚན་ཉིད་མེད་ཅིང་བྱུང་མེད་དེ། །ནམ་མཁའ་འདྲ་བར་ཤེས་པས་ན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-138"/>“Knowing hell to be beyond attributes and unarisen, Similar to the sky,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-219">
            <prop type="folio">F.189.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-377</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཏིང་འཛིན་ཞི་བ་བརྗོད་པ་ནི། །སེམས་ཅན་དམྱལ་བའི་གཟུགས་ཀྱིས་བསྟན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>This statement on the peace of absorption I have made with reference to the hell beings’ figures.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-220">
            <prop type="folio">F.189.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-377</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་དེ་ལྟར་ན་སེམས་ཅན་དམྱལ་བའི་གཟུགས་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་དུ་རྟོགས་པར་བྱའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Mañjuśrī, this is how you should understand hell beings’ figures to be absorption.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-221">
            <prop type="folio">F.189.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-377</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་དེ་ལ་ཇི་ལྟར་ན་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔས་དུད་འགྲོའི་སྐྱེ་གནས་ཀྱི་གཟུགས་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་དུ་རྟོགས་པར་བྱ་ཞེ་ན། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-140"/>“Mañjuśrī, how should bodhisattvas understand figures in the animal realm to be absorption?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-222">
            <prop type="folio">F.189.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-377</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དཔེར་ན་ཇི་ལྟར་སྤྲིན་གྱི་གཟུགས། །ཁ་དོག་སྣ་ཚོགས་བྱུང་བ་དག །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“For instance, cloud formations Appear in various colors;</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-223">
            <prop type="folio">F.189.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-377</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ལ་ཁ་དོག་ཡོད་མིན་ཡང་། །མི་མཁས་པ་དག་རྨོངས་པར་བྱེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Though the clouds have no real color, They fool the unwise.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-224">
            <prop type="folio">F.189.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-377</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་བཞིན་སེམས་ཀྱང་མེད་པའི་ཕྱིར། །སྤྲིན་གྱི་གཟུགས་དང་མཚུངས་འདྲ་ཡང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-142"/>“Likewise, since the mind does not exist It is like the form of a cloud:</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-225">
            <prop type="folio">F.189.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-377</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དུད་འགྲོའི་སྐྱེ་གནས་རྣམས་སུ་ནི། །རྣམ་པ་སྣ་ཚོགས་ལུས་ཀྱང་སྟོན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>In the realms of animals, It displays bodies in various forms.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-226">
            <prop type="folio">F.189.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-377</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལས་ནི་སྒྱུ་མའི་རང་བཞིན་དང་། །བྱུང་མེད་མཚན་ཉིད་མེད་པར་ཤེས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-143"/>“Karmic actions<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="UT22084-040-005-144"/> are of an illusory nature. I know them to be unarisen and beyond characteristics.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-227">
            <prop type="folio">F.189.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-377</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཏིང་འཛིན་ཞི་བ་བརྗོད་པ་ནི། །དུད་འགྲོའི་གཟུགས་ཀྱིས་བསྟན་པ་ཡིན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>This statement on the peace of absorption I have made with reference to animals’ figures.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-228">
            <prop type="folio">F.189.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-378</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་<tei:ref folio="F.189.b"/>དཔལ་དེ་ལྟར་ན་དུད་འགྲོའི་སྐྱེ་གནས་ཀྱི་གཟུགས་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་དུ་རྟོགས་པར་བྱའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Mañjuśrī, this is how you should understand figures in the animal realm to be absorption.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-229">
            <prop type="folio">F.189.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-378</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་དེ་ལ་ཇི་ལྟར་ན་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔས་གཤིན་རྗེའི་འཇིག་རྟེན་གྱི་གཟུགས་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་དུ་རྟོགས་པར་བྱ་ཞེ་ན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-146"/>“Mañjuśrī, how should bodhisattvas understand the figures in the world of the Lord of Death to be absorption?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-230">
            <prop type="folio">F.189.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-378</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ནག་པོ་དང་ནི་དཀར་པོ་ཡི། །སྡིག་དང་ཁ་ན་མ་ཐོ་དང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Black misdeeds and objectionable deeds And white irreproachable deeds</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-231">
            <prop type="folio">F.189.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-378</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཁ་ན་མ་ཐོ་མེད་པའི་ལས། །རབ་འབྲིང་ཐ་མ་འདྲེས་བྱས་པས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Have all become mixed up In terms of the best, the middling, and the worst.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-232">
            <prop type="folio">F.189.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-378</prop>
            <prop type="alternative-source"/>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཤིན་རྗེའི་འཇིག་རྟེན་སྡུག་བསྔལ་ཞིང་། །ཚོལ་བར་ཀུན་དུ་འཁོར་བ་ཡིན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-148"/>“Then, in the world of the Lord of Death, Beings suffer and spin around in confusion.<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="UT22084-040-005-149"/>
                </seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-233">
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ལ་གཤིན་རྗེའི་འཇིག་རྟེན་མེད། །དེ་ནི་ངོ་བོ་ཉིད་ཀྱིས་སྟོང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Yet there is no realm of the Lord of Death— It is inherently empty.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-234">
            <prop type="folio">F.189.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-378</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྨི་ལམ་ན་ནི་མྱོང་བ་བཞིན། །འཇུག་པ་མེད་ཅིང་གྲུབ་པ་མེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-150"/>“Like experiences in a dream, It is without beginning or completion.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-235">
            <prop type="folio">F.189.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-378</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཤིན་རྗེའི་འཇིག་རྟེན་ཡོད་མིན་པས། །དེས་ན་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་དུ་བསྟན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Since the realm of the Lord of Death is nonexistent, I have taught it to be absorption.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-236">
            <prop type="folio">F.189.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-378</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་དེ་ལྟར་ན་གཤིན་རྗེའི་འཇིག་རྟེན་གྱི་གཟུགས་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་དུ་རྟོགས་པར་བྱའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Mañjuśrī, this is how you should understand the figures in the world of the Lord of Death to be absorption.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-237">
            <prop type="folio">F.189.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-378</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་དེ་ལ་ཇི་ལྟར་ན་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔས་འདོད་ཆགས་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་དུ་རྟོགས་པར་བྱ་ཞེ་ན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-152"/>“Mañjuśrī, how should bodhisattvas understand desire to be absorption?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-238">
            <prop type="folio">F.189.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-378</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡོངས་སུ་རྟོག་ལས་འདོད་ཆགས་འབྱུང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Desire surges from the imagination;</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-239">
            <prop type="folio">F.189.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-378</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྟོག་པ་དེ་ཡང་འབྱུང་བ་མེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Those fancies too are unarisen.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-240">
            <prop type="folio">F.189.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-378</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འབྱུང་བ་མེད་ལ་གནས་པ་མེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>That which has no arising has no abiding—</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-241">
            <prop type="folio">F.189.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-378</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ཡི་གནས་ཀྱང་རྙེད་མི་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Its location can never be determined.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-242">
            <prop type="folio">F.189.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-378</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གནས་མེད་གནས་པ་ཡོད་མིན་པས། །འདོད་ཆགས་ནམ་མཁའ་འདྲ་བ་ཡིན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-154"/>“Since it does not abide and has no location, Desire is like the sky.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-243">
            <prop type="folio">F.189.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-378</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱིས་པ་བསླད་པར་གྱུར་རྣམས་ཀྱིས། །ཀུན་ནས་ཉོན་མོངས་ཡོངས་སུ་བརྟགས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Yet immature defiled beings Imagine it to be affliction.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-244">
            <prop type="folio">F.189.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-378</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཀུན་ནས་ཉོན་མོངས་མེད་ཆོས་དེ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-155"/>“This phenomenon, which knows no affliction,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-245">
            <prop type="folio">F.189.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-378</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདོད་ཆགས་ཞེས་བྱའི་མིང་གིས་བརྗོད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Is then designated by the word desire.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-246">
            <prop type="folio">F.189.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-378</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཕྱོགས་བཅུ་དག་ཏུ་བཙལ་བྱས་ཀྱང་། །དེ་ཡི་དངོས་པོ་རྙེད་མི་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Were one to search in all ten directions, One would not find its substance.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-247">
            <prop type="folio">F.189.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-378</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདོད་ཆགས་དངོས་པོ་མེད་པ་ལ། །བྱིས་པ་རྨོངས་པ་འཇིགས་བྱེད་དེ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-156"/>“This insubstantial desire Is feared by confused, childish beings.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-248">
            <prop type="folio">F.189.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-378</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇིགས་མེད་འཇིགས་པའི་འདུ་ཤེས་ཅན། །དེ་དག་ལ་ནི་བདེ་བ་མེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Those who fear where there is no danger Can know no happiness.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-249">
            <prop type="folio">F.189.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-378</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཇི་ལྟར་སྐྱེས་བུ་ལ་ལ་དག །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-157"/>“For instance, some people</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-250">
            <prop type="folio">F.189.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-378</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མཁའ་ལ་འཇིགས་པར་འདུ་ཤེས་ནས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Might perceive the sky as something frightening.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-251">
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྐྲག་ཅིང་བདག་གིས་ནམ་མཁའ་ནི། །མི་མཐོང་བྱ་ཞེས་འབྲོས་བྱེད་ཀྱང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Terrified, they will run away, exclaiming, ‘I must not see the sky!’</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-252">
            <prop type="folio">F.189.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-378</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ནམ་མཁས་ཀུན་དུ་ཁྱབ་པས་ན། །སུ་ཡང་དེ་ལས་མི་ཐར་ཏེ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-158"/>“Yet, since space is omnipresent, No one can be free from it.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-253">
            <prop type="folio">F.189.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-378</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱིས་པ་བསླད་པར་གྱུར་རྣམས་ཀྱིས། །ཕྱིན་ཅི་ལོག་ཏུ་རྣམ་པར་བརྟགས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Corrupted, immature beings Imagine it falsely.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-254">
            <prop type="folio">F.189.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-378</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ལྟར་ཆོས་རྣམས་མཁའ་འདྲ་བར། །ཤེས་པར་མ་གྱུར་བྱིས་པ་རྣམས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-159"/>“Thus, childish beings who do not know Phenomena to be like the sky</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-255">
            <prop type="folio">F.189.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-378</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དངོས་པོ་མེད་པའི་འདོད་ཆགས་ལ། །ཡོངས་སུ་སྤང་བར་མངོན་པར་འདོད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Yearn to rid themselves Of insubstantial desire.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-256">
            <prop type="folio">F.189.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-378</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདོད་ཆགས་ནམ་མཁའ་འདྲ་བས་ན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-160"/>“Since desire is like the sky</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-257">
            <prop type="folio">F.189.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-378</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སུ་ཡང་དེ་ལས་གྲོལ་བ་མེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>No one can be freed from it.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-258">
            <prop type="folio">F.190.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-379</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གྲོལ་ཞིང་རྣམ་གྲོལ་ཕུན་<tei:ref folio="F.190.a"/>སུམ་ཚོགས། །ཆོས་རྣམས་མྱ་ངན་འདས་དང་འདྲ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Perfectly freed and liberated, Phenomena are like nirvāṇa.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-259">
            <prop type="folio">F.190.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-379</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སངས་རྒྱས་གང་དག་འདས་པ་དང་། །འདྲེན་པ་གང་དག་བཞུགས་པ་དང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-161"/>“The buddhas of the past, The guides of the present,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-260">
            <prop type="folio">F.190.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-379</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་དག་འབྱུང་འགྱུར་རྫོགས་སངས་རྒྱས། །དེ་ཀུན་སྤྱོད་ཡུལ་འདོད་ཆགས་ཡིན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>And the perfect buddhas yet to come All have desire as their domain of experience.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-261">
            <prop type="folio">F.190.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-379</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདོད་ཆགས་སྟོང་པར་ཤེས་གྱུར་ན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-162"/>“When you have known desire to be empty,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-262">
            <prop type="folio">F.190.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-379</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཆགས་ལས་གྲོལ་བ་གང་ཡང་མེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>There is no deliverance from it whatsoever.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-263">
            <prop type="folio">F.190.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-379</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་དག་ཆགས་ལ་འཇིགས་འདུ་ཤེས། །དེ་དག་ཆགས་ལས་གྲོལ་བྱར་སེམས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>It is those who perceive desire as something frightening Who think they must free themselves from it.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-264">
            <prop type="folio">F.190.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-379</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཅི་ཡང་མེད་པའི་མཐའ་འདི་ནི། །འདོད་ཆགས་མཐའ་སྟེ་འོད་གསལ་ཞིང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-163"/>“Being a limit of nothing whatsoever, The limit of desire is luminosity.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-265">
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མཚན་མ་མེད་ལ་རྟག་མཉམ་པར། །བྱང་ཆུབ་སྙིང་པོར་ང་ཡིས་མཐོང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>As it is without characteristics, permanent, and sameness— I see it as the seat of awakening.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-266">
            <prop type="folio">F.190.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-379</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དངོས་པོར་འདུ་ཤེས་སེམས་ཅན་གང་། །དེ་དག་འདོད་ཆགས་འབྲི་བར་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-165"/>“Beings who perceive it as existent Aim to diminish desire.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-267">
            <prop type="folio">F.190.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-379</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡོད་པ་མིན་པ་ཡོངས་བརྟགས་པས། །དེ་དག་གིས་ནི་སྤོང་བ་བརྟགས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Imagining the nonexistent, They imagine its abandonment.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-268">
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བདག་གིས་འདོད་ཆགས་སྤང་བྱ་ཞེས། །དེ་འདྲའི་འདུ་ཤེས་སྐྱེས་ནས་ནི། །</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“ ‘I must abandon desire’— Giving rise to such a conception,</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-269">
            <prop type="folio">F.190.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-379</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ལ་སྤངས་ཞེས་བརྗོད་པར་བྱ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They would speak of its abandonment;</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-270">
            <prop type="folio">F.190.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-379</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འགྲོ་བ་འདི་དག་འདུ་ཤེས་ཙམ། །འདོད་ཆགས་མཐའ་ནི་བསམ་ཡས་ཏེ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>But such is these beings’ mere conception. <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-167"/>“The limit of desire defies thought</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-271">
            <prop type="folio">F.190.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-379</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མཐའ་དེ་འཇིག་པ་མེད་པས་ན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>And is indestructible.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-272">
            <prop type="folio">F.190.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-379</prop>
            <prop type="alternative-source"/>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡང་དག་མཐའ་དང་དེ་མཉམ་པས། །དེ་ལས་གྲོལ་བར་མ་རྟོགས་ཤིག །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Thus it is equal to the limit of reality. So, do not think<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="UT22084-040-005-168"/> of being freed from it!</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-273">
            <prop type="folio">F.190.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-379</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གལ་ཏེ་ཆགས་ལས་གྲོལ་གྱུར་ན། །སྟོང་པ་ཉིད་ལས་གྲོལ་བར་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-169"/>“If one were freed from desire, One would be freed from emptiness.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-274">
            <prop type="folio">F.190.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-379</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདོད་ཆགས་དང་ནི་སྟོང་པ་ཉིད། །དེ་གཉིས་གཉིས་སུ་ཡོད་མ་ཡིན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Desire and emptiness Are not two separate things.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-275">
            <prop type="folio">F.190.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-379</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདི་ལྟར་སྐྱེ་བ་མེད་པ་ལ། །དེ་དག་སྐྱེ་བར་རྣམ་བརྟགས་པས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-170"/>“In this way, these beings imagine<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="UT22084-040-005-171"/> The birth of the unborn.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-276">
            <prop type="folio">F.190.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-379</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱིས་པ་གཉིས་སུ་ཤེས་རྣམས་ལ། །ངས་ནི་སྤོང་བ་རབ་ཏུ་བསྟན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Therefore, to such immature beings whose consciousness is dualistic, I have taught abandonment.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-277">
            <prop type="folio">F.190.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-379</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདོད་ཆགས་དེ་ནི་སྐྱེ་མེད་ན། །འདོད་ཆགས་ཤེས་བྱའི་མིང་དུ་བརྗོད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-172"/>“Since it is unborn, Desire is just a label.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-278">
            <prop type="folio">F.190.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-379</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མིང་རྣམས་ཀུན་དུ་ཆགས་མེད་པས། །མིང་ལ་སུ་ཡང་ཆགས་པ་མེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Names have no desire, And no one at all is attached to a name.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-279">
            <prop type="folio">F.190.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-379</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདོད་ཆགས་ཆགས་པ་མེད་ཤེས་ཤིང་། །མཐའ་ལས་འདས་པའི་སྟོང་མཐོང་ན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-173"/>“Knowing desire to be without attachment, And seeing it as limitless emptiness,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-280">
            <prop type="folio">F.190.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-379</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདོད་ཆགས་རྣམ་པར་གཞིག་པའི་ཕྱིར། །ཐར་པ་མཁས་པས་མི་མཐོང་ངོ་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The wise do not see liberation As a way to eliminate desire.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-281">
            <prop type="folio">F.190.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-379</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདོད་ཆགས་སངས་རྒྱས་ཆོས་མཚུངས་ཤིང་། །མྱ་ངན་འདས་པ་འདྲར་ཤེས་ནས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-174"/>“Knowing that desire is like the qualities of awakening, And like nirvāṇa,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-282">
            <prop type="folio">F.190.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-379</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྡུལ་དང་བྲལ་བའི་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན། །འདོད་ཆགས་སྒྲས་ནི་ངས་བསྟན་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>I have taught immaculate<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="UT22084-040-005-175"/> absorption<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="UT22084-040-005-176"/> With reference to the word desire.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-283">
            <prop type="folio">F.190.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-379</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཞི་བའི་དབྱིངས་ལ་རྟེན་པ་ཡིན། །འདོད་ཆགས་རབ་ཏུ་ཞི་ཤེས་ནས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-177"/>“Desire rests on the sphere of peace. Knowing it to be complete peace,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-284">
            <prop type="folio">F.190.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-379</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མཁས་པ་རྣམས་ལ་ང་ཡིས་ནི། །ཏིང་འཛིན་འདོད་ཆགས་སྒྲར་བསྟན་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>To the wise ones I have taught Absorption with reference to the word desire.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-285">
            <prop type="folio">F.190.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-380</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་དེ་ལྟར་ན་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔས་འདོད་<tei:ref folio="F.190.b"/>ཆགས་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་དུ་རྟོགས་པར་བྱའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Mañjuśrī, this is how bodhisattvas should understand desire to be absorption.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-286">
            <prop type="folio">F.190.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-380</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་དེ་ལ་ཇི་ལྟར་ན་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔས་ཞེ་སྡང་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་དུ་རྟོགས་པར་བྱ་ཞེ་ན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-179"/>“Mañjuśrī, how should bodhisattvas understand anger to be absorption?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-287">
            <prop type="folio">F.190.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-380</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྤོང་ལས་ཞེ་སྡང་ཀུན་དུ་འབྱུང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“As anger comes from rejecting,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-288">
            <prop type="folio">F.190.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-380</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཉོན་མོངས་པ་ཡང་རྐྱེན་ལས་སྐྱེ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>It is also an affliction born from conditions.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-289">
            <prop type="folio">F.190.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-380</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བདག་མེད་པ་ལས་བྱུང་བའི་བདག །མང་པོའི་ཚོགས་ལས་སྐྱེས་པ་ཡིན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>This self, which has arisen from a lack of self, Comes about through the aggregation of many things.<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="UT22084-040-005-181"/>
                </seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-290">
            <prop type="folio">F.190.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-380</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྩུབ་པོའི་སྒྲ་ལས་ཞེ་སྡང་ནི། །དུག་རྣོན་ལྟ་བུ་ཀུན་དུ་འབྱུང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-182"/>“Anger at harsh words Comes about like lethal poison.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-291">
            <prop type="folio">F.190.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-380</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྒྲ་ནི་ང་རོའི་རང་བཞིན་པས། །ཤིན་དུ་ཡོད་པ་མ་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Words are simply the nature of sound And therefore completely nonexistent.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-292">
            <prop type="folio">F.190.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-380</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཇི་ལྟར་ཚོགས་པས་གཙུབ་ཤིང་དང་། །གཙུབ་སྟན་ལས་ནི་མེ་བྱུང་སྟེ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-183"/>“For instance, fire is kindled through the meeting</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-293">
            <prop type="folio">F.190.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-380</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཚོགས་དང་བྲལ་བར་གྱུར་ན་ནི། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Of the grinding stick and grinding support.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-294">
            <prop type="folio">F.190.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-380</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ན་མེ་ཡང་ཡོད་མིན་ལྟར། །དེ་བཞིན་ཡིད་དུ་མི་འོང་བའི། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Without these materials coming together, Fire cannot be.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-295">
            <prop type="folio">F.190.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-380</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྒྲ་ལས་ཞེ་སྡང་གསོག་འབྱུང་ཞིང་། །གསོག་གི་སྒྲ་ལས་ཡང་བརྟགས་ན</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-184"/>“Likewise, from unpleasant words Arises vain anger;</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-296">
            <prop type="folio">F.190.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-380</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ལ་ཞེ་སྡང་རྙེད་མི་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>But if you examine these hollow<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="UT22084-040-005-185"/> words,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-297">
            <prop type="folio">F.190.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-380</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཞེ་སྡང་སྒྲ་ལས་མ་བྱུང་ཞིང་། །ནང་ནའང་གནས་པ་མ་ཡིན་ལ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>You will find no anger there. <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-186"/>“Anger does not come from words.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-298">
            <prop type="folio">F.190.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-380</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཞེ་སྡང་ཕྱི་རོལ་མ་འོངས་ཏེ། །བྱུང་བ་མེད་པས་གསོག་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>It does not reside inside, Nor does anger arise from the outside—<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="UT22084-040-005-187"/>
                </seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-299">
            <prop type="folio">F.190.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-380</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྒྱུ་རྣམས་ཕན་ཚུན་འདུས་པ་ལས། །ཞེ་སྡང་ཀུན་དུ་བྱུང་བ་ཡིན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Since it is without origination, it is hollow.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-300">
            <prop type="folio">F.190.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-380</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཕན་ཚུན་བྲལ་བར་གྱུར་ན་ནི། །དེ་ལ་ཞེ་སྡང་རྙེད་མི་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-188"/>“The coming together of causes Is the source of anger. If the causes come apart, Anger is nowhere to be found.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-301">
            <prop type="folio">F.190.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-380</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཇི་ལྟར་ཞོ་དང་འོ་མ་ལ། །སྐྱེས་བུས་བཙལ་ཏེ་སྲུབ་ཤིང་གིས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-189"/>“People may seek Curd and milk, churn it with a stick,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-302">
            <prop type="folio">F.190.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-380</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བསྲུབ་པ་བྱས་པས་རྐྱེན་རྣམས་ལས། །མར་ནི་ཀུན་དུ་བྱུང་བ་ལྟར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>And create the conditions For butter to appear.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-303">
            <prop type="folio">F.190.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-380</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་བཞིན་ཡིད་དུ་མི་འཐད་པའི། །སྒྲ་ལས་ཞེ་སྡང་གསོག་འབྱུང་ཞིང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-190"/>“Likewise, unpleasant words Are sources of hollow anger:</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-304">
            <prop type="folio">F.190.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-380</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡོངས་སུ་བརྟགས་པས་དེ་གནས་ལ། །མི་མཁས་པ་དག་རབ་ཏུ་འབར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Because of their illusions, The unwise get fired up about them.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-305">
            <prop type="folio">F.190.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-380</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཀུན་ཏུ་བརྟགས་པས་ཞེ་སྡང་ནི། །ཤིན་དུ་དངོས་མེད་ཤེས་པས་ན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-191"/>“Knowing anger to be caused by imputation, And therefore utterly insubstantial,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-306">
            <prop type="folio">F.190.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-380</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཏིང་འཛིན་ཞི་བ་བརྗོད་པ་ནི། །ཞེ་སྡང་སྒྲ་ཡིས་རབ་ཏུ་བསྟན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>I have made this statement on the peace of absorption With reference to the word anger.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-307">
            <prop type="folio">F.190.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-380</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཞེ་སྡང་ཡང་དག་མཐའ་དང་མཉམ། །དེ་བཞིན་ཉིད་ལ་རྟེན་པ་ཡིན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-192"/>“Knowing anger to be equal to the limit of reality, Rooted in suchness,<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="UT22084-040-005-193"/>
                </seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-308">
            <prop type="folio">F.190.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-380</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཆོས་ཀྱི་དབྱིངས་དང་འདྲར་ཤེས་པས། །དེས་ན་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་ཅེས་བསྟན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>And similar to the realm of phenomena, I have taught about absorption.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-309">
            <prop type="folio">F.190.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-380</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་དེ་ལྟར་ན་ཞེ་སྡང་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་དུ་རྟོགས་པར་བྱའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Mañjuśrī, this is how you should understand anger to be absorption.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-310">
            <prop type="folio">F.190.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-380</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་དེ་ལ་ཇི་ལྟར་ན་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔས་གཏི་མུག་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་དུ་རྟོགས་པར་བྱ་ཞེ་ན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-195"/>“Mañjuśrī, how should bodhisattvas understand delusion to be absorption?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-311">
            <prop type="folio">F.190.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-380</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མ་རིག་པ་ལས་གཏི་མུག་བྱུང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Delusion comes from ignorance;</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-312">
            <prop type="folio">F.190.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-380</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མ་རིག་པ་ཡང་ཡོད་མ་ཡིན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Ignorance too is nonexistent.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-313">
            <prop type="folio">F.190.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-380</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་ན་གཏི་མུག་ཡོད་མིན་པ། །དེ་ན་གང་ཡང་རྨོངས་པ་མེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Where there is no delusion, There can be no confusion.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-314">
            <prop type="folio">F.190.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-380</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྨོངས་མེད་སེམས་ཅན་རྨོངས་གྱུར་ཅིང་། །ཆགས་མེད་ཆགས་པར་འདུ་ཤེས་པ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-197"/>“Beings confuse what is without confusion, And perceive attachment where there is none.<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="UT22084-040-005-198"/>
                </seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-315">
            <prop type="folio">F.191.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-381</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཇི་ལྟར་བྱིས་པས་ནམ་མཁའ་<tei:ref folio="F.191.a"/>ལ། །མདུད་པ་བོར་བས་གསོག་བཞིན་ནོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>This is just like a childish being Vainly trying to tie a knot in space.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-316">
            <prop type="folio">F.191.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-381</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡོད་པ་མ་ཡིན་ཆོས་རྣམས་ལ། །ཀུན་ནས་ཉོན་མོངས་རྣམ་བཏགས་པ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-199"/>“Labeling<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="UT22084-040-005-200"/> nonexistent phenomena As defilements:</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-317">
            <prop type="folio">F.191.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-381</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱིས་པ་རྣམས་ཀྱི་འདི་མཚར་ཏེ། །མཆོག་ཏུ་ཤིན་དུ་བྱ་བར་དཀའ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>This [problem] of childish beings is outrageous. It is indeed the most heinous of evil deeds.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-318">
            <prop type="folio">F.191.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-381</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཇི་ལྟར་སྐྱེས་བུ་ལ་ལ་ཞིག །ནམ་མཁའ་ལ་ནི་འཇལ་བྱེད་ཅིང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-201"/>“Just as someone May examine the sky</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-319">
            <prop type="folio">F.191.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-381</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བསྐལ་པ་བྱེ་བར་གཞལ་བྱས་ཀྱང་། །དེ་ལ་ཕུང་པོ་མི་རྙེད་ལྟར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>For ten million eons And find no aggregates in it—</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-320">
            <prop type="folio">F.191.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-381</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་བཞིན་རྨོངས་པས་བྱིས་པ་ཡི། །སྔོན་གྱི་མཐའ་ནི་བསམ་མི་ཁྱབ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-202"/>“Likewise, due to confusion The origin of immature beings is inconceivable.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-321">
            <prop type="folio">F.191.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-381</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཏི་མུག་ཕུང་པོར་འབྱུང་མེད་དེ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Ignorance does not heap up—</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-322">
            <prop type="folio">F.191.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-381</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེས་ནི་ཅི་ཡང་བཀང་བ་མེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>It cannot fill anything up.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-323">
            <prop type="folio">F.191.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-381</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཇི་ལྟར་ནམ་མཁའ་གཞལ་བྱས་ཀྱང་། །དེ་ལ་སྔོན་གྱི་མཐའ་མེད་ཅིང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-203"/>“One may try to measure the sky, But it has no beginning.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-324">
            <prop type="folio">F.191.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-381</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ན་ཅི་ཡང་བཀང་བ་མེད། །གཞལ་བར་ནུས་པ་མེད་པ་ལྟར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The sky cannot be filled by anything: It is immeasurable.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-325">
            <prop type="folio">F.191.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-381</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་བཞིན་བསྐལ་པ་སྟོང་རྣམས་སུ། །ཀུན་དུ་རྨོངས་པས་དགང་བྱས་ཀྱང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-204"/>“Likewise, for thousands of eons Beings have been filled with<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="UT22084-040-005-205"/> ignorance; Still,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-326">
            <prop type="folio">F.191.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-381</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ལ་བཀང་བ་ཅི་ཡང་མེད། །ངོམས་པའང་ཅུང་ཟད་ཡོད་མ་ཡིན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>they are never being filled, And they are never satisfied in the slightest.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-327">
            <prop type="folio">F.191.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-381</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཇི་ལྟར་སྐྱེས་བུ་ལ་ལ་ཡིས། །སྦུད་པ་སྟོང་པ་བུད་བྱས་ཤིང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-206"/>“When a person who uses a bellow First empties it, expelling its air,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-328">
            <prop type="folio">F.191.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-381</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཞག་ནས་སྦུད་པ་རྙོངས་པ་ན། །དེ་ཡི་ནང་ན་རྙེད་མིན་ལྟར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>and Having compressed it, opens it up again, Nothing is to be found inside it.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-329">
            <prop type="folio">F.191.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-381</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་བཞིན་འདོད་པ་སྦུད་འདྲ་བ། །ཀུན་དུ་རྨོངས་པས་སྤྱོད་པར་བྱེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-207"/>“Likewise, desire is like a bellow: Those who act out of delusion</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-330">
            <prop type="folio">F.191.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-381</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནི་ངོམས་པར་མི་འགྱུར་ཏེ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Can never find satisfaction,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-331">
            <prop type="folio">F.191.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-381</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཕྱིར་ཞིང་འདོད་པ་ཚོལ་བར་བྱེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>But only pursue further desires.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-332">
            <prop type="folio">F.191.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-381</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཏི་མུག་ཡོད་པ་མིན་ཞེས་བརྗོད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-208"/>“Ignorance is said to be nonexistent:</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-333">
            <prop type="folio">F.191.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-381</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྩ་བ་ཆད་ཅིང་དངོས་པོ་མེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>It is uprooted and insubstantial,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-334">
            <prop type="folio">F.191.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-381</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྩ་བ་མེད་ཅིང་གནས་ཀྱང་མེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Rootless and without location;</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-335">
            <prop type="folio">F.191.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-381</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེས་ན་གཏི་མུག་ཟད་པ་མེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Therefore, ignorance is inexhaustible.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-336">
            <prop type="folio">F.191.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-381</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདི་ལྟར་གཏི་མུག་མི་ཟད་པས། །དེ་ཡི་མཐའ་མ་རྙེད་མི་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-209"/>“Since ignorance is inexhaustible,<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="UT22084-040-005-210"/> Its end cannot be found.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-337">
            <prop type="folio">F.191.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-381</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ཕྱིར་སེམས་ཅན་ཐམས་ཅད་ལ། །ཟད་པར་བྱ་བར་ངས་མི་ནུས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Therefore, I cannot make it disappear For all sentient beings.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-338">
            <prop type="folio">F.191.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-381</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གལ་ཏེ་དཔེ་ཙམ་བརྗོད་བྱ་ན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-211"/>“To make an analogy,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-339">
            <prop type="folio">F.191.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-381</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བསྐལ་པ་བྱེ་བ་བསམ་ཡས་སུ། །ང་ཡི་ཚེ་ནི་གནས་གྱུར་ལ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Even if I were to remain alive For inconceivably many tens of millions of eons</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-340">
            <prop type="folio">F.191.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-381</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཉིན་གཅིག་བཞིན་དུ་ཉིན་རེ་ལ། །སྟོང་གསུམ་སེམས་ཅན་ཇི་སྙེད་པ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>And every single day <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-212"/>“Cause as many beings as there are in a trichiliocosm</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-341">
            <prop type="folio">F.191.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-381</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཐམས་ཅད་མྱ་ངན་བཟླ་བྱས་ཞིང་། །ཐམས་ཅད་དེ་ལྟར་བྱས་ཀྱང་ནི། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>To pass into nirvāṇa, Though I may succeed in this,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-342">
            <prop type="folio">F.191.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-381</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སེམས་ཅན་ཁམས་ལ་ཟད་པ་མེད། །གཏི་མུག་གིས་ནི་བསྐྱེད་པའི་ཁམས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The realms of beings would still not be depleted. <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-213"/>“Created by ignorance,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-343">
            <prop type="folio">F.191.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-381</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སེམས་ཅན་ཁམས་ལ་མཚན་ཉིད་མེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The realms of beings are without marks.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-344">
            <prop type="folio">F.191.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-381</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཏི་མུག་དེ་ནི་སྒྱུ་མ་འདྲ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Ignorance is like an illusion,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-345">
            <prop type="folio">F.191.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-381</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེས་ན་དེ་ཡི་མཐའ་མི་རྙེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>And its end can therefore not be found.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-346">
            <prop type="folio">F.191.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-381</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སངས་རྒྱས་གཏི་མུག་མཉམ་པས་ན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-214"/>“Since Buddha is the same as ignorance,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-347">
            <prop type="folio">F.191.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-381</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་དག་གཉིས་སུ་མེད་པར་བསྟན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>I have taught that they are no different.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-348">
            <prop type="folio">F.191.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-381</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྨོངས་གྱུར་བྱིས་པ་དེ་དག་གིས། །འདིར་ནི་སངས་རྒྱས་རྣམ་པར་བརྟགས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>It is confused, childish beings Who have given me the name Buddha.<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="UT22084-040-005-367"/>
                </seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-349">
            <prop type="folio">F.191.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-381</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཐམས་ཅད་མཁྱེན་ཉིད་གཏི་མུག་མཉམ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-215"/>“Omniscience and ignorance are the same;</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-350">
            <prop type="folio">F.191.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-381</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཏི་མུག་ཐམས་ཅད་ཡོད་མ་ཡིན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>All ignorance is nonexistent.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-351">
            <prop type="folio">F.191.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-381</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཏི་མུག་སེམས་ཅན་ཀུན་དང་མཉམ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Ignorance is the same as all beings,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-352">
            <prop type="folio">F.191.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-382</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སེམས་<tei:ref folio="F.191.b"/>ཅན་ཀུན་ཀྱང་བསམ་མི་ཁྱབ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>And all beings are inconceivable. </seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-353">
            <prop type="folio">F.191.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-382</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བསམ་མི་ཁྱབ་དང་གཏི་མུག་ནི། །སེམས་བསྐྱེད་པ་ཡིས་རྣམ་པར་བརྟགས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-216"/>“Inconceivability and ignorance Are thus imputed by thought.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-354">
            <prop type="folio">F.191.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-382</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སེམས་ཀུན་བསམ་གྱིས་མི་ཁྱབ་སྟེ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>All of the mind<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="UT22084-040-005-217"/> is inconceivable,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-355">
            <prop type="folio">F.191.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-382</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ཡི་ཚད་ནི་ཡོད་མ་ཡིན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>And has no limit.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-356">
            <prop type="folio">F.191.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-382</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཏི་མུག་དེ་ལ་ཚད་མེད་པས། །དེ་ཡི་འབྱུང་བ་རྙེད་མི་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-218"/>“Since ignorance is immeasurable, One cannot find its origin.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-357">
            <prop type="folio">F.191.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-382</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འབྱུང་བ་ཡོད་པ་མ་ཡིན་ན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Without an origin,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-358">
            <prop type="folio">F.191.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-382</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྐྱེ་བ་ཡོད་པར་ག་ལ་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>How can it arise?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-359">
            <prop type="folio">F.191.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-382</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཏི་མུག་སྐྱེས་པ་མ་ཡིན་ན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-219"/>“If ignorance is unborn,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-360">
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ཡི་རྨོངས་བྱེད་ཅི་འདྲ་ཞིག །དེ་ཡི་རྨོངས་བྱེད་ཅི་འདྲ་བ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>How could it ever cause confusion? How could it ever cause confusion</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-361">
            <prop type="folio">F.191.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-382</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སངས་རྒྱས་ཀུན་ཀྱང་དེ་དང་འདྲ། །ཐ་དད་དབྱེ་བ་མེད་ཤེས་ན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Is how it also is with all buddhas.<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="UT22084-040-005-365"/> <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-220"/>“Knowing that they are neither different nor separate,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-362">
            <prop type="folio">F.191.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-382</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཆོས་རྣམས་ཐམས་ཅད་གཉིས་སུ་མེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>And that all phenomena are nondual,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-363">
            <prop type="folio">F.191.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-382</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཏིང་འཛིན་ཞི་བ་བརྗོད་པ་ནི། །གཏི་མུག་སྒྲ་ཡིས་རབ་ཏུ་བསྟན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>I made this statement on the peace of absorption With reference to the word ignorance.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-364">
            <prop type="folio">F.191.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-382</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་ཚེ་ང་ཡིས་མཉམ་ཉིད་ཤེས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-221"/>“When I came to know sameness,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-365">
            <prop type="folio">F.191.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-382</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནི་དེ་དང་གཏི་མུག་མཉམ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>I [understood] that ignorance was the same as it.<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="UT22084-040-005-222"/>
                </seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-366">
            <prop type="folio">F.191.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-382</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་དག་ཐམས་ཅད་མཉམ་ཤེས་ནས། །ཏིང་འཛིན་དེ་ལྟར་ཤེས་པར་གྱིས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Knowing all of these to be the same, Understand absorption accordingly.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-367">
            <prop type="folio">F.191.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-382</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་དེ་ལྟར་ན་གཏི་མུག་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་དུ་རྟོགས་པར་བྱའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Mañjuśrī, this is how you should understand ignorance to be absorption.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-368">
            <prop type="folio">F.191.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-382</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་དེ་ལ་ཇི་ལྟར་ན་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔས་མི་དགེ་བ་ཐམས་ཅད་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་དུ་རྟོགས་པར་བྱ་ཞེ་ན། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-224"/>“Mañjuśrī, how should bodhisattvas understand all nonvirtues to be absorption?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-369">
            <prop type="folio">F.191.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-382</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདོད་ཆགས་སྤྱོད་པའི་རྟགས་གང་དང་། །ཞེ་སྡང་སྤྱོད་པའི་གཡོ་བ་དང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“The features of being desirous, And the turbulence of being angry,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-370">
            <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཏི་མུག་སྤྱོད་པ་གང་ཡིན་པ། །ཐམས་ཅད་ཏིང་འཛིན་ཤེས་པར་གྱིས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>As well as being ignorant— Know them all to be absorption.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-371">
            <prop type="folio">F.191.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-382</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཉོན་མོངས་ཀུན་གྱི་སྒྲུབ་པ་ནི། །ཏིང་འཛིན་ཡིན་པར་མོས་པར་གྱིས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-226"/>“The production<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="UT22084-040-005-227"/> of any affliction<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="UT22084-040-005-228"/> Is absorption—be confident of that!</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-372">
            <prop type="folio">F.191.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-382</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བརྫུན་དང་ཡང་དག་མ་ཡིན་པར། །ཐམས་ཅད་དེ་བཞིན་བསྒོམ་པར་གྱིས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Afflictions are false and unreal; Meditate on them all in this way.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-373">
            <prop type="folio">F.191.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-382</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་དེ་ལྟར་ན་མི་དགེ་བ་ཐམས་ཅད་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་དུ་རྟོགས་པར་བྱའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Mañjuśrī, this is how you should understand all nonvirtues to be absorption.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-374">
            <prop type="folio">F.191.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-382</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་དེ་ལ་ཇི་ལྟར་ན་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔས་དགེ་བ་ཐམས་ཅད་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་དུ་རྟོགས་པར་བྱ་ཞེ་ན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-230"/>“Mañjuśrī, how should bodhisattvas understand all virtues to be absorption?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-375">
            <prop type="folio">F.191.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-382</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སེམས་ཅན་རྣམས་ཀྱི་ཇི་སྙེད་དགེ །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Whatever virtues beings may have,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-376">
            <prop type="folio">F.191.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-382</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སེམས་དང་སྤྱོད་པ་ཅི་འདྲ་བ། །སྤྱོད་པ་ཐམས་ཅད་སྤྱོད་གཅིག་སྟེ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>And howsoever their minds and conduct may be, All conduct is but one conduct;</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-377">
            <prop type="folio">F.191.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-382</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ལྟར་ཏིང་འཛིན་ཤེས་པར་གྱིས། །སེམས་ཅན་ཀུན་གྱི་སྤྱོད་པ་དག །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Know absorption to be like this! <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-232"/>“Knowing the conduct of all beings</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-378">
            <prop type="folio">F.191.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-382</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བསྒྲུབ་པ་གཅིག་ཏུ་ཤེས་པས་ན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>To be but one performance,<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="UT22084-040-005-233"/>
                </seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-379">
            <prop type="folio">F.191.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-382</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཏིང་འཛིན་ཞི་བ་བརྗོད་པ་ནི། །ཀུན་གྱི་སྒྲ་ཡིས་བསྟན་པ་ཡིན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>I have made this statement on the peace of absorption With reference to the word all.<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="UT22084-040-005-234"/>
                </seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-380">
            <prop type="folio">F.191.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-382</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་དེ་ལྟར་ན་དགེ་བ་ཐམས་ཅད་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་དུ་རྟོགས་པར་བྱའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Mañjuśrī, in this way, you should understand all virtues to be absorption.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-381">
            <prop type="folio">F.191.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-382</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་དེ་ལ་ཇི་ལྟར་ན་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔས་འདུས་བྱས་ཐམས་ཅད་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་དུ་རྟོགས་པར་བྱ་ཞེ་ན། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-236"/>“Mañjuśrī, how should bodhisattvas understand all conditioned phenomena to be absorption?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-382">
            <prop type="folio">F.191.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-382</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདུ་བྱེད་ཐམས་ཅད་འདུ་བྱེད་མིན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Formations are not formations.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-383">
            <prop type="folio">F.191.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-382</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་དག་བགྲང་བས་གཞལ་བྱས་ན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>In terms of numerical estimation,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-384">
            <prop type="folio">F.191.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-382</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཞལ་དུ་མེད་ཅིང་དཔག་ཏུ་མེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They are uncountable and immeasurable—</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-385">
            <prop type="folio">F.192.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-383</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ལྟར་ཏིང་འཛིན་ཤེས་པར་གྱིས། །དཔག་ཏུ་མེད་<tei:ref folio="F.192.a"/>པར་ཤེས་ན་ནི། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Know absorption to be so. <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-238"/>“Knowing formations to be immeasurable,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-386">
            <prop type="folio">F.192.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-383</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལུས་མེད་དངོས་པོ་ཡོད་མིན་པས། །ཏིང་འཛིན་ཞི་བ་བརྗོད་པ་ནི། །འདུ་བྱེད་ཀུན་གྱིས་བསྟན་པ་ཡིན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Without body or substance, I have made this statement on the peace of absorption With reference to all formations.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-387">
            <prop type="folio">F.192.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-383</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་དེ་ལྟར་ན་འདུས་བྱས་ཐམས་ཅད་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་དུ་རྟོགས་པར་བྱའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Mañjuśrī, this is how you should understand all conditioned phenomena to be absorption.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-388">
            <prop type="folio">F.192.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-383</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་དེ་ལ་ཇི་ལྟར་ན་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔས་འདུས་མ་བྱས་ཐམས་ཅད་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་དུ་རྟོགས་པར་བྱ་ཞེ་ན། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-240"/>“Mañjuśrī, how should bodhisattvas understand all unconditioned phenomena to be absorption?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-389">
            <prop type="folio">F.192.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-383</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཆོས་འདི་རང་བཞིན་ཞི་བས་ན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Since this Dharma is naturally peaceful,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-390">
            <prop type="folio">F.192.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-383</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ལ་གྲངས་ནི་ཡོད་མ་ཡིན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>It is beyond number.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-391">
            <prop type="folio">F.192.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-383</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མ་རིག་པ་ཡིས་བསྒྲུབ་ཞི་བ། །ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་གྱིས་བསྒྲུབ་པར་བསྟན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>I have taught that peace formed by ignorance Is formed by absorption.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-392">
            <prop type="folio">F.192.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-383</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདུས་བྱས་ཀུན་ལ་བརྗོད་མེད་ཅིང་། །བསྒྲུབ་པ་མེད་པར་ཤེས་ནས་ནི། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-242"/>“Knowing everything conditioned to be inexpressible And uncreated,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-393">
            <prop type="folio">F.192.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-383</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སེམས་ཅན་གང་དག་བརྗོད་ལ་ཆགས། །དེ་དག་རྣམས་ལ་དེ་ལྟར་བསྟན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>I have taught such To all beings who are attached to words.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-394">
            <prop type="folio">F.192.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-383</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་དེ་ལྟར་ན་འདུས་མ་བྱས་ཐམས་ཅད་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་དུ་རྟོགས་པར་བྱའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Mañjuśrī, this is how you should understand all unconditioned phenomena to be absorption.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-395">
            <prop type="folio">F.192.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-383</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཚིགས་སུ་བཅད་པ་མངོན་པར་བསྒྲུབས་པའི་སྒྲ་བསམ་གྱིས་མི་ཁྱབ་པ་བསྟན་པ་འདི་བཤད་པ་ན་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་དགུ་ཁྲི་ཉིས་སྟོང་གིས་མི་སྐྱེ་བའི་ཆོས་ལ་བཟོད་པ་ཐོབ་བོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-244"/>As he completed these verses, thus delivering this inconceivable teaching, ninety-two thousand bodhisattvas gained the acceptance of phenomena being unborn.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-396">
            <prop type="folio">F.192.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-383</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལྷ་བྱེ་བ་ཁྲག་ཁྲིག་བརྒྱ་སྟོང་ཕྲག་བདུན་ཅུ་རྩ་གཉིས་ཀྱིས་བླ་ན་མེད་པ་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་བྱང་ཆུབ་ཏུ་སེམས་བསྐྱེད་དོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Seventy-two sextillion gods formed the resolve to attain unsurpassed and perfect awakening.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-397">
            <prop type="folio">F.192.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-383</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དགེ་སློང་སུམ་ཁྲི་དྲུག་སྟོང་ནི་ལེན་པ་མེད་པར་ཟག་པ་རྣམས་ལས་སེམས་རྣམ་པར་གྲོལ་ལོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Thirty-six thousand monks liberated their minds from the defilements, without further appropriation.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-398">
            <prop type="folio">F.192.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-383</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དགེ་སློང་མ་དྲུག་སྟོང་ཉིས་བརྒྱས་ཀྱང་བླ་ན་མེད་པ་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་བྱང་ཆུབ་ཏུ་སེམས་བསྐྱེད་དོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Six thousand two hundred nuns also formed the resolve to achieve unsurpassed and perfect awakening.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-399">
            <prop type="folio">F.192.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-383</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དགེ་བསྙེན་ས་ཡ་བརྒྱད་འབུམ་གྱིས་ཀྱང་བླ་ན་མེད་པ་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་བྱང་ཆུབ་ཏུ་སེམས་བསྐྱེད་དོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Eight million one hundred thousand male lay practitioners formed the resolve to achieve unsurpassed and perfect awakening.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-400">
            <prop type="folio">F.192.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-383</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དགེ་བསྙེན་མ་ས་ཡ་ཕྲག་བཞི་དང་ཉིས་འབུམ་གྱིས་ཀྱང་བླ་ན་མེད་པ་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་བྱང་ཆུབ་ཏུ་སེམས་བསྐྱེད་དོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Four million two hundred thousand female lay practitioners also formed the resolve to reach unsurpassed and perfect awakening.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-401">
            <prop type="folio">F.192.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-383</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ལ་འཇམ་དཔལ་གཞོན་ནུར་གྱུར་པས་འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་གསོལ་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-245"/>Then Prince Mañjuśrī said to the Blessed One,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-402">
            <prop type="folio">F.192.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-383</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་དབང་པོ་རྣོན་པོ་གང་དག་འབྱུང་བ་དེ་དག་གིས་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་རྣམས་ཀྱི་མིང་ཐོས་ན་ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་ལ་སྣང་བ་འཐོབ་པར་འགྱུར་བ་དང་། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“If those bodhisattvas with sharp faculties who have come here hear the names of some absorptions, they will attain illumination in all phenomena.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-403">
            <prop type="folio">F.192.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-383</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བདུད་ཀྱི་རིས་ཀྱི་ལྷའི་བུ་ཐམས་ཅད་དང་། གང་ཟག་དམིགས་པའི་ལྟ་བ་ཅན་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་ཐུལ་བར་དཀའ་བ་དང་། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They will be impervious to all the gods belonging to the entourage of Māra and to those who hold the view that apprehends the person.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-404">
            <prop type="folio">F.192.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-383</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡི་གེ་གཅིག་གིས་ཡི་གེ་ཐམས་ཅད་རྟོགས་པར་འགྱུར་བ་དང་། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Through a single letter, they will understand all letters, and through all letters,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-405">
            <prop type="folio">F.192.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-383</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡི་གེ་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱིས་ཡི་གེ་གཅིག་རྟོགས་པར་འགྱུར་བ་དང་། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>they will understand<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="UT22084-040-005-246"/> one letter.<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="UT22084-040-005-247"/>
                </seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-406">
            <prop type="folio">F.192.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-384</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཐོགས་པ་མ་མཆིས་པའི་སྤོབས་པས་<tei:ref folio="F.192.b"/>སེམས་ཅན་ཐམས་ཅད་ལ་ཆོས་སྟོན་པ་ལ་མཁས་པར་འགྱུར་བ་དང་། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They will become skilled in teaching the Dharma to all beings with unimpeded confident eloquence. </seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-407">
            <prop type="folio">F.192.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-384</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཆོས་ཟབ་མོ་ལ་བཟོད་པར་འགྱུར་བ་དང་། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They will gain acceptance of the profound Dharma.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-408">
            <prop type="folio">F.192.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-384</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྤྱོད་པ་ཐམས་ཅད་ལ་མཚན་ཉིད་གཅིག་ཏུ་རྟོགས་ཤིང་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They will understand all conduct to be of a single defining characteristic.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-409">
            <prop type="folio">F.192.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-384</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སོ་སོ་ཡང་དག་པར་རིག་པ་བཞིས་མུན་པ་མ་མཆིས་པར་འཐོབ་པར་འགྱུར་བའི་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་རྣམས་ཀྱི་མིང་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་བསྟན་དུ་གསོལ། དེ་སྐད་ཅེས་གསོལ་པ་དང་། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They will achieve an unobscured state through the four correct discriminations. I beseech the Blessed Ones to teach the names of these absorptions.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-410">
            <prop type="folio">F.192.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-384</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་འཇམ་དཔལ་གཞོན་ནུར་གྱུར་པ་ལ་འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་བཀའ་སྩལ་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-248"/>To this the Blessed One responded,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-411">
            <prop type="folio">F.192.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-384</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་དེའི་ཕྱིར་ལེགས་པར་རབ་ཏུ་ཉོན་ལ་ཡིད་ལ་ཟུང་ཤིག་དང་བཤད་དོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Mañjuśrī, to that end, listen carefully and keep in mind what I shall say.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-412">
            <prop type="folio">F.192.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-384</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་གཞོན་ནུར་གྱུར་པས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་དེ་བཞིན་ནོ་ཞེས་གསོལ་ཏེ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Prince Mañjuśrī answered, “Blessed One, so be it.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-413">
            <prop type="folio">F.192.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-384</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱི་ལྟར་ཉན་པ་དང་། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He then listened<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="UT22084-040-005-250"/> as the Blessed One had directed.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-414">
            <prop type="folio">F.192.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-384</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་དེ་ལ་འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་བཀའ་སྩལ་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-251"/>The Blessed One then said,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-415">
            <prop type="folio">F.192.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-384</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་མཐའ་ཡས་དྲི་མེད་ཅེས་བྱ་བའི་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་ཡོད་དེ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Mañjuśrī, there is the absorption called the infinite immaculate.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-416">
            <prop type="folio">F.192.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-384</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་དེ་ཐོབ་ན་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་གཟུགས་ཐམས་ཅད་ཡོངས་སུ་དག་པར་སྟོན་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>If bodhisattvas obtain this absorption, they will reveal all forms<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="UT22084-040-005-252"/> to be pure.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-417">
            <prop type="folio">F.192.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-384</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་མགྱོགས་པར་འགྲོ་བ་ཞེས་བྱ་བའི་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་ཡོད་དེ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-253"/>“Mañjuśrī, there is the absorption called swift travel.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-418">
            <prop type="folio">F.192.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-384</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་དེ་ཐོབ་ན་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཉི་མ་དང་། ཟླ་བའི་འོད་ཟིལ་གྱིས་གནོན་པར་བྱེད་དོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>If bodhisattvas obtain this absorption, they will outshine the light of the sun and the moon.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-419">
            <prop type="folio">F.192.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-384</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་འོད་ཟེར་འབྱུང་བ་ཞེས་བྱ་བའི་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་ཡོད་དེ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-254"/>“Mañjuśrī, there is the absorption called source of light.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-420">
            <prop type="folio">F.192.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-384</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་དེ་ཐོབ་ན་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་བརྒྱ་བྱིན་དང་། ཚངས་པ་དག་གི་གཟི་བརྗིད་ཟིལ་གྱིས་གནོན་པར་བྱེད་དོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>If bodhisattvas obtain this absorption, they will overwhelm Śakra and Brahmā in their splendor.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-421">
            <prop type="folio">F.192.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-384</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་ཡུལ་སྟོན་པ་ཞེས་བྱ་བའི་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་ཡོད་དེ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-255"/>“Mañjuśrī, there is the absorption called showing the land.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-422">
            <prop type="folio">F.192.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-384</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་དེ་ཐོབ་ན་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་འཁོར་འདུས་པ་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱི་འདོད་ཆགས་དང་། ཞེ་སྡང་དང་། གཏི་མུག་ཞི་བར་བྱེད་དོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>If bodhisattvas obtain this absorption, they will pacify the desire, anger, and ignorance of all their assembled retinues.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-423">
            <prop type="folio">F.192.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-384</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་འོད་ཟེར་ཐོགས་པ་མེད་པ་ཞེས་བྱ་བའི་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་ཡོད་དེ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-256"/>“Mañjuśrī, there is the absorption called unobstructed light.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-424">
            <prop type="folio">F.192.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-384</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་དེ་ཐོབ་ན་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱི་ཞིང་ཐམས་ཅད་འོད་ཟེར་གྱིས་སྣང་བར་བྱེད་དོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>If bodhisattvas obtain this absorption, they will illuminate all buddha realms.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-425">
            <prop type="folio">F.192.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-384</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་མི་བརྗེད་པ་ཞེས་བྱ་བའི་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་ཡོད་དེ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-257"/>“Mañjuśrī, there is the absorption called forgetting no Dharma.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-426">
            <prop type="folio">F.192.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-384</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་དེ་ཐོབ་ན་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱི་ཆོས་བསྟན་པ་ཐམས་ཅད་འཛིན་ཅིང་གཞན་ལ་ཡང་སྟོན་པར་བྱེད་དོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>If they obtain this absorption, bodhisattvas will retain all the Dharma teachings taught by the Buddha and teach them to others as well.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-427">
            <prop type="folio">F.192.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-384</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་སེང་གེའི་སྒྲ་མངོན་པར་བསྒྲགས་པའི་དབྱངས་ཡིད་དུ་འོང་བ་རྗེས་སུ་སྒྲོགས་པ་ཞེས་བྱ་བའི་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་ཡོད་དེ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-258"/>“Mañjuśrī, there is the absorption called imitating the pleasant sound of the lion’s roar.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-428">
            <prop type="folio">F.193.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-385</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་དེ་ཐོབ་ན་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཚངས་པའི་འཇིག་<tei:ref folio="F.193.a"/>རྟེན་གྱི་བར་དུ་སྒྲས་མངོན་པར་གོ་བར་བྱེད་དོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>If they obtain this absorption, bodhisattvas will make themselves heard all the way up to the Brahmā realm.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-429">
            <prop type="folio">F.193.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-385</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་དགའ་བ་དང་། མགུ་བ་དང་། ཚིམ་པ་ཐམས་ཅད་ཡང་དག་པར་བསྐྱེད་པ་ཞེས་བྱ་བའི་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་ཡོད་དེ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-259"/>“Mañjuśrī, there is the absorption called truly creating all forms of joy, contentment, and satisfaction.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-430">
            <prop type="folio">F.193.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-385</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་དེ་ཐོབ་ན་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་ཅན་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱི་སེམས་དང་བསམ་པ་སྣ་ཚོགས་ཡང་དག་པར་མགུ་བར་བྱེད་དོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>If they obtain this absorption, bodhisattvas will gladden the various minds and thoughts of all sentient beings.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-431">
            <prop type="folio">F.193.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-385</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་ལྟ་བས་ཆོག་མི་ཤེས་ཤིང་མཆོག་ཏུ་དགའ་བ་དང་ལྡན་པ་ཞེས་བྱ་བའི་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་ཡོད་དེ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-260"/>“Mañjuśrī, there is the absorption called captivating to behold and greatly joyous.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-432">
            <prop type="folio">F.193.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-385</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་དེ་ཐོབ་ན་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་བལྟ་བ་དང་། མཉན་པས་ཆོག་མི་ཤེས་པར་འགྱུར་རོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>If they obtain this absorption, bodhisattvas will become captivating to behold and to listen to.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-433">
            <prop type="folio">F.193.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-385</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་ཡོན་ཏན་བསམ་གྱིས་མི་ཁྱབ་པའི་འབྱུང་གནས་ཤེས་རབ་ཀྱི་ཡུལ་རིན་པོ་ཆེའི་འབྱུང་ཁུངས་རྒྱུན་ཅིག་པ་ཉོན་མོངས་པ་མེད་པ་ཞེས་བྱ་བའི་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་ཡོད་དེ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-261"/>“Mañjuśrī, there is the absorption called source of inconceivable qualities, wellspring of the precious domain of wisdom, singular stream free of affliction.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-434">
            <prop type="folio">F.193.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-385</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་དེ་ཐོབ་ན་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་རྫུ་འཕྲུལ་བསྟན་པ་ཐམས་ཅད་སྟོན་པ་དང་། སེམས་ཅན་རྣམས་འདུལ་བར་བྱེད་དོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>If they obtain this absorption, bodhisattvas will be able to display all miracles and subdue all beings.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-435">
            <prop type="folio">F.193.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-385</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་སྒྲ་སྐད་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱི་བརྡ་ཞེས་བྱ་བའི་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་ཡོད་དེ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-262"/>“Mañjuśrī, there is the absorption called the symbol of all languages.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-436">
            <prop type="folio">F.193.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-385</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་དེ་ཐོབ་ན་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སྒྲ་སྐད་དང་བརྗོད་པ་དང་། བརྡ་ཐམས་ཅད་རྟོགས་ཤིང་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>If they obtain this absorption, bodhisattvas will understand all languages, expressions, and signs.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-437">
            <prop type="folio">F.193.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-385</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡི་གེ་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱིས་ཡི་གེ་གཅིག་སྟོན་པ་དང་། ཡི་གེ་གཅིག་གིས་ཡི་གེ་ཐམས་ཅད་སྟོན་པར་བྱེད་དོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They will reveal a single letter through all letters, and all letters through a single letter.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-438">
            <prop type="folio">F.193.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-385</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་ལས་ཀྱི་རྣམ་པར་སྨིན་པ་ལས་བྱུང་བའི་བསོད་ནམས་དང་། དགེ་བའི་རྩ་བ་ཐམས་ཅད་བསགས་ཤིང་སྟོན་པར་བྱེད་པ་ཞེས་བྱ་བའི་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་ཡོད་དེ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-263"/>“Mañjuśrī, there is the absorption called accumulation and demonstration of all merit and roots of virtue arisen from ripened action.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-439">
            <prop type="folio">F.193.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-385</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་དེ་ཐོབ་ན་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཅང་མི་སྨྲ་བར་སྙོམས་པར་ཞུགས་ཏེ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>If they obtain this absorption, bodhisattvas will remain in equipoise without saying anything.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-440">
            <prop type="folio">F.193.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-385</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡི་གེ་གཅིག་ཙམ་ཡང་མི་བརྗོད་པར་སེམས་ཅན་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱིས་སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱི་སྒྲ་དང་། ཆོས་ཀྱི་སྒྲ་དང་། དགེ་འདུན་གྱི་སྒྲ་དང་། ཉན་ཐོས་ཀྱི་སྒྲ་དང་། རང་སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱི་སྒྲ་དང་། བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའི་སྒྲ་དང་། ཕ་རོལ་དུ་ཕྱིན་པའི་སྒྲ་ཐོས་པར་བྱེད་དོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Without uttering a single sound, they will cause all beings to hear the words Buddha, Dharma, Saṅgha, hearers, solitary buddhas, bodhisattvas, and perfections.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-441">
            <prop type="folio">F.193.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-385</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་གཟུངས་ཐམས་ཅད་ལས་མངོན་པར་འཕགས་པའི་རྒྱལ་པོ་ཞེས་བྱ་བའི་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་ཡོད་དེ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-264"/>“Mañjuśrī, there is the absorption called the exalted king of all dhāraṇīs.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-442">
            <prop type="folio">F.193.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-385</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་དེ་ཐོབ་ན་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་གཟུངས་མཐའ་ཡས་པ་བསྒྲུབ་པ་ལ་འཇུག་པ་ཁོང་དུ་ཆུད་པར་འགྱུར་རོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>If they obtain this absorption, bodhisattvas will know how to engage in the accomplishment of infinite dhāraṇīs.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-443">
            <prop type="folio">F.193.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-386</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་ལ་སྤོབས་པ་བཀོད་པ་ཞེས་བྱ་བའི་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་<tei:ref folio="F.193.b"/>ཡོད་དེ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-265"/>“Mañjuśrī, there is the absorption called the array of confident eloquence in all Dharma teachings. </seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-444">
            <prop type="folio">F.193.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-386</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་དེ་ཐོབ་ན་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཡི་གེ་ཐམས་ཅད་ལ་སྤོབས་ཤིང་སྒྲ་སྐད་ཐམས་ཅད་དང་། དབྱངས་ཐམས་ཅད་དང་། བརྗོད་པ་ཐམས་ཅད་ལ་ཡང་སྤོབས་པར་འགྱུར་རོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>If they obtain this absorption, bodhisattvas will become confidently eloquent in all utterances, languages, sounds, and expressions.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-445">
            <prop type="folio">F.193.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-386</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ལ་འཇམ་དཔལ་གཞོན་ནུར་གྱུར་པས་འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་གསོལ་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-266"/>Then Prince Mañjuśrī said to the Blessed One,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-446">
            <prop type="folio">F.193.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-386</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་བདག་ཆོས་ཀྱི་རྣམ་གྲངས་འདིའི་ཡོན་ཏན་བརྗོད་པའི་ཁྱད་པར་ལ་སྤོབས་ལགས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Blessed One, I have an insight to share regarding the unique description of qualities expressed in this Dharma teaching.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-447">
            <prop type="folio">F.193.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-386</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་བཀའ་སྩལ་པ། འཇམ་དཔལ་ཁྱོད་སྤོབས་པར་བྱོས་ཤིག །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The Blessed One responded, “Mañjuśrī, please share your insight.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-448">
            <prop type="folio">F.193.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-386</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་གྱིས་གསོལ་པ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-268"/>Mañjuśrī then said,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-449">
            <prop type="folio">F.193.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-386</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་གང་དག་ནེམ་ནུར་མ་མཆིས་པ་དང་། །ཐེ་ཚོམ་མ་མཆིས་པའི་སེམས་ཀྱིས་ཆོས་ཀྱི་རྣམ་གྲངས་འདི་སྟོན་པ་དང་། འཆང་བ་དང་། ཀློག་པ་དང་། ཀུན་ཆུབ་པར་བགྱིད་པ་དང་། གཞན་དག་ལ་ཡང་རྒྱ་ཆེར་ཡང་དག་པར་རབ་ཏུ་སྟོན་པར་བགྱིད་པ་དེ་ཚེ་འདི་ཉིད་ལ་གདོན་མི་འཚལ་བར་སྤོབས་པ་འཐོབ་པར་རེ་བར་བགྱི་སྟེ</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Blessed One, I wish that those bodhisattvas who are free of doubt and hesitation and who teach, hold, recite, integrate, and authentically and extensively expound this Dharma teaching to others, undoubtedly achieve confident eloquence in this very lifetime.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-450">
            <prop type="folio">F.193.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-386</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྤོབས་པ་མྱུར་བ་དང་། སྤོབས་པ་རྒྱ་ཆེ་བ་དང་། ཟབ་མོ་ལ་སྤོབས་པ་དང་། མི་བརྗེད་པའི་སྤོབས་པ་དང་། སྤོབས་པ་སྣ་ཚོགས་ཐོབ་པར་རེ་བར་བགྱིའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>I wish that they obtain swift confidence, vast confidence, confidence in the profound, unforgetting confidence, and variegated confidence.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-451">
            <prop type="folio">F.193.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-386</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནི་སེམས་ཅན་ཐམས་ཅད་ལ་ཞེ་འགྲས་པ་མ་མཆིས་པའི་སེམས་སུ་གྱུར་པར་རེ་བར་བགྱིའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>I wish that their minds become free from all animosity toward any sentient being.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-452">
            <prop type="folio">F.193.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-386</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ཅིའི་སླད་དུ་ཞེ་ན། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Why do I make that wish?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-453">
            <prop type="folio">F.193.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-386</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་ཇི་ཙམ་དུ་ཆོས་ཀྱི་རྣམ་གྲངས་འདི་བསྒྲུབ་པ་དེ་ནི་སྤྱོད་པ་འདི་ཉིད་དང་རྗེས་སུ་འབྲེལ་བ་ལགས་པའི་སླད་དུའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>It is because the accomplishment of this Dharma teaching depends on precisely this conduct.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-454">
            <prop type="folio">F.193.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-386</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་འཇམ་དཔལ་གཞོན་ནུར་གྱུར་པ་ལ་ལེགས་སོ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་བྱིན་ཏེ</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-269"/>The Blessed One then approved of Prince Mañjuśrī, saying</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-455">
            <prop type="folio">F.193.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-386</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་ལེགས་སོ་ལེགས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Mañjuśrī, excellent, excellent.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-456">
            <prop type="folio">F.193.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-386</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཁྱོད་ཀྱིས་ཚིག་འདི་ལེགས་པར་སྨྲས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Your words are well spoken.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-457">
            <prop type="folio">F.193.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-386</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་འདི་ལྟ་སྟེ། དཔེར་ན་སྦྱིན་པ་ནི་ལོངས་སྤྱོད་ཆེན་པོ་འཐོབ་པར་སླུ་བ་མེད་དོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Mañjuśrī, for instance, it is incontrovertible that generosity yields great wealth.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-458">
            <prop type="folio">F.193.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-386</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཚུལ་ཁྲིམས་ནི་མཐོ་རིས་སུ་སྐྱེ་བར་སླུ་བ་མེད་དོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>It is incontrovertible that discipline leads to rebirth in the upper realms.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-459">
            <prop type="folio">F.193.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-386</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཐོས་པ་ནི་ཤེས་རབ་ཆེན་པོར་འགྱུར་བར་སླུ་བ་མེད་དོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>It is incontrovertible that study leads to great insight.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-460">
            <prop type="folio">F.193.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-386</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྒོམ་པ་ནི་འབྲལ་བར་འགྱུར་བར་སླུ་བ་མེད་དོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>It is incontrovertible that familiarization leads to separation.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-461">
            <prop type="folio">F.193.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-386</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་དེ་བཞིན་དུ་ཆོས་ཀྱི་རྣམ་གྲངས་འདི་ཡང་ཚེ་འདི་ཉིད་ལ་སྤོབས་པ་སྐྱེ་བར་སླུ་བ་མེད་དོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Likewise, Mañjuśrī, it is incontrovertible that this Dharma teaching will bring forth confident eloquence in this very lifetime.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-462">
            <prop type="folio">F.193.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-386</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་འདི་ལྟ་སྟེ། དཔེར་ན་ཉི་མ་ཤར་བས་ནི་མུན་པ་མུན་ནག་ཐམས་ཅད་སེལ་བར་བྱེད་དོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-270"/>“Mañjuśrī, the rising sun dispels all the thick black of darkness.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-463">
            <prop type="folio">F.194.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-387</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་དེ་བཞིན་དུ་ཆོས་ཀྱི་རྣམ་གྲངས་འདི་ཡང་བསྟན་མ་ཐག་ཏུ་སྤོབས་པ་སྐྱེ་བར་རེ་བར་<tei:ref folio="F.194.a"/>བྱའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Mañjuśrī, likewise, you should wish for confident eloquence to arise as soon as this Dharma teaching is delivered. </seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-464">
            <prop type="folio">F.194.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-387</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་འདི་ལྟ་སྟེ། དཔེར་ན་བྱང་ཆུབ་ཀྱི་སྙིང་པོ་ལ་འདུག་པའི་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་ནི་ངེས་པར་བླ་ན་མེད་པ་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་བྱང་ཆུབ་མངོན་པར་རྫོགས་པར་འཚང་རྒྱ་བར་འགྱུར་རོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-271"/>“Mañjuśrī, for instance, bodhisattvas who abide on the seat of awakening are certain to fully awaken to unsurpassed and perfect buddhahood.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-465">
            <prop type="folio">F.194.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-387</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་དེ་བཞིན་དུ་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོ་གང་ཆོས་ཀྱི་རྣམ་གྲངས་འདི་རབ་ཏུ་འདོན་པ་དེ་ཡང་ཐེ་ཚོམ་མེད་པར་ངེས་པར་ཚེ་འདི་ཉིད་ལ་སྤོབས་པ་ཐོབ་པར་འགྱུར་རོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Likewise, Mañjuśrī, bodhisattva great beings who recite this Dharma teaching are certain to achieve confident eloquence in this very lifetime.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-466">
            <prop type="folio">F.194.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-387</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་དེ་ལྟ་བས་ན་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོ་ཚེ་འདི་ཉིད་ལ་སྤོབས་པ་ཐོབ་པར་འདོད་པས་ནེམ་ནུར་མེད་པ་དང་། ཐེ་ཚོམ་མེད་པའི་སེམས་ཀྱིས་ཆོས་ཀྱི་རྣམ་གྲངས་འདི་གཟུང་བར་བྱ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-272"/>“Mañjuśrī, therefore, bodhisattva great beings who wish to achieve confident eloquence in this very lifetime should without doubt or hesitation obtain this Dharma teaching,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-467">
            <prop type="folio">F.194.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-387</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅང་བར་བྱ། ཁ་ཏོན་དུ་བྱ། བཀླག་པར་བྱ། ཀུན་ཆུབ་པར་བྱ། གཞན་དག་ལ་ཡང་རྒྱ་ཆེར་ཡང་དག་པར་རབ་ཏུ་བསྟན་པར་བྱའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>hold it, recite it, read it, understand it, and expound it extensively and correctly to others.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-468">
            <prop type="folio">F.194.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-387</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ལ་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོ་དྲི་མ་མེད་པའི་སྙིང་པོས་འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་གསོལ་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-273"/>Then the bodhisattva great being Amalagarbha said to the Blessed One,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-469">
            <prop type="folio">F.194.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-387</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་བདག་གིས་ཀྱང་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཡོངས་སུ་མྱ་ངན་ལས་འདས་ནས་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་གང་ནེམ་ནུར་མ་མཆིས་པ་དང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Blessed One, after you pass into parinirvāṇa, I too will work to ensure that those bodhisattvas who have no doubt or</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-470">
            <prop type="folio">F.194.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-387</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཐེ་ཚོམ་མ་མཆིས་པའི་སེམས་ཀྱིས་ཆོས་ཀྱི་རྣམ་གྲངས་འདི་འཛིན་པ་དང་། འཆང་བ་དང་། ཀློག་པ་དང་། ཀུན་ཆུབ་པར་བགྱིད་པ་དང་། གཞན་དག་ལ་ཡང་རྒྱ་ཆེར་ཡང་དག་པར་རབ་ཏུ་སྟོན་པར་འགྱུར་བ་དེ་ལ་སྤོབས་པ་ཉེ་བར་བསྒྲུབ་པར་བགྱིའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>hesitation and who retain, hold, read, understand, and correctly and extensively expound this Dharma teaching to others achieve confident eloquence in it.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-471">
            <prop type="folio">F.194.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-387</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་བདུད་སྡིག་ཅན་ངུ་ཞིང་སྨྲེ་སྔགས་འདོན་བཞིན་དུ་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ག་ལ་བ་དེར་སོང་སྟེ་ཕྱིན་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ལ་འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་གསོལ་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-274"/>At this point, the evil Māra came weeping and wailing before the Blessed One and said,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-472">
            <prop type="folio">F.194.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-387</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་དགྲ་བཅོམ་པ་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་སངས་རྒྱས་ནི་ཐུགས་རྗེ་དང་ལྡན་ཞིང་སེམས་ཅན་སྡུག་བསྔལ་བ་རྣམས་ལ་བདེ་བ་རབ་ཏུ་སྩོལ་བ་ལགས་ན། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Blessed One, if the thus-gone, worthy, perfect buddha is compassionate and bestows<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="UT22084-040-005-275"/> happiness to suffering beings,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-473">
            <prop type="folio">F.194.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-387</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་བདག་གི་ཡིད་མི་བདེ་བ་དེ་ལེགས་པར་བསལ་བའི་སླད་དུ་ཆོས་ཀྱི་རྣམ་གྲངས་འདི་སླར་ཞིང་བྱིན་གྱིས་མི་བརླབ་ཏུ་གསོལ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>then I beseech the Blessed One not to further bless this Dharma teaching, so as to dispel my own mental anguish.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-474">
            <prop type="folio">F.194.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-387</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་གང་གི་ཚེ་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་བྱང་ཆུབ་ཀྱི་སྙིང་པོ་ལ་བཞུགས་པ་དང་། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Blessed One, when the Blessed One was seated on the seat of awakening, and</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-475">
            <prop type="folio">F.194.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-388</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ད་ལྟར་ཆོས་ཀྱི་རྣམ་གྲངས་འདི་བསྟན་པའི་ཚེ་<tei:ref folio="F.194.b"/>བདག་འདིར་ཤིན་དུ་ཆེར་སྡུག་བསྔལ་ཞིང་ཡིད་མི་བདེ་བ་དང་། མྱ་ངན་གྱི་ཟུག་རྔུས་གཟིར་བར་གྱུར་པ་ལགས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>now as he delivered this Dharma teaching, I was tormented by intense suffering, anguish, and sorrow.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-476">
            <prop type="folio">F.194.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-388</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཐ་ན་ཆོས་ཀྱི་རྣམ་གྲངས་འདི་སེམས་ཅན་གང་དག་གི་རྣ་ལམ་དུ་གྲག་པར་གྱུར་པ་དེ་དག་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱང་བླ་ན་མེད་པ་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་བྱང་ཆུབ་ལས་སླར་མི་ལྡོག་པར་འགྱུར་ལགས་ན། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Blessed One, if any sentient being who so much as hears this Dharma teaching will proceed irreversibly to unsurpassed and perfect awakening,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-477">
            <prop type="folio">F.194.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-388</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་དག་གིས་ཐོས་ནས་འཛིན་པ་དང་། འཆང་བ་དང་། ཀློག་པ་དང་། ཀུན་ཆུབ་པར་བགྱིད་པ་དང་། གཞན་དག་ལ་ཡང་རྒྱ་ཆེར་ཡང་དག་པར་རབ་ཏུ་སྟོན་པར་བགྱིད་པ་དེ་ཐམས་ཅད་བླ་ན་མེད་པ་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་བྱང་ཆུབ་ལས་སླར་མི་ལྡོག་པར་འགྱུར་བ་ལྟ་སྨོས་ཀྱང་ཅི་འཚལ་ཏེ</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>then no need to mention that those who not only hear but retain, hold, read, understand, and expound this Dharma teaching extensively and correctly to others will likewise proceed irreversibly to unsurpassed and perfect awakening.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-478">
            <prop type="folio">F.194.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-388</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སེམས་ཅན་དེ་དག་ཐམས་ཅད་ནི་ཡོངས་སུ་མྱ་ངན་ལས་འདའ་བར་འགྱུར་ལགས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>All these beings will fully pass into nirvāṇa.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-479">
            <prop type="folio">F.194.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-388</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་དེའི་སླད་དུ་བདག་གི་བདུད་ཀྱི་གནས་སྟོངས་པར་འགྱུར་བ་ལགས་ན་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Therefore, Blessed One, my māra realm will become empty.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-480">
            <prop type="folio">F.194.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-388</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་དགྲ་བཅོམ་པ་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་སངས་རྒྱས་ནི་ཐུགས་རྗེ་དང་ལྡན་ཞིང་སྡུག་བསྔལ་བ་རྣམས་ལ་བདེ་བ་སྩོལ་བ་ལགས་ན། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>If the thus-gone, worthy, perfect buddha is compassionate and bestows happiness onto those who suffer,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-481">
            <prop type="folio">F.194.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-388</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་བདག་དབུགས་དབྱུང་དུ་གསོལ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>then I beseech the Blessed One to relieve my suffering.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-482">
            <prop type="folio">F.194.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-388</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བདེ་བར་གཤེགས་པ་བདག་དབུགས་དབྱུང་དུ་གསོལ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>I beseech the Blissful One to relieve my suffering.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-483">
            <prop type="folio">F.194.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-388</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་བདུད་སྡིག་ཅན་ལ་འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་བཀའ་སྩལ་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-276"/>Then the Blessed One responded to the evil Māra,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-484">
            <prop type="folio">F.194.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-388</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྡིག་ཅན་མ་འཇིགས་ཤིག །སེམས་ཅན་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱང་ཡོངས་སུ་མྱ་ངན་ལས་འདའ་བར་མི་འགྱུར་ལ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Evil one, do not fear. Not all sentient beings will fully pass into nirvāṇa.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-485">
            <prop type="folio">F.194.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-388</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྡིག་ཅན་ང་ཡང་ཆོས་ཀྱི་རྣམ་གྲངས་འདི་ལ་བྱིན་གྱིས་རློབ་པར་མི་བྱེད་ཀྱིས་སྡིག་ཅན་མ་འཇིགས་ཤིག །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Evil one, nor will I bless this Dharma teaching, so do not fear.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-486">
            <prop type="folio">F.194.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-388</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་དབུགས་དབྱུང་བ་མཛད་པས་བདུད་སྡིག་ཅན་ཚིམ་ཞིང་མགུ་ལ་ཡི་རངས་ཏེ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>When the Blessed One had consoled him, the evil Māra was satisfied, pleased, and happy.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-487">
            <prop type="folio">F.194.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-388</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རབ་ཏུ་དགའ་ཞིང་། དགའ་བ་དང་། ཡིད་བདེ་བ་སྐྱེས་ནས་དེ་ཉིད་དུ་མི་སྣང་བར་གྱུར་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He became joyful, delighted, and elated, and instantly disappeared.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-488">
            <prop type="folio">F.194.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-388</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ལ་འཇམ་དཔལ་གཞོན་ནུར་གྱུར་པས་འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་གསོལ་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-278"/>Then Prince Mañjuśrī spoke to the Blessed One,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-489">
            <prop type="folio">F.194.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-388</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཅི་ལས་དགོངས་ཏེ་དེ་སྐད་དུ་ང་ཆོས་ཀྱི་རྣམ་གྲངས་འདི་ལ་བྱིན་གྱིས་རློབ་པར་མི་བྱེད་དོ་ཞེས་བདུད་སྡིག་ཅན་ལ་བཀའ་སྩལ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Blessed One, with what intention did you tell the evil Māra that you would not bless this Dharma teaching?”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-490">
            <prop type="folio">F.194.b</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-388</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་བཀའ་སྩལ་པ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The Blessed One responded,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-491">
            <prop type="folio">F.195.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-389</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་ནི་བྱིན་གྱི་རླབས་མེད་པས་བྱིན་<tei:ref folio="F.195.a"/>གྱིས་བརླབས་པ་ཡིན་ཏེ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Mañjuśrī, since no phenomenon is blessed, all phenomena are blessed.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-492">
            <prop type="folio">F.195.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-389</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཆོས་ཀྱི་རྣམ་གྲངས་འདི་ཡང་བྱིན་གྱི་རླབས་མེད་པས་བྱིན་གྱིས་བརླབས་པ་ཡིན་པས། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Since this Dharma teaching is not blessed either, it is blessed.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-493">
            <prop type="folio">F.195.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-389</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་དེའི་ཕྱིར་ངས་བདུད་སྡིག་ཅན་ལ་འདི་སྐད་དུ་ང་ཆོས་ཀྱི་རྣམ་གྲངས་འདི་ལ་བྱིན་གྱིས་རློབ་པར་མི་བྱེད་དོ་ཞེས་སྨྲས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Mañjuśrī, that is why I told the evil Māra that I would not bless this Dharma teaching.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-494">
            <prop type="folio">F.195.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-389</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་བདེན་པ་དང་བདེན་པའི་ཚིག་གང་གིས་ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་བྱིན་གྱི་རླབས་མེད་པས་བྱིན་གྱིས་བརླབས་པ་དང་། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Mañjuśrī, by the power of truth and the truth of these words, since no phenomenon is blessed, they are all blessed.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-495">
            <prop type="folio">F.195.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-389</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཐ་དད་དུ་དབྱེར་མེད་པ་དང་། བརྗོད་དུ་མེད་པ་དང་། མཚན་ཉིད་མེད་པ་དང་། བསྙད་དུ་མེད་པ་དང་། སྨྲར་མེད་པ་དང་། གཉིས་སུ་མེད་པ་དང་། གཉིས་དང་བྲལ་བ་དང་། ཡང་དག་པའི་མཐའ་དང་མཉམ་པ་དང་། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They are beyond distinction, inexpressible, without characteristics, inexplicable, unutterable, nondual, without duality, and identical with the limit of reality.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-496">
            <prop type="folio">F.195.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-389</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་བཞིན་ཉིད་དུ་ཞུགས་པ་དང་། ཆོས་ཀྱི་དབྱིངས་ཀྱི་མཚན་ཉིད་ཡིན་པའི་བདེན་པ་དང་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They are steeped in suchness and are of the nature of the realm of phenomena.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-497">
            <prop type="folio">F.195.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-389</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བདེན་པའི་ཚིག་དེས་ཆོས་ཀྱི་རྣམ་གྲངས་འདི་འཛམ་བུའི་གླིང་ན་རབ་ཏུ་སྤྱོད་པར་གྱུར་ཅིག །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>By the power of this truth and these true words, may this Dharma teaching spread throughout the world!”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-498">
            <prop type="folio">F.195.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-389</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་བདེན་པའི་བྱིན་གྱིས་བརླབས་དེ་མཛད་ནས་ཚེ་དང་ལྡན་པ་ཀུན་དགའ་བོ་ལ་བཀའ་སྩལ་པ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-280"/>Then, having performed this truth blessing, the Blessed One addressed the venerable Ānanda,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-499">
            <prop type="folio">F.195.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-389</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཀུན་དགའ་བོ་ཆོས་ཀྱི་ཕུང་པོ་བརྒྱད་ཁྲི་བཞི་སྟོང་གང་ཡིན་པ་དང་། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Ānanda, this Dharma teaching and all the eighty-four thousand sections of Dharma are the same,<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="UT22084-040-005-281"/> so</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-500">
            <prop type="folio">F.195.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-389</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཆོས་ཀྱི་རྣམ་གྲངས་འདི་གང་ཡིན་པ་དེ་དག་ནི་མཉམ་པའི་ཕྱིར་ཁྱོད་ཀྱིས་ཀུན་ནས་སྒོའི་ཆོས་ཀྱི་རྣམ་གྲངས་འདི་ཟུང་ཤིག །ཆོངས་ཤིག །ལྷོགས་ཤིག །ཀུན་ཆུབ་པར་གྱིས་ཤིག །གཞན་དག་ལ་ཡང་རྒྱ་ཆེར་ཡང་དག་པར་རབ་ཏུ་སྟོན་ཅིག །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>you must therefore retain this teaching of The Universal Gateway. You must hold it, read it, master it, and teach it extensively and authentically to others.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-501">
            <prop type="folio">F.195.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-389</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ཅིའི་ཕྱིར་ཞེ་ན། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Why is that?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-502">
            <prop type="folio">F.195.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-389</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཀུན་དགའ་བོ་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་ནི་ཀུན་ནས་སྒོའི་ཆོས་ཀྱི་དབྱིངས་འདི་ལེགས་པར་ཐུགས་སུ་ཆུད་ནས་སེམས་ཅན་རྣམས་ལ་ཆོས་ཀྱི་ཕུང་པོ་བརྒྱད་ཁྲི་བཞི་སྟོང་སྟོན་པར་མཛད་པའི་ཕྱིར་རོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Ānanda, it is because the thus-gone ones teach the eighty-four thousand sections of the Dharma to beings once they have understood this realm of Dharma<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="UT22084-040-005-282"/> of The Universal Gateway.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-503">
            <prop type="folio">F.195.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-389</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཀུན་དགའ་བོ་དེ་ལྟ་བས་ན་ཆོས་ཀྱི་རྣམ་གྲངས་འདི་ལེགས་པར་བསྲུང་བ་དང་། ལེགས་པར་གཟུང་བ་དང་། ལེགས་པར་ཀུན་ཆུབ་པར་གྱིས་ཤིག །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Ānanda, for that reason you must guard, retain, and master this Dharma teaching.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-504">
            <prop type="folio">F.195.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-389</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་དེ་སྐད་ཅེས་བཀའ་སྩལ་ནས</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-283"/>When the Blessed One had said this,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-505">
            <prop type="folio">F.195.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-389</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོ་དྲི་མ་མེད་པའི་སྙིང་པོ་དང་། འཇམ་དཔལ་གཞོན་ནུར་གྱུར་པ་དང་། ཚེ་དང་ལྡན་པ་ཀུན་དགའ་བོ་དང་། ལྷ་དང་། མི་དང་། ལྷ་མ་ཡིན་དང་། དྲི་ཟར་བཅས་པའི་འཇིག་རྟེན་ཡི་རངས་ཏེ། བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་གསུངས་པ་ལ་མངོན་པར་བསྟོད་དོ།། །།</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>the bodhisattva great being Amalagarbha, Prince Mañjuśrī, Venerable Ānanda, and the whole world with its gods, humans, asuras, and gandharvas rejoiced and praised the Blessed One’s words.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-506">
            <prop type="folio">F.195.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-389</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཕགས་པ་དཀོན་མཆོག་བརྩེགས་པ་ཆེན་པོའི་ཆོས་ཀྱི་རྣམ་གྲངས་ལེའུ་སྟོང་ཕྲག་བརྒྱ་པ་ལས། ཀུན་ནས་སྒོའི་ལེའུ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་སྟེ་ལེའུ་བཅུ་པ་རྫོགས་སོ།། །།</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-284"/>This completes The Universal Gateway, the tenth chapter within the one-hundred-thousand-chapter Dharma discourse of The Noble Great Heap of Jewels.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-040-005-TU-507">
            <prop type="folio">F.195.a</prop>
            <prop type="location-id">UT22084-040-005-389</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྒྱ་གར་གྱི་མཁན་པོ་ཛི་ན་མི་ཏྲ་དང་། སུ་རེན་དྲ་བོ་དྷི་དང་། ཞུ་ཆེན་གྱི་ལོ་ཙྪ་བ་བན་དེ་ཡེ་ཤེས་སྡེས་བསྒྱུར་ཅིང་ཞུས་ཏེ་གཏན་ལ་ཕབ་པ།། །།</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-040-005-285"/>It was translated, edited, and finalized by the Indian preceptors Jinamitra and Surendrabodhi along with the chief editor-translator Bandé Yeshé Dé.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
</body>
</tmx>