<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tmx xmlns="http://www.lisa.org/tmx14" xmlns:eft="http://read.84000.co/ns/1.0" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<header creationtool="linguae-dharmae/84000" datatype="PlainText" segtype="block" adminlang="en-us" srclang="bo" o-tmf="TEI" eft:text-id="UT22084-091-066" eft:text-version="v-1.0.4-2023"/>
<body>
<tu id="UT22084-091-066-TU-1">
    <prop type="location-id">translation</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>
                    <tei:ref folio="F.202.a"/>༄༅༅། །འཕགས་པ་ནག་པོ་ཆེན་པོའི་གཟུངས་རིམས་ནད་ཐམས་ཅད་ལས་ཐར་བར་བྱེད་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The Noble Mahākāla Dhāraṇī: A Cure for All Diseases and Illnesses</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-091-066-TU-2">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-091-066-59</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སངས་རྒྱས་དང་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཐམས་ཅད་ལ་ཕྱག་འཚལ་ལོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-091-066-59"/>Homage to all buddhas and bodhisattvas.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-091-066-TU-3">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-091-066-59</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ནག་པོ་ཆེན་པོ་སྐྱེས་བུ་ནག་སེར་མཆེ་བ་རྣོན་པོ། མཆེ་བ་ཆེན་པོ་རིམས་ནད་ཐམས་ཅད་ལས་རྣམ་པར་ཐར་བར་བྱེད་པ་བརྗོད་པར་བྱ་སྟེ། ཕྱོགས་གང་དང་གང་དུ་བལྟས་པ་དེར་བདག་ལ་རིམས་ནད་མེད་པར་གྱུར་ཅིག །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>I will recite the dhāraṇī of Mahākāla, the great black being with sharp yellow fangs, the great fanged one who cures all diseases and illnesses. Wherever I direct my gaze, may I be free of disease and illness.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-091-066-TU-4">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-091-066-65</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཏདྱ་ཐཱ། ཧ་ན་ཧ་ན་རཱ་ཛ་དྷཱུ་ཏེ་ན། ད་ཧ་ད་ཧ་རཱ་ཛ་དྷཱུ་ཏེ་ན། པ་ཙ་པ་ཙ་པ་རཱ་ཛ་དྷཱུ་ཏེ་ན། བ་ཧུ་ཤྲ་བེ། བ་ཧུ་པ་རི་པཱ་རི། བ་ཧུ་པ་རི་ཤོ་དྷ་ནེ། ཨི་མྃ་ཛཱ་ར་ཙཎྜ་ལྃ། ཧ་ན་ཧ་ན།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-091-066-65"/>tadyathā | hana hana rājadhūtena daha daha rājadhūtena paca paca rājadhūtena bahuśrave bahuparipāri bahupariśodhane imaṃ jāracaṇḍalaṃ hana hana</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-091-066-TU-5">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-091-066-66</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཨོྃ་སུཾ་བྷ་ནི་སུཾ་བྷ་ཤི་ར་མུཉྩ། ཙཀྵུ་མུཉྩ། ཤྲོ་ཏྲ་མུཉྩ། གྷྲཱ་ཎ་མུཉྩ། ཛི་ཧྭཱ་མུཉྩ། ཀཎ་ཋ་མུཉྩ། གྲཱི་བ་མུཉྩ། པྲེཥྛ་མུཉྩ། ཀཱ་ཊི་ཀཱ་མུཉྩ། ཀུ་ཀྵ་མུཉྩ། ཨཱུ་རུ་མུཉྩ། ཛ་ནཽ་མུཉྩ། ཧསྟ་མུཉྩ། པཱ་དཽ་མུཉྩ། ཨཾ་གུ་ལི་མུཉྩ། ཨྃ་ག་པྲ་ཏྱྃ་ག་མུཉྩ། ཨ་པ་ས་ར་ཨ་ཎྱ་སཱི་མུཉྩ། གཙྪཿ། ཛྭ་ར་མུ་ཏོ་སི་བདག་ལ་སྭཱ་ཧཱ། ཨོཾ་ཛྭ་ལ་མཱ་ཨཾ་གུ་ལི་ཧཱུྃ། སརྦ་ཛྭ་རཱ་ནན་ཕཊ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-091-066-66"/>oṃ suṃbha nisuṃbha śira muñca cakṣu muñca śrotra muñca ghrāṇa muñca jihvā muñca kaṇṭha muñca grīva muñca pṛṣtha muñca kaṭikā muñca kukṣa muñca ūru muñca jānu muñca hasta muñca pādau muñca aṅguli muñca aṅgapratyaṅga muñca apasara anyasmiñca gaccha jvara mukto ’si me svāhā <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-091-066-69"/>oṃ jvala mā aṅguli hūṁ sarvajvarānan phaṭ |</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-091-066-TU-6">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-091-066-70</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཕགས་པ་ནག་པོ་ཆེན་པོའི་གཟུངས་རིམས་ནད་ཐམས་ཅད་ལས་རྣམ་པར་ཐར་བར་བྱེད་པ་རྫོགས་སོ།། །།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-091-066-70"/>This concludes “The Noble Mahākāla Dhāraṇī: A Cure for All Diseases and Illnesses.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-091-066-TU-7">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-091-066-71</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།​།རྒྱ་གར་གྱི་མཁན་པོ་པྲཛྙཱ་བརྨ་དང་། ཞུ་ཆེན་གྱི་ལོ་ཙྪ་བ་བནྡེ་ཡེ་ཤེས་སྡེས་བསྒྱུར་ཅིང་ཞུས་ཏེ་གཏན་ལ་ཕབ་པ།​། །​།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-091-066-71"/>This text was translated, edited, and finalized by the Indian preceptor Prajñāvarman and the great editor-translator Bande Yeshé Dé.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>

</body>
</tmx>