<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tmx xmlns="http://www.lisa.org/tmx14" xmlns:eft="http://read.84000.co/ns/1.0" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<header creationtool="monlam-ai/84000" datatype="PlainText" segtype="block" adminlang="en-us" srclang="bo" o-tmf="TEI" eft:text-id="UT22084-043-009" eft:text-version="v-1.0.10-2023"/>
<body>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-1">
    <prop type="location-id">translation</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>
                    <tei:ref folio="F.194.a"/>༄༅༅། །འཕགས་པ་དཀོན་མཆོག་བརྩེགས་པ་ཆེན་པོའི་ཆོས་ཀྱི་རྣམ་གྲངས་ལེའུ་སྟོང་ཕྲག་བརྒྱ་པ་ལས་ལེའུ་ཉི་ཤུ་རྩ་བརྒྱད་པ་སྟེ་ཁྱིམ་བདག་དཔས་བྱིན་གྱིས་ཞུས་པ། བམ་པོ་གཅིག་པ། རྒྱ་གར་སྐད་དུ། ཨཱརྱ་བཱི་ར་དཏྟ་གྲྀ་ཧ་པ་ཏི་པ་རི་པྲྀཙྪཱ་ནཱ་མ་མ་ཧཱ་ཡཱ་ན་སཱུ་ཏྲ། བོད་སྐད་དུ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg/>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-2">
    <prop type="location-id">translation</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཕགས་པ་ཁྱིམ་བདག་དཔས་བྱིན་གྱིས་ཞུས་པ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་ཐེག་པ་ཆེན་པོའི་མདོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The Noble Great Vehicle Sūtra The Questions of the Householder Vīradatta</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-3">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-25</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སངས་རྒྱས་དང་། བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཐམས་ཅད་ལ་ཕྱག་འཚལ་ལོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-009-25"/>Homage to all the buddhas and bodhisattvas!</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-4">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-27</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།འདི་སྐད་བདག་གིས་ཐོས་པ་དུས་གཅིག་ན།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-009-27"/>Thus did I hear at one time.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-5">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-27</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་མཉན་ཡོད་ན་རྒྱལ་བུ་རྒྱལ་བྱེད་ཀྱི་ཚལ་མགོན་མེད་ཟས་སྦྱིན་གྱི་ཀུན་དགའ་ར་བ་ན། དགེ་སློང་སྟོང་ཉིས་བརྒྱ་ལྔ་བཅུའི་དགེ་སློང་གི་དགེ་འདུན་ཆེན་པོ་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱང་དགྲ་བཅོམ་པ། ཟག་པ་ཟད་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The Blessed One was staying in Prince Jeta’s Grove, Anāthapiṇḍada’s pleasure garden, in Śrāvastī together with a great monastic assembly of 1,250 monks. All were arhats whose contaminants had been exhausted.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-6">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-27</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཉོན་མོངས་པ་མེད་པ། དབང་དང་ལྡན་པར་གྱུར་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They were free from defilements and had attained mastery.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-7">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-27</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སེམས་ཤིན་ཏུ་རྣམ་པར་གྲོལ་བ། ཤེས་རབ་ཤིན་ཏུ་རྣམ་པར་གྲོལ་བ། ཅང་ཤེས་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Their minds were completely free, and their insight perfectly liberated.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-8">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-27</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གླང་པོ་ཆེན་པོ། བྱ་བ་བྱས་པ། བྱེད་པ་བྱས་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They were well-born great elephants, successful and accomplished.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-9">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-27</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཁུར་བོར་བ། བདག་གི་དོན་རྗེས་སུ་ཐོབ་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They had laid down their burdens and fulfilled their aims.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-10">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-27</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྲིད་པར་ཀུན་ཏུ་སྦྱོར་བ། ཡོངས་སུ་ཟད་པ། ཡང་དག་པའི་ཤེས་པས་སེམས་ཤིན་ཏུ་རྣམ་པར་གྲོལ་བ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They had eliminated the fetters of existence, and their minds were completely liberated through perfect knowledge.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-11">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-27</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སེམས་ཀྱི་དབང་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱི་དམ་པའི་ཕ་རོལ་དུ་སེམས་པ། མངོན་པར་ཤེས་པས་མངོན་པར་ཤེས་པ་ཤ་སྟག་སྟེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They had attained supreme perfection in mastering all mental states.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-12">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-27</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་ཟག་གཅིག་མ་གཏོགས་པ་ནི་འདི་ལྟ་སྟེ། ཚེ་དང་ལྡན་པ་ཀུན་དགའ་བོའོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Indeed, they were all this way—with the exception of one person, Venerable Ānanda.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-13">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-27</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་ལྔ་བརྒྱ་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱང་གཟུངས་ཐོབ་པ། ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་ཐོབ་པ་ཤ་སྟག་དང་ཐབས་ཅིག་ཏུ་བཞུགས་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They were accompanied by five hundred bodhisattvas, all of whom had attained retention and meditative absorption.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-14">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-28</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེའི་ཚེ་གྲོང་ཁྱེར་ཆེན་པོ་མཉན་ཡོད་ན་ཁྱིམ་བདག་དཔས་བྱིན་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་ཕྱུག་པ། ནོར་ཆེ་བ། བདག་དབང་བ་མང་བ། ནོར་དང་ཡོ་བྱད་མང་བ། ནོར་དང་། འབྲུ་དང་། མཛོད་དང་། བང་བའི་ཚོགས་མང་བ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-009-28"/>At that time, in the great city of Śrāvastī there was a householder named Vīradatta who had immense wealth, extensive assets, abundant capital and provisions, and multiple storehouses and treasuries of jewels and grain.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-15">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-28</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གླང་པོ་ཆེ་དང་། རྟ་དང་། རྔ་མོ་དང་། ར་ལུག་དང་། བ་ལང་མང་བ། བྲན་ཕོ་དང་། བྲན་མོ་དང་། ལས་བྱེད་པ་དང་། ཞོ་ཤས་འཚོ་བ་མང་བ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He had many elephants, horses, camels, goats, and cows, and he also possessed many male and female slaves, employees, and day laborers.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-16">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-29</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དབྱིག་དང་། གསེར་དང་། ནོར་བུ་དང་། མུ་ཏིག་དང་། བཻ་དཱུརྱ་དང་། <tei:ref folio="F.194.b"/>དུང་དང་། མན་ཤེལ་དང་། བྱི་རུ་དང་། ས་ལེ་སྦྲམ་དང་། དངུལ་མང་བ་ཞིག་གནས་པ་དེ་ཁྱིམ་བདག་ལྔ་བརྒྱ་ཙམ་དང་ལྷན་ཅིག་ཏུ་འདུས་ཏེ་འདུག་པར་གྱུར་ཏོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He also had a great quantity of jewels, gold, gems, pearls, lapis lazuli, conch shells, crystal, coral, fine gold, and silver. <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-009-29"/>In this place, five hundred householders congregated and sat together.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-17">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-29</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་དག་འདུས་ཏེ་འཁོད་པའི་ཚེ་བར་སྐབས་སུ་འདི་ལྟ་བུའི་གཏམ་རྗོད་དེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>While assembled, they conversed:</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-18">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-29</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཀྱེ་གྲོགས་པོ་དག་སངས་རྒྱས་འབྱུང་བ་རྙེད་པར་དཀའ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Hey, friends! The appearance of a buddha is rarely met with.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-19">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-29</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མིར་སྐྱེ་བ་རྙེད་པར་དཀའ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>A human birth is rarely met with.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-20">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-29</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དལ་བ་ཕུན་སུམ་ཚོགས་པ་རྙེད་པར་དཀའ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The excellent freedoms are rarely met with.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-21">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-29</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པའི་བསྟན་པ་ལ་དད་པ་རྙེད་པར་དཀའ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Faith in the teaching of the Tathāgata is rarely met with.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-22">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-29</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རབ་ཏུ་བྱུང་བ་རྙེད་པར་དཀའ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>A renunciate is rarely met with.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-23">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-29</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དགེ་སློང་གི་དངོས་པོ་རྙེད་པར་དཀའ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Monkhood is rarely met with.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-24">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-29</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ནན་ཏན་བྱེད་པ་རྙེད་པར་དཀའ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>One who strives earnestly is rarely met with.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-25">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-29</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སེམས་ཅན་གང་དག་བྱས་པ་གཟོ་ཞིང་བྱས་པ་ཤེས་ལ་གང་དག་བྱས་པ་ཆུང་ངུ་ཡང་ཆུད་མི་གཟོན་ན་མང་པོ་ལྟ་ཅི་སྨོས་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Some sentient beings have gratitude and understand deeds; they do not squander even small deeds, not to mention extensive ones.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-26">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-29</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་དག་ཆེས་རྙེད་པར་དཀའ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Such people are rarely found.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-27">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-29</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་བས་ཀྱང་སེམས་ཅན་གང་དག་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པའི་བསྟན་པ་ལ་ཡིད་ཆེས་པ་དེ་དག་ཆེས་རྙེད་པར་དཀའ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Even rarer to be found are those sentient beings who have conviction in the teachings of the Tathāgata.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-28">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-29</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་བས་ཀྱང་སེམས་ཅན་གང་དག་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པའི་བསྟན་པ་ལ་ཡིད་ཆེས་ནས་ནན་ཏན་གྱིས་སྒྲུབ་པ་དེ་དག་ཆེས་རྙེད་པར་དཀའ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Still rarer to be found are those sentient beings who, based on their conviction in the teachings of the Tathāgata, earnestly practice them.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-29">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-29</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་བས་ཀྱང་སེམས་ཅན་གང་དག་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པའི་བསྟན་པ་ལ་མཛེས་པ་དེ་དག་ཆེས་རྙེད་པར་དཀའ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Rarer yet to be found are those sentient beings who are adorned with the teaching of the Tathāgata.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-30">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-29</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཁོར་བ་ལས་གྲོལ་བ་རྙེད་པར་དཀའ་ན། ཅི་བདག་ཅག་ཉན་ཐོས་ཀྱི་ཐེག་པས་ཡོངས་སུ་མྱ་ངན་ལས་འདའ་བར་བྱའམ། འོན་ཏེ་རང་སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱི་ཐེག་པས་སམ། འོན་ཏེ་ཐེག་པ་ཆེན་པོ་བླ་ན་མེད་པས་ཡོངས་སུ་མྱ་ངན་ལས་འདའ་བར་བྱ་ཞེས་འཐུན་པར་འདུས་ཏེ་འཁོད་པ་དེ་དག་ཐམས་ཅད་དེ་ལྟ་བུའི་དཔྱོད་པ་སྐྱེས་ནས་བདག་ཅག་ཐེག་པ་ཆེན་པོ་བླ་ན་མེད་པས་ཡོངས་སུ་མྱ་ངན་ལས་འདའ་བར་བྱ་བ་ནི་མཆོག་ཡིན་གྱི། ཉན་ཐོས་ཀྱི་ཐེག་པས་ནི་མ་ཡིན། རང་སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱི་ཐེག་པས་ནི་མ་ཡིན་ནོ་སྙམ་མོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>When liberation from saṃsāra is so rarely to be found, will we attain parinirvāṇa through the Śrāvaka Vehicle or the Pratyekabuddha Vehicle, or will we attain it through the unsurpassable Great Vehicle?” Thus, all those harmoniously assembled and seated together, who investigated things in this way considered that the best way to attain parinirvāṇa was not through the Śrāvaka Vehicle or the Pratyekabuddha Vehicle but through the unsurpassable Great Vehicle.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-31">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-30</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་ཁྱིམ་བདག་དཔས་བྱིན་ཁྱིམ་བདག་ལྔ་བརྒྱ་ཙམ་དེ་དག་གིས་ཡོངས་སུ་བསྐོར་ཅིང་མདུན་དུ་བདར་ཏེ་ལྷན་ཅིག་ཏུ་གྲོང་ཁྱེར་ཆེན་པོ་མཉན་ཡོད་ནས་བྱུང་སྟེ། རྒྱལ་བུ་རྒྱལ་བྱེད་ཀྱི་ཚལ་མགོན་མེད་ཟས་སྦྱིན་གྱི་ཀུན་དགའ་ར་བ་ག་ལ་བ་དང་། བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ག་ལ་བ་དེར་སོང་སྟེ་ཕྱིན་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱི་ཞབས་ལ་<tei:ref folio="F.195.a"/>མགོ་བོས་ཕྱག་འཚལ་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-009-30"/>On this occasion, the householder Vīradatta, surrounded and closely attended by those five hundred householders, proceeded together from the great city of Śrāvastī and went to where the Blessed One was residing in Anāthapiṇḍada’s pleasure garden in Prince Jeta’s Grove.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-32">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-30</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ལ་ལན་གསུམ་བསྐོར་བ་བྱས་ནས་ཕྱོགས་གཅིག་ཏུ་འཁོད་དོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They prostrated to the feet of the Blessed One and, having circumambulated the Blessed One three times, took their seats to one side.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-33">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-30</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་མཁྱེན་བཞིན་དུ་ཁྱིམ་བདག་དཔས་བྱིན་དང་། ཁྱིམ་བདག་ལྔ་བརྒྱ་ཙམ་དེ་དག་ལ་བཀའ་སྩལ་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The Blessed One then posed the following question to the householder Vīradatta and the five hundred householders, although he already knew the answer:</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-34">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-30</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཁྱིམ་བདག་ཁྱེད་དོན་གང་གི་ཕྱིར་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་དགྲ་བཅོམ་པ་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱི་ཐད་དུ་ལྷགས།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Householders, why have you approached the thus-gone, worthy, complete and perfect Buddha?”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-35">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-31</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་ཁྱིམ་བདག་དཔས་བྱིན་དང་། ཁྱིམ་བདག་ལྔ་བརྒྱ་ཙམ་དེ་དག་སྟན་ལས་ལངས་ཏེ་བླ་གོས་ཕྲག་པ་གཅིག་ཏུ་གཟར་ནས་པུས་མོ་གཡས་པའི་ལྷ་ང་ས་ལ་བཙུགས་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-009-31"/>The householder Vīradatta and the five hundred householders arose from their seats, draped their robes over one shoulder, and knelt on their right knee, bowing with palms together.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-36">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-31</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ག་ལ་བ་དེ་ལོགས་སུ་ཐལ་མོ་སྦྱར་བ་བཏུད་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ལ་འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་གསོལ་ཏོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Vīradatta replied to the Blessed One as follows:</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-37">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-31</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་དུས་གཅིག་ཅིག་ན། བདག་ཅག་ཁྱིམ་བདག་ལྔ་བརྒྱ་ཙམ་གཅིག་ཏུ་འདུས་ཏེ་མཆིས་པར་གྱུར་ནས་དེའི་ཚེ་བདག་ཅག་འདུས་ཏེ་མཆིས་པ་ཐམས་ཅད་བར་སྐབས་སུ་འདི་ལྟ་བུའི་བཀའ་མཆིད་བརྗོད་པ་བྱུང་སྟེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Blessed One, at one time I congregated and gathered together with five hundred householders, and at that time all of us who had assembled had the following conversation.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-38">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-32</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཀྱེ་གྲོགས་པོ་དག་སངས་རྒྱས་འབྱུང་བ་རྙེད་པར་དཀའ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-009-32"/>“ ‘Hey, friends! The appearance of a buddha is rarely met with.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-39">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-32</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མིར་སྐྱེ་བ་རྙེད་པར་དཀའ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>A human birth is rarely met with.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-40">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-32</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དལ་བ་ཕུན་སུམ་ཚོགས་པ་རྙེད་པར་དཀའ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The excellent freedoms are rarely met with.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-41">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-32</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པའི་བསྟན་པ་ལ་དད་པ་རྙེད་པར་དཀའ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Faith in the teaching of the Tathāgata is rarely met with.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-42">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-32</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རབ་ཏུ་བྱུང་བ་རྙེད་པར་དཀའ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>A renunciate is rarely met with.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-43">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-32</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དགེ་སློང་གི་དངོས་པོ་རྙེད་པར་དཀའ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Monkhood is rarely met with.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-44">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-32</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ནན་ཏན་བྱེད་པ་རྙེད་པར་དཀའ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>One who strives earnestly is rarely met with.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-45">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-32</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སེམས་ཅན་གང་དག་བྱས་པ་གཟོ་ཞིང་བྱས་པ་ཤེས་ལ་གང་དག་བྱས་པ་ཆུང་ངུ་ཡང་ཆུད་མི་གཟོན་ན་མང་པོ་ལྟ་ཅི་སྨོས་ཏེ་དེ་དག་ཆེས་རྙེད་པར་དཀའ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Some sentient beings are grateful and understand deeds; they do not squander even small deeds, not to mention extensive ones. Such people are rarely found.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-46">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-32</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་བས་ཀྱང་སེམས་ཅན་གང་དག་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པའི་བསྟན་པ་ལ་ཡིད་ཆེས་པ་དེ་དག་ཆེས་རྙེད་པར་དཀའ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Even rarer to be found are those sentient beings who have conviction in the teachings of the Tathāgata.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-47">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-32</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་བས་ཀྱང་སེམས་ཅན་གང་དག་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པའི་བསྟན་པ་ལ་ཡིད་ཆེས་ནས་ནན་ཏན་གྱིས་སྒྲུབ་པ་དེ་དག་ཆེས་རྙེད་པར་དཀའ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Still rarer to be found are those sentient beings who, based on their conviction in the teachings of the Tathāgata, earnestly practice them.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-48">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-32</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་བས་ཀྱང་སེམས་ཅན་གང་དག་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པའི་བསྟན་པ་ལ་མཛེས་པ་དེ་དག་ཆེས་རྙེད་པར་དཀའ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Rarer yet to be found are those sentient beings who are adorned with the teaching of the Tathāgata.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-49">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-32</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཁོར་བ་ལས་གྲོལ་བ་རྙེད་པར་དཀའ་ན། ཅི་བདག་ཅག་ཉན་ཐོས་ཀྱི་ཐེག་པས་ཡོངས་སུ་མྱ་ངན་ལས་འདའ་བར་བྱའམ། འོན་ཏེ་རང་སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱི་ཐེག་པས་སམ། འོན་ཏེ་ཐེག་པ་ཆེན་པོ་བླ་ན་མེད་པས་ཡོངས་སུ་མྱ་ངན་<tei:ref folio="F.195.b"/>ལས་འདའ་བར་བྱ་ཞེས་བཀའ་མཆིད་བགྱིས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>When liberation from saṃsāra is so rarely to be found, will we attain parinirvāṇa through the Śrāvaka Vehicle or the Pratyekabuddha Vehicle, or will we attain it through the unsurpassable Great Vehicle?’</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-50">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-33</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་དེའི་ཚེ་བདག་ཅག་ཐམས་ཅད་འདི་ལྟ་བུའི་རྟོག་པ་སྐྱེས་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-009-33"/>“On that occasion, Blessed One, we all came to the following realization:</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-51">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-33</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བདག་ཅག་ཐེག་པ་ཆེན་པོ་བླ་ན་མེད་པས་ཡོངས་སུ་མྱ་ངན་ལས་འདའ་བར་བྱ་བ་ནི་མཆོག་ལགས་ཀྱི། ཉན་ཐོས་ཀྱི་ཐེག་པས་ནི་མ་ལགས། རང་སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱི་ཐེག་པས་ནི་མ་ལགས་པ་སྙམ་བགྱིད་དེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>we concluded that the best way to attain parinirvāṇa is not through the Śrāvaka Vehicle or the Pratyekabuddha Vehicle but through the unsurpassable Great Vehicle.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-52">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-34</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་བདག་ཅག་ཆོས་ཀྱི་སྐྱེས་འདི་དང་ཆས་ཏེ་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་དགྲ་བཅོམ་པ་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱི་ཐད་དུ་མཆིས་ན།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-009-34"/>“Blessed One, we set off with this source of the Dharma and came straight to the thus-gone, worthy, complete and perfect Buddha.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-53">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-34</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོ་བླ་ན་མེད་པ་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་བྱང་ཆུབ་མངོན་པར་རྫོགས་པར་འཚང་རྒྱ་བར་འཚལ་བས་ཇི་ལྟར་བསླབ་པར་བགྱི།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Blessed One, we are now asking how should a bodhisattva mahāsattva who is seeking to fully awaken to unsurpassable complete and perfect awakening train?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-54">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-34</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བདེ་བར་གཤེགས་པ་ཇི་ལྟར་བསླབ་པར་བགྱི།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>How should one train in it, Sugata?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-55">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-34</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཇི་ལྟར་གནས་པར་བགྱི།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>How should one abide by it?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-56">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-34</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཇི་ལྟར་བསྒྲུབ་པར་བགྱི།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>How should one proceed with it?”<tei:note xml:id="UT22084-043-009-35"/>
                </seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-57">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-36</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་ཁྱིམ་བདག་དཔས་བྱིན་དང་། ཁྱིམ་བདག་ལྔ་བརྒྱ་ཙམ་དེ་དག་ལ་ལེགས་སོ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་བྱིན་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-009-36"/>The Blessed One then expressed his approval to the householder Vīradatta and the five hundred householders:</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-58">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-36</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཁྱིམ་བདག་རྣམས་ལེགས་སོ་ལེགས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Householders, excellent, excellent!</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-59">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-36</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཁྱིམ་བདག་རྣམས་ཁྱེད་འདི་ལྟར་བླ་ན་མེད་པ་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་བྱང་ཆུབ་ཏུ་ཡང་དག་པར་ཞུགས་ནས་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་དགྲ་བཅོམ་པ་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱི་ཐད་དུ་ལྷགས་པ་ཁྱེད་ཡང་ལེགས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Householders, having set out for unsurpassable complete and perfect awakening in this way, it is good that you have approached the thus-gone, worthy, complete and perfect Buddha.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-60">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-37</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཁྱིམ་བདག་རྣམས་དེའི་ཕྱིར་ལེགས་པར་རབ་ཏུ་ཉོན་ལ་ཡིད་ལ་ཟུང་ཤིག་དང་། བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོ་བླ་ན་མེད་པ་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་བྱང་ཆུབ་མངོན་པར་རྫོགས་པར་འཚང་རྒྱ་བར་འདོད་པས་ཇི་ལྟར་བསླབ་པར་བྱ་བ་དང་། ཇི་ལྟར་གནས་པར་བྱ་བ་དང་། ཇི་ལྟར་བསྒྲུབ་པར་བྱ་བ་ངས་ཁྱེད་ལ་བཤད་དོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-009-37"/>“Therefore, householders, please listen well and bear my words in mind, and I shall explain to you how a bodhisattva, a mahāsattva who is seeking to fully awaken to unsurpassable complete and perfect awakening should train in it, abide by it, and proceed with it.”<tei:note xml:id="UT22084-043-009-38"/>
                </seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-61">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-39</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་དེ་བཞིན་ནོ་ཞེས་གསོལ་ཏེ། ཁྱིམ་བདག་དཔས་བྱིན་དང་། ཁྱིམ་བདག་ལྔ་བརྒྱ་ཙམ་དེ་དག་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱི་ལྟར་ཉན་པ་དང་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-009-39"/>“So it shall be, Blessed One,” answered the householder Vīradatta and the five hundred householders, and they began to listen to the Blessed One’s view.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-62">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-40</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་དེ་དག་ལ་འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་བཀའ་སྩལ་ཏོ། །ཁྱིམ་བདག་རྣམས་འདི་ལ་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོ་བླ་ན་མེད་པ་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་བྱང་ཆུབ་ཏུ་མངོན་པར་རྫོགས་པར་འཚང་རྒྱ་བར་འདོད་པས་སེམས་ཅན་ཐམས་<tei:ref folio="F.196.a"/>ཅད་ལ་སྙིང་རྗེ་ཆེན་པོའི་སེམས་བསྐྱེད་པར་བྱ། ཀུན་ཏུ་བསྟེན་པར་བྱ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-009-40"/>The Blessed One then said to them,<tei:note xml:id="UT22084-043-009-41"/> “In this regard, householders, the bodhisattva mahāsattva who wishes to fully awaken to unsurpassable complete and perfect awakening should cultivate the spirit of great compassion for all sentient beings. He should be respectful.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-63">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-40</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ངེས་པར་བསྟེན་པར་བྱ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He should stay close to them.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-64">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-40</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བསྒོམ་པར་བྱ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He should cultivate them.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-65">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-40</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མང་དུ་བྱའོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He should do a lot for them.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-66">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-42</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཁྱིམ་བདག་རྣམས་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོ་དེས་ལུས་ལ་ཆགས་པར་མི་བྱ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-009-42"/>“Householders, such a bodhisattva mahāsattva should not be attached to the body.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-67">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-42</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྲོག་ལ་ཆགས་པར་མི་བྱ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He should not be attached to life.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-68">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-42</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་བཞིན་དུ་ནོར་དང་། འབྲུ་དང་། ཁྱིམ་དང་། ཆུང་མ་དང་། བུ་དང་། བུ་མོ་རྣམས་ལ་ཆགས་པར་མི་བྱ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Likewise, he should not be attached to wealth, grain, house, wife, sons, or daughters.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-69">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-42</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཟའ་བ་དང་། བཏུང་བ་དང་། བགོ་བ་དང་། བཞོན་པ་དང་། མལ་ཆ་དང་། མེ་ཏོག་དང་། བདུག་པ་དང་། སྤོས་དང་། བྱུག་པ་དང་། ཕྲེང་བ་རྣམས་ལ་ཆགས་པར་མི་བྱ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He should not be attached to food, drink, clothing, vehicles, bedding, flowers, incense, perfumes, ointments, or garlands.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-70">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-42</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡོ་བྱད་ཐམས་ཅད་ལ་ཆགས་པར་མི་བྱའོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He should not be attached to possessions.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-71">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-43</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ཅིའི་ཕྱིར་ཞེ་ན།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-009-43"/>“Why is this?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-72">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-43</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཁྱིམ་བདག་རྣམས་སེམས་ཅན་དག་ནི་ཕལ་ཆེར་ལུས་དང་སྲོག་ལ་ཆགས་པར་གྱུར་ནས་སྡིག་པའི་ལས་རྣམས་བྱེད་དེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Householders, it is because sentient beings usually become attached to their body and life and thus commit evil deeds.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-73">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-43</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་དག་སྡིག་པའི་ལས་བྱས་ཤིང་བསགས་པ་དེས་ངན་སོང་ངན་འགྲོ་ལོག་པར་ལྟུང་བ་སེམས་ཅན་དམྱལ་བ་རྣམས་སུ་སྐྱེའོ། །སེམས་ཅན་ཐམས་ཅད་ལ་སྙིང་རྗེ་ཆེན་པོའི་སེམས་བསྐྱེད་དེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>By committing and accumulating this evil karma, they fall headlong into evil states and bad destinies and are reborn as hell beings.<tei:note xml:id="UT22084-043-009-44"/> Cultivate the spirit of great compassion for all sentient beings.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-74">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-43</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལུས་དང་སྲོག་ལ་མ་ཆགས་པར་བྱས་ན་བདེ་འགྲོ་རྣམས་སུ་སྐྱེའོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>When one is not attached to the body and not attached to life, one takes birth in the happy destinies.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-75">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-45</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཁྱིམ་བདག་རྣམས་དེ་ལྟ་བས་ན་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོ་བླ་ན་མེད་པ་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་བྱང་ཆུབ་མངོན་པར་རྫོགས་པར་འཚང་རྒྱ་བར་འདོད་པས་སེམས་ཅན་ཐམས་ཅད་ལ་སྙིང་རྗེ་ཆེན་པོའི་སེམས་བསྐྱེད་དེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-009-45"/>“For these reasons, householders, a bodhisattva mahāsattva who wishes to fully awaken to unsurpassable complete and perfect awakening should cultivate the spirit of great compassion for all sentient beings.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-76">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-45</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལུས་ལ་ཆགས་པར་མི་བྱ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He should not be attached to the body.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-77">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-45</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྲོག་ལ་ཆགས་པར་མི་བྱ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He should not be attached to life.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-78">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-45</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་བཞིན་དུ་ནོར་དང་། འབྲུ་དང་། ཁྱིམ་དང་། ཆུང་མ་དང་། བུ་དང་བུ་མོ་རྣམས་ལ་ཆགས་པར་མི་བྱ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Likewise, he should not be attached to wealth, grain, house, wife, sons, or daughters.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-79">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-45</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཟའ་བ་དང་། བཏུང་བ་དང་། བགོ་བ་དང་། བཞོན་པ་དང་། མལ་ཆ་དང་། མེ་ཏོག་དང་། བདུག་པ་དང་། སྤོས་དང་། ཕྲེང་བ་དང་། བྱུག་པ་རྣམས་ལ་ཆགས་པར་མི་བྱ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He should not be attached to food, drink, clothing, vehicles, bedding, flowers, incense, perfumes, garlands, or ointments.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-80">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-45</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡོ་བྱད་ཐམས་ཅད་ལ་ཆགས་པར་མི་བྱ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He should not be attached to possessions.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-81">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-46</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བདོག་པ་ཐམས་ཅད་ཡོངས་སུ་གཏང་བར་ཡོངས་སུ་གཏང་བ་མང་བ་དང་། རྣམ་པར་སྨིན་པ་ལ་རེ་བ་མེད་པར་བྱ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-009-46"/>“He should renounce extensively and fully, with total renunciation and without expectation for results.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-82">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-46</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཚུལ་ཁྲིམས་རྣམ་པ་གསུམ་ཡོངས་སུ་དག་པར་ཚུལ་ཁྲིམས་ཀྱི་སྡོམ་པ་ལ་གནས་པར་བྱ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He should stand firm in the three aspects of morality, the vows of pure moral discipline.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-83">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-46</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སེམས་ཅན་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱིས་ཉེས་པ་བྱས་པ་ལ་ཇི་མི་སྙམ་པར་བཟོད་པ་དང་<tei:ref folio="F.196.b"/>དེས་པ་ཕུན་སུམ་ཚོགས་པར་བྱ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He should endure with indifference the negative deeds committed by any sentient being and thus make the most of it.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-84">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-46</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལུས་དང་སྲོག་ལ་མི་ལྟ་བར་བརྩོན་འགྲུས་ཀྱི་གོ་ཆ་ཆེན་པོ་བགོ་བར་བྱ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He should don the great armor of effort in disregarding body and life.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-85">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-46</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྣམ་པར་མི་གཡེང་བའི་སེམས་ཀྱིས་སེམས་རྩེ་གཅིག་ཏུ་བྱ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He should have one-pointedness of mind with an undistracted mind.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-86">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-46</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བདག་དང་། སེམས་ཅན་དང་། སྲོག་དང་། གསོ་བ་དང་། སྐྱེས་བུ་དང་། གང་ཟག་དང་། ཤེད་ལས་སྐྱེས་དང་། ཤེད་བུར་ལྟ་བ་དང་བྲལ་བས་ཤེས་རབ་ཀྱིས་རྣམ་པར་དཔྱད་པ་ལ་མཁས་པར་བྱ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He should become skilled in analysis by means of insight that is free from the view of a self, a being, a life force, a soul, a man, a person, a human-born one, and a human being.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-87">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-46</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེས་སྦྱིན་པ་སྦྱིན་ན་སེམས་ཅན་ཐམས་ཅད་ཡིད་ལ་བྱས་ཏེ་སྦྱིན་པ་སྦྱིན་པར་བྱ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Therefore, when giving gifts, he should give gifts while considering all sentient beings.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-88">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-46</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སེམས་ཅན་ཐམས་ཅད་ཡིད་ལ་བྱས་ཏེ་ཚུལ་ཁྲིམས་བསྲུང་བར་བྱ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He should guard moral discipline while considering all sentient beings.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-89">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-46</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སེམས་ཅན་ཐམས་ཅད་ཡིད་ལ་བྱས་ཏེ་བཟོད་པ་བསྒོམ་པར་བྱ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He should cultivate patience while considering all sentient beings.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-90">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-46</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སེམས་ཅན་ཐམས་ཅད་ཡིད་ལ་བྱས་ཏེ་བརྩོན་འགྲུས་བརྩམ་པར་བྱ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He should apply effort while considering all sentient beings.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-91">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-46</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སེམས་ཅན་ཐམས་ཅད་ཡིད་ལ་བྱས་ཏེ་བསམ་གཏན་ལ་མཉམ་པར་གཞག་པར་བྱ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He should become established in concentration while considering all sentient beings.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-92">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-46</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སེམས་ཅན་ཐམས་ཅད་ཡིད་ལ་བྱས་ཏེ་ཤེས་རབ་བསྒོམ་པར་བྱ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He should cultivate wisdom while considering all sentient beings.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-93">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-46</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སེམས་ཅན་ཐམས་ཅད་ཡིད་ལ་བྱས་ཏེ་ཐབས་ལ་མཁས་པ་བསླབ་པར་བྱའོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He should train in skillful means while considering all sentient beings.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-94">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-48</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ནས་ཁྱིམ་བདག་དཔས་བྱིན་དང་། ཁྱིམ་བདག་ལྔ་བརྒྱ་ཙམ་དེ་དག་གིས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ལ་འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་གསོལ་ཏོ། །བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་བདག་ཅག་ནི་ལུས་ལ་ལྟ་ཞིང་གནས་པ་ལགས། སྲོག་ལ་ལྟ་ཞིང་གནས་པ་ལགས། དེ་བཞིན་དུ་ནོར་དང་། འབྲུ་དང་། ཁྱིམ་དང་། ཆུང་མ་དང་། བུ་དང་། བུ་མོ་རྣམས་ལ་ལྟ་ཞིང་གནས་པ་ལགས། བཟའ་བ་དང་། བཏུང་བ་དང་། བགོ་བ་དང་། བཞོན་པ་དང་། མལ་ཆ་དང་། མེ་ཏོག་དང་། སྤོས་དང་། བདུག་པ་དང་། ཕྲེང་བ་དང་། བྱུག་པ་རྣམས་ལ་ལྟ་ཞིང་གནས་པ་ལགས། ཡོ་བྱད་ཐམས་ཅད་ལ་ལྟ་ཞིང་གནས་པ་ལགས་ན།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-009-48"/>The householder Vīradatta and the five hundred householders then said to the Blessed One, “Blessed One, if one perceives and dwells on the body and life, and likewise perceives and dwells on wealth, grain, house, wife, sons, or daughters, and likewise perceives and dwells on food, drink, clothing, vehicles, bedding, flowers, incense, perfumes, garlands, or ointments, and all one’s enjoyments, then, Blessed One, how should a bodhisattva examine these and thereby disregard the body?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-95">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-48</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཇི་ལྟར་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སོ་སོར་རྟོག་ཅིང་ལུས་ལ་མི་ལྟ་བ་ལགས། བདེ་བར་གཤེགས་པ་ཇི་ལྟར་སྲོག་ལ་མི་ལྟ་བ་ལགས།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Tathāgata, how should he disregard life?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-96">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-48</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་བཞིན་དུ་ནོར་དང་། འབྲུ་དང་། ཁྱིམ་དང་། ཆུང་མ་དང་། བུ་དང་། བུ་མོ་རྣམས་ལ་མི་ལྟ་བ་ལགས།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Likewise, how should he disregard wealth, grain, house, wife, sons, and daughters?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-97">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-48</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཟའ་བ་དང་། བཏུང་བ་དང་། བགོ་བ་དང་། བཞོན་པ་དང་། མལ་ཆ་དང་། མེ་ཏོག་དང་། བདུག་པ་དང་། སྤོས་དང་། ཕྲེང་བ་དང་། བྱུག་པ་རྣམས་ལ་མི་ལྟ་བ་ལགས།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>How should he disregard food, drink, clothing, vehicles, bedding, flowers, incense, perfumes, garlands, or ointments?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-98">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-48</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡོ་བྱད་ཐམས་ཅད་ལ་མི་ལྟ་བ་ལགས།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>How should he disregard all enjoyments?”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-99">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-49</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་<tei:ref folio="F.197.a"/>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་ཁྱིམ་བདག་དཔས་བྱིན་དང་། ཁྱིམ་བདག་ལྔ་བརྒྱ་ཙམ་དེ་དག་ལ་འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་བཀའ་སྩལ་ཏོ། །ཁྱིམ་བདག་རྣམས་འདི་ལ་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོས་ལུས་འདི་ལ་རྣམ་པ་དུ་མར་སོ་སོར་བརྟག་པར་བྱའོ། །རྣམ་པ་དུ་མ་གང་ཞེ་ན། འདི་ལྟ་སྟེ། ལུས་འདི་མཐར་གྱིས་གྲུབ་པ་དང་། མཐར་གྱིས་འཇིག་པ་དང་། རྡུལ་ཕྲ་རབ་བསགས་པ་དང་། ཁོང་སྟོང་དང་། གྱེ་གུ་ཅན་དང་། བུ་ག་དགུ་དང་། སྤུའི་ཁུང་བུ་ནས་ཟག་པ་དང་། གྲོག་མཁར་ལྟར་སྦྲུལ་གདུག་པའི་གནས་སུ་གྱུར་པ་དང་། སྦྲུལ་གདུག་པ་ལྟར་བྱས་པ་མི་གཟོ་བ་དང་། མ་སྐྱེས་དགྲའི་སྤྲེའུ་ལྟར་གྲོགས་ལ་འཁུ་བ་དང་། བཤེས་གཉེན་ངན་པ་ལྟར་འདྲིད་པའི་བདག་ཉིད་ཅན་དང་། དབུ་བ་རྡོས་པ་ལྟར་རང་བཞིན་གྱིས་ཉམ་ཆུང་བ་དང་། ཆུའི་ཆུ་བུར་ལྟར་བྱུང་ནས་འཇིག་ཅིང་འཇུ་བ་དང་། སྨིག་རྒྱུ་ལྟར་སླུ་བའི་བདག་ཉིད་ཅན་དང་། ཆུ་ཤིང་ལྟར་བཤིག་ན་སྙིང་པོ་མེད་པ་དང་། སྒྱུ་མ་ལྟར་སླུ་བའི་བདག་ཉིད་དང་། རྒྱལ་པོ་ལྟར་བགོ་བླག་མང་བ་དང་། དགྲ་ལྟར་གླགས་ལྟ་བ་དང་། རྐུན་པོ་ལྟར་ཡིད་བརྟན་དུ་མི་རུང་བ་དང་། གཤེད་མ་ལྟར་རྗེས་སུ་ཆགས་པ་མེད་པ་དང་། མི་མཛའ་བ་ལྟར་མི་ཕན་པར་འདོད་པ་དང་། གསོད་པ་ལྟར་ཤེས་རབ་ཀྱི་སྲོག་གི་བར་ཆད་བྱེད་པ་དང་། ཕྱིར་རྒོལ་བ་ལྟར་དགེ་བའི་ཕྱོགས་ཀྱི་ཆོས་ཀྱི་བར་ཆད་བྱེད་པ་དང་། གྲོང་སྟོང་ལྟར་བདག་དང་བྲལ་བ་དང་། རྫ་མཁན་གྱི་སྣོད་ལྟར་མཐར་འཇིག་པ་དང་། སྤྱང་ལྟར་མི་གཙང་བ་སྣ་ཚོགས་ཀྱིས་ཡོངས་སུ་གང་བ་དང་། སྦང་མའི་སྣོད་ལྟར་མི་གཙང་བ་ཟག་པ་དང་། སྦྲུལ་དང་། མི་དང་། ཁྱིའི་རོ་ལྟར་དྲི་མི་ཞིམ་པ་དང་། ངན་སྐྱུགས་ཀྱི་ཁུང་བུ་ལྟར་མི་གཙང་བའི་འབྱུང་གནས་དང་། རྨ་ལྟར་བསྐྱོད་མི་བཟོད་པ་དང་། ཟུག་རྔུ་ལྟར་གནོད་པའི་བདག་ཉིད་ཅན་དང་། རྗེ་བོ་སྡང་བ་ལྟར་བསྙེན་པར་དཀའ་བ་དང་། ཁང་རྙིང་ལྟར་བཅོས་ལེགས་བྱ་ཞིང་བསྟེན་པ་དང་། གྲུ་རྙིང་ལྟར་བཅོས་ལེགས་བྱ་ཞིང་སྤྱད་པ་དང་། བུམ་པ་སོ་མ་བཏང་བ་ལྟར་ནན་ཏན་གྱིས་བག་བྱ་དགོས་པ་དང་། གྲོགས་པོ་མི་སྲུན་པ་ལྟར་རྟག་ཏུ་རྗེས་<tei:ref folio="F.197.b"/>སུ་བསྲུང་དགོས་པ་དང་། ཆུ་འགྲམ་གྱི་ཤིང་ལྟར་གཡོ་ཞིང་འགུལ་བ་དང་། ཆུ་ཀླུང་ཆེན་པོའི་རྒྱུན་ལྟར་མཐར་མཆི་བའི་རྒྱ་མཚོ་ལ་ཐུག་པ་དང་། བློ་བུར་བའི་ཁྱིམ་ལྟར་སྡུག་བསྔལ་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱི་གནས་སུ་གྱུར་པ་དང་། མགྲོན་པོ་མེད་པའི་གནས་ཁང་ལྟར་ཡོངས་སུ་གཟུང་བ་མེད་པ་དང་། བཙོན་སྲུངས་ལྟར་གསུག་གིས་བསྒྲུབ་པར་བྱ་བ་དང་། མཐའ་འཁོབ་ཀྱི་གྲོང་ཁྱེར་ལྟར་རྟག་ཏུ་གནོད་པ་འབྱུང་བ་དང་། བྱེ་མའི་གྲོང་ཁྱེར་ལྟར་རྟག་ཏུ་འཇིག་པའི་བདག་ཉིད་ཅན་དང་། མེ་ལྟར་ཆོག་མི་ཤེས་པ་དང་། རྒྱ་མཚོ་ལྟར་དགང་དཀའ་བ་དང་། སྦྲུལ་གྱི་གཟེབ་ལྟར་ནན་ཏན་གྱིས་བག་བྱ་བ་དང་། བྱིས་པ་ཆུང་ངུ་ལྟར་རྟག་ཏུ་ཡོངས་སུ་བསྐྱང་དགོས་པ་དང་། སྣོད་ཆག་པ་ལྟར་རྟག་ཏུ་བག་བྱ་དགོས་པ་དང་། ཡུལ་ངན་པ་ལྟར་རྟག་ཏུ་གནོད་པ་འབྱུང་བ་དང་། ཟས་དུག་ཅན་ལྟར་རྟག་ཏུ་ཡོངས་སུ་སྤང་བར་བྱ་བ་དང་། རེ་ཤིག་དགོས་པའི་ཕྱིར་སྣོད་བརྙན་མ་ལྟ་བུ་དང་། ཁུར་བཀུར་བའི་ཕྱིར་ཤིང་རྟ་ལྟ་བུ་ཡིན་པ་འབའ་ཞིག་བློས་གཟུང་བར་བྱའོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-009-49"/>The Blessed One said to the householder Vīradatta and the five hundred householders, “In this regard, householders, the bodhisattva mahāsattva should examine multiple aspects of this body. What are the multiple aspects? They consist in this body’s gradual development and gradual deterioration, its being a collection of minute particles, its hollow interior, its crookedness, and its contamination through the nine crevices and the hair pores. Like an anthill, it serves as a den for poisonous snakes. As with a poisonous snake, people avoid dealing with it. Like the monkey of Ajātaśatru, it is hostile to friends. Like a wicked friend, it is the embodiment of deceit. Like a mass of foam, it is vacuous by nature. Like a water bubble, it breaks when grasped. Like a mirage, it is the embodiment of deception. Like a plantain, it lacks any core when split apart. <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-009-50"/>“Like an illusion, it is the embodiment of deceptiveness. Like a king, it is pampered a lot.<tei:note xml:id="UT22084-043-009-51"/> Like an enemy, it looks for opportunities. Like a thief, it cannot be trusted. Like an executioner, it is without any affection. Like a foe, it wants to be unbeneficial. Like a murderer, it hinders the life force of insight. Like hostile forces, it hinders qualities conducive to virtue. Like a ghost town, it is devoid of self. Like a potter’s vase, it will eventually disintegrate. Like a mire, it is filled with all sorts of filth. Like a mug of malt dregs, it is contaminated with impurities. Like the corpse of a snake, man, or dog, it has an unpleasant smell. Like a puddle of vomit, it is a source of filth. Like a wound, it is unbearable when disturbed. Like a thorn, it has the nature of piercing. Like an indignant ruler, it is difficult to appease. Like an old house, it needs attention and proper repairs. Like an old boat, it needs upkeep and proper repairs. Like a freshly made clay pot, it needs to be handled carefully. As with a mischievous friend, one must always be on guard against it. <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-009-52"/>“Like a tree on a riverbank, it is unstable. Like the stream of a great river, it ends in the ocean of death. Like a house of drifters, it is the haven of all miseries. Like a hotel without guests,<tei:note xml:id="UT22084-043-009-53"/> it is unidentifiable. Like a jailer, it is susceptible to bribes. Like a town in savage border lands, it presents a constant threat. Like a city made of sand, it is always deteriorating. Like a fire, it is insatiable. Like the ocean, it is hard to fill up. Like a basket containing a viper, it has to be handled carefully. Like a young child, it needs constant protection. Like a broken vessel, it needs constant attention. Like a famine, it brings constant misfortune. Like poison food, it must always be purged. It is like a borrowed vessel because its purpose is temporary. It is like a cart because it bears a burden.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-100">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-55</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཁྱིམ་བདག་རྣམས་གཞན་ཡང་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔས་ལུས་འདི་ཐོག་མ་དང་ཐ་མའི་རྒྱུ་ལ་སོ་སོར་བརྟག་པར་བྱའོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>One should apprehend the body intellectually as nothing more than these things.<tei:note xml:id="UT22084-043-009-54"/>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-009-55"/> “Moreover, householders, a bodhisattva should examine this body according to the initial and final causes.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-101">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-55</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཕ་མའི་ཁུ་ཆུ་དང་ཁྲག་འདུས་པ་ལས་འབྱུང་སྟེ། འདི་ལ་ཁུ་ཆུ་དང་ཁྲག་ནི་ལུས་ཀྱི་ཐོག་མའི་རྒྱུ་ཡིན་ནོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The initial cause of the body is its genesis from the combination of the seminal fluid and blood of one’s father and mother.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-102">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-55</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཐ་མའི་རྒྱུ་ནི་ཟས་འཇུ་བ་ལ་སོགས་པ་སྟེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The final cause is the digestion of food and so forth.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-103">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-55</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཁམ་གྱིས་བཟའ་བའི་ཟས་ཟོས་མ་ཐག་ཏུ་བད་ཀན་གྱི་གནས་སུ་འགྲོའོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>As soon as food is eaten by the mouthful, it goes to the site of phlegm.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-104">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-55</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།བད་ཀན་གྱི་གནས་སུ་ཕྱིན་ནས་བད་ཀན་གྱིས་རྐྱང་རྐྱང་པོར་བྱས་ཏེ་ཤིན་ཏུ་མི་གཙང་བར་འགྱུར་རོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Having gone to the site of phlegm, it is worked on extensively by the phlegm and becomes very impure.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-105">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-55</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེའི་འོག་ཏུ་མཁྲིས་པའི་གནས་སུ་འགྲོ་སྟེ། མཁྲིས་པའི་གནས་སུ་ཕྱིན་ནས་ཞུ་ཞིང་སྐྱུར་པོར་གྱུར་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Below there, it goes into the site of bile, and having reached the site of bile, it dissolves and becomes acidic.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-106">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-55</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རླུང་གི་གནས་སུ་འགྲོའོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Then it goes to the site of winds.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-107">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-55</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཞུ་སྟེ་རླུང་གི་གནས་སུ་ཕྱིན་ནས་རླུང་གིས་ཚིགས་མ་ལོགས་ཤིག །དངས་མ་ལོགས་ཤིག་ཏུ་རྣམ་པར་འབྱེད་དེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Having dissolved and gone to the site of winds, the winds break down the waste part and make the refined part very pure.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-108">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-55</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཚིགས་མ་ལས་ནི་གཅིན་དང་། ངན་སྐྱུགས་ལ་སོགས་ཏེ་དྲི་མ་རྣམས་འབྱུང་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>From the waste part comes ordure such as urine and vomit.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-109">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-55</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དངས་མ་ལས་ནི་ཁྲག་ཏུ་འགྱུར་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>From the refined part comes blood.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-110">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-55</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཁྲག་ལས་ཤའོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>From blood comes flesh.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-111">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-55</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཤ་ལས་ཚིལ་ལོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>From flesh comes fat.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-112">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-55</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཚིལ་ལས་རུས་པའོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>From fat comes bone.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-113">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-55</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།རུས་པ་ལས་རྐང་ངོ་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>From bone comes marrow.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-114">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-55</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།རྐང་ལས་ཁུ་ཆུའོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>From marrow comes seminal fluid.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-115">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-55</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཁུ་ཆུ་ལས་ལུས་འདི་ལྟ་སྟེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>From seminal fluid comes the body.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-116">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-56</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ལྟར་ཐོག་མ་དང་ཐ་མའི་རྒྱུ་མི་གཙང་བའི་ཕྱིར་ལུས་མི་<tei:ref folio="F.198.a"/>གཙང་བར་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔས་བསམ་པར་བྱའོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>In this way the initial and final causes are impure. <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-009-56"/>“Because the initial and final causes are impure, bodhisattvas should consider the body to be impure.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-117">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-56</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ལུས་ལ་མི་གཙང་བར་ལྟ་བ་ན་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔས་འདི་སྙམ་དུ་བསམ་པར་བྱ་སྟེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>When viewing the body as impure, the bodhisattva should consider the following points:</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-118">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-56</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལུས་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་འདི་ནི་རུས་པ་སུམ་བརྒྱ་དྲུག་ཅུས་ཁོག་པ་བསླང་བ། ཤིང་ངན་པའི་ཁྱིམ་ལྟར་ཚིགས་སུམ་བརྒྱས་སྦྱར་བ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>This so-called body is erected on the inside by three hundred and sixty bones, three hundred of which are connected like a house of rotten wood.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-119">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-56</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྩའི་དྲ་བ་བཞི་བརྒྱས་གླགས་པ། ཤ་སྤར་ཚད་ལྔ་བརྒྱས་གཡོགས་པ། སྡོམ་རྩ་དྲུག་གིས་ཁེབས་པ། རྩ་བདུན་བརྒྱས་གང་བ། རྒྱུས་པ་བདུན་བརྒྱས་འབྲེལ་བ། ཆུ་བ་བཅུ་དྲུག་གིས་བརྟེན་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>It is interlaced with four hundred networks of veins, sheathed with five hundred handfuls of flesh, covered by six connected channels, filled with seven hundred nerves, held together by seven hundred tendons, and supported by sixteen ligaments.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-120">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-56</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཆུ་བ་གཉིས་ཀྱིས་ཁྱབ་པར་དཀྲིས་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>These are surrounded by two ligaments.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-121">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-56</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྒྱུ་མ་འདོམ་ཕྱེད་དང་བཞིས་ནང་ཁྲོལ་བྱས་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The small intestines are made up of three and a half cubits of entrails.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-122">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-56</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལོང་ཀ་དང་། ཕོ་བ་དང་འབྲེལ་བའི་གཉེ་མ་རིམ་པ་བཅུ་དྲུག་ཏུ་འཁྱིལ་བ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The intestines connected to the large intestine and stomach are coiled sixty times.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-123">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-56</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྩ་ཕྲན་ཉིས་སྟོང་ལྔ་བརྒྱས་སྐར་ཁུང་བྱས་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>There are openings made by twenty-five hundred subsidiary channels.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-124">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-56</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཤིས་བརྒྱ་རྩ་བདུན་གྱིས་སྣོད་ཆག་པ་ལྟར། ཤིག་ཤིག་པོར་གྱུར་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>There is a weakening by way of one hundred and seven vital essences, like a broken vessel.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-125">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-56</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྤུའི་ཁུང་བུ་བྱེ་བ་བརྒྱ་སྟོང་ཕྲག་བརྒྱད་ཅུས་རྩ་ལྟར་ཁེབས་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>It is carpeted, like grass, with eighteen million hair pores.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-126">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-56</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དབང་པོ་ལྔའི་བུ་ག་དགུ་ཡོད་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>There are nine orifices including the five sense powers.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-127">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-56</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གནས་བདུན་དང་ལྡན་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>It has seven sites.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-128">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-56</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མི་གཙང་བས་ཡོངས་སུ་གང་བ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>It is filled with filth.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-129">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-56</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཀླད་པ་སྙིམ་པ་གང་དང་། ཚིལ་སྙིམ་པ་གང་དང་། ཞག་སྙིམ་པ་གསུམ་དང་། བད་ཀན་སྙིམ་པ་དྲུག་དང་། མཁྲིས་པ་སྙིམ་པ་དྲུག་དང་། རླུང་གིས་མཐའ་དག་དྲངས་པ་དང་། ཁྲག་བྲེ་གང་དང་། ངན་སྐྱུགས་ཕུལ་གང་དང་། དེ་དག་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱིས་བང་བ་བར་ཆད་ཅན་ལྟར་སོ་སོར་ཡོངས་སུ་གང་བ། པགས་པ་རིམ་པ་བདུན་གྱིས་ཀུན་ནས་བསྐོར་བ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>It has two handfuls of brains, two handfuls of marrow, six handfuls of fat, six handfuls of phlegm, and six handfuls of bile, all drawn by the winds. It is filled with liters<tei:note xml:id="UT22084-043-009-57"/> of blood and a handful of vomit. It is completely filled with all these things, like a jam-packed storehouse, and it is totally ensconced in seven layers of skin.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-130">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-56</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རོ་བྲོ་བ་དྲུག་གིས་གསོ་བ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>It is nourished by six flavors.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-131">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-56</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལུས་ཀྱི་མེ་ལ་ངན་སྐྱུགས་ཀྱི་སྦྱིན་སྲེག་བྱེད་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>There is a burnt offering of ordure made into the bodily fire.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-132">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-56</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྟག་ཏུ་མཐར་འཛག་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The extremities leak continuously.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-133">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-58</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལུས་ཀྱི་ཡན་ལག་དེ་དག་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱིས་བལྟ་ན་མི་སྡུག་པ། དྲི་ང་བ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-009-58"/>“All the parts of the body are unpleasant when observed. There are bad smells.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-134">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-58</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྣག་གི་རང་བཞིན་ཡིན་ན་འདི་ལ་སུ་ཞིག་གུས་པར་བྱེད་དེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Given that it has the nature of pus, who would have reverence for it?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-135">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-58</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྐད་ཅིག་དགོས་པའི་ཕྱིར་སྣོད་བརྙན་མ་ཙམ་དུ་ཟད་པ་དང་། ཁུར་བཀུར་བའི་ཕྱིར་ཤིང་རྟ་ལྟ་བུ་འབའ་ཞིག་ཡིན་པར་ཆོས་ཀྱི་བློས་གཟུང་བར་བྱའོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>It is merely a borrowed vessel because its purpose is fleeting. One should apprehend with the mind of the Dharma that it is only, like a cart, for the purpose of bearing a burden.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-136">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-58</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ལ་འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་བྱ་སྟེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>In this regard the following is said:</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-137">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-59</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདི་ལྟར་མི་གཙང་ཕུང་པོའི་ལུས་ལ་ནི།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-009-59"/>“ ‘Thus, concerning this impure body of the aggregates,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-138">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-59</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།གཟུགས་མངོན་ང་རྒྱལ་ཅན་གང་གུས་བྱེད་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Just as one with overweening pride who admires its form</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-139">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-59</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།བྱིས་པའི་བློ་ཅན་དེ་ནི་མངོན་བཞིན་དུ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Exhibits a childish mind,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-140">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-60</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།མི་ཤེས་ངན་སྐྱུགས་བུམ་པ་ཐོགས་ཤིང་འགྲོ །དེ་ཡི་<tei:ref folio="F.198.b"/>སྣ་ནས་རྣག་གི་རྣམ་པ་འཛག།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>So do the ignorant cling to and move around with this pot of vomit. <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-009-60"/>“ ‘From its nose leaks a kind of mucous.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-141">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-60</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཁ་ནས་དྲི་མི་ཞིམ་པ་རྟག་ཏུ་འབྱུང་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>From its mouth foul odors always rise.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-142">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-60</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།མིག་རྡུལ་ཆགས་ཤིང་སྐྱེ་བོ་སྲིན་བུ་ཅན།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The eyes get clogged with dust, and people are subject to parasites.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-143">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-60</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ལ་སུ་ཞིག་ཆགས་ཤིང་གུས་པར་བྱེད།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Who would have attachment to and admiration for that?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-144">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-61</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དཔེར་ན་བྱིས་པ་སོལ་བ་ཐོགས་ནས་སུ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-009-61"/>“ ‘As an analogy, though a fool holding charcoal</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-145">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-61</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།འདི་ནི་དཀར་པོར་བྱ་ཞེས་འདར་བྱེད་ཀྱང་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Announces, “I will make this white,”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-146">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-61</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དཀར་པོའི་དངོས་པོར་མི་འགྱུར་ཟད་པར་འགྱུར།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He grows exhausted, as it will never become something white.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-147">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-61</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།བྱིས་བློ་ཕྱིན་ཅི་ལོག་གི་ང་རྒྱལ་ཅན།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Thus, the childish are subject to the arrogance of mistaken thought.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-148">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-62</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ལྟར་མི་གང་གཙང་སྦྲའི་བློ་གྲོས་ཅན།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-009-62"/>“ ‘In this way, a person who cares about hygiene</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-149">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-62</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ང་ཡིས་ལུས་འདི་གཙང་མར་བྱ་ཞེས་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>And exclaims, “I will make this body clean,”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-150">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-62</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།བསྐུས་ཕྱིས་འབབ་སྟེགས་བརྒྱར་ནི་ཁྲུས་བྱས་ཀྱང་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>May wash at a hundred bathing ghats,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-151">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-62</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།འཆི་བདག་དབང་གིས་ཟད་འགྱུར་གཙང་མི་འགྱུར།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Yet it never becomes clean before it is destroyed by the power of the Lord of Death.’ ”<tei:note xml:id="UT22084-043-009-63"/>
                </seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-152">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-64</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་ཡང་ཁྱིམ་བདག་དཔས་བྱིན་དང་། ཁྱིམ་བདག་ལྔ་བརྒྱ་ཙམ་དེ་དག་ལ་བཀའ་སྩལ་པ། ཁྱིམ་བདག་རྣམས་འདི་ལ་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོ་བླ་ན་མེད་པ་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་བྱང་ཆུབ་མངོན་པར་རྫོགས་པར་འཚང་རྒྱ་བར་འདོད་པས་རྣམ་པ་བཞི་བཅུ་རྩ་བཞིས་ལུས་ལ་བརྟག་པར་བྱ་སྟེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-009-64"/>Thereupon, the Blessed One said to the householder Vīradatta and the five hundred householders, “In this regard, householders, a bodhisattva mahāsattva who wishes to fully awaken to unsurpassable complete and perfect awakening should consider the body in forty-four aspects.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-153">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-64</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྣམ་པ་བཞི་བཅུ་རྩ་བཞི་གང་ཞེ་ན། འདི་ལྟ་སྟེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>What are these forty-four aspects?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-154">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-64</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཁྱིམ་བདག་རྣམས་འདི་ལ་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོས་ལུས་ཡིད་དུ་མི་འོང་བ་དང་། རང་བཞིན་གྱིས་མི་འཐུན་པ་སྟེ། སྨད་པར་བརྟག་པར་བྱ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Householders, they are as follows: (1) A bodhisattva mahāsattva should consider the body as unpleasant, disagreeable by nature, and disgusting.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-155">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-64</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔས་ལུས་རྣག་ཟག་པ་སྟེ། དྲི་མི་ཞིམ་པར་བརྟག་པར་བྱ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>(2) A bodhisattva should consider the body as contaminated with mucous and therefore having an offensive smell.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-156">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-64</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔས་ལུས་མཐར་འཇིག་པ་སྟེ། སྙིང་པོ་མེད་པར་བརྟག་པར་བྱ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>(3) A bodhisattva should consider that body as disintegrating at the end and therefore without essence.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-157">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-64</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔས་ལུས་རྒྱུས་པའི་བོག་རེས་སྦྲེལ་བ་སྟེ། ཉམ་ཆུང་བར་བརྟག་པར་བྱ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>(4) A bodhisattva should consider the body as stitched together with tendons and therefore having little strength.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-158">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-64</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔས་ལུས་མི་གཙང་བ་ཟག་པ་སྟེ། མི་གཙང་བར་བརྟག་པར་བྱ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>(5) A bodhisattva should consider the body as contaminated with filth and therefore impure.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-159">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-64</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔས་ལུས་ཡང་དག་པ་མ་ཡིན་པ་སྟེ། སྒྱུ་མ་ལྟ་བུར་བརྟག་པར་བྱ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>(6) The bodhisattva should consider the body unreal and therefore like an illusion.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-160">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-64</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔས་ལུས་སྐྱེ་བོ་མི་མཁས་པ་བྱིས་པ་སོ་སོའི་སྐྱེ་བོ་རྣམས་འཁྲུག་པར་བྱེད་པར་བརྟག་པར་བྱ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>(7) A bodhisattva should consider the body as something that agitates unwise, childish, ordinary individuals.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-161">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-64</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔས་ལུས་འཇིག་པ་དང་། བུ་ག་དགུའི་སྒོ་ནས་འཛག་པར་བརྟག་པར་བྱ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>(8) A bodhisattva should consider the body as deteriorating and oozing through its nine orifices.<tei:note xml:id="UT22084-043-009-65"/>
                </seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-162">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-64</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔས་ལུས་འདོད་ཆགས་ཀྱི་མེས་ཀུན་ཏུ་འབར་བར་བརྟག་པར་བྱ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>(9) A bodhisattva should consider the body as being ablaze with the fire of sensual desire.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-163">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-64</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔས་ལུས་ཞེ་སྡང་གི་མེས་ཚིག་པར་བརྟག་པར་བྱ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>(10) A bodhisattva should consider the body as burning with the fire of hatred.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-164">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-64</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱང་<tei:ref folio="F.199.a"/>ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔས་ལུས་གཏི་མུག་གི་མེས་མེ་ལྕེ་གཅིག་ཏུ་གྱུར་པར་བརྟག་པར་བྱ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>(11) A bodhisattva should consider the body as turning into flames with the fire of delusion.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-165">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-64</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔས་ལུས་འདོད་ཆགས་དང་། ཞེ་སྡང་དང་། གཏི་མུག་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་ལྡོངས་པར་བརྟག་པར་བྱ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>(12) A bodhisattva should consider the body as blinded by sensual desire, hatred, and bewilderment.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-166">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-64</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔས་ལུས་འདོད་ཆགས་ཀྱི་དྲ་བས་ཁེབས་ཤིང་སྲེད་པའི་དྲ་བར་ཆུད་པར་བརྟག་པར་བྱ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>(13) A bodhisattva should consider the body as enmeshed in the net of sensual desire and thrust into the net of craving.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-167">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-64</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔས་ལུས་ཀུན་ནས་བུ་གས་ཡོངས་སུ་གང་བས་བུ་གའི་གནས་སུ་བརྟག་པར་བྱ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>(14) A bodhisattva should consider the body as totally riddled with pores and thus a repository of pores.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-168">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-64</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔས་ལུས་ནད་བཞི་བརྒྱ་རྩ་བཞེས་གཙེས་པར་བརྟག་པར་བྱ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>(15) A bodhisattva should consider the body as ravaged by four hundred and four diseases.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-169">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-64</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔས་ལུས་སྲིན་བུའི་རིགས་བརྒྱད་ཁྲི་བཞི་སྟོང་གི་གནས་སུ་བརྟག་པར་བྱ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>(16) A bodhisattva should consider the body as a haven for 84,000 species of parasites.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-170">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-64</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔས་ལུས་འཆི་བའི་ཆོས་ཉིད་ཡིན་པས་མི་རྟག་པར་བརྟག་པར་བྱ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>(17) A bodhisattva should consider the body as impermanent since it is of the nature of dying.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-171">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-64</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔས་ལུས་ཆོས་ལ་རྨོངས་པས་བེམས་པོ་ཡིན་པར་བརྟག་པར་བྱ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>(18) A bodhisattva should consider the body as insentient since it is deluded regarding phenomena.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-172">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-64</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔས་ལུས་མཐར་གྱིས་འགྲུབ་ཅིང་ཐ་མར་འཇིག་པས་བུམ་པ་ལྟ་བུར་བརྟག་པར་བྱ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>(19) A bodhisattva should consider the body as jar-like since it is gradually formed and eventually disintegrates.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-173">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-64</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔས་ལུས་མྱ་ངན་གྱིས་གནོད་པ་མང་པོས་གང་བས་ཉམ་ཐག་པར་བརྟག་པར་བྱ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>(20) A bodhisattva should consider the body as destitute since it is rife with all sorts of painful afflictions.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-174">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-64</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔས་ལུས་ཐ་མར་རྒ་ཤིར་འགྱུར་བས་རྟོན་པ་མེད་པར་བརྟག་པར་བྱ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>(21) A bodhisattva should consider the body as unreliable since it eventually grows old and dies.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-175">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-64</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔས་ལུས་གཡོ་དང་སྒྱུའི་ཉེ་བར་སྤྱོད་པ་དག་གིས་གླགས་པར་བརྟག་པར་བྱ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>(22) A bodhisattva should consider the body as driven by deceitful and dishonest activities.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-176">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-64</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔས་ལུས་དགང་དཀའ་བས་སའི་གཏིང་ལྟ་བུར་བརྟག་པར་བྱ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>(23) A bodhisattva should consider the body to be like the depths of the earth since it is hard to fill up.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-177">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-64</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔས་ལུས་དགའ་བའི་གཟུགས་དང་། བདེ་བའི་གཟུགས་ལ་ཞེན་པས་མེ་ལྟ་བུར་བརྟག་པར་བྱ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>(24) A bodhisattva should consider the body to be like a mirror,<tei:note xml:id="UT22084-043-009-66"/> since one grows attached to pleasant and pleasurable forms.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-178">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-64</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔས་ལུས་འདོད་པའི་ཡོན་ཏན་ལྔ་པོ་དག་གིས་ཆོག་མི་ཤེས་པར་བརྟག་པར་བྱ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>(25) A bodhisattva should consider the body as something that is unable to be satisfied by the five sense pleasures.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-179">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-64</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔས་ལུས་རྗེས་སུ་ཆགས་པ་དང་། ཁོང་ཁྲོ་བ་དག་གིས་འཇོམས་པར་བརྟག་པར་བྱ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>(26) A bodhisattva should consider the body as overcome by attachment and anger.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-180">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-64</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔས་ལུས་བསྟི་སྟང་དང་། གནོད་པ་མྱོང་བས་མི་བརྟན་པར་བརྟག་པར་བྱ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>(27) A bodhisattva should consider the body as unstable due to experiencing reverence and abuse.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-181">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-64</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔས་ལུས་ཆུ་ཀླུང་གི་རྒྱུན་བཞིན་དུ་གཞན་དང་གཞན་འབྱུང་བས་རྐྱེན་གཞན་དང་གཞན་དུ་བརྟག་པར་བྱ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>(28) A bodhisattva should consider the body as other-conditioned since it arises as one thing after another like a stream of a river.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-182">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-64</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔས་ལུས་ཚུལ་བཞིན་མ་ཡིན་པ་རྣམ་པ་སྣ་ཚོགས་ཡིད་ལ་བྱེད་པའི་རྣམ་པར་རྟོག་པ་དག་<tei:ref folio="F.199.b"/>གིས་ཡིད་ཀྱི་སེམས་པ་ཡིན་པར་བརྟག་པར་བྱ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>(29) A bodhisattva should consider the body as a focus of mental intention due to thoughts that are focused on various inappropriate aspects.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-183">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-64</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔས་ལུས་ཐ་མར་དུར་ཁྲོད་ལ་ཐུག་པས་བྱས་པ་མི་གཟོ་བར་བརྟག་པར་བྱ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>(30) A bodhisattva should consider the body as ungrateful since it will end up arriving at the cremation ground.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-184">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-64</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔས་ལུས་སྤྱང་ཀི་དང་། ཅེ་སྤྱང་དང་། ཁྱི་རྗེན་ཤ་ཟ་བ་དག་གི་ཟས་སུ་བརྟག་པར་བྱ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>(31) A bodhisattva should consider the body as the food of wolves, jackals, dogs, and flesh-eating demons.<tei:note xml:id="UT22084-043-009-67"/>
                </seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-185">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-64</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔས་ལུས་རུས་པ་དང་། རྒྱུས་པའི་བོག་རེས་སྦྲེལ་བས་འཁྲུལ་འཁོར་ལྟ་བུར་བརྟག་པར་བྱ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>(32) A bodhisattva should consider the body as like a machine stitched together with bones and tendons.<tei:note xml:id="UT22084-043-009-68"/>
                </seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-186">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-64</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔས་ལུས་བཤང་བ་དང་། གཅི་བ་དང་། མཆིལ་མ་དང་། སྣབས་དང་། རྣག་དང་། ཁྲག་གིས་ཡོངས་སུ་གང་བ་སྟེ། བལྟ་བའི་འོས་མ་ཡིན་པར་བརྟག་པར་བྱ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>(33) A bodhisattva should consider the body as unsuitable for viewing as it is full of crap, piss, spit, mucus, pus, and blood.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-187">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-64</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔས་ལུས་ཟས་དང་སྐོམ་ལས་བྱུང་བ་སྟེ། རང་གི་ཁ་ན་ལས་པ་མ་ཡིན་པར་བརྟག་པར་བྱ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>(34) A bodhisattva should consider the body to be without independence since it has developed due to food and drink.<tei:note xml:id="UT22084-043-009-69"/>
                </seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-188">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-64</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔས་ལུས་མི་རྟག་པ་སྟེ། ཤིན་ཏུ་ཟད་པའི་ཆོས་ཉིད་ཡིན་པས་དོན་མེད་པའི་གླགས་པས་གླགས་པར་བརྟག་པར་བྱ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>(35) A bodhisattva should consider the body as driven by aimless pursuits since it is impermanent and of the nature of deterioration.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-189">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-64</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔས་ལུས་ཕྱིར་རྒོལ་བ་མང་པོ་འབྱུང་བས་དགྲ་ལྟ་བུར་བརྟག་པར་བྱ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>(36) A bodhisattva should consider the body as an enemy since it gives rise to many hostile forces.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-190">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-64</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔས་ལུས་ཡང་དང་ཡང་དུ་སྡུག་བསྔལ་མྱོང་བས་གསོད་པ་ལྟ་བུར་བརྟག་པར་བྱ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>(37) A bodhisattva should consider the body to be like a killer since it experiences suffering again and again.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-191">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-64</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔས་ལུས་སྡུག་བསྔལ་གསུམ་གྱིས་གཙེས་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>(38) A bodhisattva should consider the body as a receptacle of suffering since it is tormented by the three types of suffering.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-192">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-64</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གསུམ་གང་ཞེ་ན། འདི་ལྟ་སྟེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>What are the three?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-193">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-64</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདུ་བྱེད་ཀྱི་སྡུག་བསྔལ་ཉིད་དང་། འགྱུར་བའི་སྡུག་བསྔལ་ཉིད་དང་། སྡུག་བསྔལ་གྱི་སྡུག་བསྔལ་ཉིད་ཀྱིས་ཏེ་སྡུག་བསྔལ་གྱི་སྣོད་ཡིན་པར་བརྟག་པར་བྱ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They are conditioned suffering, the suffering of change, and the suffering of suffering.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-194">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-64</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔས་ལུས་ཕུང་པོ་ལྔ་མངོན་པར་གྲུབ་པས་སྡུག་བསྔལ་གྱི་གོང་བུ་ཡིན་པར་བརྟག་པར་བྱ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>(39) A bodhisattva should consider the body as being a mass of suffering since it is composed of the five aggregates.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-195">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-64</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔས་ལུས་རྐྱེན་ཐ་དད་པ་ལས་བྱུང་བས་བདག་མེད་པ་དང་། བདག་པོ་མེད་པར་བརྟག་པར་བྱ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>(40) A bodhisattva should consider the body to be selfless and ownerless since it arises from varied conditions.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-196">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-64</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔས་ལུས་སྐྱེས་པ་དང་། བུད་མེད་དང་བྲལ་བས་སྲོག་མེད་པར་བརྟག་པར་བྱ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>(41) A bodhisattva should consider the body to be lifeless since it is devoid of male and female.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-197">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-64</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔས་ལུས་ཕུང་པོ་དང་། ཁམས་དང་། སྐྱེ་མཆེད་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་སྟོང་པར་བརྟག་པར་བྱ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>(42) A bodhisattva should consider the body to be empty of the aggregates, elements, and sense bases.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-198">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-64</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔས་ལུས་རྨི་ལམ་ལྟ་བུ་སྟེ། གསོག་ཏུ་བརྟག་པར་བྱ།  བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔས་ལུས་སྒྱུ་མ་ལྟ་བུ་སྟེ། ཡང་དག་པ་མ་ཡིན་པར་བརྟག་པར་བྱ།  བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔས་ལུས་<tei:ref folio="F.200.a"/>སྨིག་རྒྱུ་ལྟ་བུ་སྟེ། འཁྲུལ་པར་བྱེད་པར་བརྟག་པར་བྱ།  བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔས་ལུས་བྲག་ཅ་ལྟ་བུ་སྟེ། སླུ་བར་བརྟག་པར་བྱ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>(43) A bodhisattva should consider the body to be ephemeral like a dream, unreal like an illusion, bewildering like a mirage, and deceptive like an echo.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-199">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-64</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔས་ལུས་མིག་ཡོར་ལྟ་བུ་སྟེ། སླུ་བའི་བདག་ཉིད་དུ་བརྟག་པར་བྱ་སྟེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>(44) A bodhisattva should consider the body to have a deceptive nature like an optical illusion.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-200">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-64</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཁྱིམ་བདག་རྣམས་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོས་རྣམ་པ་བཞི་བཅུ་རྩ་བཞི་པོ་དེ་དག་གིས་ལུས་ལ་བརྟག་པར་བྱའོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Householders, a bodhisattva mahāsattva should consider the body according to these forty-four aspects.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-201">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-64</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ལྟར་རྟོག་པའི་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོ་ལུས་ལ་ལུས་སུ་འདུན་པ་དང་། ལུས་ལ་དགའ་བ་དང་། ལུས་བདག་གིར་བྱེད་པ་དང་། ལུས་ལ་སྲེད་པ་དང་། ལུས་ལ་གནས་པ་དང་། ལུས་ལ་ཞེན་པ་གང་ཡིན་པ་དེ་དག་ཐམས་ཅད་སྤོང་ངོ་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>A bodhisattva mahāsattva who understands things in this way regarding the body relinquishes all longing for bodies, delighting in the body, taking the body as mine, craving for the body, relying on the body, and being attached to the body.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-202">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-70</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།སྲོག་ལ་སྲོག་ཏུ་འདུན་པ་དང་། སྲོག་ལ་དགའ་བ་དང་། སྲོག་བདག་གིར་བྱེད་པ་དང་། སྲོག་ལ་སྲེད་པ་དང་། སྲོག་ལ་གནས་པ་དང་། སྲོག་ལ་ཞེན་པ་གང་ཡིན་པ་དང་། དེ་བཞིན་དུ་ནོར་དང་། འབྲུ་དང་། ཁྱིམ་དང་། ཆུང་མ་དང་། བུ་དང་། བུ་མོ་དང་། བཟའ་བ་དང་། བཏུང་བ་དང་། བགོ་བ་དང་། བཞོན་པ་དང་། མལ་ཆ་དང་། མེ་ཏོག་དང་། བདུག་པ་དང་། སྤོས་དང་། ཕྲེང་བ་དང་། བྱུག་པ་རྣམས་དང་། ཡོ་བྱད་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱི་བར་དག་ལ་འདུན་པ་དང་། དགའ་བ་དང་། བདག་གིར་བྱེད་པ་དང་། སྲེད་པ་དང་། གནས་པ་དང་། ཞེན་པ་གང་ཡིན་པ་དེ་དག་ཐམས་ཅད་སྤོང་སྟེ། དེ་ལུས་དང་སྲོག་ལ་མི་ལྟའོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-009-70"/>“Where life is concerned, he relinquishes all hankering for life, delighting in life, identifying with life as mine, craving for life, relying on life, and being attached to life. Likewise, he relinquishes all hankering for, delighting in, taking as mine, craving for, relying on, and being attached to wealth, grain, house, wife, sons, daughters, food, drink, clothing, vehicles, bedding, flowers, incense, perfumes, garlands, ointments, or any other possessions. <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-009-71"/>“Thus, he disregards body and life.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-203">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-70</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་བཞིན་དུ་ནོར་དང་། འབྲུ་དང་། ཁྱིམ་དང་། ཆུང་མ་དང་། བུ་དང་། བུ་མོ་དང་། བཟའ་བ་དང་། བཏུང་བ་དང་། བགོ་བ་དང་། བཞོན་པ་དང་། མལ་ཆ་དང་། མེ་ཏོག་དང་། བདུག་པ་དང་། སྤོས་དང་། ཕྲེང་བ་དང་། བྱུག་པ་རྣམས་ལ་མི་ལྟ་བར་ཕ་རོལ་ཏུ་ཕྱིན་པ་དྲུག་མྱུར་དུ་ཡོངས་སུ་རྫོགས་པར་བྱེད་དོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Likewise, he disregards wealth, grain, house, wife, sons, daughters, food, drink, clothing, vehicles, bedding, flowers, incense, perfumes, garlands, and ointments; he quickly completes the six perfections.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-204">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-70</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཁྱིམ་བདག་རྣམས་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོ་ཕ་རོལ་ཏུ་ཕྱིན་པ་དྲུག་ཡོངས་སུ་རྫོགས་ནས་མྱུར་དུ་བླ་ན་མེད་པ་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་བྱང་ཆུབ་མངོན་པར་རྫོགས་པར་འཚང་རྒྱའོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Householders, the bodhisattva mahāsattva who completes the six perfections will quickly become awakened to unsurpassable complete and perfect awakening.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-205">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-72</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་ལུས་རྒྱ་ཆེར་ཡོངས་སུ་བསྟན་པའི་ཕྱིར་དེའི་ཚེ་ཚིགས་སུ་བཅད་<tei:ref folio="F.200.b"/>པ་འདི་དག་བཀའ་སྩལ་ཏོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-009-72"/>Then, on this occasion, in order to elaborate on the body in more detail, the Blessed One spoke the following verses:</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-206">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-73</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།མི་ཉིད་ཤིན་ཏུ་རྙེད་དཀའ་རྙེད་པ་ལ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-009-73"/>“This human existence is very difficult to find,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-207">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-73</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ལུས་ཀྱི་ཕྱིར་ནི་སྡིག་པ་མ་བྱེད་ཅིག །འདི་ནི་དུར་ཁྲོད་པ་སྟེ་ཅེ་སྤྱང་ཟས། །ལུས་ཀྱི་ཕྱིར་ནི་ཡ་ངར་མ་འཇུག་ཅིག །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>So do not commit sins for the sake of the body. Do not expose yourself to the dangers of this body, Which is food for charnel-ground dwellers and jackals.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-208">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-74</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཡོ་ལྡན་ལུས་ལ་སྲེད་པ་བསྐྱེད་ནས་ནི།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-009-74"/>“Arousing craving for this cunning body,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-209">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-74</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།བྱིས་པ་རྟག་ཏུ་རྣམ་པར་རྨོངས་ཏེ་འཁྱམ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The childish are always deluded and go astray.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-210">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-74</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ལུས་འདི་བྱས་པ་མི་གཟོ་དངོས་ཡིན་པས།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Since this body is, in fact, ungrateful,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-211">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-74</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཉིན་དང་མཚན་དུ་སྡུག་བསྔལ་ཚོར་བ་མྱོང་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>One experiences sensations of suffering day and night.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-212">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-75</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།རྟག་ཏུ་ནད་འདྲ་སྡུག་བསྔལ་འཁྲུལ་འཁོར་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-009-75"/>“A machine always suffering with sickness and the like,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-213">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-75</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ལུས་འདི་ངན་སྐྱུགས་རྣམས་དང་མཆིལ་མས་གང་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>This body is filled with vomit and mucous.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-214">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-75</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།བཀྲེས་དང་སྐོམ་པས་རྟག་ཏུ་མངོན་པར་གཙེས།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Since it is always tormented with hunger and thirst,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-215">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-75</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།མཁས་པ་སུ་ཞིག་ལུས་ལ་སྲེད་པ་སྐྱེད།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>What wise person would arouse craving for the body?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-216">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-76</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ལུས་ནི་ས་གཏིང་འདྲ་སྟེ་ཆོག་མི་ཤེས།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-009-76"/>“The body is insatiable like the depths of the earth.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-217">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-76</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།གཤེད་མ་མི་མཛའ་འདྲ་ཡང་བྱིས་པས་གསོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Though it is like a hostile executioner, it is pampered by the childish.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-218">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-76</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ལུས་ཀྱི་ཆེད་དུ་སྡིག་པའི་ལས་ཀྱང་བྱེད།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Committing evil for the sake of the body,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-219">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-76</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ཕྱིར་དེ་དག་སྡུག་བསྔལ་ཚོར་བ་མྱོང་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They thus experience the sensations of suffering.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-220">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-77</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ལུས་འདི་རྡོ་རྗེ་ལྟ་བུར་སྲ་མ་ཡིན།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-009-77"/>“This body is not solid like a diamond,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-221">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-77</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ལུས་ཀྱི་ཆེད་དུ་སྡིག་པ་མ་བྱེད་ཅིག །འཆི་བར་རྟོགས་ནས་བསོད་ནམས་མྱུར་དུ་བྱོས།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>So do not commit evil for the sake of the body. Having understood death, quickly perform meritorious deeds!</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-222">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-77</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་བཞིན་སངས་རྒྱས་བསྟན་ལ་དད་པ་སྐྱེད།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Likewise, arouse faith in the Buddha’s teaching.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-223">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-78</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཟས་དང་སྐོམ་དང་བྱུག་པ་གོས་རྣམས་ཀྱིས། །ལུས་འདི་ཇི་སྲིད་ཡུན་རིང་བསྙེན་བཀུར་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-009-78"/>“For as long as this body is honored With food, drink, ointments, and garments,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-224">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-78</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།བརྟན་པར་བྱས་ཀྱང་འཇིག་པར་འགྱུར་ཡིན་ན།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>If it steadily deteriorates despite attempts to make it endure,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-225">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-78</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།འདི་ལ་འབད་པ་དོན་མེད་ཅི་ཕྱིར་བྱ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Why make such useless efforts for it?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-226">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-79</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།བསྐལ་པ་བརྒྱར་ཡང་ཤིན་ཏུ་རྙེད་དཀའ་བ། །ཐུབ་པའི་འབྱུང་འདི་ཁྱེད་ཀྱིས་རྙེད་པ་ལ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-009-79"/>“As you have found this appearance of the Sage, Extremely difficult to find for a hundred eons,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-227">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-79</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།སངས་རྒྱས་བསྟན་ལ་དེ་བཞིན་དད་པ་སྐྱེད།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>And have aroused faith in the Buddha’s teachings,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-228">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-80</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཤིན་ཏུ་འཇིགས་པའི་ངན་འགྲོར་མ་འགྲོ་ཤིག །ལོ་སྟོང་བྱེ་བར་སུ་ཞིག་འཚོ་གྱུར་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Do not descend to the lower realms!<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-009-80"/> “If one who has lived there for tens of millions of years</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-229">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-80</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེས་ཀྱང་ཆགས་པ་ཡོངས་སུ་སྤང་བྱ་ན། །སུ་ཞིག་ལོ་བརྒྱ་ཐུབ་པར་མི་འགྱུར་བ། །དེ་ཕྱིར་དགའ་བ་མི་རྙེད་སྨོས་ཅི་དགོས།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Must still relinquish such attachments, Then need it be said that one who is unable to do so In one hundred years will not find happiness?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-230">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-81</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།མ་བསྡམས་མི་རྣམས་ཁ་ཅིག་འདི་སྐད་དུ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-009-81"/>“Some uninhibited people say,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-231">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-81</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།མིར་རྙེད་ཤིན་ཏུ་དཀའ་བ་རྙེད་པ་ལ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>‘Having found this human existence, which is so hard to find,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-232">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-81</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།གཞོན་ཚེ་རྩེད་མོ་དག་དང་དགའ་བྱ་ཞིང་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>We should have fun and enjoy this time of youth,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-233">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-81</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ནོར་བཙལ་བདེ་བ་མྱོང་བར་བྱ་ཞེས་ཟེར།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>And experience the joys of seeking wealth.’</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-234">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-82</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ནོར་ཚོལ་བ་ལ་བདེ་བ་ག་ལ་ཡོད།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-009-82"/>“But how can there be any joy in seeking wealth</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-235">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-82</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།བསྲུང་བའི་ཕྱིར་ཡང་སྡུག་བསྔལ་མྱོང་བར་འགྱུར།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>When we experience such miseries for the sake of protecting it?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-236">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-82</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ཕྱིར་མཁས་པས་ཆགས་པ་ཡོངས་སྤངས་ལ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Therefore, the wise should relinquish all attachment</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-237">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-82</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ངན་ངོན་ཙམ་གྱིས་ཆོག་ཤེས་ཐོབ་པར་བྱོས།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>And find contentment in just the bare necessities.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-238">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-83</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ལོངས་སྤྱོད་སྒྱུ་མ་འདྲ་ཞིང་རྨི་ལམ་མཚུངས།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-009-83"/>“Enjoyments are like an illusion and like a dream.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-239">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-83</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།འདི་དག་བྱིས་པའི་སྐྱེ་བོ་འདྲིད་པ་ཡིན།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They deceive childish people.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-240">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-83</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།སྐད་ཅིག་འབྱུང་ཞིང་<tei:ref folio="F.201.a"/>སྐད་ཅིག་འཇིག་པར་འགྱུར།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They arise one moment and perish the next.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-241">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-83</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།མཁས་པ་སུ་ཞིག་ལོངས་སྤྱོད་སྲེད་པ་སྐྱེད།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>What wise person would arouse craving for possessions?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-242">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-84</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།སྒྱུ་མ་འདྲ་ཞིང་གར་མཁན་ལྟ་དང་མཚུངས།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-009-84"/>“They are illusion-like and similar to watching an actor;</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-243">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-84</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དྲི་ཟའི་གྲོང་ཁྱེར་སྣ་ཚོགས་ཅི་འདྲ་བ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They are like any of the myriad cities of the gandharvas.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-244">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-84</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ལོངས་སྤྱོད་དེ་དག་འདི་འདྲ་བྱིས་པ་འདྲིད།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Such enjoyments deceive the childish.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-245">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-84</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ལྟར་ལོག་པ་ཚོལ་ཞིང་བྱིས་པ་འཁྱམ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Thus, the childish wrongly seek them and go astray.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-246">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-85</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།སྡུག་བསྔལ་བརྒྱ་ཡིས་ལོངས་སྤྱོད་བཙལ་བཙལ་བ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-009-85"/>“When desired possessions pursued with a hundred miseries</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-247">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-85</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ལུས་ལ་གནོད་པ་མཚུངས་མེད་བསྐྱེད་བྱས་ནས།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Bring incomparable harm to the body</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-248">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-85</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།རྒྱལ་པོའི་མཐུ་ཡིས་དེ་དག་ཕྲོགས་གྱུར་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>And may then be seized under the command of a king,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-249">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-85</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་དག་ལ་ནི་མཁས་གང་དགའ་བ་སྐྱེད།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>What wise person would arouse joy for them?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-250">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-86</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།བུ་དང་ཆུང་མའི་དབང་དུ་མི་འགྱུར་བར།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-009-86"/>“While remaining aloof from one’s children and spouse,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-251">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-86</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།རྒྱལ་པོས་ཉེས་པ་བྱུང་བའི་ནོར་ཕྲོགས་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>One’s wrongly obtained wealth may be seized by a king.<tei:note xml:id="UT22084-043-009-87"/>
                </seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-252">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-86</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཉེས་པ་དེ་དག་འདི་འདྲ་རིག་ནས་སུ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Knowing evils such as this,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-253">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-86</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།མཁས་པ་རྣམས་ནི་ཁྱིམ་ལ་སྲེད་མི་སྐྱེད།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Wise people do not arouse craving for the home.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-254">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-88</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།རྟག་ཏུ་བརྣབ་ཅིང་ལོངས་སྤྱོད་ཚོལ་བྱེད་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-009-88"/>“Ever covetous and seeking enjoyments,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-255">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-88</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ནི་ཕ་དང་མ་ལ་མི་གུས་ཤིང་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>One is disrespectful toward one’s father and mother.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-256">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-88</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།བུ་དང་ཆུང་མ་རྣམས་ལ་མི་བྱམས་པར།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>One is not loving toward one’s children and spouse</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-257">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-88</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་དག་རྟག་ཏུ་ཆགས་ལ་འཇུག་པར་བྱེད།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>But nonetheless harbors constant attachment to them.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-258">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-89</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།བདག་གི་ལོངས་སྤྱོད་འགྲིབ་པར་འགྱུར་འོང་ཞེས།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-009-89"/>“A covetous woman who exclaims, ‘My enjoyments will decline,’</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-259">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-89</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།བརྣབ་མོ་བྱས་གཟོ་ནམས་ཀྱང་རྙེད་མི་འགྱུར།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Will never discover gratitude.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-260">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-89</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།གཡོ་དང་སྒྱུས་ནི་ནོར་རྣམས་ཚོལ་བྱེད་པ། །བརྣབ་མོ་དག་ལ་མཁས་པ་ཡིད་མི་རྟོན།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>A wise person does not confide in covetous people Who seek wealth through cunning and deception.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-261">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-90</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།སེམས་ཅན་བརྣབ་མོ་གཡོ་ལྡན་འདྲིད་པ་ཉིད། །ཡིད་གཞན་སེམས་ལ་ཚིག་གིས་དགའ་བར་བྱེད།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-009-90"/>“Beings are fooled by deceitful, covetous women And delighted by words that express an intent to fulfill others’ wishes.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-262">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-90</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཡིད་བརྟན་ཀྱང་ནི་དེ་ལ་ཡིད་མི་རྟོན།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Despite their confidence, one should not confide in them,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-263">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-90</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།འོན་ཀྱང་བུ་འདྲར་སྡུག་པར་སྟོན་པར་བྱེད།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Though they display affections like a child.<tei:note xml:id="UT22084-043-009-91"/>
                </seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-264">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-92</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།སེམས་ཅན་བརྣབ་མོ་འཇིག་རྟེན་གང་རྒྱུ་བ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-009-92"/>“Covetous women who are active in the world</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-265">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-92</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།སྨན་དང་བསྟན་བཅོས་དག་ལ་མཁས་སྟོན་ཅིང་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>May teach scholars about medicine and treatises,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-266">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-92</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།སྨད་འཚོང་ལྟ་བུར་ཚིག་གིས་འདྲིད་བྱེད་ལ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Thereby deceiving them with words like a prostitute,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-267">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-92</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཁོང་ནས་མི་བདེ་ཤིན་ཏུ་རྩུབ་པ་ཡིན།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>But at bottom they are unpleasant and very harsh.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-268">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-93</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།བརྣབ་མོ་དག་ལ་མཛའ་བོ་ནམས་ཀྱང་མེད།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-009-93"/>“Covetous women are never friendly partners.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-269">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-93</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཉེ་དུ་མེད་ཅིང་སྙིང་སླེབས་གྲོགས་ཀྱང་མེད།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They are without relatives and without close friends.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-270">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-93</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།འོན་ཀྱང་དེ་དག་ནོར་ཕྱིར་སྟེན་པར་བྱེད།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They nonetheless put on a show for the sake of money.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-271">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-93</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།སྐྱེ་བོ་བརྣབ་ལ་མཁས་པ་ཡིད་མི་རྟོན།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The wise should not confide in covetous people.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-272">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-94</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།བརྣབ་མོ་ལོངས་སྤྱོད་ཆེད་དུ་བྱ་མིན་བྱེད།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-009-94"/>“Not committing any deed for the sake of covetous women and enjoyments,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-273">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-94</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཤིན་ཏུ་མི་བཟད་སེམས་ནི་ཀུན་ཏུ་སྐྱེད།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>One fully engenders a mind that is utterly inexhaustible.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-274">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-94</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ཕྱིར་མཁས་པས་ཡང་དག་རྟོགས་བྱས་ལ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Therefore, the wise gain perfect understanding</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-275">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-94</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ངན་ངོན་ཅི་ཡང་རུང་བས་ཆོག་ཤེས་གྱིས།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>And find contentment in even the barest of necessities.<tei:note xml:id="UT22084-043-009-95"/>
                </seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-276">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-96</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།གསེར་དང་མུ་ཏིག་ནོར་བུ་བྱི་རུ་དང་། །ལས་དགེས་དེ་དག་ལྦུ་བ་ལས་ཀྱང་འབྱུང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-009-96"/>“Gold, pearls, jewels, and coral— For the virtuous, these things arise as if from bubbles.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-277">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-96</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་དག་སྒྱུ་མའི་རང་བཞིན་མ་རྟོགས་ནས། །དེ་དག་ཕྱིར་ནི་འཐབ་ཅིང་རྩོད་པ་བྱེད།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>When they are not recognized as having the nature of illusion, People argue and fight for the sake of these things.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-278">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-97</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།བྱམས་པ་ཞེས་བྱ་གང་ཞིག་འདིར་འབྱུང་སྟེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-009-97"/>“The one who is called Maitreya will appear here.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-279">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-97</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་<tei:ref folio="F.201.b"/>བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་དེ་ནི་འབྱུང་བའི་ཚེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>And at the time of that tathāgata’s appearance,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-280">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-97</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ས་འདི་གསེར་གྱིས་རབ་ཏུ་གང་བར་འགྱུར།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>This earth will be totally filled with gold.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-281">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-97</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ཡི་ཚེ་ན་དེ་ནི་ག་ལས་འབྱུང་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Whence will he appear on that occasion?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-282">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-98</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།འདོད་པའི་ཡོན་ཏན་ལྔ་དག་འབྱུང་བ་སྟེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-009-98"/>“The appearance of the five sensual pleasures</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-283">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-98</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།བརྫུན་པའི་ཆོས་ཅན་འཁྲུལ་བྱེད་རྨོངས་པར་བྱེད།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Is of the nature of deception, creating confusion and delusion.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-284">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-98</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དཔེར་ན་སོས་ཀའི་ཉི་མ་གུང་དུས་ན། །སྨིག་རྒྱུར་ཆུར་སྣང་འདོད་པ་དེ་བཞིན་ནོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>As an analogy, it is like desiring the water That seems to appear in a mirage, at midday in the hot season.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-285">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-99</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།བསྐལ་པ་གཅིག་ལོན་ནས་ནི་འཇིག་རྟེན་འདི། །ནམ་མཁའི་རང་བཞིན་ནམ་མཁར་འགྱུར་བར་འོང་། །ལྷུན་པོ་དག་ཀྱང་འཚིག་ཅིང་རྣམ་པར་འཇིག །དེ་དག་གང་ནས་འོངས་ཤིང་གང་དུ་འགྲོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-009-99"/>“Once this single eon has elapsed, this world, Which is of the nature of space, will turn into space. Even mountains will burn and be destroyed. Where do they come from? Where do they go?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-286">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-100</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཆུ་མིག་མཚེའུ་དང་རྫིང་དང་རྒྱ་མཚོ་རྣམས།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-009-100"/>“Fountains, ponds, lakes, and oceans</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-287">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-100</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་དག་མེད་འགྱུར་སྐམས་འགྱུར་འབྱུང་བར་འགྱུར།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Will dry up and cease to exist.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-288">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-100</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་བཞིན་འདོད་པ་གསོག་སྟེ་སྙིང་པོ་མེད།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Likewise, desired things hoarded are without essence.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-289">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-100</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།མཁས་པ་སུ་ཞིག་དེ་ལ་དགའ་བར་བྱེད།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>What wise person would take joy in them?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-290">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-101</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།མཁས་པ་གང་དག་བློ་ཡི་སྟོབས་ལྡན་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-009-101"/>“Wise people with strength of mind</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-291">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-101</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་དག་རྟག་ཏུ་ཁྱིམ་གྱི་སྐྱོན་ལ་རྟོག །འདི་ལ་རོ་མྱོང་བྱེད་པ་སུ་ཡོད་ན།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Always examine the drawbacks of the home. When one has experienced the taste of these,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-292">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-101</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།འདི་དག་ཅི་ཕྱིར་ཁྱིམ་ནི་སྤོང་མི་བྱེད།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Why would one not relinquish them?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-293">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-102</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།འདྲེན་མའི་ལས་ཀྱིས་ལོངས་སྤྱོད་ཚོལ་བྱེད་ཅིང་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-009-102"/>“Through a mix of karma one seeks enjoyments</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-294">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-102</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།བུ་དང་དེ་བཞིན་ཆུང་མ་གསོ་བར་བྱེད།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>And provides for children along with a spouse.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-295">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-102</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཤིན་ཏུ་སྡུག་བསྔལ་གྱུར་པ་དེ་དུས་ན།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>But in times when one suffers intensely,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-296">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-102</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།བུ་དང་ཆུང་མ་སྐྱབས་སུ་འགྱུར་མ་ཡིན།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Children and spouse provide no refuge.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-297">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-103</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཇི་ལྟར་སྣ་ཚོགས་ལས་བྱས་བླངས་པ་བཞིན།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-009-103"/>“When one accepts doing various deeds,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-298">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-103</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།བུ་དང་ཆུང་མ་དག་ཀྱང་འདོར་བར་འགྱུར།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Children and spouses will be neglected.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-299">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-103</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།བདག་ཉིད་གཅིག་པུས་སྡུག་བསྔལ་མྱོང་བར་འོང་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>But when one experiences suffering all alone,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-300">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-103</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་དག་དེ་ཚེ་བདག་གི་སྐལ་མི་ལེན།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They do not accept your predicament.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-301">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-104</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།མྱ་ངན་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་བདེ་ཕྱིར་དེ་དག་བླངས།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-009-104"/>“Dejected people accept these things for the sake of happiness.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-302">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-104</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།འདི་ན་དེ་དག་སྡུག་བསྔལ་མྱ་ངན་འགྱུར།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>In this way, they become disheartened with suffering.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-303">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-104</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།སྲིད་གསུམ་འཇིགས་པ་འདི་ན་བཤེས་ཀྱང་མེད།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>In this horror of the three worlds, there are no friends,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-304">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-104</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་བཞིན་བུ་དང་ཆུང་མ་རྩ་ལག་མེད།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>And likewise no children, spouse, or relatives.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-305">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-105</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཕ་མ་སྤུན་དང་བུ་དང་ཆུང་མ་དང་། །བྲན་དང་ནོར་དང་རྩ་ལག་ཚོགས་ཀྱི་རྣམས།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-009-105"/>“The multitude of parents, siblings, children, spouses, Servants, wealth, and relatives</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-306">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-105</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཤི་བའི་གཤིན་ཕྱིར་དེ་དག་འགྲོ་བ་མེད།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Do not transmigrate because the Lord of Death has come;</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-307">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-105</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ལས་རྣམས་རྗེས་སུ་འབྲང་ཞིང་བྱིས་པ་འགྲོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The childish transmigrate in the wake of their karmic deeds.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-308">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-106</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ལས་ནི་རྗེས་སུ་འབྲང་ཞིང་མི་ཀུན་འདོང་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-009-106"/>“People all depart in the wake of their karmic deeds.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-309">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-106</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ལས་ཀྱིས་གནས་པ་འཇིག་རྟེན་རྣམ་པར་རྒྱུ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Through karmic deeds, they are transported to worldly abodes.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-310">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-106</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།སྐྱེ་འདི་ལས་ཀྱི་བདག་ཉིད་རིག་གྱུར་ནས།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Knowing the nature of the karma of this rebirth,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-311">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-106</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།མཁས་པ་དག་ནི་དགེ་བའི་ལས་རྣམས་བྱེད།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The wise perform virtuous deeds.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-312">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-107</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།མནར་མེད་སོང་ཚེ་དེ་དག་སྐྱབས་མིན་པས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-009-107"/>“When they have gone to hell, they will have no refuge.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-313">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-107</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཕ་མ་སྤུན་དང་སྙིང་སྡུག་བུ་རྣམས་དང་། །རྩ་ལག་ཉེ་དུ་སྣག་གི་གཉེན་མཚམས་དང་། །དེ་དག་<tei:ref folio="F.202.a"/>ཆེད་དུ་མཁས་པ་སྡིག་མི་བྱེད།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Thus, the wise do not commit evil misdeeds For the sake of parents, siblings, loved ones, children, Kinsmen, and maternal relatives.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-314">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-108</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ལས་དེ་ཡོངས་སུ་ཟད་པ་མ་གཏོགས་པར།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-009-108"/>“Apart from exhausting all that karma,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-315">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-108</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།རབ་ཏུ་མི་བཟད་འཇིགས་ལས་མི་མི་འགྲོལ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>A person is not liberated from the most frightful terrors.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-316">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-108</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ཕྱིར་སྡིག་པས་འཇིགས་པའི་མི་རྣམས་ཀྱིས།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Therefore, those who are fearful of misdeeds</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-317">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-108</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།བསྒྲིམས་ཏེ་སྡིག་པ་ཡོངས་སུ་སྤང་བར་བྱ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Should concentrate and eliminate all misdeeds.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-318">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-109</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཇི་ལྟར་ལས་རྣམས་བྱས་པ་མ་གཏོགས་པར།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-009-109"/>“In any case, apart from the deeds one performs,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-319">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-109</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།གཤིན་རྗེ་དང་ནི་གཤིན་རྗེའི་རང་རྟ་དང་། །མཛའ་བཤེས་དག་དང་རྩ་ལག་ཚོགས་དང་སྤུན།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The Lord of Death, the horse of the Lord of Death, And the throng of friends, relatives, siblings,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-320">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-109</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཕ་མ་བུ་དང་ཆུང་མ་སྲུང་མི་བྱེད།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Parents, children, and spouse will offer no protection.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-321">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-110</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཁྱོད་ཀྱིས་མི་ཡི་ལུས་ནི་ཐོབ་གྱུར་ལ། །ཐོབ་ནས་སྡིག་པ་སྤང་བ་མ་བྱས་པས། །ཀྱེ་མ་ད་ལྟར་སྡུག་བསྔལ་མི་བཟད་མྱོང་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-009-110"/>“You have attained a human body, but having attained it, You have not set about relinquishing misdeeds. Alas! You now experience unbearable suffering.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-322">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-110</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།འདི་ནི་མི་དགེའི་ལས་ཀྱི་རྣམ་སྨིན་ཡིན།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>This is but the ripening of nonvirtuous karmic action.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-323">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-111</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ལས་ཀྱི་རྣམ་པར་སྨིན་ལ་ཡིད་མ་ཆེས།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-009-111"/>“Without having conviction in the ripening of karmic action,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-324">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-111</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཁྱོད་ནི་རང་གི་སེམས་ཀྱིས་མི་དགེ་བྱས།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>You create nonvirtue through your own mind.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-325">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-111</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།འདི་ལ་ངས་ནི་ཅི་ཡང་མ་ལན་ཞེས།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>For this, one answers ‘I did not do anything at all.’</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-326">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-111</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ལ་ཆོས་རྒྱལ་གཤིན་རྗེ་དེ་སྐད་སྨྲ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Then the Dharma king Lord of Death states the following:</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-327">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-112</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།རང་གིས་ལས་བྱས་རང་ལ་རྣམ་པར་སྨིན། །རང་གི་ལས་ཀྱིས་ཁྱོད་ནི་འདིར་འོངས་ཀྱིས། །ཇི་ལྟར་སྔོན་ཆད་མི་འདོད་ལས་བྱས་པ། །སྡུག་བསྔལ་དེ་ནི་ཉིད་ཀྱིས་མྱོང་བར་གྱིས།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-009-112"/>“ ‘The karma you yourself committed ripens within you. Having come here due to your own karma, Just as you previously committed undesirable deeds, So you now experience this suffering.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-328">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-113</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ཚེ་ཕ་མ་རང་གི་ཆུང་མ་རྣམས།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-009-113"/>“ ‘At this time, your parents and your spouse</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-329">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-113</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།སྡུག་བསྔལ་ཉེན་པ་ཡོངས་སུ་ཐར་མི་བྱེད།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Also do not escape the torments of suffering.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-330">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-113</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ལེགས་པའི་ལས་བྱས་པས་ནི་གྲོལ་བར་འགྱུར།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>You will be liberated by well-performed actions.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-331">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-114</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ལྟར་ཁྱིམ་ནི་ཡོངས་སུ་སྤང་བར་བྱ། །ཁུ་སྒོ་དབྱུག་པ་ལྟུང་གི་ཆད་པ་རྣམས། །སུ་ཞིག་སྤོང་འདོད་ཞི་བ་དོན་གཉེར་བས།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Accordingly, you should completely abandon the home. <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-009-114"/>“ ‘Striving for the goal of peace with the wish to abandon The punishments of transgressions involving fetters and bludgeons,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-332">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-114</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཁྱིམ་ལ་འཇིགས་པར་གྱིས་ཏེ་སྤང་བྱོས་ལ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>You should fear the home and thus abandon it!</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-333">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-115</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།འཇིག་རྟེན་མཁས་པའི་བསྟན་ལ་ཆོས་སྤྱོད་ཅིག །ཁྱིམ་ནི་རབ་འབར་སྡུག་བསྔལ་མང་པོའི་རྩ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>You should practice the Dharma, the teaching of one who is wise about the world. <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-009-115"/>“ ‘The home is the root of manifold miseries that blaze forth.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-334">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-115</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།སེམས་ལས་བྱུང་བ་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་རྟག་ཏུ་འབར།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Ever ablaze once it has arisen in the mind,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-335">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-115</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།མེ་མུར་འོབས་འདྲ་འཇིགས་པར་བྱེད་པ་ལ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>It is terrifying like a pit of hot coals.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-336">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-115</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།མཁས་པ་སུ་ཞིག་དེ་ལ་སྲེད་པ་སྐྱེད།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>What wise person would arouse craving for that?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-337">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-116</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཁྱིམ་གནས་བུ་དང་ཆུང་མའི་མྱ་ངན་བྱེད།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-009-116"/>“ ‘Home life brings the sorrows of children and spouse.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-338">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-116</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཁྱིམ་གནས་དེ་བཞིན་ལོངས་སྤྱོད་མྱ་ངན་བྱེད།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The enjoyments of home life likewise bring sorrow.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-339">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-116</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཉེས་པ་འདི་དང་གཞན་ཡང་དཔག་མེད་དེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The drawbacks of these, moreover, are immeasurable.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-340">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-116</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ལྟས་ཁྱིམ་ནི་ཡོངས་སུ་སྤང་བར་བྱ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>In this regard, the home should be totally abandoned.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-341">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-117</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།འདྲེན་པ་རྣམས་ཀྱི་བསྟན་ལ་དགའ་བྱེད་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-009-117"/>“ ‘The teachings of spiritual guides bring joy.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-342">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-117</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།མ་བཏབ་མ་རྨོས་བདེ་དང་ཡིད་བདེའི་རྒྱུ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Without needing to sow or plough, they cause happiness and satisfaction.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-343">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-117</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།སྡུག་བསྔལ་མང་པོའི་རྩ་བ་ཁྱིམ་འདི་ལ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The root of manifold miseries is the home.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-344">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-117</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།བླུན་པོ་དགའ་ཡི་མཁས་པ་གཞར་མི་དགའ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Joy for the fool, it is not enjoyable to the wise.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-345">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-118</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།པགས་པ་ཆུ་རྒྱུས་ཤ་དང་རུས་པའི་ལུས།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-009-118"/>“ ‘This body of skin, ligaments and nerves, flesh, and bones</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-346">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-118</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།འདི་ནི་ང་ཡི་ཆུང་མ་<tei:ref folio="F.202.b"/>འདུ་ཤེས་བསྐྱེད།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Creates the notion my spouse.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-347">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-118</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།བྱིས་པ་རྨོངས་པ་འདོད་ཆགས་སྐྱེད་པར་བྱེད།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Deluded, childish people develop attachment to it,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-348">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-118</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།བུད་མེད་སྒྱུ་མ་ལྟ་བུར་ཡོང་མ་ཤེས།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Not knowing that the spouse is like an illusion.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-349">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-119</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཤེས་རབ་ལྡན་པས་ཁྱིམ་གྱི་ཉེས་རིག་ནས།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-009-119"/>“ ‘Knowing the drawbacks of the home,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-350">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-119</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ཕྱིར་འདོད་པའི་དགའ་བ་ཀུན་སྤངས་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Those with insight thus abandon the joys they desire.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-351">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-119</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཆོས་ལ་སྨན་གྱི་འདུ་ཤེས་བཞག་བྱས་ནས།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Having affirmed the notion that Dharma is medicine,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-352">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-119</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།མ་ཆགས་ཁྱིམ་ནས་མྱུར་དུ་འབྱུང་བར་བྱེད།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They swiftly leave the home without attachment.’ ”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-353">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-120</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ནས་ཁྱིམ་བདག་དཔས་བྱིན་དང་། ཁྱིམ་བདག་ལྔ་བརྒྱ་ཙམ་དེ་དག་གིས་ཆོས་ཀྱི་རྣམ་གྲངས་འདི་ཐོས་ནས་མི་སྐྱེ་བའི་ཆོས་ལ་བཟོད་པ་ཐོབ་པར་གྱུར་ཏོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-009-120"/>At this point, the householder Vīradatta and the five hundred householders, having heard this Dharma discourse, attained the acceptance that phenomena are unborn.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-354">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-120</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་དག་བཟོད་པ་ཐོབ་ནས་མཆོག་ཏུ་དགའ་བ་དང་མགུ་བར་གྱུར་ཏེ་དེའི་ཚེ་ཚིགས་སུ་བཅད་པ་འདི་དག་གསོལ་ཏོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Having gained this acceptance, they were overjoyed and pleased. On that occasion, they spoke the following verses:</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-355">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-121</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།སངས་རྒྱས་ཆོས་ལ་འདོད་གྱུར་ནས།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-009-121"/>“Desiring the qualities of a buddha,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-356">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-121</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།གང་དག་གིས་ནི་སེམས་བསྐྱེད་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>We cultivate the resolve for awakening.<tei:note xml:id="UT22084-043-009-122"/>
                </seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-357">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-121</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཀྱེ་མ་རྙེད་པ་རྙེད་པ་ཆེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Hey! This discovery, this great discovery,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-358">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-123</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།འདི་ནི་རྙེད་པ་ཀུན་གྱི་མཆོག །བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་ནི་དགའ་བ་སྟེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Is the best of all discoveries! <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-009-123"/>“The resolve for awakening is joyful.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-359">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-123</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།སེམས་ཅན་ཐམས་ཅད་བདེ་བགྱིད་པའི། །སེམས་འདིར་སུ་དག་དགའ་སྐྱེད་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Those who here cultivate this resolve, Which brings happiness to all sentient beings,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-360">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-123</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་དག་འཚོ་བ་ལེགས་པར་འཚོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Will live a good life.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-361">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-124</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།སེམས་ཅན་ཀུན་ལ་ཕན་བགྱིད་པའི། །སེམས་འདི་གང་དག་བསྐྱེད་གྱུར་པ། །དེ་དག་སེམས་ཅན་ཐམས་ཅད་དགའ། །དེ་དག་མཐོང་ན་དགའ་བར་འགྱུར།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-009-124"/>“Whoever cultivates this resolve, Which benefits all sentient beings, Will be overjoyed when they see That all sentient beings are joyful.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-362">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-125</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་ལ་སུ་དགའ་བ། །དེ་དག་ལུས་ནི་གསེར་འདྲ་ཞིང་། །མཚན་གྱིས་ཤིན་ཏུ་སྤྲས་པ་དང་། །འཇིག་རྟེན་སྣང་བར་བྱེད་པར་འགྱུར།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-009-125"/>“Those who delight in the resolve for awakening Will become illuminators of the world, With bodies like gold And fully adorned with the special marks.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-363">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-126</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་ནི་སེམས་ཆེ་སྟེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-009-126"/>“The resolve for awakening is a great resolve.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-364">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-126</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།སེམས་ཀུན་ནང་ན་དགེ་བ་མཆོག །ཡོན་ཏན་ཐམས་ཅད་ཕུན་སུམ་ཚོགས།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>It is the supreme happiness among all sentient beings. It is the most excellent of all qualities.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-365">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-126</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ནད་ཀུན་རབ་ཏུ་ཞི་བར་བགྱིད།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>It pacifies all illness.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-366">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-127</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།སེམས་ཅན་བསོད་ནམས་ཆུང་ངུ་རྣམས།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-009-127"/>“Sentient beings of little merit</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-367">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-127</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་ནི་འདོད་མི་བགྱིད།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Do not wish for the resolve for awakening.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-368">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-127</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།འཁོར་བ་ལ་ནི་མི་རྟོག་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They do not think of it in saṃsāra,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-369">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-127</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་ཀྱིས་སྐྱོ་བར་འགྱུར།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>And the resolve for awakening makes them weary.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-370">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-128</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་ཀྱི་བསོད་ནམས་གང་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-009-128"/>“If the merits of the resolve for awakening</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-371">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-128</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ལ་གལ་ཏེ་གཟུགས་མཆིས་ན།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Were to assume physical form,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-372">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-128</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ནམ་མཁའི་ཁམས་ནི་ཀུན་གང་སྟེ། །དེ་ནི་དེ་བས་ལྷག་པར་འགྱུར།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They would fill the whole expanse of space And exceed even that.<tei:note xml:id="UT22084-043-009-129"/>
                </seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-373">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-130</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།གང་གཱའི་བྱེ་མའི་གྲངས་སྙེད་ཀྱི། །སངས་རྒྱས་ཞིང་རྣམས་མི་གང་གིས། །རིན་ཆེན་དག་གིས་རབ་བཀང་སྟེ། །འཇིག་རྟེན་མགོན་ལ་ཕུལ་བ་བས།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-009-130"/>“If someone were to fill with jewels As many buddha fields as there are grains of sand In the Ganges River, As an offering to the Protector of the World,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-374">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-131</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།གང་གིས་ཐལ་མོ་སྦྱར་བགྱིས་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-009-131"/>“This offering would be surpassed</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-375">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-131</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།བྱང་ཆུབ་ཏུ་ནི་སེམས་བཏུད་ན། །མཆོད་པ་འདི་ནི་ཁྱད་པར་འཕགས།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>When someone with joined palms Directs their resolve toward awakening,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-376">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-131</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ལ་མཐའ་ནི་མ་མཆིས་<tei:ref folio="F.203.a"/>སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Because that does not have a limit.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-377">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-132</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་ནི་ཅི་འདྲ་བ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-009-132"/>“What is the resolve for awakening like?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-378">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-132</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དྲང་སྲོང་མཆོག་གིས་བསྟན་མཛད་པའི།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Transmitted by the exalted Seer,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-379">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-132</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་འདྲའི་མཆོད་པ་གཞན་མ་མཆིས།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>There is no other offering like it.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-380">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-132</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དཔལ་ཡང་གཞན་ནི་མཆིས་མ་ལགས།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>There is nothing so magnificent.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-381">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-133</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།སྨན་གྱི་དམ་པ་ནད་མ་མཆིས།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-009-133"/>“The best of medicines for being without illness,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-382">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-133</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་ནི་ཡོན་ཏན་ལྡན།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The resolve for awakening possesses all good qualities.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-383">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-133</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ནད་ཀུན་རབ་ཏུ་ཞི་བར་བགྱིད།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>It thoroughly quells all illnesses.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-384">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-134</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།སེམས་ཅན་ཐམས་ཅད་བདེ་བར་བགྱིད། །མེ་གསུམ་དག་གིས་གདུངས་པ་ཡི། །སེམས་ཅན་སྡུག་བསྔལ་མཐོང་ནས་ནི།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>It makes all sentient beings happy. <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-009-134"/>“Having witnessed the suffering of sentient beings Tormented by the three fires,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-385">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-134</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།བསྐལ་པ་དཔག་ཏུ་མེད་པར་སྤྱོད།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The wise practice for immeasurable eons,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-386">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-134</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།མཁས་རྣམས་སྐྱོ་བར་ཡང་མི་འགྱུར།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Never becoming discouraged.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-387">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-135</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།གང་དག་བྱང་ཆུབ་སྤྱད་སྤྱོད་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-009-135"/>“Those who perform practices dedicated to awakening</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-388">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-135</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དཔའ་བོ་སྨན་པའི་རྒྱལ་པོ་འདྲ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Are heroes comparable to the king of physicians.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-389">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-135</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་དག་སེམས་ཅན་སྡུག་བསྔལ་སྐྱོབ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Protecting beings from suffering,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-390">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-135</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།སྐྱོ་བ་རྟག་ཏུ་རྣམ་པར་སྤངས།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They always abandon discouragement.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-391">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-136</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དཔའ་བོ་སངས་རྒྱས་ཆོས་འཚལ་བ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-009-136"/>“These heroes seek the qualities of a buddha.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-392">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-136</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།འགྲོ་བའི་སྐྱེ་བ་ཐམས་ཅད་དུ། །སེམས་དེ་འདོར་བར་མི་བགྱིད་ཅིང་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They never give up that resolve Throughout all their rebirths in transmigration,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-393">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-136</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་དག་བརྟུལ་ཞུགས་དེ་ཡང་སྟོན།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>And they also teach this discipline.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-394">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-137</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།སེམས་འདི་ལ་ནི་གང་དགའ་བ། །ཤཱཀྱ་སེང་གེ་མི་ཡི་མཆོག །སངས་རྒྱས་ཅི་འདྲ་དེ་འདྲར་འགྱུར།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-009-137"/>“We who delight in this resolve Become the best of humans, Just like the Lion of the Śākyas.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-395">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-137</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།བདག་ཅག་རྙེད་པ་ལེགས་པར་རྙེད།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>We properly discover what is to be discovered.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-396">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-138</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་དེའི་ཚེ་འཛུམ་པ་མཛད་དོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-009-138"/>Then the Blessed One smiled.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-397">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-138</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།འདི་ནི་སངས་རྒྱས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་རྣམས་གང་གི་ཚེ་འཛུམ་པ་མཛད་པ་ན་སངས་རྒྱས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་རྣམས་ཀྱི་ཆོས་ཉིད་དེ། བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱི་ཞལ་གྱི་སྒོ་ནས་འོད་འཕྲོ་བ་ཁ་དོག་སྣ་ཚོགས་ཁ་དོག་དུ་མ་བྱུང་བ་འདི་ལྟ་སྟེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The nature of buddhas, of blessed ones, is such that when they smile, light of many colors appears from their mouth:</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-398">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-138</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྔོན་པོ་དང་། སེར་པོ་དང་། དམར་པོ་དང་། དཀར་པོ་དང་། ལེ་བརྒན་དང་། ཤེལ་དང་། དངུལ་གྱི་ཁ་དོག་ལྟ་བུ་དག་སྟེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>blue, yellow, red, white, violet, crystal, and silver.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-399">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-138</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འོད་དེས་འཇིག་རྟེན་གྱི་ཁམས་མཐའ་ཡས་མུ་མེད་པ་དག་ཁྱབ་པར་བྱས་ནས་ཚངས་པའི་འཇིག་རྟེན་གྱི་བར་དུ་མངོན་པར་བྱུང་སྟེ་ཉི་ཟླ་རྣམས་ཀྱི་གཟི་བརྗིད་ཟད་པར་བྱས་ནས་སླར་ལོག་སྟེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>These lights, after pervading the world systems without end and rising up to the worlds of Brahmā, filled the entire world with the radiance of the sun and moon.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-400">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-138</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ལ་ལན་གསུམ་བསྐོར་བ་བྱས་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱི་དབུའི་གཙུག་ཏུ་ནུབ་བོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They then came back down and, having circumambulated the Blessed One three times, disappeared into the Blessed One’s head.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-401">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-139</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ནས་ཚེ་དང་ལྡན་པ་ཀུན་དགའ་བོ་སྟན་ལས་ལངས་ཏེ་བླ་གོས་ཕྲག་པ་གཅིག་ཏུ་གཟར་ནས་པུས་མོ་གཡས་པའི་ལྷ་ང་ས་ལ་བཙུགས་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-009-139"/>At this point, Venerable Ānanda arose from his seat and, placing his robe over one shoulder, knelt on his right knee.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-402">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-139</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ག་ལ་བ་དེ་ལོགས་སུ་ཐལ་མོ་སྦྱར་བ་བཏུད་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ལ་འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་གསོལ་<tei:ref folio="F.203.b"/>ཏོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>With palms pressed together in the direction the Blessed One, he spoke the following words to the Blessed One:</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-403">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-139</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་རྒྱུ་མ་མཆིས། རྐྱེན་མ་མཆིས་པར་ནི་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་དགྲ་བཅོམ་པ་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་སངས་རྒྱས་རྣམས་འཛུམ་པ་མི་མཛད་ན། འཛུམ་པ་མཛད་པའི་རྒྱུ་གང་ལགས།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Blessed One, since the thus-gone, worthy, completely awakened buddhas do not smile without a cause, without a reason, what is the cause for your smile?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-404">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-139</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྐྱེན་གང་ལགས།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>What is the reason?”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-405">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-140</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེའི་ཚེ་ཚིགས་སུ་བཅད་པ་འདི་དག་ཀྱང་གསོལ་ཏོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-009-140"/>On this occasion, he requested an answer with these verses:</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-406">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-141</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།རྒྱུ་མ་མཆིས་པར་རྣམ་འདྲེན་རྒྱལ་བ་མཆོག །སངས་རྒྱས་སྐྱོབ་པ་འཛུམ་པ་མི་སྟོན་ན།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-009-141"/>“If the leader, the supreme Victorious One, The Buddha, the protector, does not reveal his smile without cause,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-407">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-141</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཅི་སླད་བཅོམ་ལྡན་ཁྱོད་ཀྱིས་འཛུམ་མཛད་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Why do you smile, Blessed One?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-408">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-141</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།འཇིག་རྟེན་ཕན་དགོངས་ཐུགས་བརྩེ་བདག་ལ་གསུངས།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>I speak out of heartfelt kindness and with the intention to benefit the world.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-409">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-142</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།ཁྱོད་ཀྱིས་ཅི་སླད་དེ་རིང་འཛུམ་བསྟན་གསུངས།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-009-142"/>“Why do you reveal this smile today?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-410">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-142</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།བཀའ་མཆིད་ཆེ་ལྡན་ནོར་མཆོག་སྦྱིན་མཛད་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Please give us the supreme jewel of your superb advice,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-411">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-142</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དབུལ་པོར་གྱུར་པ་ནོར་དང་ལྡན་པར་མཛོད།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>A treasury of wealth for the poor.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-412">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-142</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།འཇིག་རྟེན་ལྡོངས་ལ་མྱུར་དུ་མིག་ཀྱང་སྩོལ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Please quickly offer these eyes for the blind in the world.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-413">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-143</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་སྐད་ཅེས་གསོལ་པ་དང་། བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་ཚེ་དང་ལྡན་པ་ཀུན་དགའ་བོ་ལ་བཀའ་སྩལ་པ། ཀུན་དགའ་བོ་ཁྱོད་ཀྱིས་གང་དག་བླ་ན་མེད་པ་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་བྱང་ཆུབ་ཏུ་སེམས་བསྐྱེད་ནས་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པའི་གན་དུ་ལྷགས་པའི་ཁྱིམ་བདག་ལྔ་བརྒྱ་ཙམ་འདི་དག་མཐོང་ངམ། གསོལ་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-009-143"/>After Venerable Ānanda spoke these words, the Blessed One replied, “Ānanda, do you see, near the Tathāgata, these five hundred householders who have produced the resolve for unsurpassable, complete and perfect awakening?”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-414">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-143</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་མཐོང་ལགས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“I see them, Blessed One,” he replied.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-415">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-143</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།བདེ་བར་གཤེགས་པ་མཐོང་ལགས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“I see them, Tathāgata.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-416">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-145</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་བཀའ་སྩལ་པ། ཀུན་དགའ་བོ་ཁྱིམ་བདག་ལྔ་བརྒྱ་ཙམ་འདི་དག་གིས་ཆོས་ཀྱི་རྣམ་གྲངས་འདི་ཐོས་ནས་མི་སྐྱེ་བའི་ཆོས་ལ་བཟོད་པ་ཐོབ་སྟེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-009-145"/>Then the Blessed One said, “Ānanda, when these five hundred householders have heard the Dharma discourses, they will attain the acceptance that phenomena are unborn.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-417">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-145</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཀུན་དགའ་བོ་ཁྱིམ་བདག་འདི་དག་ཐམས་ཅད་ནི་སྔོན་གྱི་རྒྱལ་བ་ལ་ལྷག་པར་བྱ་བ་བྱས་པ། དགེ་བའི་རྩ་བ་བསྐྱེད་པ། སངས་རྒྱས་བྱེ་བ་ཁྲག་ཁྲིག་བརྒྱ་སྟོང་མང་པོ་ལ་བསྙེན་བཀུར་བྱས་པ་དག་སྟེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Ānanda, these householders will all perform outstanding deeds for the victorious ones of the past, cultivate the roots of virtue, and pay homage to the many billions of buddhas.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-418">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-145</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཁྱིམ་བདག་འདི་དག་འདི་ནས་ཤི་འཕོས་ནས་ནམ་དུ་ཡང་ངན་འགྲོ་ལོག་པར་ལྟུང་བར་འགྲོ་བར་མི་འགྱུར་ཞིང་ཕྱིས་ཀྱང་ལྷ་དང་མི་རྣམས་ཀྱི་ནང་དུ་བདེ་བ་མྱོང་ནས་མཐར་གྱིས་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་དགྲ་བཅོམ་པ་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་སངས་རྒྱས་བྱམས་པ་མཉེས་པར་བྱེད་ཅིང་ཐུགས་བྱུང་བར་མི་བྱེད་དེ་བསྟི་སྟང་བྱེད་པར་འགྱུར། བཙུན་པར་བྱེད་པར་འགྱུར། རིམ་གྲོ་བྱེད་པར་འགྱུར། མཆོད་པ་བྱེད་པར་འགྱུར་རོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>When these householders have transmigrated from here after dying, they will never fall into lower destinies, and having later experienced happiness among gods and humans, they will eventually revere, honor, serve, and worship the thus-gone, worthy, complete and perfect Buddha Maitreya, delighting and never displeasing him.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-419">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-145</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།བསྐལ་པ་བཟང་པོའི་སངས་རྒྱས་<tei:ref folio="F.204.a"/>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱང་མཉེས་པར་བྱེད་ཅིང་ཐུགས་བྱུང་བར་མི་བྱེད་དེ་བསྟི་སྟང་བྱེད་པར་འགྱུར། བཙུན་པར་བྱེད་པར་འགྱུར། རིམ་གྲོ་བྱེད་པར་འགྱུར། མཆོད་པ་བྱེད་པར་འགྱུར་རོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They will also revere, honor, serve, and worship all the buddhas, blessed ones, of this fortunate eon, delighting and never displeasing them.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-420">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-145</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།སངས་རྒྱས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་དེ་དག་ལས་ཆོས་ཀྱང་ཉན་པར་འགྱུར་ཏེ། ཐོས་ནས་ཀྱང་འཛིན་པར་འགྱུར། ཀུན་ཆུབ་པར་བྱེད་པར་འགྱུར། གཞན་དག་ལ་ཡང་རྒྱ་ཆེར་རབ་ཏུ་སྟོན་པར་འགྱུར་རོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They will listen to the Dharma from those buddhas, those blessed ones, and having heard it, they will retain it, master it, and teach it extensively to others.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-421">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-145</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེའི་འོག་ཏུ་བསྐལ་པ་ཉི་ཤུ་རྩ་ལྔ་ན། སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱི་ཞིང་ཐ་དད་པ་དག་ཏུ་བླ་ན་མེད་པ་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་བྱང་ཆུབ་མངོན་པར་རྫོགས་པར་འཚང་རྒྱ་སྟེ། དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་དགྲ་བཅོམ་པ་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་སངས་རྒྱས་པད་མའི་དཔལ་གྱི་སྙིང་པོ་ཞེས་བྱ་བར་མཚན་འཐུན་པར་འཇིག་རྟེན་དུ་འབྱུང་བར་འགྱུར་རོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>After twenty-five eons, they will awaken to unsurpassable, complete and perfect awakening in various buddha fields, and they will equally appear in the world bearing the name thus-gone, worthy, complete and perfect Buddha Padmaśrīgarbha.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-422">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-146</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ལ་ཚེ་དང་ལྡན་པ་ཀུན་དགའ་བོས་འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་གསོལ་ཏོ། །ཀྱེ་མ་ཆོས་ཀྱི་རྣམ་གྲངས་འདི་འདི་ལྟར་རྒྱ་ཆེ་བ་ནི་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ངོ་མཚར་ཏོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-009-146"/>At this point, the venerable Ānanda said to the Blessed One, “Ah, how wonderful is this extensive Dharma discourse, Blessed One!</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-423">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-146</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།བདེ་བར་གཤེགས་པ་ངོ་མཚར་ཏོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>It is so wonderful, Sugata.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-424">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-146</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཆོས་ཀྱི་རྣམ་གྲངས་འདིའི་མིང་ཅི་ལགས། འདི་ཇི་ལྟར་གཟུང་བར་བགྱི། བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་བཀའ་སྩལ་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Blessed One, what is the name of this Dharma discourse? How should we remember it?”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-425">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-147</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཀུན་དགའ་བོ་དེའི་ཕྱིར་ཆོས་ཀྱི་རྣམ་གྲངས་འདི་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའི་རྣལ་འབྱོར་སྤྱོད་པའི་ས་བསྟན་པ་ཞེས་བྱ་བར་ཟུང་ཤིག །དཔས་བྱིན་གྱིས་ཞུས་པ་ཞེས་བྱ་བར་ཡང་ཟུང་ཤིག །བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་དེ་སྐད་ཅེས་བཀའ་སྩལ་ནས།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-009-147"/>The Blessed One replied, “In this regard, Ānanda, this Dharma discourse is called The Teaching on the Stages of Yoga for Bodhisattvas,<tei:note xml:id="UT22084-043-009-148"/> and this is how it should be remembered. It should also be remembered as The Questions of Vīradatta.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-426">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-149</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཚེ་དང་ལྡན་པ་ཀུན་དགའ་བོ་དང་། དགེ་སློང་དེ་དག་དང་། བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་དེ་དག་དང་། ཁྱིམ་བདག་ལྔ་བརྒྱ་ཙམ་དེ་དག་དང་། ལྷ་དང་། མི་དང་། ལྷ་མ་ཡིན་དང་། དྲི་ཟར་བཅས་པའི་འཇིག་རྟེན་ཡི་རངས་ཏེ། བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་གསུངས་པ་ལ་མངོན་པར་བསྟོད་དོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-009-149"/>When the Blessed One had uttered these words, the venerable Ānanda, the monks, the bodhisattvas, the five hundred householders, and the world with its gods, humans, asuras, and gandharvas all rejoiced and praised what had been proclaimed by the Blessed One.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-009-TU-427">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-009-150</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།འཕགས་པ་དཀོན་མཆོག་བརྩེགས་པ་ཆེན་པོའི་ཆོས་ཀྱི་རྣམ་གྲངས་ལེའུ་སྟོང་ཕྲག་བརྒྱ་པ་ལས་ཁྱིམ་བདག་དཔས་བྱིན་གྱིས་ཞུས་པའི་ལེའུ་ཞེས་བྱ་སྟེ་ཉི་ཤུ་རྩ་བརྒྱད་པ་རྫོགས་སོ།། །།རྒྱ་གར་གྱི་མཁན་པོ་ཛི་ན་མི་ཏྲ་དང་། དཱ་ན་ཤཱི་ལ་དང་། ཞུ་ཆེན་གྱི་ལོཙྪ་བ་བན་དེ་ཡེ་ཤེས་སྡེས་བསྒྱུར་<tei:ref folio="F.204.b"/>ཅིང་ཞུས་ཏེ་སྐད་གསར་ཆད་ཀྱིས་ཀྱང་བཅོས་ནས་གཏན་ལ་ཕབ་པ།། །།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-009-150"/>This concludes The Questions of the Householder Vīradatta, the twenty-eighth of the one hundred thousand sections of the Dharma discourse known as The Noble Great Heap of Jewels.<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-009-151"/> Translated, edited, and finalized according to the new terminological register by the Indian preceptors Jinamitra and Dānaśīla, and the chief editor-translator Bandé Yeshé Dé.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
</body>
</tmx>