<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tmx xmlns="http://www.lisa.org/tmx14" xmlns:eft="http://read.84000.co/ns/1.0" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<header creationtool="linguae-dharmae/84000" datatype="PlainText" segtype="block" adminlang="en-us" srclang="bo" o-tmf="TEI" eft:text-id="UT22084-043-010" eft:text-version="v-1.0.4-2023"/>
<body>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-1">
    <prop type="location-id">translation</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>
                    <tei:ref folio="F.204.b"/>འཕགས་པ་དཀོན་མཆོག་བརྩེགས་པ་ཆེན་པོའི་ཆོས་ཀྱི་རྣམ་གྲངས་ལེའུ་སྟོང་ཕྲག་བརྒྱ་པ་ལས་ལེའུ་ཉི་ཤུ་དགུ་པ་སྟེ་བད་སའི་རྒྱལ་པོ་འཆར་བྱེད་ཀྱིས་ཞུས་པ། བམ་པོ་གཅིག་པ། རྒྱ་གར་སྐད་དུ། ཨཱརྱ་ཨུ་ད་ཡ་ན་བད་ས་རཱ་ཛ་པ་རི་པྲྀཙྪཱ་ནཱ་མ་པ་རི་བརྟ། བོད་སྐད་དུ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg/>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-2">
    <prop type="location-id">translation</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཕགས་པ་བད་སའི་རྒྱལ་པོ་འཆར་བྱེད་ཀྱིས་ཞུས་པ་ཞེས་བྱ་བའི་ལེའུ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The Noble Episode King Udayana of Vatsa’s Questions</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-3">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-68</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སངས་རྒྱས་དང་། བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཐམས་ཅད་ལ་ཕྱག་འཚལ་ལོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-68"/>Homage to all buddhas and bodhisattvas.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-4">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-68</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདི་སྐད་བདག་གིས་ཐོས་པ་དུས་གཅིག་ན།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Thus did I hear at one time.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-5">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-68</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀཽ་ཤམྦཱི་ན། དབྱངས་ཅན་གྱི་ཀུན་དགའ་ར་བ་ན་དགེ་སློང་ལྔ་བརྒྱ་ཙམ་གྱི་དགེ་སློང་གི་དགེ་འདུན་ཆེན་པོ་དང་། བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོ་རབ་ཏུ་མང་པོ་དང་ཐབས་ཅིག་ཏུ་བཞུགས་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The Blessed One was dwelling in the Sarasvatī grove in Kauśāmbī with a great assembly of some five hundred monks and numerous bodhisattva great beings.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-6">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-68</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེའི་ཚེ་ན་མ་དུའི་བུ་མོ་བཙུན་མོ་དཔེ་མེད་ཕྲག་དོག་དང་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>At that time, Queen Anupamā, daughter of Mākandika, was overcome with jealousy and envy toward Queen Śyāmāvatī.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-7">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-72</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སེར་སྣས་ཟིན་པས་བཙུན་མོ་སྔོ་སངས་ཅན་ལ་ལྷག་པར་དམིགས་ནས་བད་སའི་རྒྱལ་པོ་འཆར་བྱེད་ལ་ལྷ་མཁྱེན་པར་མཛད་དུ་གསོལ། བཙུན་མོ་སྔོ་སངས་ཅན་ལ་སོགས་པ་བུད་མེད་ལྔ་བརྒྱ་ནི་དགེ་སྦྱོང་གཽ་ཏ་མ་དང་ལྷན་ཅིག་ཏུ་རབ་ཏུ་སྐྱོན་ཆགས་པར་བགྱིད་དེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-72"/>Queen Anupamā, daughter of Mākandika, addressed King Udayana of Vatsa: “Your Majesty, five hundred women, including Queen Śyāmāvatī, have committed dishonorable acts with Gautama the mendicant.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-8">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-72</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེའི་སླད་དུ་བདག་གིས་ལྷ་ལ་གསོལ་བ་ལགས་ཀྱིས་ཇི་ལྟར་མཁྱེན་པ་དེ་བཞིན་དུ་མཛད་དུ་གསོལ་ཞེས་བརྫུན་གྱི་ཚིག་གིས་དབྱེན་བྱས་པར་གྱུར་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>I humbly request Your Majesty to act as you see fit with regard to this situation.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-9">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-73</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་བད་སའི་རྒྱལ་པོ་འཆར་བྱེད་མ་དུའི་བུ་མོ་བཙུན་མོ་དཔེ་མེད་ཀྱིས་དབྱེན་བྱས་པས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་དང་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-73"/>With these lies, Queen Anupamā, daughter of Mākandika, sowed her discord.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-10">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-73</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཉན་ཐོས་ཀྱི་དགེ་འདུན་རྣམས་ལ་ཐ་བ་དང་། འཁྲུག་པ་དང་། ཁྲོ་བ་སྐྱེས་པར་གྱུར་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Rage, aggression, and wrath toward the Blessed One and the assembly of disciples welled up in King Udayana of Vatsa.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-11">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-73</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ཡི་མ་རངས་ཤིང་ཁྲོ་བ་དང་། རྔམ་པས་ཟིལ་གྱིས་ནོན་པས་བཙུན་མོ་སྔོ་སངས་ཅན་གསད་པའི་ཕྱིར་གཞུ་བདུངས་ནས་མདའ་སྟེའུ་ཀ་ཉ་རྔ་མ་བླངས་ཏེ་འཕངས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Miserable and overcome with a wrathful fury, he drew his bow and shot a razor-sharp arrow at Queen Śyāmāvatī with murderous intent.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-12">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-74</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་དེའི་མོད་ལ་བཙུན་མོ་སྔོ་སངས་ཅན་གྱིས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་དགྲ་བཅོམ་པ་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་སངས་རྒྱས་ལ་ཕྱག་འཚལ་ལོ་ཞེས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ལ་ཕྱག་བྱས་ཤིང་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱི་བསྔགས་པ་བརྗོད་ནས་བྱམས་པའི་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་ལ་སྙོམས་པར་ཞུགས་སོ། <tei:ref folio="F.205.a"/>
                </seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-74"/>In that instant, Queen Śyāmāvatī called out, “Homage to the Blessed One, the thus-gone, worthy, perfect Buddha!” She prostrated herself to the Blessed One, praised him, and entered into meditative absorption on loving-kindness.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-13">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-74</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་འདི་ལྟར་སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱི་མཐུས་མདའ་སྟེའུ་ཀ་ཉ་རྔ་མ་དེ་དེ་ནས་ཕྱིར་ལོག་སྟེ། བད་སའི་རྒྱལ་པོ་འཆར་བྱེད་དེ་ཉིད་ཀྱི་མགོའི་དྲང་ཐད་ཀྱི་སྟེང་གི་བར་སྣང་ལ་འབར།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Through the power of the Buddha, the razor-sharp arrow turned back and burst into flames directly above King Udayana of Vatsa’s head.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-14">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-74</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རབ་ཏུ་འབར། ཀུན་ཏུ་རབ་ཏུ་མཆེད་དེ་འབར་ཞིང་མེ་ལྕེ་གཅིག་ཏུ་གྱུར་ཏེ་ཕར་འགྲོ་ཚུར་འགྲོ་ཞིང་འདུག་འདུག་ནས།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>As it burned and blazed, it became a single flame, sometimes moving about and sometimes standing still.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-15">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-74</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བད་སའི་རྒྱལ་པོ་འཆར་བྱེད་ག་ལ་བ་དེར་སོང་ནས་བད་སའི་རྒྱལ་པོ་འཆར་བྱེད་ཀྱི་གཡོན་རོལ་ལོགས་སུ་འདུག་པར་གྱུར་ཏེ། དེ་ལུས་ལ་ནི་མ་ཕོག་གོ །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Then, moving toward King Udayana of Vatsa, the arrow remained on his right side without touching his body.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-16">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-75</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལན་གཉིས་ལན་གསུམ་དུ་དེ་ལྟར་གྱུར་པ་དང་། དེ་ནས་བཙུན་མོ་སྔོ་སངས་ཅན་གྱིས་བད་སའི་རྒྱལ་པོ་འཆར་བྱེད་ལ་འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་སྨྲས་སོ། །རྒྱལ་པོ་ཆེན་པོ་དེ་ལྟ་ལགས་པས་གལ་ཏེ་ཁྱོད་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་ལ་ཕྱག་འཚལ་ན་ཁྱོད་ལ་ཡང་བདེ་ལེགས་སུ་འགྱུར་ལགས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-75"/>King Udayana of Vatsa shot two or three more arrows with the same result before Queen Śyāmāvatī said to him, “Great King, in this situation, if you were to prostrate to the Thus-Gone One, you too would find well-being.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-17">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-76</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་བད་སའི་རྒྱལ་པོ་འཆར་བྱེད་འཇིགས་ཤིང་དངངས་ལ་སྒྱིད་ལུག་ཅིང་སྤུ་ཟིང་ཞེས་བྱེད་པར་གྱུར་ཏེ་ས་ལ་འགྱེལ་ནས་བཙུན་མོ་སྔོ་སངས་ཅན་ལ་ཚིགས་སུ་བཅད་དེ་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-76"/>Full of terror and fear, King Udayana of Vatsa became weak, and his hair stood on end. Falling to the ground, he spoke these verses to Queen Śyāmāvatī: <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-77"/>“Are you a goddess or a gandharvī?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-18">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-76</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཁྱོད་ནི་ལྷ་མོ་འམ་དྲི་ཟ་མོ། །ཤ་ཟ་མོ་འམ་སྲིན་མོའམ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Are you a piśācī or a rākṣasī?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-19">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-76</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ངས་ནི་ཇི་ལྟར་གཟུང་བར་བྱ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>How is it that I should consider you?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-20">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-76</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ང་ཡིས་དྲིས་པ་དེ་སྨྲོས་ཤིག །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Answer my question thus.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-21">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-78</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་ལ་མཚོན་གྱིས་མི་གནོད་པའི། །བུད་མེད་འགའ་ཡང་ཡོད་མིན་ཏེ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-78"/>“There is no woman anywhere Who is not harmed by weapons.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-22">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-78</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ངས་ནི་འདི་ལ་གང་དུ་ཡང་། །ཐོས་སམ་མཐོང་ངམ་ཤེས་པའང་མེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>I have never heard of nor seen, Nor known of someone like that.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-23">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-79</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ང་ནི་སྟོབས་ལྡན་བརྩོན་འགྲུས་ཅན། །འཕོང་གི་ཤེས་པ་ལེགས་བསླབས་པས། །ང་ཡི་མདའ་ནི་གདོན་མི་ཟ། །ནམ་ཡང་མི་ཕོག་ཡོད་མིན་ཏེ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-79"/>“I am mighty and diligent And skilled in the art of archery; There is no doubting my arrow For never has it missed.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-24">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-80</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྤྲེའུ་འམ་ཡང་ན་བྱ་དང་ནི། །མིའམ་ཡང་ན་འབེམ་ཀྱང་རུང་། །གང་ལ་ང་ཡིས་མདའ་འཕངས་པ། །ནམ་ཡང་མི་ཕོག་ཡོད་མིན་ན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-80"/>“Whether it be monkeys or birds, No matter if it be men or targets, Wherever I shoot my arrow, Never yet has it missed its mark.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-25">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-81</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་རིང་མདའ་འདི་འཕངས་པ་ནི། །བཟློག་པའི་ཚུལ་དུ་ཕྱིར་འོངས་ཏེ། །ལུས་ལ་གནོད་པ་མེད་པར་ནི། །ང་ཡི་མདུན་དུ་འདུག་པར་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-81"/>“And yet today, this arrow that I shot Returned back as if counteracted, And—without any physical harm— It came to rest right in front of me.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-26">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-82</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཞན་གྱི་ཚིག་ནི་མཉན་ནས་ཀྱང་། །ང་ནི་ཁྱོད་ལ་གསོད་འདོད་པ། །ང་ནི་ཁྱོད་ལ་སྐྱབས་སུ་འགྲོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-82"/>“Having heeded the words of others, I desired to bring about your death, Yet now I go to you for protection.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-27">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-82</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྡུག་བསྔལ་གྱུར་པ་ང་ལ་སྐྱོབས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Please protect me, pitiful being that I am.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-28">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-83</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཕྱིན་ཅད་འདི་འདྲ་མི་བྱེད་ཀྱིས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-83"/>“Henceforth I will not act in this manner.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-29">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-83</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྡུག་བསྔལ་བ་ལ་དེང་བཟོད་ཀྱིས། །ཁྱོད་སྔོན་དགའ་བ་དྲན་བྱོས་ལ། །དང་བར་གྱིས་ཤིག་ཁྲོ་ཐུལ་ཅིག །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Please be patient with miserable beings, Recollect your past love for me, and Delight therein, curbing your wrath.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-30">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-83</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་བཙུན་མོ་སྔོ་སངས་ཅན་གྱིས་བད་སའི་རྒྱལ་པོ་འཆར་བྱེད་<tei:ref folio="F.205.b"/>ལ་ཚིགས་སུ་བཅད་དེ་སྨྲས་པ། །བདག་ནི་ལྷ་མིན་དྲི་ཟ་མིན། །ཤ་ཟ་མོ་མིན་སྲིན་མོ་མིན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-83"/>Queen Śyāmāvatī responded in verse to King Udayana of Vatsa: <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-86"/>“I am neither goddess nor gandharvī, Nor am I a piśācī or rākṣasī.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-31">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-83</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བདག་ནི་བཙུན་མོ་སྔོ་སངས་ཅན། །འཇིག་རྟེན་མགོན་པོའི་ཉན་ཐོས་མ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>I am the queen Śyāmāvatī, A disciple of the Lord of the World.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-32">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-87</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལྷ་ཁྱོད་ལ་ནི་སྙིང་བརྩེ་བས། །བདག་གི་སེམས་ནི་མཉམ་བཞག་གིས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-87"/>“Out of affection for Your Majesty, I rested my mind in meditative absorption.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-33">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-87</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཁྱབ་བདག་འཇིག་རྟེན་མགོན་པོ་ལ། །ཐུགས་ནི་རབ་ཏུ་དང་བར་མཛོད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Let your mind now develop faith In the sovereign master, the Lord of the World.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-34">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-88</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བསྐལ་པ་བྱེ་བ་སྟོང་རྣམས་སུ། །གང་གིས་བྱམས་པ་ལེགས་བསྒོམས་ཏེ། །བྱམས་ལ་གནས་པའི་སྐྱེས་བུ་དང་། །བུད་མེད་དག་ནི་མི་སོད་གསུངས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-88"/>“He has taught that one should not kill Any man or woman who has cultivated Loving-kindness for billions of eons, And who abides in loving-kindness.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-35">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-89</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་ཞིག་ལོ་ཏོག་སྨིན་པ་ལ། །སེར་ལྟར་ཡང་དག་ཇི་བཞིན་མཁྱེན། །བུད་མེད་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་གནོད་མེད་པ། །དེ་ཡི་བསྟན་ལ་བདག་དགའ་ལགས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-89"/>“He who is unharmed by women, And who knows the true nature of things, As one knows ripe grain by its golden color, It is in his teaching that I find joy.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-36">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-90</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇིག་རྟེན་མགོན་པོ་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱིས། །བུད་མེད་རྣམས་ནི་སྨད་པར་གསུངས། །བུད་མེད་རྣམས་ལ་མི་ལྟ་བ། །འཇིག་རྟེན་མགོན་པོ་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་བསྔགས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-90"/>“All the lords of the world Have taught that women are loathsome; Those who avoid gazing upon women Are exalted by the lords of the world.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-37">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-91</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སངས་རྒྱས་རྣམས་དང་རང་སངས་རྒྱས། །བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཉན་ཐོས་རྣམས། །བུད་མེད་བསྟེན་པར་མི་མཛད་དེ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-91"/>“Buddhas, pratyekabuddhas, Bodhisattvas, and disciples Do not indulge in women For it is but a foolish pursuit.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-38">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-92</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནི་བྱིས་པའི་སྤྱོད་ཡུལ་ལགས། །བུད་མེད་རྣམས་ལ་བསྟེན་པ་ནི། །ཀུན་ནས་བདུད་ཀྱི་ཞགས་པར་གསུངས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-92"/>“To indulge in women Is taught to be Māra’s noose.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-39">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-92</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྡིག་པ་རྣམས་ལ་ཆགས་པ་ནི། །ཀུན་འཇོམས་དཀྲུགས་པའི་ཤུལ་དང་འདྲ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Attachment to negative deeds Is a path to distress and destruction.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-40">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-94</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མི་མཁས་བུད་མེད་ཆགས་པ་དང་། །སྡིག་པའི་ལས་ནི་བགྱིས་པ་དང་། །ཡེ་ཤེས་སྤོང་བར་འཚལ་བ་ཡིས། །སེམས་ཅན་རྣམས་ནི་ངན་འགྲོར་ཁྲིད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-94"/>“The unwise who cling to women, Perform acts of wickedness, And seek to reject wisdom Will be led to the lower realms.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-41">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-95</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མཁས་པ་ཐར་བར་འཚལ་བ་ཡིས། །བུད་མེད་བསྟེན་པར་མི་བགྱི་སྟེ། །ཞུགས་གཏམས་ངུ་བ་མ་མཆིས་པའི། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-95"/>“The wise who wish for liberation Do not keep company with women.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-42">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-95</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དོང་དུ་མཆོངས་པ་མི་དངོ་ལགས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They do not jump into The pit of smokeless fire.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-43">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-96</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡིད་འོང་བཀའ་མཆིད་བགྱིས་པ་དང་། །བལྟས་པས་ཀྱང་ནི་འཆིང་བགྱིད་ཅིང་། །མི་བཟད་དམྱལ་བར་ལྟུང་བས་ན། །ཁྱོད་ནི་བུད་མེད་ཚིག་མ་གསན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-96"/>“Since they talk so attractively, And snare you with only a look, Then send you to the unbearable hells, Heed not the words of women!</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-44">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-97</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བདག་ནི་ཁྲོ་བ་མ་མཆིས་ཏེ། །བདག་གི་ཡིད་ནི་རབ་ཏུ་དང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-97"/>“I am not possessed of anger –— My mind is, instead, full of faith.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-45">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-97</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཁྱབ་བདག་འཇིག་རྟེན་མགོན་པོ་ལ། །ཐུགས་ནི་རབ་ཏུ་དང་བར་མཛོད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Let your mind, too, have faith In the sovereign master, the Lord of the World.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-46">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-98</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྒྱལ་པོ་ཆེན་པོ་བཞུད་མཛོད་དེ། །ཁྱོད་ཀྱིས་རྐང་གཉིས་མཆོག་གཟིགས་ལ། །དེ་ཡིས་ཆོས་ནི་གང་བསྟན་པ། །གཡེལ་མ་མཆིས་པར་ཁྱོད་ཀྱིས་གསོན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-98"/>“O Great King, be on your way And gaze upon the supreme human, Being mindful and paying heed To the Dharma that he teaches.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-47">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-99</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་<tei:ref folio="F.206.a"/>བད་སའི་རྒྱལ་པོ་འཆར་བྱེད་བཙུན་མོ་སྔོ་སངས་ཅན་གྱིས་བསྐུལ་བས་རྒྱལ་པོའི་མཐུ་ཆེན་པོ་དང་། རྒྱལ་པོའི་འབྱོར་པ་ཆེན་པོ་དང་། སྐྱེ་བོའི་ཚོགས་ཕལ་པོ་ཆེས་ཡོངས་སུ་བསྐོར་ཅིང་མདུན་དུ་བདར་ནས་བརྟད་ཅིང་མྱུར་བ་མྱུར་བས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱི་སྤྱན་སྔར་སོང་བ་དང་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-99"/>Inspired by Queen Śyāmāvatī, King Udayana of Vatsa, surrounded by a great assembly of people and his royal power and wealth, went to meet the Blessed One with great speed and haste.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-48">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-99</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་མཛེས་པ། དང་བར་འགྱུར་བ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He saw the Blessed One, elegant and beautiful.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-49">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-99</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དབང་པོ་ཞི་བ། ཐུགས་ཞི་བ། དུལ་བ་དང་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The Blessed One’s sense faculties and mind were calmed, and he was completely controlled.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-50">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-99</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཞི་གནས་ཀྱི་མཆོག་དམ་པའི་ཕ་རོལ་ཏུ་བྱོན་པ། བསམ་གཏན་དམ་པ་རྣམས་ཀྱི་ཕ་རོལ་དུ་གཤེགས་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He had perfected the most sublime tranquility meditations and the most sublime meditative concentrations.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-51">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-99</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གསེར་གྱི་མཆོད་སྡོང་ལྟར་མངོན་པར་འཕགས་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He rose above the crowd like a golden sacrificial post resplendent with glory.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-52">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-99</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དཔལ་གྱིས་མཛེས་ཤིང་། ལྷམ་མེ་ལྷན་ནེ་ལྷང་ངེ་སྟེ། སྐྱེས་བུ་ཆེན་པོའི་མཚན་སུམ་ཅུ་རྩ་གཉིས་ཀྱིས་སྐུ་ལེགས་པར་བརྒྱན་པ། དགེ་སློང་དང་། དགེ་སློང་མ་དང་། དགེ་བསྙེན་དང་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The Blessed One’s body was brilliant, vibrant, and beautifully adorned with the thirty-two marks of a great being.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-53">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-99</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དགེ་བསྙེན་མ་དང་། བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའི་དགེ་འདུན་གྱིས་ཡོངས་སུ་བསྐོར་བ། ལྷ་དང་། ཀླུ་དང་། གནོད་སྦྱིན་དང་། དྲི་ཟ་དང་། ལྷ་མ་ཡིན་དང་། ནམ་མཁའ་ལྡིང་དང་། མིའམ་ཅི་དང་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Surrounded by an assembly of monks, nuns, laymen, laywomen, and bodhisattvas, the Blessed One was venerated by gods, nāgas, yakṣas, gandharvas, asuras, garuḍas, kinnaras, mahoragas, humans, and non-humans.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-54">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-99</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལྟོ་འཕྱེ་ཆེན་པོ་དང་། མི་དང་། མི་མ་ཡིན་པ་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་མདུན་གྱིས་བལྟས་པ་མཐོང་བར་གྱུར་ཏོ། །མཐོང་ནས་ཀྱང་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ག་ལ་བ་དེར་སོང་སྟེ་ཕྱིན་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱི་ཞབས་གཉིས་ལ་གཏུགས་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Having seen that, the king approached the Blessed One and bowed at his feet.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-55">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-100</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ལ་འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་གསོལ་ཏོ། །བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་བདག་གིས་སྔོན་མ་མཐོང་བའི་རྨད་དུ་བྱུང་བ་ཞིག་མཐོང་བ་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ལ་གསོལ་བར་འཚལ་ན།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-100"/>Addressing the Blessed One, he said, “Blessed One, I have witnessed wonders the likes of which I have never seen before.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-56">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-100</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་བདག་ལ་སྐབས་དབྱེ་བར་ཅི་གནང་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Will the Blessed One grant me the opportunity to make a request?”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-57">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-100</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་སྐད་ཅེས་གསོལ་པ་དང་། བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་བད་སའི་རྒྱལ་པོ་འཆར་བྱེད་ལ་འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་བཀའ་སྩལ་ཏོ། །རྒྱལ་པོ་ཆེན་པོ་ཁྱོད་ཀྱིས་ཇི་ལྟར་བཟོད་པ་དེ་ལྟར་སྨྲོས་ཤིག །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The Blessed One replied to King Udayana of Vatsa, “Great King, make a request as you wish.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-58">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-100</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཟློས་ཤིག །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Speak!”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-59">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-102</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ལ་བད་སའི་རྒྱལ་པོ་འཆར་བྱེད་ཀྱིས་འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་གསོལ་ཏོ། །བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་བདག་འདོད་པའི་རྒྱུ་དང་། འདོད་པའི་གཞི་དང་། འདོད་པ་ལ་ལྷག་པར་ཞེན་པས་དེང་མ་དུའི་བུ་མོ་དཔེ་མེད་ཀྱི་ཚིག་གིས་ཁྲོས་ཤིང་རྔམ་པས་ཟིལ་གྱིས་ནོན་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཉན་ཐོས་ཀྱི་དགེ་འདུན་དང་བཅས་པ་ལ་ཐ་བ་དང་ཞེ་སྡང་གི་<tei:ref folio="F.206.b"/>སེམས་ཀྱང་བསྐྱེད།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-102"/>King Udayana of Vatsa then said to the Blessed One, “Blessed One because I am attached to my desires and their cause and basis, today I was overcome with wrath and fury by the words of Queen Anupamā, daughter of Mākandika.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-60">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-102</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་བདག་གིས་མཆིས་བྲང་སྔོ་སངས་ཅན་དགུམ་པའི་སླད་དུ་མདའ་སྟེའུ་ཀ་ཉ་རྔ་མ་ཞིག་འཕངས་ན།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>I was overcome with thoughts of rage and anger toward the Blessed One and his assembly of disciples and shot a razor-sharp arrow at my wife Śyāmāvatī with murderous intent.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-61">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-102</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་བར་སྣང་ལ་འབར།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>When I did, it burst into flames in the sky, and as it burned and blazed, it became a single flame.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-62">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-102</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རབ་ཏུ་འབར། ཀུན་ཏུ་རབ་ཏུ་མཆེད་དེ་འབར་ཞིང་མེ་ལྕེ་གཅིག་ཏུ་གྱུར་ནས་བཟློག་པའི་ཚུལ་དུ་སླར་ལོག་སྟེ་བདག་གི་གཡོན་རོལ་ལོགས་སུ་མཆིས་པར་གྱུར་ཅིང་ལུས་ལ་ནི་མ་ཕོག་ནས།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>As if the arrow were counteracted, it returned back to remain on my right side, without touching my body.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-63">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-103</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་བདག་གིས་མཆིས་བྲང་སྔོ་སངས་ཅན་གྱི་སུག་པ་རྐང་པ་གཉིས་ལ་གཏུགས་ཏེ། མཆིས་བྲང་སྔོ་སངས་ཅན་ལ་འདི་སྐད་དུ་ཁྱོད་ལྷ་མོ་ཞིག་གམ། འོན་ཏེ་ཀླུ་མོའམ། དྲི་ཟ་མོའམ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-103"/>“Blessed One, I bowed at the feet of my wife Śyāmāvatī, and asked her, ‘Are you a goddess, nāginī, gandharvī, piśācī, rākṣasī, or something else?’</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-64">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-103</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཤ་ཟ་མོའམ། སྲིན་མོའམ། སུ་ཞིག་ལགས་ཞེས་བགྱིས་པ་དང་། དེ་བདག་ལ་འདི་སྐད་དུ་རྒྱལ་པོ་ཆེན་པོ་བདག་ནི་ལྷ་མོ་ཡང་མ་ལགས། ཀླུ་མོ་ཡང་མ་ལགས།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>She told me, ‘I am not a goddess, nāginī, gandharvī, piśācī, or rākṣasī.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-65">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-103</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དྲི་ཟ་མོ་ཡང་མ་ལགས། ཤ་ཟ་མོ་ཡང་མ་ལགས། སྲིན་མོ་ཡང་མ་ལགས་ཀྱི། བདག་ནི་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་དགྲ་བཅོམ་པ་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་སངས་རྒྱས་དེའི་ཉན་ཐོས་མ་ལགས་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Rather, I am a disciple of the Blessed One, the thus-gone, worthy, completely perfect Buddha.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-66">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-103</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཁྱོད་ཉིད་ལ་སྙིང་བརྩེ་བའི་སླད་དུ་སེམས་མཉམ་པར་བཞག་པ་ལགས་སོ་ཞེས་མཆི་ནས།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Out of love for you, I have rested my mind in equipoise.’</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-67">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-103</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་མཆིས་བྲང་སྔོ་སངས་ཅན་གྱིས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱི་བསྔགས་པ་རྣམ་གྲངས་དུ་མས་བརྗོད་པ་དང་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>My wife Śyāmāvatī then sang the praise of the Blessed One in various ways.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-68">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-104</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་དེ་ལ་བདག་འདི་སྙམ་དུ་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་དགྲ་བཅོམ་པ་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་སངས་རྒྱས་དེའི་ཉན་ཐོས་མ་འདི་ཡང་དེ་ལྟ་བུའི་སྙིང་རྗེའི་བསམ་པ་དང་། དེ་ལྟ་བུའི་བྱམས་པ་ཐོབ་པ་དང་། དེ་ལྟར་རྫུ་འཕྲུལ་ཆེ་བ་དང་། དེ་ལྟར་མཐུ་ཆེ་བ་དང་། དེ་ལྟར་དབང་ཆེ་བར་གྲགས་པ་ལགས་ན།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-104"/>“Then, Blessed One, I had this thought: ‘If a disciple of the Blessed One, the thus-gone, worthy, perfectly awakened Buddha, is so full of compassion, loving-kindness, great superhuman power, and great marvelous strength, and is of such great distinction, then what must the Blessed One, the thus-gone, worthy, perfectly awakened Buddha himself be like?’</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-69">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-105</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་དགྲ་བཅོམ་པ་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་སངས་རྒྱས་ལྟ་སྨོས་ཀྱང་ཅི་འཚལ་སྙམ་དུ་སེམས་པར་གྱུར་ལགས་ཏེ། བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་བདག་འདི་ལྟར་བྱིས་པ་ལྟ་བུ་དང་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-105"/>“Blessed One, in that way, because I was like a fool—ignorant, unclear, and unwise—I felt rage and hatred toward the Thus-Gone One and the assembly of disciples.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-70">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-105</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདི་ལྟར་རྨོངས་པ་དང་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>For this, I request your forgiveness.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-71">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-105</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདི་ལྟར་མི་གསལ་བ་དང་། འདི་ལྟར་མི་མཁས་པས་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་ཉན་ཐོས་ཀྱི་དགེ་འདུན་དང་བཅས་པ་ལ་བདག་གིས་ཐ་བ་དང་ཞེ་སྡང་གི་སེམས་བསྐྱེད་པ་དེ་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ལ་བཟོད་པར་གསོལ་ཞིང་ཉན་ཐོས་ཀྱི་དགེ་འདུན་གྱི་<tei:ref folio="F.207.a"/>མདུན་དུ་ཡང་ནོངས་པ་འཆགས་ཤིང་མཆིས་ན།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>In the presence of the assembly of disciples, I confess my errors.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-72">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-105</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཐུགས་བརྩེ་བའི་སླད་དུ་བདག་གིས་ནོངས་པ་ནོངས་པར་བཤགས་པ་དེ་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་ལེགས་པར་རྗེས་སུ་གཟུང་བར་གསོལ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>In the hope that you may show me compassion, I confess my errors. I request you, Blessed One, to treat me with kindness.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-73">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-105</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེང་སླན་ཆད་ཀྱང་སྡོམ་པར་འཚལ་ལགས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>I vow to practice restraint from this day forward.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-74">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-106</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་རྒྱལ་པོ་ཆེན་པོ་ཁྱོད་ལོངས་ལ་རང་གི་སྟན་གང་ཡིན་པ་ལ་འདུག་ཤིག་ཅེས་བད་སའི་རྒྱལ་པོ་འཆར་བྱེད་ཀྱིས་ཉེས་པ་བཤགས་པ་རྗེས་སུ་གཟུང་བར་གནང་ངོ་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-106"/>The Blessed One said, “Great King, rise and be seated,” and he accepted with kindness King Udayana of Vatsa who had confessed his faults.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-75">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-106</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་བད་སའི་རྒྱལ་པོ་འཆར་བྱེད་ཀྱིས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱི་ཞབས་གཉིས་ལ་མགོ་བོས་ཕྱག་འཚལ་ཏེ་ཕྱོགས་གཅིག་ཏུ་འདུག་གོ །ཕྱོགས་གཅིག་ཏུ་འདུག་ནས་ཀྱང་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ལ་བད་སའི་རྒྱལ་པོ་འཆར་བྱེད་ཀྱིས་འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་གསོལ་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>King Udayana of Vatsa bowed his head at the feet of the Blessed One and sat to one side.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-76">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-107</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་བདག་ནི་གཏུམ་ཞིང་གཟུ་ལུམས་ཆེ་ལ་དྲག་ཤུལ་ཅན་ལགས་པས་བདག་གིས་བུད་མེད་ཀྱི་ཚིག་གིས་སྡིག་པའི་སུག་ལས་མངོན་པར་འདུས་བགྱིས་པ་དེས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་བདག་སེམས་ཅན་དམྱལ་བར་མཆི་བར་བདག་གིས་ཡང་དག་པར་འཚལ་ན།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-107"/>King Udayana of Vatsa, sitting to one side, addressed the Blessed One: “Blessed One, because of how cruel, obstinate, and quick to anger I was, I have been driven to negative actions by the words of women. Because of that, Blessed One, I will go to the hell realms.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-77">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-107</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་བདག་ལ་ཐུགས་བརྩེ་བའི་སླད་དུ་ཅི་ནས་ཀྱང་བདག་སླན་ཆད་བུད་མེད་ཀྱི་དབང་དུ་མཆིས་ནས་སྡིག་པའི་སུག་ལས་མངོན་པར་འདུ་བགྱིད་པར་མི་འགྱུར་ཞིང་། སེམས་ཅན་དམྱལ་བར་མི་ལྟུང་བ་དང་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Blessed One, out of compassion for me, I request the Blessed One to describe thoroughly and correctly the faults of women so that, from today onward, I will not, by any means, fall under the sway of women and be driven to negative deeds that will lead me to fall into the hell realms.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-78">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-107</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བདག་དང་སེམས་ཅན་ཐམས་ཅད་ལ་ཡུན་རིང་པོའི་དོན་དང་། སྨན་པ་དང་། བདེ་བར་འགྱུར་བའི་སླད་དུ་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་བུད་མེད་ཀྱི་སྐྱོན་དེ་དག་ལེགས་པར་ཡང་དག་པར་རབ་ཏུ་བཤད་ཅིང་བུད་མེད་ཀྱི་སྤྱོད་པ་རྣམས་དང་། བུད་མེད་ཀྱི་མཚན་མ་རྣམས་དང་། བུད་མེད་ཀྱི་སྒྱུ་རྣམས་དང་། བུད་མེད་ཀྱི་གཡོ་རྣམས་དང་། བུད་མེད་ཀྱི་གྱ་གྱུ་རྣམས་དང་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>It would be for the long-term benefit of myself and all sentient beings, so that we may be helped and happy.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-79">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-107</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བུད་མེད་ཀྱི་མི་བརྟན་པ་རྣམས་དང་། བུད་མེད་ཀྱི་འགྱུར་ལྡོག་རྣམས་དང་། བུད་མེད་ཀྱི་སྟེན་པ་རྣམས་དང་། བུད་མེད་ཀྱི་ཚིག་རྣམས་དང་། བུད་མེད་ཀྱི་འཁྲུལ་པ་རྣམས་ཡང་དག་པར་རབ་ཏུ་བཤད་དུ་གསོལ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Please describe thoroughly and correctly the behaviors of women, the characteristics of women, the treachery of women, the deceitfulness of women, the dishonesty of women, the unsteadiness of women, the fickleness of women, the dependencies of women, the words of women, and the deceptiveness of women.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-80">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-108</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་སྐད་ཅེས་གསོལ་པ་དང་། བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་བད་སའི་རྒྱལ་པོ་འཆར་བྱེད་ལ་འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་བཀའ་སྩལ་ཏོ། །རྒྱལ་པོ་ཆེན་པོ་གནས་དེ་ལྟ་བུ་<tei:ref folio="F.207.b"/>ཡོངས་སུ་ཞུས་པས་ཁྱོད་ལ་ཅི་ཞིག་བྱ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-108"/>The Blessed One asked King Udayana of Vatsa, “Great King, what is your purpose in asking such questions?”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-81">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-109</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ལ་བད་སའི་རྒྱལ་པོ་འཆར་བྱེད་ཀྱིས་ཡང་འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་གསོལ་ཏོ། །བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཅི་ནས་བདག་བུད་མེད་ཀྱི་དབང་དུ་མཆིས་པར་གྱུར་ན་བུད་མེད་ནི་མ་རུངས་མ། འཁོན་ཅན། གཏུམ་མོ་དྲག་ཤུལ་ཅན་ལགས་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-109"/>King Udayana of Vatsa responded, “Blessed One, I fall under the sway of women because they are vicious, hateful, fierce, and quick to anger.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-82">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-109</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་བུད་མེད་དེ་ནི་བདག་སེམས་ཅན་དམྱལ་བར་མཆི་བར་བགྱིད་འཚལ་བ་ལགས་པས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ལས་བདག་དོན་དེ་ཉིད་ཉན་པར་འཚལ་ལགས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Blessed One, it is women who will lead me to the hell realms. Thus, Blessed One, please heed this request of mine.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-83">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-110</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་སྐད་ཅེས་གསོལ་པ་དང་། བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་བད་སའི་རྒྱལ་པོ་འཆར་བྱེད་ལ་འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་བཀའ་སྩལ་ཏོ། །རྒྱལ་པོ་ཆེན་པོ་ཁྱོད་ཀྱིས་ཇེ་རང་གི་སྐྱོན་རྣམས་ཡོངས་སུ་རྟོགས་ཤིག་དང་། དེ་ནས་ཕྱིས་བུད་མེད་ཀྱི་སྐྱོན་རྣམས་ཡོངས་སུ་རྟོགས་པར་འགྱུར་རོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-110"/>The Blessed One said to King Udayana of Vatsa, “Great King, you must first understand your own faults and then you will come to understand the faults of women.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-84">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-111</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་སྐད་ཅེས་བཀའ་སྩལ་པ་དང་། བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ལ་བད་སའི་རྒྱལ་པོ་འཆར་བྱེད་ཀྱིས་འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་གསོལ་ཏོ། །བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ལེགས་སོ་ལེགས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-111"/>King Udayana of Vatsa responded to the Blessed One, “Excellent, Blessed One, excellent!</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-85">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-111</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྐྱེས་པ་སྐྱོན་ཇི་ལྟ་བུ་དག་དང་ལྡན་ན་སྐྱེས་པ་བུད་མེད་ཀྱི་དབང་དུ་མཆི་བར་འགྱུར་བའི་སྐྱེས་པའི་སྐྱོན་རྣམས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་བདག་ལ་ཡང་དག་པར་རབ་ཏུ་བཤད་དུ་གསོལ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>When men possess certain faults, they fall under the sway of women. Please, Blessed One, explain these faults of men to me.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-86">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-112</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་སྐད་ཅེས་གསོལ་པ་དང་། བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་བད་སའི་རྒྱལ་པོ་འཆར་བྱེད་ལ་འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་བཀའ་སྩལ་ཏོ། །རྒྱལ་པོ་ཆེན་པོ་དེའི་ཕྱིར་ཁྱོད་ལེགས་པར་ཉོན་ལ་རབ་ཏུ་ཡིད་ལ་ཟུང་ཤིག་དང་ངས་ཁྱོད་ལ་བཤད་པར་བྱའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-112"/>The Blessed One responded to King Udayana of Vatsa, “Yes, Great King, listen carefully and pay attention. I will now explain.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-87">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-112</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བད་སའི་རྒྱལ་པོ་འཆར་བྱེད་ཀྱིས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་དེ་བཞིན་ནོ་ཞེས་གསོལ་ཏེ། བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱི་ལྟར་ཉན་པ་དང་། བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་དེ་ལ་འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་བཀའ་སྩལ་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>King Udayana of Vatsa said, “Very well, Blessed One,” and he listened as the Blessed One had instructed.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-88">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-114</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྒྱལ་པོ་ཆེན་པོ་སྐྱེས་པ་སྐྱོན་གང་དག་དང་ལྡན་ན་སྐྱེས་པ་བུད་མེད་ཀྱི་དབང་དུ་འགྲོ་བར་འགྱུར་བའི་སྐྱེས་པའི་སྐྱེས་བུའི་སྐྱོན་ནི་བཞི་པོ་འདི་དག་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-114"/>The Blessed One addressed him, saying, “Great King, when men possess four particular faults, they fall under the sway of women.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-89">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-114</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཞི་པོ་གང་ཞེ་ན།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>What are the four?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-90">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-115</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདི་ལྟ་སྟེ། རྒྱལ་པོ་ཆེན་པོ་འདི་ལ་སྐྱེས་པ་འདོད་པ་རྣམས་ལ་ཆགས་པར་གྱུར་ཅིང་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They are as follows: <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-115"/>“Great King, men are attached to the objects of their desire and become reckless in pursuit of them.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-91">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-115</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་འདོད་པ་རྣམས་ལ་བག་མེད་པར་གྱུར་ནས་ཕྱིར་ཞིང་བུད་མེད་ལ་ལྟ་འདོད་དེ། ཚུལ་ཁྲིམས་དང་ལྡན་པ། ཡོན་ཏན་དང་ལྡན་པ། ཤེས་<tei:ref folio="F.208.a"/>རབ་དང་ལྡན་པའི་དགེ་སྦྱོང་དང་བྲམ་ཟེ་དག་ལ་ལྟ་བར་མི་འདོད་ཅིང་། དེས་ཚུལ་ཁྲིམས་དང་ལྡན་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Intoxicated by sense pleasures, they ignore the morally disciplined, virtuous, and wise mendicants and brahmins and, instead, only desire to gaze upon women again and again.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-92">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-115</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡོན་ཏན་དང་ལྡན་པ། ཤེས་རབ་དང་ལྡན་པའི་དགེ་སྦྱོང་དང་བྲམ་ཟེ་དག་མཐོང་ན་སྙེན་པར་མི་བྱེད། སྟེན་པར་མི་བྱེད། བསྙེན་བཀུར་མི་བྱེད་པས་དེ་ཚུལ་ཁྲིམས་དང་ལྡན་པ། ཡོན་ཏན་དང་ལྡན་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They do not serve, follow, or venerate the morally disciplined, virtuous, and wise mendicants and brahmins when they see them.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-93">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-115</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཤེས་རབ་དང་ལྡན་པའི་དགེ་སྦྱོང་དང་བྲམ་ཟེ་དག་གིས་ཡོངས་སུ་སྤངས་པས་དད་པ་ལས་ཡོངས་སུ་ཉམས། ཚུལ་ཁྲིམས་ལས་ཡོངས་སུ་ཉམས། གཏོང་བ་ལས་ཡོངས་སུ་ཉམས།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>By abandoning the morally disciplined, virtuous, and wise mendicants and brahmins, they also abandon their own faith, moral discipline, generosity, and wisdom.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-94">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-115</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཤེས་རབ་ལས་ཡོངས་སུ་ཉམས་ཤིང་དད་པ་དང་བྲལ་བ། ཚུལ་ཁྲིམས་འཆལ་བ། ཐོས་པ་ཉུང་བ། སེར་སྣ་ཅན་དུ་གྱུར་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Those men are faithless, their discipline is faulty, they lack learning, and they are stingy.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-95">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-115</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡི་དགས་ཀྱི་ཡོན་ཏན་གྱི་ཆོས་ལ་ཀུན་ཏུ་སྤྱོད་པ། ཤེས་རབ་འཆལ་བ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They behave like hungry spirits; they are weak-minded, attracted to open sores, and involved with excrement.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-96">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-115</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྨ་ལ་ཆགས་པ། བཙོག་པའི་སྤྱོད་ཡུལ་ཅན། བཤུལ་བར་མནམ་པ་ལ་མངོན་པར་དགའ་བ། མི་གཙང་བ་ལ་དགའ་བ། བུད་མེད་ལ་དད་ཆེ་བ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They delight in the smell of backsides, they enjoy filth, and they have a craving for women.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-97">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-115</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཞི་བ་ཡོངས་སུ་མི་ཚོལ་བ་ཆགས་པའི་སྤྱོད་ཡུལ་ཅན། འགྲོ་བར་བྱ་བ་མ་ཡིན་པར་སོང་བ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They do not seek peace, they are occupied with their attachments, and they go to places where they should not.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-98">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-115</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྨད་པར་འོས་པ། མི་གཙང་བའི་སྲིན་བུ་དང་འདྲ་བ། སྙིགས་མ་ལེན་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They are contemptible, they resemble maggots in excrement, and they welcome defilement.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-99">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-115</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདོད་པ་ལ་བརྐམ་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They lust after the objects of their desire, abandoning all shame and modesty.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-100">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-115</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཁྲེལ་དང་ངོ་ཚ་བོར་བ། ལྷ་དང་མིའི་ཆོས་ལས་ཉམས་པ། ངན་པར་སྨད་པའི་འཚོ་བས་འཚོ་བ། མཁས་པས་སྨད་པ། བྱིས་པའི་སྐྱེ་བོ་ལ་སྟེན་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They violate the laws of gods and men, lead despicable lives, are detested by the wise, and keep company with foolish beings.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-101">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-115</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྡིག་པའི་བསམ་པ་དང་ལྡན་པ། སྡིག་པའི་གྲོགས་པོ་ལ་སྟེན་པ། སྡིག་པ་ལ་ཀུན་ཏུ་འཇུག་པ། སྡིག་པ་ལ་གཞོལ་བ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They entertain negative thoughts, keep company with bad friends, are constantly engaging in bad actions, and are inclined toward bad actions.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-102">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-117</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བུད་མེད་ཀྱི་ཐུལ་འོག་ཏུ་ཆུད་པ། བུད་མེད་ཀྱིས་འཁོལ་བ། བུད་མེད་ཀྱི་དབང་དུ་སོང་བ། བུད་མེད་ལ་གཞོལ་བ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-117"/>“They become controlled by women and enslaved by them.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-103">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-117</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བུད་མེད་དང་གནས་པ། རྨའི་སྒོའི་སྤྱོད་ཡུལ་ཅན།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They fall under the sway of women as they become dedicated to them and live beside them.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-104">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-117</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྨའི་སྒོ་ལ་རྟེན་པ། རྨའི་སྒོ་ལ་གནས་པ། ཁ་ཆུ་དང་། སྣབས་དང་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They are fixated upon orifices, dependent on orifices, and reliant on orifices.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-105">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-117</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མཆིལ་མ་དང་། ངར་སྣབས་དང་། རྣག་དང་། ཤེའུ་རུལ་དང་། གླད་རྒྱས་དང་། མི་གཙང་བའི་སྤྱོད་ཡུལ་ཅན།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They are occupied with saliva, mucus, phlegm, snot, pus, fetid excretions, cerebral secretions, and excrement.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-106">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-117</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལུག་དང་། བ་ལང་དང་། བྱ་གག་དང་། ཁྱི་དང་། ཕག་པ་དང་། ཝ་དང་། བོང་བུའི་ཆོས་སྤྱོད་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They behave like sheep, cows, chickens, dogs, pigs, jackals, and asses.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-107">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-117</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གནོད་པས་འཚོ་བ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They make their living by harming others.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-108">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-117</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཕ་མ་ལ་ཕངས་པར་མི་<tei:ref folio="F.208.b"/>འཛིན་པ། དགེ་སྦྱོང་དང་། བྲམ་ཟེ་དང་། སྦྱིན་གནས་ལ་ཕངས་པར་མི་འཛིན་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They do not cherish their parents, nor do they cherish mendicants, brahmins, or others worthy of receiving offerings.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-109">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-117</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སངས་རྒྱས་དང་། ཆོས་དང་། དགེ་འདུན་ལ་དད་པ་ཡོངས་སུ་ཉམས་པ། མྱ་ངན་ལས་འདའ་བ་ལ་ཡོངས་སུ་ཉམས་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They lose their faith in the Buddha, Dharma, and Saṅgha; they lose nirvāṇa.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-110">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-117</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སེམས་ཅན་དམྱལ་བ་དང་། དུད་འགྲོའི་སྐྱེ་གནས་དང་། གཤིན་རྗེའི་འཇིག་རྟེན་ལ་ཞུགས་ཤིང་གཞོལ་བ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They enter the hells, the animal realm, and the realm of the Lord of Death—they fall to that level.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-111">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-117</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སེང་གེ་དང་། ནམ་མཁའ་ལྡིང་གི་ལུས་ལ་ཡང་དག་པར་ཞུགས་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They take up the bodies of lions and garuḍas.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-112">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-117</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལྕགས་ཀྱི་ཤིང་ཤལ་མ་ལི་མཐོན་པོ་དང་། མེ་མ་མུར་ལ་གཞོལ་བ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They sink to the level of the Hell of Iron-Thorn Trees and the Hell of Burning Coals.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-113">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-117</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སེམས་ཅན་དམྱལ་བ་ཡང་སོས་དང་། ཐིག་ནག་དང་། བསྡུས་འཇོམ་དང་། ངུ་འབོད་དང་། ངུ་འབོད་ཆེན་པོ་དང་། ཚ་བ་དང་། རབ་ཏུ་ཚ་བ་དང་། མནར་མེད་པའི་སེམས་ཅན་དམྱལ་བ་ཆེན་པོར་ཞུགས་པ་ནི་བུད་མེད་ཀྱི་སྐྱོན་འདི་ལྟ་བུ་འདི་དག་ཐོས་ཀྱང་བུད་མེད་ལ་ཆགས་ཤིང་བུད་མེད་དང་སྟེན་པས་བགད་པ་དང་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They enter the Reviving Hell, Black Line Hell, Crushing Hell, Howling Hell, Great Howling Hell, Hot Hell, Fiercely Hot Hell, and the Hell of Endless Torment.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-114">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-119</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ངུས་པ་དང་། ཅ་ཅོ་འདོན་འདོད་པ་དང་། བྲོ་བརྡུངས་པ་དང་། གླུ་བླངས་པ་དང་། རོལ་མོ་བྱས་པ་དག་རྗེས་སུ་དྲན་པར་བྱེད་ཅིང་སྐྱོ་བ་མི་སྐྱེད་ཡིད་བྱུང་བར་མི་བྱེད་དེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-119"/>“Even after hearing about these faults of women, these men feel neither anxiety nor disgust when they reflect on how they laughed, cried, and felt like shouting aloud, and how they danced, sang, and played music while desiring women and keeping company with them.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-115">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-121</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྒྱལ་པོ་ཆེན་པོ་བྱིས་པའི་ཆོས་ལ་ཀུན་ཏུ་སྤྱོད་ཅིང་ཀུན་ཏུ་སྤྱོད་པ་དེ་དག་དང་ལྡན་པའི་སྐྱེས་པ་ནི་ངན་སོང་རྣམས་སུ་སྐྱེ་བར་འགྱུར་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-121"/>“Great King, such is the conduct of foolish beings. Beings with these behaviors will be reborn in the lower realms.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-116">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-121</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྒྱལ་པོ་ཆེན་པོ་བུད་མེད་ཀྱི་དབང་དུ་སོང་ནས་འདོད་པ་ལ་རྟེན་ཅིང་། ངན་འགྲོར་འགྲོ་བར་འཇུག་པ་དེ་ནི་སྐྱེས་པའི་སྐྱེས་བུའི་སྐྱོན་དང་པོ་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Great King, attachment to sense pleasures is the first fault of men whereby they fall under the influence of women and are reborn in the lower realms.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-117">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-123</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་དེའི་ཚེ་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་ཚིགས་སུ་བཅད་པ་འདི་དག་བཀའ་སྩལ་ཏོ། །འདོད་པ་དྲི་ང་མི་གཙང་སྨད་པར་འོས་པ་དང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The Blessed One then spoke the following verses:<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-123"/> “Foul and filthy, objects of desire ought to be despised.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-118">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-123</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མི་མཐུན་འཇིགས་བྱེད་མི་རྟག་ལས་བྱུང་སྡུག་བསྔལ་བྱེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Dissatisfying, frightful, and impermanent, they cause suffering.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-119">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-123</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དོན་མེད་ཕུང་བར་བྱེད་ཅིང་དམན་པ་ཡིན་པས་ན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Pointlessly, these inferior things lead to one’s demise.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-120">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-123</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མཁས་པ་སུ་ཞིག་འདོད་པའི་སྐོམ་ལ་སྟེན་པར་བྱེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Thus, who among the wise would indulge their desirous cravings?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-121">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-124</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཙོག་པས་གང་བའི་ཆབ་ཁུང་དྲི་ང་ལྟ་བུ་དང་། །མནམ་པར་གྱུར་ཅིང་རུལ་པའི་ཁྱིམ་རྣམས་ཇི་བཞིན་དང་། །ཤི་བ་དུར་ཁྲོད་ས་ན་ཤིན་ཏུ་སྨད་པ་ལྟར། །དེ་བཞིན་འདོད་པ་རྣམས་ཀྱང་མཆོག་ཏུ་སྨད་པ་ཡིན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-124"/>“Sense pleasures are utterly loathsome, Like the stench of a cesspit brimming with excrement, A dwelling filled with rotten, overpowering odors, Or the loathsome charnel grounds of the dead.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-122">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-126</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྦྲང་བུ་རྨ་ཞིག་མཐོང་ནས་རྒྱུག་པ་ཅི་འདྲ་དང་། །ཕག་ནི་ངན་སྐྱུགས་མཐོང་ནས་རྒྱུག་པ་ཅི་འདྲ་དང་། །ཁྱི་ནི་ཤ་ཡི་དོན་དུ་ཤེན་སར་འགྲོ་བ་ལྟར། །དེ་<tei:ref folio="F.209.a"/>བཞིན་མི་མཁས་བུད་མེད་དག་ལ་དགའ་བར་བྱེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-126"/>“Just as flies, upon seeing a wound, swarm to it, And pigs, after seeing excrement, run to it, And dogs run to the butcher for meat, So, too, do the unwise delight in women.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-123">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-128</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གྲགས་པ་མེད་ཅིང་མི་སྙན་ཡོན་ཏན་འབྲི་བ་དང་། །དེ་ལས་ཚུལ་ཁྲིམས་དམ་པ་ཉམས་པར་འགྱུར་བ་དང་། །མཐོ་རིས་ཉམས་ཤིང་དམྱལ་བ་དག་ཏུ་ལྟུང་བས་ན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-128"/>“Infamous and shameful, they degrade positive qualities; Because of them, one’s pure discipline declines, And the higher realms are lost as one falls into the hells.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-124">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-128</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མཁས་པ་སུ་ཞིག་འདོད་པའི་སྐོམ་ལ་རྟེན་པར་བྱེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Who among the wise would indulge their desirous cravings?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-125">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-129</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཇི་ལྟར་ཧ་ལ་ཧ་ལའི་དུག་ནི་ཟོས་པ་ན། །ལུས་དག་རྨྱ་ཞིང་རྨོངས་པ་སྐྱེ་བ་འགྱུར་བ་ལྟར། །དེ་བཞིན་འདི་ན་བྱིས་པ་རྣམས་ནི་འདོད་པའི་རྒྱུས། །རང་གི་ལུས་ཀྱི་དབྱིབས་ནི་དུག་ཏུ་མི་རིག་གོ །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-129"/>“Just as the body deteriorates and delusions arise When one consumes halāhala poison, In the same way sense pleasures cause foolish beings Not to see physical forms, like one’s own body, as poison.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-126">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-130</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཇི་ལྟར་སྒྱུ་མ་ཤིན་ཏུ་བསླབ་པའི་མི་ཞིག་གིས། །རྣམ་པར་འཕྲུལ་པས་སེམས་ཅན་བརྒྱ་དག་དགའ་བྱེད་ལྟར། །དེ་བཞིན་བྱིས་པ་བདག་ལ་བདེ་བར་འདོད་པ་རྣམས། །འདོད་ལ་དགའ་བའི་རྒྱུ་ལས་ངན་འགྲོར་རབ་ཏུ་ལྟུང་། །ཟས་སྐོམ་སྟོན་མོ་བཟང་པོ་ཐ་དད་པ་དག་དང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-130"/>“In the same way that a skilled magician Delights hundreds with conjured illusions, Foolish beings, who seek pleasure for themselves, Fall to the lower realms because of their delight in sense pleasures.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-127">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-131</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གླུ་བྲོ་སིལ་སྙན་བཟང་པོ་ཐ་དད་པ་དག་གིས། །ཁང་པ་མཆོག་ནས་བྱུང་བའི་ཆུང་མ་ལེན་པ་ནི། །གནོད་པ་རྙེད་པ་ཡིན་ཞིང་སྡུག་བསྔལ་སོགས་པ་ཡིན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-131"/>“Using feasts of food and drink, Accompanied by song, dance, and music, To take a bride from a good family Is the accrual of pain, the accumulation of suffering.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-128">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-132</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདོད་པའི་དགའ་ལ་བརྐམ་པ་དག་ནི་གནོད་ཡིན་ཏེ། །མི་གཙང་མཚོན་འདྲ་རྨོངས་གྱུར་དག་ལ་བསྔགས་པ་རྗོད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-132"/>“Craving for the enjoyment of sense pleasures is pain, Yet people praise these filthy things, which cause injury and ignorance.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-129">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-132</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདོད་པ་དམན་པ་དག་ལ་བསྔགས་ཤིང་བསྟེན་པས་ནི། །དམན་པ་དེ་དག་ངན་འགྲོར་རབ་ཏུ་ལྟུང་བར་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>By praising and indulging in such lowly desires, Inferior people will fall to the lower realms.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-130">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-133</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གནོད་པ་འདོད་པ་དག་གིས་ཡུལ་རྣམས་རབ་བསྔགས་ཤིང་། །འདོད་པ་གནོད་པ་ཡིད་ལ་དགའ་བའི་བྱིས་པ་རྣམས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-133"/>“Those who desire for such pain praise these objects And delight in such harmful desires.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-131">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-133</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་དག་དོན་མེད་འཚོ་བ་རྣམ་པར་སྤངས་ནས་ནི། །མི་བཟད་གཡང་ས་ཆེན་པོར་རབ་ཏུ་ལྟུང་བར་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Pointlessly forsaking their lives, these foolish beings Will fall down into the great and unbearable abyss.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-132">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-134</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ང་རྒྱལ་རྨོངས་པས་བཅོམ་པའི་སྐྱེས་བུ་འདི་དག་ནི། །རྒྱ་མཚོའི་ཕ་རོལ་མ་མཐོང་བ་ཡི་བྱ་བཞིན་དུ། །ལྕགས་ཀྱི་མེ་ལྕེ་ལྔ་པོ་དག་ལ་ཆགས་གྱུར་ན། །བྱིས་པ་རྣམས་ནི་རབ་ཏུ་འབར་ཞིང་འཁྱམ་པར་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-134"/>“These people who are dominated by pride and ignorance Are like birds unable to see the far shores of the ocean; For so long as they are consumed with the five precious metals, These foolish beings will wander and burn.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-133">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-135</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདི་ནི་བྱིས་པ་མྱོས་ཤིང་ཤིན་ཏུ་རྨོངས་པ་རྣམས། །ཤེལ་དུ་མི་མཐོང་སྣོད་མཆོག་ཡིན་པར་སེམས་པ་ལྟར། །ལམ་ལ་རྣམ་པར་རྨོངས་རྣམས་འདོད་པའི་ཆེད་ཀྱི་ཕྱིར། །རྟག་ཏུ་འདིར་གནས་འདི་ནི་གྱ་ནོམ་ཡིན་ཞེས་འཛེར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-135"/>“These foolish beings, utterly intoxicated and confused, Mistake mere glass for an exquisite vase; Ignorant as to the path, they will remain forever here, Where they claim, ‘It is perfect,’ due to their desires.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-134">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-136</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་ཕྱིར་རྣམ་པ་སྣ་ཚོགས་ལས་དག་མི་ཤེས་པས། །འགྲོ་བ་ཐམས་ཅད་རབ་ཉམས་གུས་པ་ཡོད་མིན་པས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-136"/>“Because they do not know karma in all its diversity, They do not believe in the downfall of all beings.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-135">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-136</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཕ་དང་མ་དང་བུ་དང་བུ་མོ་དག་ལ་ནི། །དོན་<tei:ref folio="F.209.b"/>གྱིས་མཆོད་པ་མི་བྱེད་གནོད་པ་ཐོབ་པ་ཡིན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They do not truly honor their fathers and mothers Or their sons and daughters, and, instead, bring them pain.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-136">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-137</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་དག་རྟག་ཏུ་བུད་མེད་འདྲིས་པ་རྗོད་བྱེད་ཅིང་། །དེ་འདྲའི་ལས་ཀྱི་ཚུལ་ལ་རབ་ཏུ་འཇུག་པར་བྱེད། །དེ་དག་གཏི་མུག་དྲ་བ་སྡིག་པ་རབ་སོགས་ཤིང་། །ངན་སོང་འགྲོ་བར་འགྱུར་བའི་ལམ་ཡང་སོགས་པར་བྱེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-137"/>“Constantly chattering about intimacy with women And fully preoccupied with such behavior, They amass negative deeds in a net of delusion And pave the way to the lower realms.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-137">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-138</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མི་རྣམས་དེ་དག་དེར་ཆགས་བདེ་བར་འདུ་ཤེས་ཤིང་། །ཕ་དང་མ་ཡང་ཡོངས་སུ་རབ་ཏུ་སྤོང་བར་བྱེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-138"/>“Perceiving their passion as bliss, These people utterly abandon both father and mother.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-138">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-138</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་དག་མཆོད་འོས་རྣམས་ལ་མཆོད་པ་མི་བྱེད་ཅིང་། །སྨད་པར་འོས་པའི་འདོད་པ་དག་ལ་སྟེན་པར་བྱེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They fail to make offerings those who are worthy And indulge in sense pleasures that ought to be deplored.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-139">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-139</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཕན་ཚུན་གདུངས་པར་འགྱུར་བ་ལ་ནི་གཞོལ་བྱེད་ཅིང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-139"/>“Such people seek their own torment here and there.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-140">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-139</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྣམ་རྟོག་མུ་ཡིས་ངེས་བཅོམ་མི་རྣམས་ཉོན་མོངས་པ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The flow of their thoughts is certain to cause destruction.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-141">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-139</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཀུར་སྟི་ཡོངས་སུ་ཚོལ་ལ་དགའ་ཞིང་མ་འཕགས་རྣམས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Those afflicted people search for praise and delight therein.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-142">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-139</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཆོས་མ་ཡིན་པར་འཇིག་རྟེན་རབ་ཏུ་འཛུད་པར་བྱེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Such ignoble people are not of the Dharma, but wholly of the world.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-143">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-140</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཞི་དེ་ལས་ནི་མཚོན་ཆ་དག་དང་ལྕགས་རྣམས་དང་། །དེ་བཞིན་བཅིང་བ་དང་ནི་འཐབ་ཅིང་རྩོད་པ་དང་། །ངེས་པར་འཆི་བའི་སྡུག་བསྔལ་རབ་ཏུ་མྱོང་བར་འགྱུར། །ཤི་འཕོས་ནས་ནི་མནར་མེད་འཇིགས་སུ་རུང་བར་འགྲོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-140"/>“On that basis, they are bound to experience Torment from weapons and iron shackles, From bonds, battles, strife, and certain death, After they die, they will go to the fearsome Hell of Endless Torment.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-144">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-141</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཚེ་འདི་ཉིད་ལ་དེ་བཞིན་སྡུག་བསྔལ་འབྱུང་འགྱུར་ཞིང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-141"/>“In this very life, too, such suffering abounds.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-145">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-141</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ནོར་ཉམས་སྙིང་དུ་སྡུག་པ་རབ་ཏུ་འཇིག་འགྱུར་ལ། །མཐོ་རིས་ཉམས་ཤིང་དམྱལ་བར་རབ་ཏུ་ལྟུང་བས་ན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>As their wealth diminishes and their beauty fades, The higher realms slip away and they descend to hell.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-146">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-141</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མཁས་པ་སུ་ཞིག་འདོད་པའི་འདུ་ཤེས་སྐྱེད་པར་བྱེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Thus, who among the wise would give rise to desirous thoughts.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-147">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-142</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལྕགས་ལས་གྲུབ་པའི་ནགས་ཚལ་སྔོན་པོའི་ཁྲོད་དག་ཏུ། །མཁས་པས་བདག་ཉིད་རབ་ཏུ་བོར་བ་དེ་བླ་ཞིང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-142"/>“Even for the wise, it is easy to lose themselves In the midst of dense forests made of iron.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-148">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-142</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མཛངས་པ་སྤུ་གྲིའི་སོ་ཡིས་བཅད་པ་བྱས་བླ་ལ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>It is easy for the learned to get cut on the razor blades.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-149">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-142</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རལ་གྲི་དག་གི་ཁྲོད་དུ་མལ་ཡང་བཅས་སླ་ཞིང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>It is all too easy to end up preparing one’s bed of knives.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-150">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-143</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རབ་ཏུ་མེ་འབར་ཐུ་ལུམ་བཟུང་བ་དེ་སླ་ལ། །དེ་བཞིན་ལྕགས་ཀྱི་ཐུ་ལུམ་འབར་བ་ཟ་སླ་ཞིང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-143"/>“It is easy to end up seizing lumps of burning iron; It is easy to end up swallowing such iron balls.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-151">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-143</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མེ་དོང་འཇིགས་སུ་རུང་བ་རྣམས་ལ་རེག་སླ་ཡི། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>To encounter fearsome, fiery pits is easy indeed.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-152">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-143</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལག་པ་གཉིས་ཀྱིས་ནམ་ཡང་བུད་མེད་རེག་མི་བྱ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Thus, never let your two hands touch a woman.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-153">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-144</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མིས་ནི་ཇི་ལྟ་ཇི་ལྟར་འདོད་པ་རྣམ་སྟེན་པ། །དེ་ལྟ་དེ་ལྟར་བདེ་བ་ཐམས་ཅད་རབ་སྤོང་ཞིང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-144"/>“The extent to which people indulge in sense pleasures Is the extent to which they forsake complete happiness.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-154">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-144</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདི་ལྟར་འདོད་རྣམས་གཅིག་ཏུ་སྡུག་བསྔལ་མི་གཙང་བས། །འདོད་པ་སྡུག་བསྔལ་མི་གཙང་བ་དག་རྣམ་པར་སྤོངས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Given that sense pleasures are nothing but pain and filth, Give up such pleasures, along with misery and impurity.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-155">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-145</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདོད་པ་སྡུག་བསྔལ་ཀུན་གྱི་གཞི་བོར་གྱུར་པ་དང་། །གང་ཕྱིར་ནོར་ནི་ཆུད་ཟད་འགྱུར་བར་བྱེད་པ་དང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-145"/>“Desires are the ground for all suffering, For they cause one’s wealth to be squandered.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-156">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-145</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡིད་འོང་སྐྱེ་བོ་རྣམས་ཀྱི་ཉམས་པའི་རྩ་བ་བས། །བུད་མེད་ངེས་པར་སྟེན་<tei:ref folio="F.210.a"/>པ་གནོད་པ་ཐོབ་པ་ཡིན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Attraction is the root of men’s downfall; Thus, those who associate with women find only pain.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-157">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-146</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྐྱེས་བུ་གང་གིས་དེ་འདྲའི་ཆོས་ཚུལ་རིག་ནས་ནི། །བུད་མེད་རྣམས་ལ་རབ་ཏུ་བག་མེད་མི་འགྱུར་བ། །དེས་ནི་རྟག་ཏུ་མཐོ་རིས་ལམ་ཡང་རྣམ་སྦྱངས་ཤིང་། །དེས་ནི་བྱང་ཆུབ་དམ་པ་རྙེད་པར་དཀའ་མ་ཡིན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-146"/>“For a man who comprehends such guidance, And does not act carelessly regarding women, The path to the higher realms will always be clear, And supreme awakening will not be hard to achieve.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-158">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-148</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྒྱལ་པོ་ཆེན་པོ་གཞན་ཡང་མིའི་ཕ་མ་དག་ནི་དཀའ་བ་བྱེད་པ་དག་ཡིན་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-148"/>“Furthermore, Great King, one’s parents undergo hardship.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-159">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-148</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཟླ་བ་དགུ་འམ་ཟླ་བ་བཅུར་མངལ་ན་བཟུང་སྟེ་ཤིན་ཏུ་སྡུག་བསྔལ་བར་གསོས་ཤིང་། གཅིན་དང་ཕྱི་ས་ཡང་འཕྱི་བར་བྱེད།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>For nine or ten months, your mother carries you in the womb, enduring much pain to raise you.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-160">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-148</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>པང་དུ་བླངས་ནས་ནུ་ཞོ་ལྡུད་པར་བྱེད།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>She wipes away your urine and excrement and nurses you on her lap.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-161">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-148</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཕུང་པོ་རྣམས་སྐྱེད་པར་བྱེད། ཁམས་རྣམས་གསོ་བར་བྱེད།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>She helps you to grow and nurtures you.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-162">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-148</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇིག་རྟེན་སྟོན་པར་བྱེད། འཛམ་བུའི་གླིང་སྣ་ཚོགས་སྟོན་པར་བྱེད།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Parents show you the world and teach you all about it.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-163">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-148</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དོན་དུ་འདོད།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They are concerned about you and wish for your well-being.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-164">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-148</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཕན་པར་འདོད།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They desire your benefit and wish you well.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-165">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-148</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གྲུབ་པ་དང་བདེ་བར་འདོད།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They desire your success and happiness.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-166">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-148</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇིག་རྟེན་ལ་ཡང་ཕན་པར་འདོད་པ་སྟེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They desire to help you out in the world.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-167">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-148</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྦྱིན་པའི་གནས་ཡིན་ལ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>As such they are worthy of generosity.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-168">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-149</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བུ་ལ་ཕན་པ་དང་བདེ་བར་འདོད་པས་དེ་དག་གིས་རང་གི་ནོར་གྱི་ཚོགས་ཀྱིས་གཞན་གྱི་ཁྱིམ་ནས་གཞན་གྱི་བུ་མོ་བླངས་པ་དང་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-149"/>“Out of desire to help their son and for him to be happy, they use the wealth they have saved to find him a bride from a different family.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-169">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-149</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་དེ་ལ་ཆགས་ཤིང་མྱོས་ལ་འཆུམས་ཤིང་བརྒྱལ་བ་དང་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The son then becomes attached and intoxicated; he lusts after her to the point of fainting.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-170">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-149</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལྷག་པར་ཞེན་པ་དང་། ལྷག་པར་ཞེན་ཅིང་འདུག་པར་གྱུར་ནས།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He becomes fixated on her and remains infatuated.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-171">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-149</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཞན་གྱི་ཁྱིམ་ནས་བླངས་པའི་བུད་མེད་དེ་ལ་ཆགས་ཤིང་མྱོས་པས་སྦྱིན་པའི་གནས་ཕ་མ་རྒས་འཁོགས་པ། གཏུགས་ལ་ལུས་ཉམ་ཆུང་ཞིང་མིག་མི་མཐོང་བ་དག་ལ་བརྙས་ཤིང་ལོངས་སྤྱོད་མེད་པ་དང་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Attached to and intoxicated by this girl from a different family, he neglects his parents who are worthy of generosity and who have grown old, frail, weak, and blind.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-172">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-149</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ནོར་མེད་པར་བྱས་ནས་རང་གི་ཁྱིམ་ནས་ཕྱུང་སྟེ་སྐྲོད་པར་བྱེད་དོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He kicks them out of their own home, banishing them without resources or wealth.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-173">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-150</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྒྱལ་པོ་ཆེན་པོ་འདི་ལྟར་ཕ་མ་དགའ་བ་བྱེད་བྱེད་པ་སྦྱིན་པའི་གནས་ལ་རྟག་ཏུ་རྒྱུན་མི་འཆད་པར་ཡང་དག་པའི་བདེ་བས་བསྟི་སྟང་དུ་བྱ། བླ་མར་བྱ། བརྗེད་པར་བྱ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-150"/>“Great King, one should constantly, at all times, and with genuine happiness, honor one’s kind and venerable parents.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-174">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-150</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མཆོད་པར་བྱ་བའི་རིགས་ན།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>One should revere, venerate, and worship them.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-175">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-150</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེས་དེའི་ཚེ་ཕ་མ་དག་རང་གི་ཁྱིམ་ནས་ཕྱུང་སྟེ་བསྐྲད་ནས་གཞན་གྱི་ཁྱིམ་ནས་བླངས་པའི་བུད་མེད་ལ་བཟའ་བ་དང་། བཏུང་བ་དང་། གོས་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་བསྙེན་བཀུར་བྱེད་ཅིང་བསྟི་སྟང་དུ་བྱེད།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>And yet, men kick their parents out of their own homes, banishing them, as they give their respect and honor to the girl taken from another family, presenting her food, drink, and clothing.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-176">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-150</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཅེས་སུ་བྱེད། རིམ་གྲོ་བྱེད་ལ་མཆོད་པ་བྱེད་ཅིང་ཡང་དག་པའི་བདེ་བས་བསྙེན་བཀུར་བྱེད་ཀྱི་ཕ་མ་ལ་ནི་མི་བྱེད་པའི་མི་སྙིང་བརྩེ་བ་མེད་པ་དང་། མི་ལྟ་བ་དང་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They cherish, esteem, worship, and respect her with genuine happiness, yet not their parents.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-177">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-150</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ངན་པའི་སེམས་དང་ལྡན་པ་ལ་ལྟོས།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Just look at these heartless and inconsiderate people with their wicked minds!</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-178">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-151</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྒྱལ་པོ་ཆེན་པོ་དེས་བདེ་འགྲོར་འགྲོ་བའི་ཆོས་གང་ཡིན་པ་དེ་ནི་སྤངས་ལ། <tei:ref folio="F.210.b"/>
                </seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-151"/>“Great King, look at these people who forsake the Dharma that leads to the higher realms as they adopt the way of life that leads to the lower realms.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-179">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-151</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ངན་འགྲོར་འགྲོ་བའི་ཆོས་གང་ཡིན་པ་དེ་ནི་ཡང་དག་པར་བླངས་ཏེ་འདུག་པའི་མི་དེ་ལ་ཡང་ལྟོས། རྒྱལ་པོ་ཆེན་པོ་བུད་མེད་ཀྱི་དབང་དུ་སོང་ནས་འདོད་པ་རྣམས་ལ་སྟེན་ཅིང་ཕ་མ་ལ་བརྙས་པ་དང་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Great King, indulging in objects of one’s desire and falling under the sway of women, such men neglect their parents and proceed to the lower realms.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-180">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-151</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ངན་འགྲོར་འགྲོ་བར་འཇུག་པ་དེ་ནི་སྐྱེས་པའི་སྐྱེས་བུའི་སྐྱོན་གཉིས་པ་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>This is the second fault of men.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-181">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-153</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་དེའི་ཚེ་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་ཚིགས་སུ་བཅད་པ་འདི་དག་བཀའ་སྩལ་ཏོ། །གང་དག་ཕ་མ་རྒས་པ་གསོ་བར་བྱེད་པ་ནི། །དེ་དག་རྟག་ཏུ་བདེ་ཞིང་ཡིད་ཀྱང་བདེ་འགྱུར་ལ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The Blessed One then spoke the following verses:<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-153"/> “Those who take care of their elderly parents Will always be happy and content.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-182">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-153</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདི་ལ་ལྷ་དང་བཅས་པ་དང་ནི་དབང་པོ་དང་། །དེ་བཞིན་འདི་ལ་ཚངས་པར་བཅས་པའི་རིགས་སུ་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They will be among the class of gods, The likes of Indra and Brahmā themselves.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-183">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-154</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་དག་ཕ་མ་རྒས་པ་གསོ་བར་བྱེད་པ་ནི། །དེ་དག་སོང་ན་ཕྱིར་འོང་བ་ཡང་འགྲུབ་འགྱུར་ཞིང་། །རྒྱ་མཚོ་ཆེན་པོ་ནས་ཀྱང་བདེ་ཞིང་ལེགས་འོང་སྟེ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-154"/>“Those who take care of their elderly parents Will successfully return triumphant and safe Whenever they depart for and return from the great seas.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-184">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-154</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ལྟར་བྱེད་པ་དག་ནི་རབ་མཆོག་རྙེད་པ་ཡིན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Those who do so will find supreme treasures.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-185">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-155</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་དག་ཕ་མ་རྒས་པ་གསོ་བར་བྱེད་པ་ཡི། །ཚོང་པ་དེ་དག་ཡོན་ཏན་ཀུན་གྱི་གཙོར་འགྱུར་ཞིང་། །དེ་བཞིན་ཞིང་ལས་འབྲས་བུ་ཕུན་སུམ་ཚོགས་འབྱུང་སྟེ། །བསོད་ནམས་བགྲང་བའི་དོན་དུ་བརྗོད་པར་མི་ནུས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-155"/>“Those merchants who take care of their elderly parents Will reach the pinnacle of success; Like a bountiful harvest reaped from the fields The merit gained is simply impossible to measure.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-186">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-156</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་དག་ཕ་མ་རྒས་པ་གསོ་བར་བྱེད་པ་ནི། །དེ་དག་ཁུར་རྣམས་ཁྱེར་བའི་རྔ་མོ་རྣམས་དང་ཡང་། །ཡང་ན་གླང་དང་བོང་བུ་དག་ཏུའང་མི་འགྱུར་ཏེ། །མི་རྣམས་དེ་དག་སྤུ་གྲིའི་སོ་ལ་རྫི་མི་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-156"/>“Those who take care of their elderly parents Will not be reborn as pack animals, Such as camels, oxen, donkeys, and the like, Nor will men cut them with sharp blades.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-187">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-157</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་དག་ཕ་མ་རྒས་པ་གསོ་བར་བྱེད་པ་ནི། །དེ་དག་ཆུ་བོ་རབ་མེད་དང་ནི་མེ་མུར་དང་། །སྤུ་གྲིའི་སོ་དང་ལྡན་པ་ལ་ཡང་མི་རྒལ་ཏེ། །དེ་དག་ཟངས་ཁུ་བསྐོལ་བ་འཐུངས་པར་ཡོང་མི་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-157"/>“Those who take care of their elderly parents Will not have to cross the Blazing River Hell, The Hell of Burning Coals, or the Hell of Razor Blades, Nor will they find themselves drinking molten copper.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-188">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-158</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་དག་ཕ་མ་རྒས་པ་གསོ་བར་བྱེད་པ་ནི། །དེ་དག་ནོར་དང་འབྲུ་ནི་མི་ཉུང་བ་དག་དང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-158"/>“Those who take care of their elderly parents Will not lack in wealth or grain.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-189">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-158</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཆུང་མ་དང་ནི་བུ་དང་བུ་མོ་དག་དང་ཡང་། །བཻ་དཱུརྱ་དང་རིན་ཆེན་ས་ལེ་སྦྲམ་ཡང་རྙེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They will acquire wives and sons and daughters, As well as precious beryl and fine gold.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-190">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-159</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་དག་ཕ་མ་རྒས་པ་གསོ་བར་བྱེད་པ་ནི། །དེ་དག་རབ་འཕྲུལ་ལྷའི་ཕོ་བྲང་དག་དང་ནི། །རྩུབ་འགྱུར་དང་ནི་འདྲེས་པའི་ཚལ་ཡང་མཐོང་འགྱུར་ཏེ། །ལྷ་རྣམས་དུ་མས་རྟག་ཏུ་མདུན་དུ་བདར་བར་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-159"/>“Those who take care of their elderly parents Will behold the palace of the Nirmāṇarata heaven, As well as the Pāruṣika and Miśrakā groves; There will always be scores of gods gathered before them.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-191">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-160</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མི་ཡི་གཙོ་བོར་གྱུར་ཅིང་ལྷ་ཡི་ལྷར་གྱུར་པ། །ཐུབ་པ་ཆེན་པོ་འདི་འདྲའི་གསུང་ནི་ཐོས་གྱུར་ན། །རྒས་ཤིང་དབང་པོ་ཤིན་ཏུ་ཉམ་ཆུང་གྱུར་པ་ཡི། །ཕ་མ་སྦྱིན་<tei:ref folio="F.211.a"/>གནས་དམ་པ་སུ་ཞིག་གསོ་མི་བྱེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-160"/>“The Great Sage, foremost among men and god of gods, Has taught it to be so; having heard this, who would not Take care of the sublime objects of veneration, Their elderly parents, whose faculties have declined.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-192">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-161</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྒྱལ་པོ་ཆེན་པོ་གཞན་ཡང་སྐྱེས་བུ་དམ་པ་མ་ཡིན་པ་ནི་སྐྱེས་བུ་དམ་པ་མ་ཡིན་པའི་ལས་བྱེད་ཅིང་ལོག་པར་ལྟ་བ་ལ་མངོན་པར་ཞེན་པ་ཡིན་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-161"/>“Great King, inferior people are those who perform the acts of inferior people and tenaciously adhere to wrong views.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-193">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-161</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནི་དགེ་བ་དང་མི་དགེ་བ་གང་ཡིན་ཞེས་བདག་གི་དོན་མི་ཤེས་ཤིང་མི་བརྟན་པ་ཡིན་པས་སྐྱེ་བོ་མང་པོ་རྣམས་མི་དགའ་ཞིང་བྱིས་པའི་སྐྱེ་བོས་བསྔགས་པ་ལ་མངོན་པར་དགའ་བ་དང་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Such people wonder about virtue and nonvirtue and do not understand how to act in their own self-interest. Because they are insecure, they are disliked by many beings and delight in the praises of foolish beings.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-194">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-161</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདོད་ཆགས་དང་ཞེ་སྡང་དག་གིས་རྨོངས་པར་གྱུར་པ་དང་། སྐྱེས་བུ་མཛངས་པ་དག་གིས་སྨད་པ་དང་། ཁྲོ་བས་ཟིལ་གྱིས་ནོན་ཅིང་སྡིག་པའི་ལས་བྱེད་པ་དང་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Deluded by desire and aversion, they are despised by the wise, consumed by anger, and perform nonvirtuous deeds.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-195">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-161</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སངས་རྒྱས་དང་། བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་ཡོངས་སུ་སྤངས་པ་དང་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They are forsaken by the buddhas and the bodhisattvas.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-196">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-161</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལོངས་སྤྱོད་ཀྱི་རྒྱགས་པས་མྱོས་པ་དང་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They are intoxicated by the pride of wealth.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-197">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-161</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སེར་སྣ་ཅན་དུ་གྱུར་པ་དང་། གཞན་ལ་གནོད་པར་མངོན་པར་དགའ་ཞིང་ཆོས་སྒོམ་པར་མི་དགའ་བ་ཡིན་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They are miserly, delight in harming others, and despise cultivating the Dharma.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-198">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-163</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྒྱལ་པོ་ཆེན་པོ་སྐྱེས་བུ་དམ་པ་མ་ཡིན་པ་སྐྱེས་བུ་དམ་པ་མ་ཡིན་པའི་ལས་ལ་མངོན་པར་དགའ་ཞིང་སྐྱེས་བུ་དམ་པའི་ལས་ལ་མི་དགའ་བ་དེ་ལ་ལྟོས།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-163"/>“Great King, look how these inferior people delight in the acts of inferior people and despise the acts of superior people.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-199">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-163</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྒྱལ་པོ་ཆེན་པོ་འདོད་པ་རྣམས་ལ་སྟེན་ཅིང་ངན་འགྲོར་འགྲོ་བར་འཇུག་པ་དེ་ནི་སྐྱེས་པའི་སྐྱེས་བུའི་སྐྱོན་གསུམ་པ་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Great King, this is the third fault of men who indulge in the objects of desire and proceed to the lower realms.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-200">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-165</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་དེའི་ཚེ་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་ཚིགས་སུ་བཅད་པ་འདི་དག་བཀའ་སྩལ་ཏོ། །འདོད་པ་རྣམས་ཀྱི་གཞིས་ནི་སྐྱེས་བུ་རྣམ་ཉམས་ཤིང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The Blessed One then spoke the following verses:<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-165"/> “Objects of desire are the basis for the downfall of men.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-201">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-165</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཞི་དེ་ལས་ནི་སྡིག་པ་དག་ཀྱང་རབ་ཏུ་བྱེད། །ལོག་པར་ལྟ་བས་རྨོངས་ནས་འདིར་ནི་འཁྱམ་འགྱུར་ཞིང་། །དེ་ནི་རྣམ་པར་འཁྲུལ་པས་ངན་འགྲོར་འགྲོ་བར་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Based on them, beings perform wicked deeds; Deluded by wrong views, they wander this world And are led to the lower realms by their confusion.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-202">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-166</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལོག་དང་ལྡན་པས་ཡོན་ཏན་ཀུན་གྱིས་རྣམ་སྤངས་ཤིང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-166"/>“With their backward ways, they lack good qualities.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-203">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-166</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནི་རྟོག་པ་མེད་ཅིང་བློ་ཡང་ནོར་པ་ཡིན། །གང་དག་ཆུ་ཀླུང་དག་ཏུ་ཨུད་པལ་རྩྭ་ཚོལ་ལྟར། །ལོག་པར་ལྟ་བས་ཡོངས་སུ་འཁོར་བར་བྱེད་པ་ཡིན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They are heedless and their reasoning is flawed, As if searching for the roots of blue lotuses in a river, Their wrong views perpetuate the cycle of saṃsāra.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-204">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-167</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བདེ་བའི་དོན་དུ་བདག་ཉིད་ཡོངས་སུ་སྐྱོང་བྱེད་ཅིང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-167"/>“In seeking happiness, they only look after themselves.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-205">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-167</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཆོས་མ་ཡིན་ལ་ཆགས་པའི་མི་རྣམས་མང་པོ་དག །དེ་བཞིན་བདེ་བའི་རྒྱུ་ཕྱིར་འདོད་པ་རྣམས་ཚོལ་བ། །དེ་དག་གཏི་མུག་རྨོངས་པས་སེམས་ཅན་དམྱལ་བར་འགྲོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Like the multitude of people who are attracted to nonvirtue, They pursue sense pleasures for the sake of finding happiness, And go to the hell realms in the darkness of their delusion.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-206">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-168</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་དག་འདོད་པ་རྣམས་ཀྱི་དོན་དུ་རྟག་ཏུ་ནི། །དེ་བཞིན་སེམས་ལ་གཅགས་པའི་སྐྱེས་བུ་ཐ་མ་དང་། །འདོད་པའི་བདག་ཉིད་ཅན་དང་སྐྱེ་<tei:ref folio="F.211.b"/>བོ་སྡིག་ཅན་དང་། །འདུ་ཤེས་ལོག་པ་དག་ལ་བདེ་བ་ག་ལ་ཡོད། །མི་རྣམས་དེ་དག་བྱས་པ་མི་གཟོ་སྡིག་བཅས་ཤིང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-168"/>“Those inferior men who constantly obsess Over the objects of their desire Embody their desire and commit evil deeds; How could those with such wrong ideas ever be happy?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-207">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-169</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དད་པ་རྣམ་ཉམས་ཚུལ་འཆོས་གུས་པ་མེད་པ་དང་། །འཕགས་པའི་ཚོགས་ཀྱིས་རྟག་ཏུ་རྣམ་པར་སྤངས་པས་ན། །དམྱལ་བ་བཟོད་བརླག་ཤིན་ཏུ་འཇིགས་སུ་རུང་བར་ལྟུང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-169"/>“They repay kindness with evil deeds; They are charlatans with diminished faith, lacking true devotion; They will be forsaken by the assembly of noble ones, And, for that reason, will fall down to the unbearable, fearsome hells.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-208">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-170</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཟུགས་དང་སྒྲ་དང་རོ་ལ་ཆགས་པའི་མི་རྣམས་ནི། །བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་རྣམས་དང་མཁས་པ་མི་མཆོད་ཅིང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-170"/>“People who fixate on forms, sounds, and tastes Do not honor the bodhisattvas or the wise.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-209">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-170</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལོག་པར་ལྟ་བས་ཆོས་ཀྱང་ཉན་པར་མི་བྱེད་ལ། །ལན་འགའ་འང་དགེ་འདུན་ལེགས་པར་མཆོད་པར་མི་བྱེད་པས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Because of their distorted views, they do not listen to the Dharma And they never even occasionally honor the Saṅgha.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-210">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-171</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཕགས་པ་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་རྣམ་སྤངས་ངན་སོང་ལྟུང་བས་ན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-171"/>“Forsaken by the noble ones, they are destined for the lower realms.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-211">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-171</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ཕྱིར་མིའི་སྲིད་པ་འདི་ནི་རྙེད་པ་ལ། །སྦྱིན་དུལ་ཡང་དག་སྡོམ་ལ་ངེས་པར་སྟེན་ཅིག་དང་། །དེ་ལས་བྱང་ཆུབ་དམ་པ་མཆོག་ཀྱང་ཐོབ་པར་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Therefore, in this precious human life that one has acquired, One must earnestly practice generosity, discipline, and abstinence, And, in that way, attain supreme and authentic awakening.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-212">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-172</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྒྱལ་པོ་ཆེན་པོ་གཞན་ཡང་སྐྱེས་པ་ནི་བཟོའི་གནས་སྣ་ཚོགས་དང་། ལས་ཀྱི་གནས་སྣ་ཚོགས་འདི་དག་གིས་འཚོ་བར་བྱེད་དེ། རྒྱལ་པོ་ཆེན་པོ་འདི་ལྟར་ཡི་གེའམ། །རྩིས་སམ། གྲངས་སམ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-172"/>“Great King, men make their living from a variety of occupations and professions.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-213">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-172</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལག་རྩིས་སམ། མཚོན་ཆའམ། རྒྱལ་པོ་ལ་ཞོ་ཤས་འཚོ་བའམ། ཞིང་ལས་སམ། ཚོང་བྱེད་པའམ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Great King, they may be scribes, astrologers, accountants, palmists, armorers, royal servants, farmers, merchants, or herdsmen.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-214">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-172</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བ་ལང་འཚོ་བའམ། དེ་ལྟ་བུའི་བཟོའི་གནས་སྣ་ཚོགས་དང་། ལས་ཀྱི་གནས་སྣ་ཚོགས་དག་གིས་འཚོ་བར་བྱེད་ཅིང་འདི་ལྟ་སྟེ། ནོར་གྱི་ཕྱིར་ལམ་མ་ཡིན་པར་ཡང་འགྲོ་བར་བྱེད།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>From these occupations and professions, they make their livelihood.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-215">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-172</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལམ་ངན་པར་ཡང་འགྲོ་བར་བྱེད། གཅོང་རོང་དང་ཆུ་ཀླུང་ཅན་གྱི་ལམ་དུ་ཡང་འགྲོ་བར་བྱེད། མཚོན་ཆའི་ལམ་དུ་ཡང་འགྲོ་བར་བྱེད། རྒྱ་མཚོར་འཇུག་པར་ཡང་འཇུག་པར་བྱེད། གྲང་བའི་དུས་ན་ཡང་ལྷགས་པས་གནོད་པར་བྱེད། དྲོ་བའི་དུས་ན་ཡང་ཚ་བས་གནོད་པར་བྱེད་ཅིང་བཀྲེས་པ་དང་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>For the sake of wealth, they travel where there are no roads or where the roads are poor; they cross canyons, rivers, war zones, and oceans; they endure the icy winds of winter and the heat of summer; they suffer from hunger and thirst, and, all the while they delight in such journeys.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-216">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-172</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྐོམ་པ་དག་གིས་གནོད་བཞིན་དུ་འགྲོ་བ་ལ་ཡང་སྤྲོ་བར་བྱེད་དེ། ལོངས་སྤྱོད་ཡོངས་སུ་ཚོལ་བ་ན་དེ་ལྟ་བུའི་སྡུག་བསྔལ་དག་གིས་ལོངས་སྤྱོད་ཡོངས་སུ་བཙལ་ནས་ཀྱང་རང་གི་འཚོ་བ་དག་གི་ཕྱིར་ཉེ་བར་སྒྲུབ་པར་བྱེད་པས་དགེ་སྦྱོང་དང་བྲམ་ཟེ་དག་དང་། བཀྲེན་པ་དང་། སྡུག་ཕོངས་པ་དང་། སློང་མོ་བ་དག་ལ་སྦྱིན་པ་སྦྱིན་པར་མི་བཟོད་ཅིང་བུད་མེད་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་དབང་དུ་བྱས་པ་དང་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They endure such suffering as this for the sake of their own livelihood, yet they will not donate any of the wealth they earn to mendicants, brahmins, the destitute, the poor, or beggars, because they are under the sway of women, controlled by them, enthralled by them, and enslaved by them.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-217">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-172</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བུད་མེད་རྣམས་<tei:ref folio="F.212.a"/>ཀྱིས་ཐུལ་འོག་ཏུ་ཆུད་པ་དང་། བུད་མེད་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་བསྐོལ་བ་དང་། བུད་མེད་རྣམས་ལ་བྱམས་པ་དེ་ཉིད་ཀྱིས་བུད་མེད་དེ་དག་ཉིད་གསོ་བའི་ཕྱིར་སྦྱིན་པ་སྦྱིན་པ་དང་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Because of this same love for women, these men are unable to give gifts even to support their women or to practice moral discipline.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-218">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-172</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཚུལ་ཁྲིམས་ཡང་དག་པར་ལེན་པར་མི་ནུས་ཤིང་དེ་དེ་ལ་ཆགས་ལ་བུད་མེད་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་སྤྱོས་པ་བཟོད་པར་བྱེད་ཅིང་བུད་མེད་ཀྱིས་བསྡིགས་པ་དང་། བལྟས་པ་དང་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Infatuated by their women, they will endure their chatter, and even put up with their abuse, evil looks, and reprimands.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-219">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-172</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བརྒྱབ་པ་དག་ཀྱང་བཟོད་པར་བྱེད་དེ། དེ་སྐྱེས་པར་གྱུར་ཀྱང་བུད་མེད་ཀྱིས་བསྡིགས་པ་དང་དུ་ལེན་ཅིང་།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>When abused by women, those men will voluntarily accept it and still regard those same women without ill will.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-220">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-172</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མི་དགའ་བ་མེད་པར་དེའི་ངོར་ལྟ་བར་བྱེད་པ་ནི་འདོད་པའི་གཞིས་བུད་མེད་ཀྱི་དབང་དུ་སོང་བ་ཡིན་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Those men fall under the sway of women who are the objects of their desire.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-221">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-174</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྒྱལ་པོ་ཆེན་པོ་བུད་མེད་ལ་སྟེན་ཅིང་ངན་འགྲོར་འགྲོ་བར་འཇུག་པ་དེ་ནི་སྐྱེས་པ་བུད་མེད་ལ་བརྐམ་ཞིང་ངན་སྐྱུགས་ཀྱི་སྒོ་ལ་གདུ་བ་དང་། མི་གཙང་བ་ལ་དགའ་བ་དང་། ཤེས་བཞིན་མེད་པར་སྤྱོད་པའི་སྐྱེས་བུའི་སྐྱོན་བཞི་པ་ཡིན་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-174"/>“Great King, this is the fourth fault of men who crave women, consider filth to be the highest bliss, delight in foulness, and act without awareness Thereby, they indulge in women and proceed to the lower realms.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-222">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-174</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྒྱལ་པོ་ཆེན་པོ་སྐྱོན་དེ་དག་དང་ལྡན་པའི་སྐྱེས་པ་ནི་འདོད་པ་རྣམས་ཀྱི་དབང་དུ་འགྲོ་བ་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Great King, a man who possesses these faults comes under the power of sense pleasure.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-223">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-176</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་དེའི་ཚེ་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་ཚིགས་སུ་བཅད་པ་འདི་དག་བཀའ་སྩལ་ཏོ། །འདོད་པ་རྣམས་ནི་ཚོལ་བ་དང་། །རབ་ཏུ་མྱོས་པ་ག་ལ་བདེ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The Blessed One then spoke these verses:<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-176"/> “Pursuing sense pleasures in a drunken state, How could one be happy?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-224">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-176</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདོད་པ་དམན་པ་རྣམས་སྟེན་པ། །དེ་ནི་གང་གིས་བདེ་བར་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Indulging in these base desires, How could one be happy?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-225">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-177</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྐྱེས་བུ་དམ་པ་མ་ཡིན་པའི། །ལས་རྣམས་བྱེད་ཅིང་མི་སྡོམ་ལ། །འདོད་པའི་འདོད་ཆགས་ཚོལ་བྱེད་པ། །དེ་དག་རབ་ཉམས་ཆུད་ཀྱང་ཟ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-177"/>“Those who perform, without restraint, The deeds of an inferior being, And pursue their craving for sense pleasures, Must suffer their own downfall.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-226">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-178</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མི་རྣམས་གང་དག་མི་མཁས་པ། །རྔ་མོ་བོང་བུའི་ཆོས་སྤྱོད་ཅིང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-178"/>“Those unwise people Behave like camels and donkeys.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-227">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-178</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བུད་མེད་མཐོང་ན་རབ་སྙེགས་པ། །ངན་སྐྱུགས་གནས་ལ་ཕག་རྣམས་བཞིན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>When they see a woman, they rush over, Just like pigs to a pile of feces.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-228">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-179</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་ལ་བྱིས་པ་གུས་བཅས་པའི། །འདོད་རྣམས་དྲི་ང་མི་གཙང་ཡང་། །འདོད་པའི་སྐྱོན་རྣམས་མི་མཐོང་བ། །ས་ཡི་སྟེང་ན་དམུས་ལོང་བཞིན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-179"/>“Even though the precious objects of their desire Are stinking and unclean, Those fools cannot see the faults of those objects— Like the blind moving through the world.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-229">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-180</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཟུགས་ཀྱི་འཆིང་བས་བཅིངས་པ་རྣམས། །འདོད་པའི་འདུ་ཤེས་རབ་ཏུ་འཇུག །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-180"/>“Those who are bound by their attachment to material form Are enthralled by thoughts of sensual pleasure.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-230">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-180</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱིས་པ་འདོད་རྣམས་སྟེན་པ་དག །ཁྱི་དང་ཝ་རྣམས་ཇི་བཞིན་ནོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Foolish beings who indulge in sense pleasures Are no different from the likes of dogs and jackals.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-231">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-181</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྒྲ་དྲི་རོ་དང་རེག་རྣམས་ཀྱིས། །གང་ལ་སོ་སོའི་སྐྱེ་བོ་རྣམས། །བྱིས་པ་འཁོར་བ་ཡོངས་འཁོར་བ། །སྤྲེའུ་རྣམས་ཕུར་ལ་བཏགས་པ་བཞིན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-181"/>“Sound, smell, taste, and touch Keep ordinary beings Foolishly spinning in saṃsāra, Like monkeys tied to a post.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-232">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-182</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱིས་པ་མ་རིག་ཁེབས་པ་རྣམས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-182"/>“Foolish beings are shrouded in ignorance.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-233">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-182</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མུན་པའི་ཕུང་པོས་བསྒྲིབས་གྱུར་ཅིང་། <tei:ref folio="F.212.b"/>བུད་མེད་རྣམས་ལ་ཆགས་པ་ནི། །མི་གཙང་གནས་ལ་ཁྭ་བཞིན་ནོ། །གང་གིས་ངན་འགྲོར་རབ་འཇུག་པ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Covered by a great mass of darkness; Attached to women, they are befuddled Like crows flocking to feces.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-234">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-184</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནི་བདུད་ཀྱི་སྤྱོད་ཡུལ་ཡིན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-184"/>“They are within Māra’s domain.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-235">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-184</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རོ་མྱང་འདུ་ཤེས་ཆགས་གྱུར་པ། །ངན་སྐྱུགས་གནས་ལ་སྲིན་བུ་བཞིན། །གསང་བའི་གཤེད་མ་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་ནི། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Those headed to the lower realms Are addicted to enjoyment Just like maggots in a pile of feces.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-236">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-186</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཇི་ལྟར་མི་ཞིག་བོར་བ་ལྟར། །ཤེས་ན་ཐར་པ་ཐོབ་འགྱུར་ཞིང་། །བུད་མེད་དབང་དུ་འགྲོ་མི་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-186"/>“If one thinks about how executioners Discard the body parts of a human, It will lead one to find liberation And not to fall under the sway of women.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-237">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-187</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདོད་པ་བུད་མེད་ལྟ་བྱེད་པའི། །ཀུན་ཏུ་སྦྱོར་ལས་འཇིགས་པ་སྐྱེ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-187"/>“Being caught up in gazing upon women, The objects of one’s desires, is a fearsome situation.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-238">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-187</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱིས་པ་མཚན་མར་འཛིན་པ་རྣམས། །འདོད་པའི་སྲེད་པ་རབ་ཏུ་འཕེལ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Yet foolish beings fixate on appearances And their craving for sense pleasure grows.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-239">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-188</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སོས་ཀའི་དུས་ན་མི་ཞིག་ནི། །དགོན་པ་ཆེན་པོར་སོང་གྱུར་ནས། །བྱིས་པས་ལན་ཚྭའི་ཆུ་འཐུངས་ན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-188"/>“They are like travelers in the summertime, Making their way across a great desert, Who foolishly drink salt water.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-240">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-188</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྐོམ་པ་ཕྱིར་ཞིང་རབ་སྐྱེད་ལྟར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Their thirst returns more strongly.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-241">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-189</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་བཞིན་བདེན་པ་མ་མཐོང་བའི། །བྱིས་པ་རྨོངས་པས་འཚོ་བ་རྣམས། །འདི་ན་ཕྱིར་ཞིང་བུད་མེད་ལ། །འདོད་པའི་སྲེད་པ་བརྟན་པར་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-189"/>“Similarly, foolish beings, blind to the truth, Who live out their lives in states of ignorance, Will strengthen desirous cravings For women here in this world.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-242">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-190</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཇི་ལྟར་མི་ལུས་མཛེ་ཅན་ལ། །སྲོག་ཆགས་རྣམས་ནི་ཟ་བ་ལྟར། །འདོད་བརྐམ་སོ་སོའི་སྐྱེ་བོ་རྣམས། །དེ་བཞིན་བུད་མེད་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་ཟོས། །མི་གཙང་བུམ་པ་ཁྲ་བོ་ཞིག །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-190"/>“In the same way that a leper’s body becomes food for tiny insects, So, too, ordinary beings who crave sense pleasures Are devoured by women.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-243">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-191</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཁ་དོག་ལྡན་པར་སྣང་མོད་ཀྱི། །ནང་ན་ཧ་ལ་ཧ་ལའི་དུག །དྲག་པོ་ཆེན་པོ་ཡོད་པ་ལྟར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-191"/>“A chamber pot may be decorated with many variegated colors Yet be filled with halāhala, The strongest of all poisons.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-244">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-193</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་བཞིན་བུད་མེད་བརྒྱན་པ་དག །གང་དང་གང་ན་སྣང་བ་ཡང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-193"/>“Bejeweled women are like that too.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-245">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-193</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཅིན་དང་ཕྱི་སས་གང་བ་ཡི། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They may glitter with adornments, Yet they are filled with urine and excrement.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-246">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-193</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྐྱལ་བ་རླུང་གིས་གང་བ་བཞིན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They are like leather bellows filled with air.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-247">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-195</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འབྲུ་མར་གྱིས་ནི་བདར་བའི་མཚོན། །གོས་ཀྱིས་དཀྲིས་པ་ཇི་བཞིན་དུ། །དེ་བཞིན་བུད་མེད་བརྒྱན་པ་ཡང་། །རལ་གྲི་རླིང་བ་གཡོགས་པ་བཞིན། །ཇི་ལྟར་མེ་དོང་གང་གྱུར་ལ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-195"/>“Just like a blade sharpened with oil And wrapped in a cloth, So too is a dressed-up woman Like a sword sheathed in a scabbard.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-248">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-196</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དུ་བ་མེད་ཅིང་འབར་ལྡན་ལྟར། །བུད་མེད་དེ་བཞིན་མེ་འདྲ་ཞིང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-196"/>“In the same way a blazing fire pit Can burn without any smoke, Women are like fire.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-249">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-196</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྲིན་བུ་གཏུམ་པོ་བཞིན་དུ་གཡོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They are deceptive, like dangerous insects.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-250">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-197</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྲེག་པའི་བསྐལ་པ་འདིར་བྱུང་ན། །ས་འདི་ཀུན་ཏུ་འབར་གྱུར་ལ། །རྩྭ་དང་གེལ་པ་འཇིག་འགྱུར་ཞིང་། །ཆུ་ཀླུང་དག་ཀྱང་སྐམས་པར་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-197"/>“When the fire at the end of the eon blazes, The entirety of this land will be consumed, The grasses and trees will be destroyed, And the rivers will completely dry up.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-251">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-198</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འབྱུང་པོ་ཆེན་པོའི་གནས་གྱུར་པ། །རྒྱ་མཚོ་ཡང་ནི་སྐམ་འགྱུར་ཞིང་། །རི་བོ་ཆེན་པོ་རྣམས་སྲེག་ལ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-198"/>“As for this abode of the great elements— The vast oceans will dry up And the great mountains will burn away.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-252">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-198</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་བཞིན་ལྷུན་པོའང་འཇིག་པར་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Even Mount Meru will likewise be destroyed.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-253">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-199</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྒྱལ་ཆེན་འབྱུང་པོ་འཛིན་པ་ཡི། །ས་འདིའང་རྣམ་པར་འཇིག་འགྱུར་ཞིང་། །<tei:ref folio="F.213.a"/>
                </seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-199"/>“This earth, the great king, sustainer of beings, Will be completely destroyed.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-254">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-199</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྲག་ཆེན་རྣམས་ནི་འཇིག་འགྱུར་ཡང་། །སྐྱོབ་པར་བྱེད་པ་ཡོད་མ་ཡིན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Even the great stone mountains will be destroyed, And there will be no protection.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-255">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-200</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཇི་ལྟར་མེ་ཡིས་རིར་བཅས་དང་། །རྒྱ་མཚོར་བཅས་པ་སྲེག་པ་ལྟར། །དེ་བཞིན་བུད་མེད་མེ་འདྲ་སྟེ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-200"/>“The way that this fire will consume The mountains and the oceans Is the same way that women resemble fire; They are dangerous and unsettling to men.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-256">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-201</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཏུམ་ཞིང་སྐྱེས་བུ་གཡོ་བར་བྱེད། །སྣབས་དང་མཆིལ་མ་ཁ་ཆུ་དང་། །ཀླད་རྒྱས་རུལ་པའི་ཀླད་པ་དང་། །ལུས་ལས་དྲི་ང་འཛག་དེ་ལ། །བྱིས་པ་རྣམས་ནི་སྦྲང་རྩི་བཞིན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-201"/>“Mucus, phlegm, and saliva, Fluids running from the head, And foul-smelling bodily discharge Are like honey for these foolish beings.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-257">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-203</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཁ་སྒོ་རུས་པས་གང་བ་དང་། །ཤ་དང་ལྤགས་ལ་སོགས་བསགས་ཤིང་། །དེ་བཞིན་ལུས་ནི་འབྲས་འདྲ་སྟེ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-203"/>“Full of bones and having a mouth for its opening, A pile of flesh and skin, And smelling like raw meat, This despicable body is like a boil.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-258">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-205</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དྲི་ང་སྨད་པར་བྱ་བ་ཡིན། །མི་གཙང་སྣ་ཚོགས་གང་བ་དང་། །འབྲས་ནི་སྨིན་པར་གྱུར་པ་ལྟར། །དེ་ལྟར་ལུས་འདི་མི་གཙང་བ། །སྣ་ཚོགས་རྣམས་ཀྱི་སྣོད་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-205"/>“Like a swelling pustule Filled with a variety of bacteria, The body is but a receptacle For feces and other types of filth.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-259">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-207</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལྟོ་ནི་གཉེ་མ་མཚེར་པ་དང་། །གློ་བས་གང་ཞིང་མཁལ་མ་དང་། །ཁྲག་དང་མཁྲིས་པས་གང་གྱུར་ལ། །ཀླད་རྒྱས་ཀྱིས་ནི་ཀླད་པ་གང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-207"/>“The body is stuffed with intestines, Colon, spleen, and lungs, Kidneys, blood, and bile, Brains, bone, and marrow.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-260">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-209</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཁོང་པའི་ནང་ན་སྲིན་བུའི་རིགས། །བརྒྱད་ཁྲི་པོ་དག་གནས་གྱུར་ཀྱང་། །གཏི་མུག་དྲ་བས་བསྒྲིབས་པ་ཡི། །བྱིས་པ་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་མི་མཐོང་ངོ་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-209"/>“Shrouded in a veil of delusion, Foolish beings do not even see The eighty thousand types of organisms That dwell within their innards.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-261">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-211</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྨ་སྒོ་དགུ་ནས་རྟག་ཏུ་ནི། །མི་གཙང་རུལ་བ་ཟག་གྱུར་ཀྱང་། །སྨྲ་བ་དག་དང་ལྟ་བ་ལ། །བྱིས་པ་རྣམས་ནི་མཚན་མར་འཛིན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-211"/>“The nine bodily orifices Are constantly excreting putrid filth, Yet fools grasp at appearances, Only what they can see and hear.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-262">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-213</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་ཞིག་ཀུན་གྱིས་སྨད་པའི་ཡུལ། །ཆགས་པ་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་ཕྱིས་མི་ཤེས། །མི་གཙང་སྤྱོད་ཡུལ་བྱིས་པ་རྣམས། །སྣབས་དང་མཆིལ་མ་ཟ་བར་བྱེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-213"/>“Those fools, whose abode is filth And who feed on mucus and saliva, After they feel desire Do not understand that this is a place despised by all.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-263">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-215</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྨད་པར་འོས་ལ་ཆགས་བྱེད་པ། །སྦྲང་བུ་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་རྨ་མཐོང་བཞིན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-215"/>“Like flies that have spotted a wo་und, They desire contemptible things.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-264">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-215</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མཆན་ཁུང་དག་ནས་རྡུལ་འཛག་ཅིང་། །སྨད་པའི་དྲི་ནི་འབྱུང་བར་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Sweat drips from their armpits And they reek with awful smells.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-265">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-217</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱིས་པ་སྡུག་བསྔལ་ཆགས་བྱེད་པ། །དེ་དག་བདག་ལ་གནོད་ཕྱིར་གཡོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-217"/>“Fools cling to their own suffering, Having been deceived into harming themselves.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-266">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-217</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེས་ནི་མྱུར་དུ་ཕོངས་གྱུར་ཏེ། །ཉ་རྣམས་ཆུ་ནས་བཏོན་པ་བཞིན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Like fish pulled from water, This will bring about their ruin.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-267">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-218</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇིགས་རུང་ལག་ན་མཚོན་ཐོགས་ཀྱིས། །ཇི་ལྟར་མི་ཞིག་གཙེས་པ་ལྟར། །མཚོན་འདྲའི་བུད་མེད་སྡིག་ཅན་གྱིས། །འདོད་ལ་ཆགས་རྣམས་དེ་བཞིན་ནོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-218"/>“The way that one is attacked By someone wielding a fearsome weapon Is the way that those attached to sense pleasures Are attacked by evil, weapon-like women.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-268">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-219</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྣམ་རྒྱལ་ལག་ན་མཚོན་ཐོགས་པས། །ཇི་ལྟར་རྒྱལ་པོ་གཙེས་པ་ལྟར། །འདོད་ཆགས་མེ་དང་འདྲ་བ་ཡིས། །འདོད་ལ་ཆགས་རྣམས་དེ་བཞིན་<tei:ref folio="F.213.b"/>སྲེག །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-219"/>“The way that a king is attacked By an opponent wielding the weapons of conquest Is the way that those attached to sense pleasures Are incinerated in the flames of desire.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-269">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-220</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཤེན་པའི་གནས་ལ་ཁྱི་རྣམས་ལྟར། །མྱང་བར་འདུ་ཤེས་བྱིས་པ་རྣམས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-220"/>“Like dogs hovering around a butcher, Foolish beings fantasize about tastes.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-270">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-220</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཇི་ལྟར་སྒྲ་ཡིས་སྐྲག་པ་ལྟར། །མྱུར་དུ་སྡུག་བསྔལ་མྱོང་བར་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Even when scared away by a loud yell, They quickly return to savoring their suffering.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-271">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-221</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རང་གི་ལས་ཀྱི་ཉེས་པ་ཡིས། །དེ་ལ་སྐྱོབ་པ་མེད་པ་ལྟར། །དེ་བཞིན་བདག་གི་ཉེས་པ་ཡིས། །སེམས་ཅན་རྣམས་ནི་ངན་འགྲོར་འགྲོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-221"/>“As there is nothing that can protect one From the faults of one’s own actions, Beings are led to the lower realms In accordance with their own faults.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-272">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-222</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་དག་སངས་རྒྱས་ཆོས་སྤངས་ནས། །བུད་མེད་རྣམས་ཀྱི་རྣག་ལ་སྟེན། །སེམས་ནི་རོ་ལ་ཆགས་གྱུར་པ། །དེ་ཡིས་ངན་འགྲོར་འགྲོ་བར་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-222"/>“Those who abandon the Buddhadharma To indulge in women’s excretions Have become attached to the taste, And, by that, are led to the lower realms.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-273">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-223</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཇི་ལྟར་སྤྲེའུ་ཞིག་ཤིང་ལས་ནི། །ཤིང་གཞན་དུ་ནི་རྒྱུ་བའི་ཚེ། །དེ་ནི་གནས་དེར་གཙེས་གྱུར་ན། །དེ་ཉིད་དུ་ནི་སྡུག་བསྔལ་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-223"/>“When a monkey hurts itself, As it swings about From one tree to the next, It experiences suffering that very instant.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-274">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-224</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་བཞིན་འདོད་ལ་བརྐམ་པ་དང་། །སྡུག་བསྔལ་འདོད་ཆགས་སྟེན་པ་དང་། །གཏི་མུག་རྒྱ་ལ་ཐོགས་པ་རྣམས། །དུས་ནི་ཡང་དང་ཡང་དུ་འདའ། །མི་བཀྲེན་རྣམས་ནི་གསལ་ཤིང་ལ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-224"/>“Similarly, those who crave the objects of desire, Who indulge in the suffering of sense pleasure, And who are caught in the cage of delusion Are just squandering their time again and again.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-275">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-225</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རབ་ཏུ་བཙུགས་ནས་འཕྱང་བ་ལྟར། །དེ་བཞིན་འདོད་ལ་ཆགས་པ་རྣམས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-225"/>“Just as some unfortunate beings Are impaled on stakes and left to hang, Those who are attached to sense pleasures Will hang high in the Hell of Iron-Thorn Trees.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-276">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-226</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཤལ་མ་ལི་ནི་མཐོ་ལ་འཕྱང་། །ཇི་ལྟར་མོན་སྲན་སྡེའུ་དང་གྲེའུ། །ལྕགས་ཟངས་རྣམས་སུ་བླུགས་བྱས་ནས། །མེས་ནི་རབ་ཏུ་བསྲེགས་པ་ན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-226"/>“When urad and mung beans Are poured into metal cauldrons And cooked over a blazing fire They will foam and boil.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-277">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-227</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དབུ་བར་བཅས་ཤིང་ཁོལ་བ་ལྟར། །དེ་བཞིན་དགེ་བ་མ་མཐོང་ཞིང་། །འདོད་ལ་ཆགས་པའི་སྐྱེ་བོ་རྣམས། །ཤི་ནས་ངན་སོང་འགྲོ་འགྱུར་ཞིང་། །ལྕགས་ཟངས་རྣམས་སུ་བཙོ་བར་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-227"/>“So, too, will beings who were blind to virtue And attached to the objects of their desire Proceed to the lower realms upon death To be cooked in metal cauldrons.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-278">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-228</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མི་རྣམས་གང་དག་སྡིག་བྱེད་པའི། །སེམས་ཅན་སྡིག་པ་རྣམས་ཀྱི་གནས། །ཟངས་ནི་བྱེ་བ་དྲུག་ཅུ་དང་། །གཞན་ཡང་བཞི་པོ་དག་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-228"/>“Those people who perform evil deeds Go to the place for evil beings, Where there are four groups Of six hundred million cauldrons.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-279">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-229</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཟངས་ནི་སོ་སོ་རེ་རེ་ལ། །ཚད་ནི་དམིགས་སུ་ཡོད་མིན་ཞིང་། །མེ་ཡི་ཕུང་པོར་ལྡན་རྣམས་སུ། །བསྐལ་པ་དུ་མར་བཙོ་བར་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-229"/>“In each one of those cauldrons, Which are unfathomably large And surrounded by masses of flame, They will boil away for many eons.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-280">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-230</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཁ་ཅིག་ཟངས་རྣམས་དེ་དག་ཏུ། །རང་གི་ལས་ཀྱིས་བསྐལ་བརྒྱ་འམ། །ཉིས་བརྒྱ་སུམ་བརྒྱ་ཚང་བར་འཚེད། །ཡང་ན་བཞི་བརྒྱར་བཙོ་བར་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-230"/>“Some will cook in those cauldrons For one, two, three hundred, Or even four hundred whole eons, Depending on their past actions.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-281">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-231</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཕྲ་སྐམ་རྣོན་པོ་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་ནི། །བཟུང་ཞིང་ཡང་དང་ཡང་སྨྱུགས་པས། །<tei:ref folio="F.214.a"/>
                </seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-231"/>“They will be seized by thin, sharp pincers And plunged again and again into the cauldrons.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-282">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-231</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་དག་ཤ་ནི་ཡོད་མིན་ཞིང་། །དུང་ལྟར་དཀར་བ་རྣམས་སུ་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They will lose their flesh And become as white as a conch shell.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-283">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-232</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལྕགས་ཀྱི་གཞོང་པར་འཇུག་ནས་ནི། །རབ་ཏུ་ཚ་ཞིང་འདྲེན་པ་མེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-232"/>“Once they are dropped into the iron pots They will be burning hot, yet never taken out.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-284">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-232</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཤི་ཞིང་ཤི་ཞིང་སྐྱེ་འགྱུར་ཏེ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They will die again and again only to be reborn.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-285">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-232</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རང་གི་ལས་ཀྱིས་གནས་པར་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Their destination is determined by their past actions.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-286">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-233</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་ཚེ་དམྱལ་བའི་སྲུངས་རྣམས་ཀྱིས། །ངན་པའི་མི་རྣམས་དེ་དག་ནི། །གཏུན་ལ་སོགས་པས་བརྡུངས་པས་ནི། །ཤ་རྐང་རུས་པ་ཕྱེ་མར་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-233"/>“When the guardians of the hell realms Beat those miserable people With clubs and other such weapons, Their flesh, bones, and marrow will be reduced to dust.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-287">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-234</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ཡིས་ཚེ་ན་དེ་དག་ལ། །ཤིན་ཏུ་གྲང་བའི་རླུང་ཡང་ལྡང་། །དེས་ནི་དམྱལ་བའི་སེམས་ཅན་རྣམས། །སྡུག་བསྔལ་གྱུར་པ་དེ་ལས་འཚོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-234"/>“At that time, a bitterly cold wind will blow And denizens of the hells Will thereby be given some relief From their suffering.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-288">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-235</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མི་རྣམས་གང་དག་སྡིག་བྱེད་པ། །གཏུན་བུ་དྲག་པོ་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་འཇོམས། །སྟ་རེ་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་གཤེག་པ་དང་། །དེ་བཞིན་གསལ་ཤིང་འཛུགས་པར་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-235"/>“Those who commit evil acts Will be smashed by mighty pestles, Split apart by axes, And impaled on stakes.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-289">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-236</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མི་རྣམས་གང་དག་སྡིག་བྱེད་པའི། །སེམས་ཅན་རྣམས་ཀྱི་ལུས་ལ་ནི། །ལྕགས་མདུང་རྩེ་མོ་བཞི་པ་དང་། །རྩེ་གསུམ་པ་དང་རྩེ་ལྔ་འབབ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-236"/>“Those who commit evil acts Will have four-pointed iron spears, As well as those with three and five points, Plunged into their bodies.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-290">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-237</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མི་རྣམས་གང་དག་སྡིག་བྱེད་པ། །རལ་གྲིའི་མཆུ་ཅན་ཁྭ་རྣམས་ཀྱིས། །མགོ་དང་གླད་པ་བཏོགས་འགྱུར་ཞིང་། །ཝ་དང་སྤྱང་ཀིས་ཟོས་པར་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-237"/>“Those who commit evil acts Will have their heads and brains picked apart By crows with knife-like beaks, And eaten by jackals and wolves.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-291">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-238</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མི་རྣམས་གང་དག་སྡིག་བྱེད་པ། །ངན་སྐྱུགས་རུལ་པ་དྲི་ང་ཞིང་། །ཀུན་གྱིས་སྨད་པར་ལྟུང་འགྱུར་ལ། །སྤུ་གྲིའི་ཆུ་ཀླུང་རྣམས་སུ་ལྟུང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-238"/>“Those who commit evil acts Will fall into putrid, rotting feces, Down to a fate reviled by all— They will fall into the Hell of Razor Blades and the Blazing River Hell.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-292">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-239</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མི་རྣམས་གང་དག་སྡིག་བྱེད་པ། །རབ་ཏུ་ཚ་བར་སྲེག་འགྱུར་ཞིང་། །ངུ་འབོད་དང་ནི་ངུ་འབོད་ཆེ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-239"/>“Those who commit evil acts Will be burned in the Fiercely Hot Hell, The Howling Hell, and the Great Howling Hell.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-293">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-239</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཐིག་ནག་ཏུ་ཡང་སྲེག་པར་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They will also be burned in the Black Line Hell.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-294">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-240</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མི་རྣམས་གང་དག་སྡིག་བྱེད་པ། །ཐིག་ནག་ཏུ་ནི་སྐྱེས་ནས་ཀྱང་། །ཡང་དང་ཡང་དུ་མེ་མུར་དང་། །སྤུ་གྲིའི་ཆུ་ཀླུང་རྣམས་སུ་ལྟུང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-240"/>“Those who commit evil acts, After their birth in the Black Line Hell, Will fall, again and again, Into the hells of burning coals, blazing rivers, and razor blades.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-295">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-242</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་ཚེ་ལྕགས་ཀྱི་ཟངས་པོ་ཆེར། །མི་རྣམས་དེ་དག་འཚེད་པ་ན། །ཁྱི་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་ནི་གཙེས་གྱུར་ནས། །དེ་དག་བདེ་བ་ཚོལ་བར་བྱེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-242"/>“When it comes time for those people To be cooked in the great iron cauldrons, They will be tormented by dogs And left longing for happiness.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-296">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-243</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མི་རྣམས་གང་དག་སྡིག་བྱེད་པ། །དམྱལ་བ་དྲག་པོ་ཆེན་པོར་ནི། །ལྷུང་ནས་དཔུང་གཉེན་ཡོད་མིན་ཞིང་། །<tei:ref folio="F.214.b"/>ལྕགས་ཀྱི་ཐུ་ལུམ་ཟ་བར་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-243"/>“When those who commit evil acts Descend to the great, brutal hells, They will have no companions As they swallow lumps of iron.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-297">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-244</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མི་རྣམས་སྡིག་པ་བྱེད་པ་དག །ལྕགས་ལས་གྲུབ་པའི་བྲག་ཆེན་དང་། །མི་སྡུག་རི་བོ་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་ནི། །དེ་ཚེ་ཀུན་ནས་ལུས་འཇོམས་བྱེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-244"/>“Those who commit evil acts Will have their bodies pulverized By giant boulders made of iron And terrible mountains.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-298">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-245</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེས་ནི་རང་གིས་ལས་བྱས་པའི། །འབྲས་བུ་དེ་འདྲ་ཐོབ་གྱུར་ཅིང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-245"/>“That is how one reaps The fruit of one’s actions.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-299">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-245</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ཡིས་ཚོར་བ་མྱོང་བས་ན། །དེ་ལ་སྐྱོབ་པ་འགའ་ཡང་མེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>There will be no protection whatsoever From the experience of that suffering.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-300">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-246</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཇི་སྙེད་རྟེན་པ་ཐམས་ཅད་ནི། །བདག་གི་མདུན་དེར་འགའ་ཡང་མེད། །དེར་ནི་མགོན་མེད་བདག་གཅིག་པུ། །སྡུག་བསྔལ་ཚོར་བ་མྱོང་བར་བྱེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-246"/>“Any support one could think of Will not be available to them; They will be alone, with no refuge, Left to undergo such suffering.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-301">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-247</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་དག་བདེ་ཕྱིར་དོན་མིན་པར། །སྔན་ཆད་ཉེས་པར་སྤྱད་བྱས་ཀྱང་། །ཕ་མ་དེ་དག་དེ་རིང་ནི། །རྣམ་པར་གྲོལ་བའི་མཐུ་ཡང་མེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-247"/>“For those engaged previously in wrongdoing In a futile search for happiness, Even their parents are powerless To save them now.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-302">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-248</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་དག་བདེ་ཕྱིར་དོན་མིན་པ། །སྔན་ཆད་ཉེས་པར་སྤྱད་བྱས་ཀྱང་། །བུ་དང་བུ་མོ་ཆུང་མ་རྣམས། །དེ་རིང་བདག་ལ་འགྲོལ་མི་ནུས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-248"/>“For those engaged previously in wrongdoing In a futile search for happiness, Even their sons and daughters Cannot save them now.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-303">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-249</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་དག་བདེ་ཕྱིར་དོན་མིན་པར། །སྔན་ཆད་ཉེས་པར་སྤྱད་བྱས་ཀྱང་། །མཛའ་བཤེས་ཉེ་དུ་དེ་དག་ཀུན། །རྣམ་པར་དགྲོལ་བར་ཡོང་མི་ནུས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-249"/>“For those engaged previously in wrongdoing In a futile search for happiness, None of their close friends Can come to save them now.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-304">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-250</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་དག་བདེ་ཕྱིར་དོན་མིན་པར། །སྔན་ཆད་ཉེས་པར་སྤྱད་བྱས་ཀྱང་། །བདག་གི་རྩ་ལག་དེ་དག་ཀུན། །དེ་རིང་འགྲོལ་བར་མི་ནུས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-250"/>“For those engaged previously in wrongdoing In a futile search for happiness, None of their other relatives Can save them now.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-305">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-251</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདོད་པ་དམན་པ་རྣམས་སྟེན་ཅིང་། །དམན་པའི་ཆོས་རྣམས་བསྟེན་ནས་ནི། །ཉེས་པའི་ལས་རྣམས་བྱེད་པ་དག །དེ་ཡིས་ངན་འགྲོར་འགྲོ་བར་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-251"/>“Indulging in inferior desires, While following inferior doctrines, They commit low, immoral deeds And proceed to the lower realms.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-306">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-253</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཤེས་རབ་འཆལ་པ་མནར་མེད་པར། །སོང་ནས་སྡུག་བསྔལ་ཚོར་བ་མྱོང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-253"/>“Those who are unwise will experience The anguish of the Hell of Endless Torment.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-307">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-253</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སངས་རྒྱས་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་བུད་མེད་དག །ཕྱི་སའི་དྲི་ལྟར་དམན་པར་བསྒྲགས། །དེ་ཕྱིར་དམན་པ་རྣམས་དང་ནི། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The buddhas have declared that women Are foul-smelling, like excrement.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-308">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-255</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དམན་པའི་བུད་མེད་རྣམས་སྟེན་པ། །བྱིས་པ་དེ་ནི་ཕྱི་ས་ཡི། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-255"/>“Thus, only inferior men have intercourse With women, who are inferior, Like fools who enter houses Carrying bags full of excrement.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-309">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-257</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྐྱལ་པ་བཟུང་ནས་གནས་པ་ཡིན། །ཅི་འདྲའི་ལས་ནི་བྱེད་པ་ལྟར། །དེ་འདྲའི་འབྲས་བུ་ཐོབ་འགྱུར་ཏེ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-257"/>“The quality of one’s actions Determines the quality of fruit that one bears.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-310">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-257</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྒྱལ་པོ་ཡི་ནི་ཆད་པ་དང་། །སྡུག་བསྔལ་བཅིང་བའང་མྱོང་བར་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The punishment of a king May leave one shackled and in pain.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-311">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-259</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བུད་མེད་གཞི་ལས་སྐྱེས་པ་ཡང་། །གསང་དང་བཅིང་བ་མྱོང་<tei:ref folio="F.215.a"/>འགྱུར་ཞིང་། །དམྱལ་སྲུངས་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་སྲེག་པ་དང་། །ངེས་པར་འཆིང་བའང་མྱོང་བར་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-259"/>“Because of women, Men will endure being bound and even killed, And they will surely be burned and bound Again by the guardians of the hells.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-312">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-260</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བུད་མེད་རྣམས་ལ་བརྐམ་པ་ཡི། །བློ་ངན་དེ་དག་བདེ་མི་འགྱུར། །གསལ་ཤིང་མཐོན་པོ་རྣམས་སུ་ནི། །བཙུགས་ཤིང་ཆུར་ཡང་བཅུག་པར་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-260"/>“Those confused men who crave women Will not find happiness But will be impaled on tall stakes And thrown into boiling water.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-313">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-261</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ས་ཡི་སེར་ཀར་བཅུག་ནས་ནི། །དེ་བཞིན་རལ་གྲིས་གདབ་པར་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-261"/>“They will be cast into fissures in the ground And stabbed with swords.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-314">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-261</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་འདྲ་བ་དག་ཐོས་ནས་ནི། །དེ་དག་ཡི་ཆད་བདེ་མི་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Such people, having heard this, Become concerned and uneasy.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-315">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-262</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྨོངས་པ་བུད་མེད་ལྷན་ཅིག་ཏུ། །ཡང་དང་ཡང་དུ་འདུ་འཛི་བྱེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-262"/>“They preoccupy themselves with women And enjoy themselves with them.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-316">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-262</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྡུག་བསྔལ་འདོད་པ་རྣམས་སྟེན་ཅིང་། །སྨད་པ་རྣམས་ཀྱང་སྨྲ་བར་བྱེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>These despicable people indulge in and talk of Sense pleasures, which are full of pain.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-317">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-264</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྨོངས་པ་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་ཆོས་ཐོས་ནས། །དགེ་བར་གསུངས་ཞེས་རྗོད་བྱེད་ཀྱང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-264"/>“When they hear the Dharma, they are confused about its meaning, But they say, ‘Well spoken!’</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-318">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-264</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་སེམས་བུད་མེད་ཕྱི་བཞིན་སོང་། །བྱི་བ་ལ་ནི་བྱི་ལ་བཞིན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Their minds are lost in women, Like a cat’s lost in a mouse.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-319">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-266</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྒྱལ་བས་གསུངས་པ་ཐོས་གྱུར་ནས། །ཡུད་ཙམ་ཞིག་ནི་ཡིད་བྱུང་ཡང་། །ཧ་ལ་ཧ་ལའི་དུག་འདྲ་བའི། །འདོད་ཆགས་ཀྱིས་ནི་དེ་ཡང་འཁྲུགས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-266"/>“Even if they feel a momentary sense of agitation By listening to the words of the Victorious One, Desire will arise again in their minds As if it were halāhala poison.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-320">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-268</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཇི་ལྟར་ཕག་ནི་ཡུད་ཙམ་ཞིག །དངངས་ཤིང་སྐྲག་པར་བྱུང་གྱུར་ཀྱང་། །དེས་ནི་ཕྱི་ས་མཐོང་ན་ཡང་། །ཆགས་པ་སྐྱེད་པར་བྱེད་པ་ལྟར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-268"/>“A pig may become timid and afraid For just a single moment, But as soon as it sees excrement, Its desires are excited again.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-321">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-270</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་བཞིན་བྱིས་པ་བདེ་འདོད་རྣམས། །རྒྱལ་བའི་བསྟན་པ་སྤངས་ནས་ནི། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-270"/>“In that same way, fools seeking happiness Abandon the Victorious One’s teachings.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-322">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-270</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདོད་པ་དམན་པ་རྣམས་བསྟེན་པས། །དེས་ནི་ངན་འགྲོར་འགྲོ་བར་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>By indulging in the lowly sense pleasures They proceed to the lower realms.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-323">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-272</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདོད་པ་རྣམས་ལ་ཆགས་མྱོས་ནས། །ཤིན་ཏུ་སྡིག་པའི་ལས་བྱས་ཤིང་། །ཚུལ་ཁྲིམས་ཅན་དག་བསླུས་བྱས་ནས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-272"/>“Intoxicated by their lust for sense pleasures They perform extremely evil deeds, And criticize those with moral discipline.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-324">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-272</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཕྱིས་ནི་ངན་འགྲོར་འགྲོ་བར་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Ultimately, they will proceed to the lower realms.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-325">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-274</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཤེས་རབ་ཅན་གྱིས་དལ་རྙེད་ཅིང་། །དེ་འདྲའི་ཆོས་ནི་ཐོས་གྱུར་ནས། །འདོད་ཀུན་སྤངས་ནས་འདི་ལ་ནི། །མཁས་པ་མངོན་པར་རབ་བྱུང་ཤིག །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-274"/>“As soon as he has the opportunity, a wise man Who has listened to a teaching such as this one Ought to abandon all sense pleasures And go forth as a renunciant.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-326">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-276</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྒྱལ་པོ་ཆེན་པོ་སྐྱེས་པ་འདོད་པ་ལ་སྟེན་པ་རྣམས་ཀྱི་སྐྱོན་ནི་དེ་དག་ཡིན་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-276"/>“Great King, these are the faults of men who indulge in sense pleasures.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-327">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-276</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདོད་པའི་གཞི་དང་། འདོད་པའི་རྨ་དང་། འདོད་པ་ལ་ལྷག་པར་ཞེན་པ་རྣམས་ནི་སེམས་ཅན་དམྱལ་བ་པ་རྣམས་ཀྱི་ཚོར་བ་<tei:ref folio="F.215.b"/>མྱོང་བར་འགྱུར་རོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Those who cling to sense pleasure, to the causes of sense pleasure, and to the bases of sense pleasure will experience the hell realms.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-328">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-276</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྒྱལ་པོ་ཆེན་པོ་དེ་ལྟ་བས་ན་ཁྱོད་ཀྱིས་རྟག་པར་རྒྱུན་ཏུ་སངས་རྒྱས་རྗེས་སུ་དྲན་པ་བསྒོམ་པར་བྱའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Therefore, Great King, you must constantly and continuously cultivate mindfulness of the Buddha.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-329">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-276</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཁྱོད་ཀྱིས་ལུས་སུ་གཏོགས་པའི་སེམས་རྗེས་སུ་དྲན་པ་བསྒོམ་པར་བྱའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>You must cultivate mindfulness of the body.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-330">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-278</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ལྟར་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་བད་སའི་རྒྱལ་པོ་འཆར་བྱེད་ལ་དེ་ལྟ་དེ་ལྟར་ཆོས་བསྟན་པར་མཛད་དེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-278"/>That is how the Blessed One taught King Udayana of Vatsa.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-331">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-278</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཆོས་བསྟན་པ་དེས་བད་སའི་རྒྱལ་པོ་འཆར་བྱེད་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་ལ་དགའ་བ་དང་། རབ་ཏུ་དགའ་བ་དང་། མཆོག་ཏུ་དགའ་བ་ཐོབ་པར་གྱུར་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>As a result of that teaching, King Udayana of Vatsa was delighted, joyful, and extremely happy with the Thus-Gone One.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-332">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-279</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ལ་བད་སའི་རྒྱལ་པོ་འཆར་བྱེད་ཀྱིས་འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་གསོལ་ཏོ། །བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཇི་ཙམ་དུ་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་དགྲ་བཅོམ་པ་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱིས་སྐྱེས་པ་དང་། བུད་མེད་རྣམས་ཀྱི་སྐྱོན་བསམ་གྱིས་མི་ཁྱབ་པའི་བར་དེ་དག་བཀའ་སྩལ་ཅིང་ལེགས་པར་གསུངས་པ་ནི་ངོ་མཚར་ལགས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-279"/>Then King Udayana of Vatsa said to the Blessed One, “Blessed One, the blessed, thus-gone, worthy, completely perfect Buddha’s explanation of the excellent teaching on the inconceivably numerous faults of men and women is truly amazing.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-333">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-279</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་བདག་ནི་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་དང་། ཆོས་དང་དགེ་སློང་གི་དགེ་འདུན་ལ་སྐྱབས་སུ་མཆི་སྟེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Blessed One, I seek refuge in the Blessed One, the Dharma, and the Saṇgha.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-334">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-279</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མཚོན་ཆ་སྤངས་ཤིང་དབྱུག་པ་སྤངས་ལ་ངོ་ཚ་མཆིས་ཤིང་སྲོག་ཆགས་འབྱུང་པོ་ཐམས་ཅད་ལ་སྙིང་བརྩེ་བར་ཞུགས་པ་ལགས་ཀྱིས།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>I have abandoned my weapons and my clubs. I have become modest, and I feel love for all living beings.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-335">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-279</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་བདག་དགེ་བསྙེན་དུ་གཟུང་དུ་གསོལ། བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་དེ་སྐད་ཅེས་བཀའ་སྩལ་ནས།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Blessed One, please accept me as a male lay disciple.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-336">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-280</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བད་སའི་རྒྱལ་པོ་འཆར་བྱེད་དང་། དགེ་སློང་དེ་དག་དང་། བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་དེ་དག་དང་། ལྷ་དང་མི་དང་ལྷ་མ་ཡིན་དང་། དྲི་ཟར་བཅས་པའི་འཇིག་རྟེན་ཡི་རངས་ཏེ་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་གསུངས་པ་ལ་མངོན་པར་བསྟོད་དོ།། །།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-280"/>When the Blessed One had finished teaching, King Udayana of Vatsa, the monks, bodhisattvas, gods, humans, asuras, and gandharvas, together with the whole world, rejoiced and praised the Blessed One’s words.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-337">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-281</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཕགས་པ་དཀོན་མཆོག་བརྩེགས་པ་ཆེན་པོའི་ཆོས་ཀྱི་རྣམ་གྲངས་ལེའུ་སྟོང་ཕྲག་བརྒྱ་པ་ལས་བད་སའི་རྒྱལ་པོ་འཆར་བྱེད་ཀྱིས་ཞུས་པའི་ལེའུ་ཞེས་བྱ་སྟེ་ཉི་ཤུ་རྩ་དགུ་པ་རྫོགས་སོ།། །།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-281"/>Thus concludes The Episode “King Udayana of Vatsa’s Questions,” the twenty-ninth of the one hundred thousand sections of the Dharma discourse known as The Noble Great Heap of Jewels.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu id="UT22084-043-010-TU-338">
    <prop type="location-id">UT22084-043-010-282</prop>
    <tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྒྱ་གར་གྱི་མཁན་པོ་ཛི་ན་མི་ཏྲ་དང་། སུ་རེན་དྲ་བོ་དྷི་དང་། ཞུ་ཆེན་གྱི་ལོ་ཙྪ་བ་བན་དེ་ཡེ་ཤེས་སྡེ་ལ་སོགས་པས་བསྒྱུར་ཅིང་ཞུས་ཏེ་གཏན་ལ་ཕབ་པ།​། །​།</seg>
            </tuv>
    <tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-043-010-282"/>Translated, edited, and finalized by, among others, the Indian preceptors Jinamitra and Surendrabodhi and the chief editor-translator, Bandé Yeshé Dé.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
</body>
</tmx>