<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tmx xmlns="http://www.lisa.org/tmx14" xmlns:eft="http://read.84000.co/ns/1.0" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" version="1.4b">
<header creationtool="InterText" creationtoolversion="1.0" datatype="PlainText" segtype="block" adminlang="en-us" srclang="bo" o-tmf="XML aligned text" eft:text-id="UT22084-062-007" eft:text-version="1.1.5 2020"/>
<body>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.95.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གླང་པོའི་རྩལ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The Strength of the Elephant</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.95.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཐེག་པ་ཆེན་པོའི་མདོ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The Great Vehicle Sūtra</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.95.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སངས་རྒྱས་དང་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཐམས་ཅད་ལ་ཕྱག་འཚལ་ལོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-37"/>Homage to all buddhas and bodhisattvas.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.95.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདི་སྐད་བདག་གིས་ཐོས་པའི་དུས་གཅིག་ན། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-38"/>Thus did I hear at one time.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.95.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་བྱ་རྒོད་ཀྱི་ཕུང་པོའི་རི་ལ་དགེ་སློང་ལྔ་བརྒྱ་ཙམ་གྱི་དགེ་སློང་གི་དགེ་འདུན་ཆེན་པོ་དང་། བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་མངོན་པར་གྲགས་པས་མངོན་པར་གྲགས་པ། གཟུངས་ཐོབ་པ། སྤོབས་པ་ཐོགས་པ་མེད་པ། གཉིས་སུ་མེད་པའི་ཆོས་འཆད་པ། རྫུ་འཕྲུལ་རྣམ་པར་འཕྲུལ་པ་བསམ་གྱིས་མི་ཁྱབ་པ་དང་ལྡན་པ་དྲུག་ཁྲི་དང་ཡང་ཐབས་ཅིག་ཏུ་བཞུགས་ཏེ</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The Blessed One was dwelling on Gṛdhrakūṭa Mountain together with a large saṅgha of monks comprised of five hundred monks as well as sixty thousand bodhisattvas who were all renowned,<tei:note xml:id="UT22084-062-007-39"/> had attained the dhāraṇīs , possessed unobstructed eloquence, taught the Dharma of nonduality, and displayed inconceivable miraculous powers.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.95.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདི་ལྟ་སྟེ། བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོ་བརྩོན་འགྲུས་དཔེ་མེད་བློ་གྲོས་དང་། མངོན་པར་གནོན་པའི་སྒྲ་སྒྲོགས་གཟི་བརྗིད་སྙིང་པོ་དང་། བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་རིན་པོ་ཆེ་བཞིའི་མེ་ཏོག་རྒྱས་པ་དང་། གློག་ཆེན་སྒྲོན་མ་དང་། མཐའ་ཡས་པར་ལྟ་ཞིང་ཡུལ་ཐམས་ཅད་ལས་འདས་པ་དང་། རི་རབ་བརྩེགས་པ་ལྟར་མངོན་པར་འཕགས་པ་དང་། མངོན་པར་དགའ་བས་མགུ་བ་སྐྱེད་པ་དང་། དཔུང་པ་དྲི་མ་མེད་པས་འོད་ཟེར་བཅོམ་པ་དང་། སེམས་ཅན་གྱི་བསམ་པ་ངེས་པའི་དོན་གྱི་ཕ་རོལ་དུ་བགྲོད་པར་དོང་བ་དང་། རྡོ་རྗེ་ལྟ་བུར་བརྟན་པ་ཐོབ་པ་དང་། སྒྲར་བརྗོད་པ་དང་། དབྱངས་དང་ང་རོ་ཐམས་ཅད་ལས་འདས་པ་དང་། ཚངས་པའི་སྒྲ་གཟི་བརྗིད་མངོན་པར་འཕགས་པ་དང་། གྲགས་པའི་སྒྲས་འཇིགས་པ་བཅོམ་པ་དང་། དགེ་བའི་རྩ་བ་རིན་པོ་ཆེ་ཐམས་ཅད་བསགས་པ་དང་། བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོ་འཇམ་དཔལ་གཞོན་ནུར་གྱུར་པ་དང་། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They included the bodhisattva great beings Perseverant Beyond Compare and Wise; Essence of the Splendor of Overwhelming Sound, Blossom of the Four Jewels; Light Beam of Great Lightning; Seeing Beyond Extremes and Transcending All Sensory Objects; Lofty Like Mount Meru’s Summit; Gladdened with Supreme Joy; Light Vanquishing with Undefiled Forces; Reaching the Far Shore of Definitive Meaning to Fulfill Beings’ Aspirations; Possessing Vajralike Solidity; Beyond All Utterances, Speech, and Sounds; Voice More Majestic Than Brahmā’s; Overcoming Fears with Words of Renown; Accumulation of All Precious Roots of Virtue; and the bodhisattva great being Youthful Mañjuśrī.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.95.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ལ་སོགས་པ་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་དྲུག་ཁྲི་རྣམས་དང་ཐབས་ཅིག་གོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>These and other such bodhisattvas in attendance were sixty thousand in number.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.95.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་ཚེ་དང་ལྡན་པ་ཤ་ར་དྭ་ཏིའི་བུ་ཕྱི་དྲོའི་དུས་ན། ནང་དུ་ཡང་དག་འཇོག་ལས་ལངས་ཏེ་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ག་ལ་བ་དེར་སོང་ངོ་། །ཡང་དེའི་ཚེ་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཤིང་གཞན་ཞིག་གི་དྲུང་ན་རབ་ཏུ་ཞི་བ་སྒྲུབ་པ་ཞེས་བྱ་བའི་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་ལ་མཉམ་པར་བཞག་སྟེ་བཞུགས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-40"/>In the afternoon, the venerable Śāradvatīputra, after arising from inner absorption, approached the Blessed One who at that time was sitting in front of another tree, immersed in the absorption known as accomplishment of perfect peace .</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.95.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་ཚེ་དང་ལྡན་པ་ཤ་ར་དྭ་ཏིའི་བུས་རྒྱང་རིང་པོ་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་སྤྱོད་ལམ་རབ་ཏུ་ཞི་བ་མཐོང་བ་དང་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>From afar, the venerable Śāradvatīputra saw the Blessed One, who was peaceful.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.96.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མྱུར་དུ་རྩྭ་བསྡུས་ནས་ཕྱོགས་གཅིག་ཏུ་སྐྱིལ་མོ་ཀྲུང་བཅས་ལུས་བསྲང་སྟེ། <tei:ref folio="F.96.a"/>དྲན་པ་མངོན་དུ་བྱས་ནས་འདུག་གོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He quickly gathered some grass and sat down mindfully to one side with his legs crossed and back straightened. </seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.96.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་དེར་འདུག་མ་ཐག་ཏུ་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>As soon as he sat there,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.96.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཨེ་མའོ་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པའི་སྤྱོད་པ་རབ་ཏུ་ཞི་བ་འདི་དང་། བདེ་བ་དང་། ཡིད་བདེ་བ་འདི་ངོ་མཚར་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“How marvelous are the Tathāgata’s perfectly peaceful behavior, happiness, and bliss!</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.96.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སེམས་ཅན་གང་དག་ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་རང་བཞིན་གྱིས་མཉམ་པར་བཞག་པར་རབ་ཏུ་ཤེས་པ་དེ་དག་ནི་བདེ་བ་དང་ལྡན་པ་ཡིན་ནོ་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Happy are the beings who realize that all phenomena naturally rest in the state of absorption!”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.96.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྙམ་དུ་སེམས་ལ་སེམས་ཀྱི་རྟོག་པ་དེ་ལྟ་བུ་སྐྱེས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>thoughts arose in his mind, such as:</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.96.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་དགོངས་ཤིང་མཁྱེན་བཞིན་དུ་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་དེ་ལས་བཞེངས་ཏེ་མགུར་བསལ་བའི་སྒྲ་ཕྱུང་ངོ་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-41"/>The Blessed One, perceiving and understanding this, emerged from his concentration and made the sound of clearing his throat.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.96.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་ཚེ་དང་ལྡན་པ་ཤ་ར་དྭ་ཏིའི་བུས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱི་མགུར་བསལ་བའི་སྒྲ་ཐོས་པ་དང་དགའ་མགུ་རངས་པར་གྱུར་ནས། བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ག་ལ་བ་དེར་སོང་སྟེ་ཕྱིན་པ་དང་། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Hearing the Blessed One clear his throat, the venerable Śāradvatīputra became filled with joy and inspiration, and walked toward where the Blessed One was sitting.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.96.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱི་སྤྱན་སྔར་འདུག་སྟེ། བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ལ་ཕྱག་འཚལ་ནས་ངོ་མཚར་དུ་གྱུར་ཏེ། །དེའི་ཚེ་ཚིགས་སུ་བཅད་པ་འདི་དག་སྨྲས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>When he arrived in the Blessed One’s presence, he prostrated to him in amazement and uttered the following verses:</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.96.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྟོང་པའི་ཆོས་ལ་ཇི་ལྟར་བདག་བཟོད་བཞིན། །གང་དག་སེམས་ཅན་ཡང་དག་མི་རྟོག་ཅིང་། །ཆོས་ལའང་ནམས་ཀྱང་རྟོག་པར་མི་བྱེད་པ། །འཇིག་རྟེན་ན་ནི་དེ་དག་མཉམ་པར་བཞག །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-42"/>“In the way I accept that phenomena are empty, Those who neither conceptualize beings Nor ever conceptualize phenomena Remain in the world in absorption.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.96.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སེམས་ཅན་འཁྲུལ་ལ་ནམས་ཀྱང་མི་ལྟ་ཞིང་། །ཆོས་རྣམས་ནམ་མཁའ་བཞིན་དུ་བསམས་བྱས་ནས། །གང་དག་སྒྱུ་མའི་ངོ་བོ་ཉིད་མོས་པ། །གང་དག་བདག་ཏུ་ལྟ་མེད་དེ་དག་བདེ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-43"/>“Never ever looking at the confusion of beings, And considering phenomena to be just like space, Happy are those who believe in the illusory nature And do not hold the view of a self.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.96.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདི་དག་སེམས་ཅན་ཡིན་ནམ་མ་ཡིན་ཞེས། །འདུ་ཤེས་ཐམས་ཅད་ལ་ནི་མི་དམིགས་པ། །སེམས་ཅན་ཀུན་ལ་འདུ་ཤེས་མེད་པ་དང་། །གང་དག་སེམས་ཅན་ལྟ་མེད་དེ་དག་བདེ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-44"/>“Happy are those who do not focus on any conception, Such as ‘these are beings’ or ‘these are not beings,’ Who have no conception of any being, And do not hold the view that there are beings.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.96.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རིལ་པོར་འདུ་ཤེས་ནམས་ཀྱང་གང་མ་ཆགས། །ནམས་ཀྱང་དངོས་པོའི་འདུ་ཤེས་རྨོངས་པ་མེད། །ལྡང་བར་མི་བྱེད་འདུག་པར་བྱེད་པའང་མེད། །གང་དག་སྲོག་ཏུ་ལྟ་མེད་དེ་དག་བདེ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-45"/>“Happy are those who are not attached to any conception of a substantial whole, Who are without the deluded conception of a substantial thing, Who neither cause things to arise nor to remain, And who are without the view of a soul.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.96.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སེམས་ཅན་ཐ་དད་མི་བྱེད་མཁས་པ་གང་། །ཆོས་ཀྱི་དབྱིངས་དང་འགལ་བར་མི་འགྱུར་ལ། །གང་ཟག་འདུ་ཤེས་ཐམས་ཅད་རྣམ་པར་བཤིག །གང་དག་ཐ་དད་བློ་མེད་དེ་དག་བདེ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-46"/>“Happy are the wise ones who do not differentiate among beings, Who do not contradict the domain of truth, Who eliminate all conceptions of personhood, And who do not think in terms of dichotomies.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.96.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་དག་སྦྱིན་དང་ཚུལ་ཁྲིམས་རྟག་ཏུ་གནས། །འཇུངས་པའི་བསམ་པར་ནམས་ཀྱང་མ་གྱུར་ཅིང་། །གོང་བུའི་ཆོས་ལའང་ཡང་དག་མི་གནས་པ། །གང་དག་ཚུལ་ཁྲིམས་རློམ་མེད་དེ་དག་བདེ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-47"/>“Happy are those who always maintain generosity and discipline, Neither forming the concept of miserliness Nor fixating on the notion of accumulation, And who remain free of moral conceit. </seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.96.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་དག་བཟོད་དང་<tei:ref folio="F.96.b"/>ངེས་པའི་ཡོན་ཏན་འཕགས། །གང་དག་ཐབ་མོ་དག་ལའང་མི་ལྟ་ཞིང་། །བརྩོན་འགྲུས་ལྡན་མིན་ལེ་ལོ་ཅན་ཡང་མིན། །གང་དག་བཟོད་པའི་འདུ་ཤེས་མེད་པ་དེ་དག་བདེ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-48"/>“Happy are those who excel in the qualities of endurance and determination,<tei:note xml:id="UT22084-062-007-49"/> Who are free from the notion of conflict, Who are neither zealous nor lazy, And who have no preconception concerning patience.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.96.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་དག་བསམ་གཏན་བྱེད་ཅིང་བརྟན་པ་མི་གནས་པ། །དེ་ཡང་གཡེང་བར་རྣམ་པར་མི་སེམས་པ། །མཉམ་པར་བཞག་པའི་ཆོས་རྣམས་རབ་ཏུ་ཤེས། །གང་དག་བསམ་གཏན་འདུ་ཤེས་མེད་པ་དེ་དག་བདེ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-50"/>“Happy are those who are not fixated on concentration and stability,<tei:note xml:id="UT22084-062-007-51"/> And yet do not think about distractions— Who understand the qualities of meditative equipoise And have no preconceptions about concentration.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.96.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་དག་འདུ་ཤེས་མེད་ཅིང་འདི་ལ་ཤེས་རབ་མེད། །མི་ཤེས་དབང་དུ་འགྲོ་བའང་མ་ཡིན་ལ། །མཁས་པའང་མ་ཡིན་རྨོངས་པའང་ཡོད་མ་ཡིན། །གང་དག་ཤེས་རབ་འདུ་ཤེས་མེད་དག་བདེ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-52"/>“Happy are those who are free from preconceptions about anything, Who have no insight regarding anything and yet are not under the sway of ignorance, Who are neither learned nor deluded, And who have no preconceptions about wisdom.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.96.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཇི་ལྟར་དགོན་པ་དེ་བཞིན་གྲོང་ན་གནས། །གཉི་གར་འདུ་ཤེས་མཚུངས་ཤིང་མཉམ་པར་འཇུག །གྲོང་གི་སྤྱོད་ཡུལ་སྨོད་པར་མི་བྱེད་ཅིང་། །གང་དག་དགོན་པས་མི་རློམ་དེ་དག་བདེ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-53"/>“Happy are those who dwell in a city as if in retreat, Who treat them equally, with similar conceptions of both— Who do not disparage city life But also do not idealize retreat.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.96.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་དག་བསོད་སྙོམས་ཁྱིམ་དང་བཅས་པར་སྤྱོད། །དེ་དག་བསོད་སྙོམས་དེ་ཡི་འདུ་ཤེས་མེད། །བསོད་སྙོམས་སྤྱོད་པ་བདག་ཡིན་སྙམ་མི་སེམས། །གང་དག་བསོད་སྙོམས་འདུ་ཤེས་མེད་དག་བདེ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-321"/>“Happy are those practice alms-begging as a householder Without any preconception about this alms-begging. Without entertaining thoughts such as ‘I am a mendicant,’ They have no preconceptions about alms-begging.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.96.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་དག་བོར་བའི་ཕྱག་དར་ཁྲོད་པ་རྣམས། །བླངས་ནས་བདག་གིས་ལུས་ལ་འཆང་བར་བྱེད། །བདག་ནི་གོས་ངན་སྙམ་དུ་དེ་མི་སེམས། །གང་དག་གཞན་ལ་མི་སྨོད་དེ་དག་བདེ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-322"/>“Happy are those who pick up refuse-rags And wear them on their body. They do not think ‘I have miserable clothing,’<tei:note xml:id="UT22084-062-007-54"/> And they do not put down others.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.96.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སངས་རྒྱས་གནང་ཞིང་བདེ་གཤེགས་བསྔགས་པ་ཡི། །ཆོས་གོས་གསུམ་ལས་ལྷག་པར་མི་འཆང་ཞིང་། །བདག་ནི་འཇིགས་མེད་ཡིན་པར་མི་རྟོག་པ། །གང་དག་ང་རྒྱལ་མེད་པ་དེ་དག་བདེ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-55"/>“Happy are those who wear nothing but the three Dharma robes Approved by the Buddha and praised by the sugatas, Yet do not think ‘I am fearless,’ And remain without pride.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.96.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་ན་བདག་མེད་སེམས་ཅན་ཡོད་མིན་པའི། །གང་དག་ཆོས་མཆོག་དམ་པ་འཆད་བྱེད་པ། །བདག་ནི་འཆད་མཁན་ཡིན་པར་སེམས་པའང་མེད། །གང་དག་མེད་པར་མ་གྱུར་དེ་དག་བདེ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-56"/>“Happy are those who teach the supreme and sacred Dharma In which there is neither self nor being. They do not even think ‘I am a master teacher,’ But they also do not amount to nothing.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.96.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དཀར་པོ་ཀུན་ལ་ཡང་དག་འདུ་ཤེས་མེད། །སྙིང་པོ་མེད་པ་རྗེས་སུ་འདུ་ཤེས་མེད། །དཀར་དང་གནག་པར་གང་དག་མི་སེམས་པ། །གང་དག་གཉིས་སུ་མི་སྤྱོད་དེ་དག་བདེ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-57"/>“Happy are those who are free from preconceptions regarding any virtue, Who do not conceive of anything as an essence or a substance,<tei:note xml:id="UT22084-062-007-58"/> Who do not think of anything as virtuous or nonvirtuous, But who do not behave in a dualistic way.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.96.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་དག་ལངས་ལ་ལངས་པར་འདུ་ཤེས་མེད། །འདུག་ཀྱང་འདུག་པར་འདུ་ཤེས་ཡོད་མ་ཡིན། །ཉིན་མཚན་ཕྱད་པར་འཆག་ཅིང་བརྩོན་འགྲུས་རྩོམ། །གང་དག་སྤྲོས་པ་མེད་པ་དེ་དག་བདེ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-59"/>“Happy are those who stand but have no preconception about standing, Who sit but have no preconception about sitting, Who at all times cultivate diligence as they move about And remain without mental elaboration.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.97.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་དག་གནས་མིན་གནས་པར་མི་རྟོག་ཅིང་། །ཁྱད་པར་ཤེས་པ་ཞི་བར་མི་རྟོག་ལ། །དེ་<tei:ref folio="F.97.a"/>བཞིན་གཤེགས་དང་མུ་སྟེགས་ཁྱད་པར་མེད། །གང་དག་མཆོག་ཏུ་རློམ་སེམས་མེད་པ་དེ་དག་བདེ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-60"/>“Happy are those who are free from preconceptions about abiding or non-abiding, Who do not conceive of some special knowledge as the state of peace, Who make no distinction between tathāgatas and non-Buddhists, And who are without assumptions about what is “the best.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.97.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་ལ་གྲངས་དང་བགྲང་བའང་ཡོད་མ་ཡིན། །ནམ་མཁའི་དབྱིངས་ལྟར་མཉམ་ཉིད་མི་གཏོང་ལ། །བདག་དང་སེམས་ཅན་ཐ་དད་མི་སེམས་པ། །གང་དག་ཁྱད་པར་ཐོབ་མེད་དེ་དག་བདེ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-61"/>“Happy are those for whom there is neither number nor enumeration, Who do not disregard equality that is like the expanse of space, Who do not think of themselves and others as distinct, And who have no special achievements.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.97.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་དག་སྒྱུ་མར་གྱུར་ཅིང་རྨི་ལམ་སྤྱོད། །རབ་ཏུ་མ་རྨོངས་མིག་ཡོར་ལྟ་བུར་གྱུར། །འཇིག་རྟེན་དག་ན་ཆུ་ཟླ་བཞིན་དུ་སྤྱོད། །གང་དག་ཀུན་ཏུ་མི་བརྩོན་དེ་དག་བདེ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-62"/>“Happy are those who appear as an illusion and behave as if in a dream, Who resemble optical illusions but are not deluded, Who are active in the worlds like reflections of the moon in water, And who do not strive in any way.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.97.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སེམས་ཅན་གང་དག་མཁས་ལ་དོན་དམ་ལྟ། །བརྡ་དང་ཐ་སྙད་སྙིང་པོ་མེད་པར་ཤེས། །རབ་ཏུ་ཞི་བའི་ཆོས་རྣམས་རྗེས་སུ་རྟོགས། །གང་དག་མཚན་མའི་སྤྱོད་ཡུལ་མ་ཡིན་དེ་དག་བདེའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-63"/>“Happy are the beings who are wise and behold the ultimate, Who understand that names and conventions have no essence, Who realize that phenomena are in the state of peace, And who remain unbound by the range of conceptual signs.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.97.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་ཚེ་དང་ལྡན་པ་ཤ་ར་དྭ་ཏིའི་བུ་ལ་ལེགས་སོ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་བྱིན་ཏེ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-64"/>Thereupon the Blessed One congratulated the venerable Śāradvatīputra:</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.97.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཤ་ར་དྭ་ཏིའི་བུ་འདི་ལྟར་ཤེས་རབ་ཟབ་པ་ལ་སྤྱོད་པའི་ཆོས་ལ་མཆོག་ཏུ་གྱུར་པ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Śāradvatīputra, supreme is this teaching that engages in this way in the profound wisdom!</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.97.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ལེགས་སོ་ལེགས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>It is excellent, excellent!</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.97.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཤཱ་རིའི་བུ་དེ་བས་ན་བྱ་རྒོད་ཀྱི་ཕུང་པོའི་རི་འདི་ལ་དགེ་སློང་དང་། བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཇི་སྙེད་ནང་དུ་ཡང་དག་འཇོག་ལ་ཞུགས་པ་དེ་དག་ཐམས་ཅད་ཁྱོད་ཀྱིས་སྡུས་ཤིག །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Therefore, Śāradvatīputra, assemble all the monks and bodhisattvas abiding in inner absorption on this Gṛdhrakūṭa Mountain, as many as there may be.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.97.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཤཱ་རིའི་བུས་གསོལ་པ། བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་བདག་ནི་མི་སྤྲོའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Blessed One,” replied Śāradvatīputra, “I would prefer not to do so.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.97.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ཅིའི་སླད་དུ་ཞེ་ན། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Why?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.97.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གླང་པོ་ཆེན་པོ་དག་ནི་མགུ་བར་དཀའ་བའི་སླད་དུའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Because elephants are difficult to please.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.97.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་དེའི་ཚེ་ཉིད་ཀྱི་སྐུ་ལས་འོད་ཟེར་ཕྱུང་ནས་དེས་འཇིག་རྟེན་གྱི་ཁམས་མཐའ་ཡས་མུ་མེད་པ་ན་གནས་པའི་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་རྣམས་ལ་བསྐུལ་བ་དང་། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-66"/>At that very moment, the Blessed One emitted light rays from his body and he summoned the bodhisattvas abiding in infinite world systems.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.97.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱ་རྒོད་ཀྱི་ཕུང་པོའི་རི་གང་ན་བ་དང་། བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་གང་ན་བ་དེར་ལྷགས་ནས་བར་སྣང་གི་ནམ་མཁའ་ལ་གནས་པར་གྱུར་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They reached the place where the Blessed One was residing on Gṛdhrakūṭa Mountain and hovered in the sky.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.97.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དགེ་སློང་དང་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོ་གང་དག་ནང་དུ་ཡང་དག་འཇོག་ལ་ཞུགས་པ་དེ་དག་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱང་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་གང་ན་བ་དེར་ལྷགས་པར་གྱུར་ཏོ། །རྒྱལ་པོའི་ཁབ་ཀྱི་གྲོང་ཁྱེར་ཆེན་པོ་ནས་ཀྱང་སྲོག་ཆགས་བརྒྱ་སྟོང་དུ་མ་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ག་ལ་བ་དེར་ལྷགས་པར་གྱུར་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>All the monks and bodhisattva great beings who had been abiding in inner absorption also arrived where the Blessed One was residing, as did hundreds of thousands of beings from the great city of Rājagṛha.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.97.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་ཐམས་ཅད་ཡོད་པའི་འཁོར་འདུས་པར་མཁྱེན་ནས་འཇམ་དཔལ་གཞོན་ནུར་གྱུར་པའི་བཞིན་ལ་གཟིགས་སོ། །གཟིགས་ནས་ཀྱང་འཛུམ་པ་མཛད་<tei:ref folio="F.97.b"/>དོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-67"/>Then the Blessed One, knowing that all were present in the assembly, looked at the face of Youthful Mañjuśrī and smiled.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.97.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་དེ་ཉིད་ཀྱི་ཚེ་འཇམ་དཔལ་གཞོན་ནུར་གྱུར་པ་སྟན་ལས་ལངས་ཏེ། བླ་གོས་ཕྲག་པ་གཅིག་ལ་གཟར་ནས་པུས་མོ་གཡས་པའི་ལྷ་ང་ས་ལ་བཙུགས་ཏེ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>At that moment, Youthful Mañjuśrī rose from his seat, draped his robe over one shoulder, and knelt on his right knee.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.97.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་གང་ན་བ་དེ་ལོགས་སུ་ཐལ་མོ་སྦྱར་བ་བཏུད་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ལ་འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་གསོལ་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He bowed in the direction of the Blessed One with joined palms and asked him,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.97.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་དགྲ་བཅོམ་པ་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་སངས་རྒྱས་རྒྱུ་དང་རྐྱེན་མ་མཆིས་པར་འཛུམ་པ་མི་མཛད་ན། བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་འཛུམ་པ་མཛད་པའི་རྒྱུ་གང་ལགས། རྐྱེན་གང་ལགས། དེ་སྐད་ཅེས་གསོལ་པ་དང་། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“As the tathāgatas, the worthy ones, the complete and perfect buddhas do not smile without causes and conditions, what are the causes for your smile, what are the conditions for it?”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.97.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་འཇམ་དཔལ་གཞོན་ནུར་གྱུར་པ་ལ་འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་བཀའ་སྩལ་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The Blessed One replied to Youthful Mañjuśrī,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.97.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་སངས་རྒྱས་ཁྲི་རྣམས་ཀྱིས། བྱ་རྒོད་ཀྱི་ཕུང་པོའི་རི་འདི་ལ་གླང་པོའི་རྩལ་ལྟ་བུ་ཞེས་བྱ་བའི་ཆོས་ཀྱི་རྣམ་གྲངས་བཤད་དོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Mañjuśrī, ten thousand buddhas have expounded the Dharma discourse known as ‘Like the Strength of the Elephant’ on this Gṛdhrakūṭa Mountain.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.97.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་ཚེ་དང་ལྡན་པ་ཀུན་དགའ་བོ་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་བཀའ་སྩལ་པ་ཐོས་པ་དང་། མྱུར་བ་མྱུར་བར་རིངས་པའི་ཚུལ་དུ་སྟན་ལས་ལངས་ཏེ། ཆོས་གོས་ཕྲག་པ་གཅིག་ལ་གཟར་ནས་པུས་མོ་གཡས་པའི་ལྷ་ང་ས་ལ་བཙུགས་ཏེ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-69"/>When the venerable Ānanda heard what the Blessed One had said, he swiftly rose from his seat, draped his robe over one shoulder, and knelt on his right knee.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.97.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་གང་ན་བ་དེ་ལོགས་སུ་ཐལ་མོ་སྦྱར་བ་བཏུད་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ལ་འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་གསོལ་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He bowed in the direction of the Blessed One with joined palms and made this request:</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.97.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ད་ཡང་གླང་པོའི་རྩལ་ལྟ་བུ་ཞེས་བགྱི་བའི་ཆོས་ཀྱི་རྣམ་གྲངས་བདག་ལ་བཤད་ན་ལེགས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Blessed One, it would be excellent if you could now teach me this Dharma discourse known as ‘Like the Strength of the Elephant.’</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.97.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བདེ་བར་གཤེགས་པ་བདག་ལ་བསྟན་ན་ལེགས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Sugata, it would be excellent if you could explain this to me.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.97.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་འཇམ་དཔལ་གཞོན་ནུར་གྱུར་པའི་བཞིན་ལ་གཟིགས་ནས་འཛུམ་པ་མཛད་པའི་ཆོས་ཀྱི་རྣམ་གྲངས་དེ་དེང་སང་ཐོས་པར་དཀོན་ལ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>It is rare nowadays to hear a Dharma discourse that would cause you, Blessed One, to smile upon seeing the face of Youthful Mañjuśrī.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.97.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཆོས་ཀྱི་རྣམ་གྲངས་དེ་ངོ་མཚར་དུ་འགྱུར་ཞིང་ཟབ་ལ་ཟབ་པར་སྣང་བ་ལགས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Such a Dharma discourse must be wonderful. It must be as profound as it seems to be.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.97.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་བཀའ་སྩལ་པ། ཀུན་དགའ་བོ་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-325"/>“Ānanda,” replied the Blessed One,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.97.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདི་ལྟར་ཁྱོད་ལྷག་མཐོང་ལ་མཁས་ཤིང་དཔྱོད་པ་ལེགས་སོ་ལེགས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“you are indeed skilled in the practice of discernment and your analysis is excellent, excellent.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.97.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་བས་ན་ཀུན་དགའ་བོ་ཁྱོད་ལེགས་པར་ཤིན་ཏུ་ཉོན་ལ་ཡིད་ལ་ཟུང་ཤིག་དང་ངས་བཤད་དོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Therefore, Ānanda, listen very well and keep this in mind. I will explain it to you.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.97.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ལེགས་སོ་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Excellent, Blessed One,”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.97.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཞེས་ཚེ་དང་ལྡན་པ་ཀུན་དགའ་བོ་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱི་ལྟར་ཉན་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>the venerable Ānanda agreed, and he listened as requested.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.97.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་ཆོས་ཀྱི་རྣམ་གྲངས་འདི་འདྲིར་གཞུག་པའི་ཕྱིར་འཇམ་དཔལ་གཞོན་ནུར་གྱུར་པ་ལ་དེ་ལྟ་བུའི་མཚན་མ་མཛད་ནས། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-72"/>The Blessed One made a sign to Youthful Mañjuśrī in order to have him make inquiries about this Dharma discourse.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.98.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེའི་ཕྱིར་གང་བདག་གིས་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་ལ་<tei:ref folio="F.98.a"/>དེ་ལྟ་བུའི་ཟབ་མོ་ཟབ་པ་གང་ཉན་ཐོས་དང་། རང་སངས་རྒྱས་རྣམས་དང་། མཚན་མར་ལྷུང་བའི་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་རྣམས་ཀྱི་ས་མ་ཡིན་པ་ཞུ་བ་ཞུའོ་སྙམ་དུ་སེམས་པར་གྱུར་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Consequently, Mañjuśrī thought to himself, “I will ask the Tathāgata what is this profound discourse that is not within the realm of hearers, solitary realizers, or bodhisattvas who have fallen into conceptual signs.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.98.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་གཞོན་ནུར་གྱུར་པས་དེ་ལྟར་ཡིད་ལ་བྱས་ནས་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>After Youthful Mañjuśrī had reflected upon this, he proposed,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.98.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ལ་འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་གསོལ་ཏོ། །གལ་ཏེ་ཞུས་ནས་ཞུ་བ་ལུང་བསྟན་པའི་སླད་དུ་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་བདག་ལ་སྐབས་ཕྱེ་ན་བདག་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་དགྲ་བཅོམ་པ་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་སངས་རྒྱས་ལ་ཕྱོགས་འགའ་ཞིག་ཞུའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“If the Blessed One is giving me this opportunity to make inquiries so that the questions can be answered, then I will pose questions on various topics to the Blessed One, the tathāgata, the worthy one, the complete and perfect Buddha.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.98.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་བཀའ་སྩལ་པ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>the Blessed One replied.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.98.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཐམས་ཅད་དང་ལྡན་པའི་འཁོར་འདི་དག་ཀྱང་འདུས་ཀྱིས་འཇམ་དཔལ་ཁྱོད་གང་དང་གང་འདོད་པ་ཞུས་ཤིག །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Since everyone in this assembly has come together, Mañjuśrī, ask whatever you wish,”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.98.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་གྱིས་གསོལ་པ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-74"/>Mañjuśrī then asked the following:</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.98.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཇི་ལྟར་ན་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཡོན་ཏན་ཐམས་ཅད་ལ་གནས་ཤིང་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའི་སྤྱོད་པ་ཐམས་ཅད་ལ་ཡང་གདའ་བ་ལགས། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Blessed One, how do bodhisattvas accomplish all their activities while also maintaining all virtuous qualities?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.98.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སེམས་ཅན་ཚད་མ་མཆིས་གྲངས་མ་མཆིས་པ་རྣམས་ཀྱང་ཡོངས་སུ་སྨིན་པར་བགྱིད་ཅིང་སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱི་ཞིང་ཐམས་ཅད་ན་ཡང་ཆུའི་ཟླ་བ་ལྟ་བུར་གདའ་བ་ལགས། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>How do they both remain in all buddhafields like the moon’s reflections in water, and also fully ripen countless beings?”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.98.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་འཇམ་དཔལ་གཞོན་ནུར་གྱུར་པ་ལ་འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་བཀའ་སྩལ་ཏོ། །འཇམ་དཔལ་ཁྱོད་ཀྱིས་མདོར་དོན་ཆེན་པོ་ཞུ་བ་ཞུས་པ་ལེགས་སོ་ལེགས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-326"/>“Mañjuśrī,” replied the Blessed One, “your concise and meaningful questions are excellent, excellent!</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.98.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེའི་རྣམ་པར་དབྱེ་བ་རྒྱ་ཆེར་ལེགས་པར་ཤིན་ཏུ་ཉོན་ལ་ཡིད་ལ་ཟུང་ཤིག་དང་ངས་ཁྱོད་ལ་བཤད་དོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Listen attentively to this detailed explanation I will give you and keep it in mind.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.98.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་དེ་བཞིན་འཚལ་ལོ་ཞེས་འཇམ་དཔལ་གཞོན་ནུར་གྱུར་པ་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱི་ལྟར་ཉན་པ་དང་། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Blessed One, I will do so,” answered Youthful Mañjuśrī, and he listened as requested.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.98.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་དེ་ལ་འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་བཀའ་སྩལ་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-77"/>The Blessed One then gave the following reply:</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.98.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་འདི་ལ་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆོས་དྲུག་དང་ལྡན་ན་བྱ་བ་དེ་དག་ཀྱང་ཡོངས་སུ་རྫོགས་པར་བྱེད་ཅིང་ཡོན་ཏན་གྱི་ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་ལ་ཡང་གནས་པར་འགྱུར་རོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Mañjuśrī, if bodhisattvas possess six qualities, they will completely accomplish their tasks and also maintain all virtuous qualities.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.98.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དྲུག་གང་ཞེ་ན། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>What are these six?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.98.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདི་ལ་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སྦྱིན་པ་བྱེད་པ་ན། སྦྱིན་པའི་བདག་པོ་བདོག་པ་ཐམས་ཅད་ཡོངས་སུ་གཏོང་བ་ཡིན་མོད་ཀྱི། བདག་སེར་སྣ་སྤྱོད་པ་ལས་རྣམ་པར་ལོག་པར་མི་མཐོང་ངོ་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>If bodhisattvas practice generosity, then although they are benefactors who let go of all their possessions, they do not regard themselves as having completely reversed miserly behavior.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.98.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཚུལ་ཁྲིམས་ལ་གནས་པ་ཡིན་མོད་ཀྱི། བདག་ཚུལ་ཁྲིམས་ངན་པའི་ལས་ལས་འདས་པ་ཡིན་པར་མི་ཤེས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Although they observe discipline, they not consider themselves as being beyond actions that result from inferior discipline.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.98.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཟོད་པ་དང་ངེས་པར་ལྡན་པ་ཡིན་མོད་ཀྱི། བདག་<tei:ref folio="F.98.b"/>གནོད་སེམས་ཀྱི་སྤྱོད་པ་དང་བྲལ་བར་མི་མཐོང་ངོ་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Although they possess patience and determination, they do not regard themselves as being free from behavior based on malicious thoughts. </seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.98.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བརྩོན་འགྲུས་བརྩམས་པ་ཡིན་མོད་ཀྱི། ལུས་དང་སེམས་ཀྱིས་བརྩོན་པ་མ་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Although they cultivate diligence, they do not exert themselves bodily or mentally.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.98.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བསམ་གཏན་དང་རྣམ་པར་ཐར་པ་དང་། ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་དང་། སྙོམས་པར་འཇུག་པ་ཐམས་ཅད་ལ་མཁས་པ་ཡིན་མོད་ཀྱི། སེམས་རྩེ་གཅིག་ཏུ་གནས་པར་གྱུར་པ་ཡང་མ་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Although they are skilled in all concentrations, liberations, absorptions, and all meditative states, they are not stuck in a one-pointed mental state.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.98.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྤྱོད་ཡུལ་ཤེས་རབ་ལ་གནས་པ་ཡིན་མོད་ཀྱི། བདག་འགྲོ་བ་ཐམས་ཅད་ལས་ཡོངས་སུ་མ་གྲོལ་བར་མཐོང་ངོ་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Although they exist within the domain of insight, they regard themselves as not being fully liberated from transmigration.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.98.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆོས་འདི་དྲུག་དང་ལྡན་ན་བྱ་བ་དེ་དག་ཡོངས་སུ་རྫོགས་པར་བྱེད་ཅིང་ཡོན་ཏན་གྱི་ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་ལ་ཡང་གནས་པ་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Mañjuśrī, if bodhisattvas possess these six qualities, they completely accomplish their tasks and also maintain all virtuous qualities.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.98.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་གཞན་ཡང་ཆོས་དྲུག་དང་ལྡན་ན། བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་བྱ་བ་དེ་དག་ཡོངས་སུ་རྫོགས་པར་བྱེད་ཅིང་ཡོན་ཏན་གྱི་ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་ལ་ཡང་གནས་པ་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-78"/>“Mañjuśrī, if bodhisattvas possess another six qualities, they can accomplish their tasks, and also maintain all virtuous qualities.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.98.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དྲུག་གང་ཞེ་ན། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>What are these six?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.98.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདི་ལ་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་ཅན་དམྱལ་བའི་གནས་ཡོངས་སུ་གཟུང་བ་ཡང་ཡོངས་སུ་འཛིན་ལ་མཐོ་རིས་ཀྱི་ཆོས་ཀྱང་མྱོང་བར་བྱེད་པ་དང་། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Bodhisattvas assume the state of a hell being while at the same time experiencing the qualities of the higher realms.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.98.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དུད་འགྲོར་འགྲོ་བའི་གནས་ཀྱང་ཡོངས་སུ་འཛིན་ལ་མིའི་ཆོས་རྒྱ་ཆེན་པོ་ཡང་མྱོང་བར་བྱེད་པ་དང་། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They assume the state of an animal, while at the same time experiencing the great extent of human qualities.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.98.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རིགས་དམའ་བར་སྐྱེ་བ་ཡོངས་སུ་གཟུང་བ་ཡང་ཡོངས་སུ་འཛིན་ལ་འཁོར་ལོས་སྒྱུར་བའི་རྒྱལ་སྲིད་ཀྱི་བདེ་བ་ཡང་མྱོང་བར་བྱེད་པ་དང་། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They assume a birth in the lower castes,<tei:note xml:id="UT22084-062-007-79"/> while at the same time experiencing the pleasures of a cakravartin’s kingdom.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.98.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྐྱེ་བ་ཐམས་ཅད་དུ་གཏོགས་པར་ཡང་སྟོན་ལ་འགྲོ་བའི་ཁྱད་པར་གྱི་བྱ་བ་རྣམས་ཀྱང་མྱོང་བར་བྱེད་པ་དང་། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They manifest within all modes of existence, while at the same time experiencing the activities associated with a specific realm.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.98.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱི་ཞིང་ཐམས་ཅད་དུ་འགྲོ་བ་ལ་མཁས་པ་ཡང་ཡིན་ལ་གནས་ནས་ཀྱང་མི་འཕོ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They are skilled in going to all buddhafields, while at the same time not moving from their location.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.98.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འགྲོ་བ་ཡང་མེད། འོང་བ་ཡང་མེད་ཅིང་སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱི་ཞིང་ཐམས་ཅད་དུ་ཡང་ཆུའི་ཟླ་བ་བཞིན་དུ་སྣང་བ་དང་། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They neither come nor go, and yet appear in all buddhafields like the moon’s reflections in water.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.98.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྒྲ་སྐད་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱང་འབྱིན་ལ་ཕན་ཚུན་འདྲེས་པར་ཡང་མི་བྱེད་པ་ཡིན་ཏེ</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They speak all languages yet do not mix them up.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.98.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆོས་དེ་དྲུག་དང་ལྡན་ན་བྱ་བ་དེ་དག་སྟོན་ཅིང་ཡོན་ཏན་གྱི་ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་ལ་ཡང་གནས་པ་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Mañjuśrī, if bodhisattvas possess these six qualities, they completely accomplish their activities and also maintain all virtuous qualities.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.98.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ལ་འཇམ་དཔལ་གཞོན་ནུར་གྱུར་པས་འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་གསོལ་ཏོ། །བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Youthful Mañjuśrī inquired, <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-80"/>“Blessed One,”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.98.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཇི་ལྟར་ན་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་ཅན་དམྱལ་བའི་གནས་ཡོངས་སུ་གཟུང་བ་ཡང་ཡོངས་སུ་འཛིན་ལ་མཐོ་རིས་ཀྱི་ཆོས་ཀྱང་མྱོང་བ་ལགས། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“how do bodhisattvas assume the state of a hell being while at the same time experiencing the qualities of the higher realms?”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.99.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་བཀའ་སྩལ་པ། <tei:ref folio="F.99.a"/>འཇམ་དཔལ་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>replied the Blessed One, “Mañjuśrī,”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.99.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདི་ལ་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོས་པད་མོ་ཆེན་པོ་ཞེས་བྱ་བའི་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་ལ་སྙོམས་པར་ཞུགས་ནས་སེམས་ཅན་དམྱལ་བའི་གནས་ཡོངས་སུ་གཟུང་བ་ཡང་ཡོངས་སུ་འཛིན་ཏེདེ་ལྷའི་བདེ་བ་གང་ཆུང་ཟད་ཡོད་པ་དེ་དག་ཐམས་ཅད་དེ་ན་མྱོང་བར་བྱེད་དོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“bodhisattva great beings assume the state of a hell being by entering the absorption known as great lotus , while at the same time experiencing all the joys of the gods, including the most subtle of them.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.99.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སེམས་ཅན་དེ་དག་གིས་ཀྱང་དེ་དམྱལ་བས་དམྱལ་བར་མཐོང་སྟེ། དེ་ཆ་ལུགས་དེས་སེམས་ཅན་དམྱལ་བ་པའི་སེམས་ཅན་དེ་དག་དམྱལ་བ་དང་བྲལ་བར་གྱུར་པ་ལ་ཆོས་འཆད་དོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>For their part, hell beings perceive these bodhisattvas as hell beings because they are themselves hell beings. Through this appearance, bodhisattvas expound the Dharma to those denizens of the hell who have the potential to be extricated from the hells.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.99.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་སེམས་ཅན་སྟོང་ཕྲག་དུ་མ་སེམས་ཅན་དམྱལ་བ་ལས་རབ་ཏུ་ཐར་བར་བྱེད་དོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They completely liberate many thousands of beings from the hells.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.99.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་དེ་ལྟར་ན་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་ཅན་དམྱལ་བའི་གནས་ཡོངས་སུ་གཟུང་བ་ཡང་ཡོངས་སུ་འཛིན་ལ་མཐོ་རིས་ཀྱི་ཆོས་ཀྱང་མྱོང་བར་བྱེད་པ་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Thus, Mañjuśrī, bodhisattvas assume the state of a hell being while at the same time experiencing the state of the higher realms.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.99.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་གྱིས་གསོལ་པ། བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-82"/>“Blessed One,” asked Mañjuśrī,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.99.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཇི་ལྟར་ན་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་དུད་འགྲོའི་གནས་ཀྱང་ཡོངས་སུ་འཛིན་ལ་མིའི་ཆོས་རྒྱ་ཆེན་པོ་ཡང་མྱོང་བར་བགྱིད་པ་ལགས། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“how do bodhisattvas assume the state of an animal, while at the same time experiencing the great extent of human qualities?”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.99.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་བཀའ་སྩལ་པ། འཇམ་དཔལ་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Mañjuśrī,” replied the Blessed One,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.99.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདི་ལ་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཉེ་བར་ཞི་བ་ལ་འཇུག་པ་ཞེས་བྱ་བའི་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་ལ་སྙོམས་པར་ཞུགས་ནས་དུད་འགྲོའི་གནས་ཡོངས་སུ་འཛིན་ཅིང་སེམས་ཉམས་པ་མེད་པར་མིའི་ཆོས་རྒྱ་ཆེན་པོ་མྱོང་བར་བྱེད་དོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“bodhisattvas assume the state of an animal by entering the absorption known as settling in complete peace , and without experiencing any impairment to their mental faculties, they experience the great extent of human qualities.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.99.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ཆ་ལུགས་དེས་དུད་འགྲོར་གྱུར་པའི་སེམས་ཅན་རྣམས་ལ་ཆོས་འཆད་དེ། དེ་སེམས་ཅན་སྟོང་ཕྲག་མང་པོ་ཆོས་ལ་འཇོག་གོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Through this appearance, they explain the Dharma to beings that have become animals and so establish many thousands of beings in the Dharma.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.99.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་དེ་ལྟར་ན་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་དུད་འགྲོའི་གནས་ཀྱང་ཡོངས་སུ་འཛིན་ལ་མིའི་ཆོས་རྒྱ་ཆེན་པོ་ཡང་མྱོང་བར་བྱེད་པ་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Thus, Mañjuśrī, bodhisattvas experience the condition of an animal while at the same time experiencing the great extent of human qualities.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.99.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་གྱིས་གསོལ་པ། བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-84"/>“Blessed One,” asked Mañjuśrī,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.99.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཇི་ལྟར་ན་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་རིགས་དམའ་བར་སྐྱེ་བ་ཡོངས་སུ་གཟུང་བ་ཡང་ཡོངས་སུ་འཛིན་ལ་འཁོར་ལོས་སྒྱུར་བའི་རྒྱལ་སྲིད་ཀྱི་བདེ་བ་ཡང་མྱོང་བར་བགྱིད་པ་ལགས། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“how do bodhisattvas embrace a birth in the lower castes, while at the same time experiencing the pleasures of a cakravartin’s kingdom?”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.99.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་བཀའ་སྩལ་པ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The Blessed One replied,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.99.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་འདི་ལ་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་མངོན་པར་གནོན་ཅིང་རྣམ་པར་གསལ་བ་ཞེས་བྱ་བའི་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་ལ་སྙོམས་པར་ཞུགས་ཏེ</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Mañjuśrī, in order to do this, bodhisattvas enter the absorption known as subduing and illuminating .</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.99.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་དེ་མངོན་པར་གནོན་པ་དང་། རྣམ་པར་གསལ་བས་རིགས་དམའ་བར་སྐྱེ་བ་ཡོངས་སུ་གཟུང་བ་ཡང་ཡོངས་སུ་འཛིན་ལ་འཁོར་ལོས་སྒྱུར་བའི་རྒྱལ་སྲིད་ཀྱི་བདེ་བ་ཡང་མྱོང་བར་བྱེད་<tei:ref folio="F.99.b"/>དེ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>By means of this absorption, which is conquering and illuminating, they embrace a birth in the lower castes, while at the same time experiencing the pleasures of a cakravartin’s kingdom. </seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.99.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཐབས་དེས་ཀྱང་སེམས་ཅན་སྟོང་ཕྲག་དུ་མ་ཆོས་ལ་འཇོག་གོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Through these skillful means, they establish many thousands of beings in the Dharma.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.99.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་དེ་ལྟར་ན་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་རིགས་དམའ་བར་སྐྱེ་བ་ཡོངས་སུ་གཟུང་བ་ཡང་ཡོངས་སུ་འཛིན་ལ་འཁོར་ལོས་སྒྱུར་བའི་རྒྱལ་སྲིད་ཀྱི་བདེ་བ་ཡང་མྱོང་བར་བྱེད་པ་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Thus, Mañjuśrī, bodhisattvas embrace a birth in the lower castes, while at the same time experiencing the happiness of a cakravartin’s kingdom.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.99.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་གྱིས་གསོལ་པ། བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-86"/>“Blessed One,” asked Mañjuśrī,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.99.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཇི་ལྟར་ན་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་འགྲོ་བ་ཐམས་ཅད་དུ་གཏོགས་པར་ཡང་སྟོན་ལ། འགྲོ་བའི་ཁྱད་པར་བགྱིད་པ་ཡང་མྱོང་བ་ལགས། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“how do bodhisattvas both manifest within all modes of existence and also experience the activities of one specific realm?”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.99.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་བཀའ་སྩལ་པ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The Blessed One replied,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.99.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་འདི་ལ་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སྤྱོད་པ་ཐམས་ཅད་ལ་བཏང་བ་སྣང་བའི་ཁྱད་པར་སྟོན་པ་ཞེས་བྱ་བའི་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་ལ་སྙོམས་པར་འཇུག་གོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Mañjuśrī, in order to do this, they enter the absorption known as particular display illuminating the abandonment of all activities .</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.99.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་དེ་ལ་གནས་ནས་འགྲོ་བ་ཐམས་ཅད་དུ་གཏོགས་པར་ཡང་སྟོན་ཅིང་འགྲོ་བའི་ཁྱད་པར་གྱི་བྱེད་པ་ཡང་མྱོང་བར་བྱེད་དེ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Abiding in that absorption, they both manifest within all modes of existence and also experience the activities of one specific realm.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.99.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་དེ་ལྟར་ན་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་འགྲོ་བ་ཐམས་ཅད་དུ་གཏོགས་པར་ཡང་སྟོན་ལ་འགྲོ་བའི་ཁྱད་པར་ཡང་མྱོང་བར་བྱེད་པ་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>In this way, Mañjuśrī, bodhisattvas manifest within all modes of existence while experiencing a particular realm.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.99.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་གྱིས་གསོལ་པ། བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-88"/>“Blessed One,” asked Mañjuśrī,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.99.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཇི་ལྟར་ན་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱི་ཞིང་ཐམས་ཅད་དུ་འགྲོ་བ་ལ་མཁས་ཤིང་གནས་ནས་ཀྱང་མི་གཡོ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“how do bodhisattvas excel in going to all buddhafields while at the same time not moving from their location?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.99.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འགྲོ་བ་ཡང་མ་མཆིས། འོང་བ་ཡང་མ་མཆིས་ལ། སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱི་ཞིང་ཐམས་ཅད་དུ་ཡང་ཆུའི་ཟླ་བ་ལྟར་གདའ་བ་ལགས། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Although they neither come nor go, how do they appear in all buddhafields in the same way the moon is reflected in water?”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.99.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་བཀའ་སྩལ་པ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The Blessed One replied,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.99.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་འདི་ལ་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་གཟུགས་ཐམས་ཅད་རྣམ་པར་གནོན་པ་ཞེས་བྱ་བའི་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་ལ་སྙོམས་པར་འཇུག་སྟེ</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Mañjuśrī, in order to do this, bodhisattvas enter the absorption known as conquering all forms .</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.99.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་དེ་ལ་གནས་པ་ན་ཕྱོགས་བཅུའི་འཇིག་རྟེན་གྱི་ཁམས་རྣམས་སུ་བདག་གི་ལུས་ཅིག་ཅར་སྣང་བར་བྱེད་ལ་གནས་ནས་ཀྱང་མི་གཡོ། འགྲོ་བ་ཡང་མེད། འོང་བ་ཡང་མེད་དེ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Then, abiding in that absorption, they at once manifest their bodies throughout the world systems of the ten directions, without moving from their location, without going or coming.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.99.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྙོམས་པར་ཞུགས་པ་ཉིད་ཀྱིས་སངས་རྒྱས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་མཐོང་ཞིང་ཆོས་ཀྱང་ཉན་ཏེ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>By remaining in equanimity, they see the Buddha, the Blessed One, and hear the Dharma.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.99.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་དེ་ལྟར་ན་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱི་ཞིང་ཐམས་ཅད་དུ་འགྲོ་བ་ལ་མཁས་པ་ཡང་ཡིན་ལ་གནས་ནས་ཀྱང་མི་གཡོ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Thus, Mañjuśrī, bodhisattvas excel in being reborn in all buddhafields while at the same time not moving from their location.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.99.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འགྲོ་བ་ཡང་མེད། འོང་བ་ཡང་མེད་དེ། སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱི་ཞིང་ཐམས་ཅད་དུ་ཡང་ཆུའི་ཟླ་བ་བཞིན་དུ་སྣང་བ་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They neither come nor go, and yet they appear in all buddhafields in the same way the moon is reflected in water.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.99.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་གྱིས་གསོལ་པ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-90"/>Mañjuśrī then asked,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.100.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཇི་ལྟར་ན་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སྒྲ་སྐད་ཐམས་ཅད་<tei:ref folio="F.100.a"/>ཀྱང་འབྱིན་པར་བགྱིད་ལ་ཕན་ཚུན་འདྲེས་པར་ཡང་མི་བགྱིད་པ་ལགས། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Blessed One, how can bodhisattvas speak all kinds of languages and yet not mix them up?”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.100.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་བཀའ་སྩལ་པ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Mañjuśrī, replied the Blessed One,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.100.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་འདི་ལ་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་མཐའ་ཡས་པར་འཁྱིལ་པ་ཞེས་བྱ་བའི་གཟུངས་ཐོབ་ནས་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“bodhisattvas possess the dhāraṇī known as infinite recitation .</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.100.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སེམས་ཅན་གྱི་སེམས་ཀྱི་བསམ་པ་མཐའ་ཡས་པ་ལ་འཇུག་ཅིང་སྒྲ་བཤད་པ་མཐའ་ཡས་པ་རྣམས་ཤེས། བདག་གི་ཚུལ་མཐའ་ཡས་པ་རྣམས་ཀྱང་རབ་ཏུ་ཤེས་ཏེ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>As a result of that, they can engage with the infinite thoughts of the minds of beings, understand infinite languages, and comprehend infinite individual ways of being.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.100.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་གཟུངས་དེ་ཐོབ་པས་སྒྲ་སྐད་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱང་འབྱིན་ལ་ཕན་ཚུན་འདྲེས་པར་ཡང་མི་བྱེད་དེ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>By possessing this dhāraṇī, they both speak all languages and also do not mix them up.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.100.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་དེ་ལྟར་ན་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སྒྲ་སྐད་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱང་འབྱིན་ལ་ཕན་ཚུན་འདྲེས་པར་ཡང་མི་བྱེད་པ་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Thus, Mañjuśrī, bodhisattvas speak all languages and yet do not mix them up.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.100.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་གྱིས་གསོལ་པ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-92"/>Mañjuśrī then inquired further:</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.100.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་རྣམས་ཀྱི་ཐབས་མཁས་པ་ནི་མངོན་པར་འབྱུང་བར་དཀའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Blessed One, the bodhisattvas’ skillful means are difficult to manifest.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.100.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་འོན་ཀྱང་ཆོས་ཀྱི་རྣམ་གྲངས་འདི་རྟོགས་པར་འཚལ་བའི་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔས་ཆོས་ཀྱི་རྣམ་གྲངས་ཇི་ལྟ་བུར་རྟོགས་པར་བགྱི། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Nonetheless, Blessed One, how should this Dharma discourse be understood by the bodhisattvas who wish to understand it?”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.100.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་བཀའ་སྩལ་པ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>replied the Blessed One,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.100.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་ཆོས་ཀྱི་རྣམ་གྲངས་འདི་རྟོགས་པར་འདོད་པའི་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔས་ནམ་མཁའི་ཚུལ་རྟོགས་པར་བྱའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Mañjuśrī,” “those bodhisattvas who wish to understand this Dharma discourse should understand it to be like space.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.100.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ནམ་མཁའི་ཚུལ་ཇི་ལྟ་བུ་ལགས། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-94"/>“How is it like space, Blessed One?”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.100.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་བཀའ་སྩལ་པ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>replied the Blessed One,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.100.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་འདི་ལྟ་སྟེ། དཔེར་ན་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Mañjuśrī,” “it may be illustrated as follows:</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.100.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ནམ་མཁའ་ནི་ཆགས་པ་མ་ཡིན། ཞེ་སྡང་བ་མ་ཡིན། རྨོངས་པ་མ་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Space is not desirous, nor angry, nor ignorant.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.100.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་བཞིན་དུ་ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱང་ཆགས་པ་མ་ཡིན། ཞེ་སྡང་བ་མ་ཡིན། རྨོངས་པ་མ་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Likewise, no phenomenon is desirous, angry, or ignorant.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.100.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདི་ལྟ་སྟེ་དཔེར་ན། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>It may be illustrated as follows:</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.100.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ནམ་མཁའ་ནི་སྦྱིན་པ་ཕུན་སུམ་ཚོགས་པ་མ་ཡིན་པ་ནས་ཤེས་རབ་ཀྱི་བར་དུ་ཕུན་སུམ་ཚོགས་པ་མ་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Space is not the excellence of generosity, and so forth, up to and including the excellence of insight.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.100.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་བཞིན་དུ་ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱང་སྦྱིན་པ་ཕུན་སུམ་ཚོགས་པ་མ་ཡིན་པ་ནས་ཤེས་རབ་ཀྱི་བར་དུ་ཕུན་སུམ་ཚོགས་པ་མ་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Likewise, no phenomenon is the excellence of generosity, and so forth, up to and including the excellence of insight.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.100.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་འདི་ལྟ་སྟེ། དཔེར་ན་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>It may be illustrated as follows:</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.100.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ནམ་མཁའ་ནི་ཡོངས་སུ་ཤེས་པར་བྱ་བ་མ་ཡིན། སྤང་བར་བྱ་བ་མ་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Space is not something to be realized, nor is it something to be abandoned.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.100.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་བཞིན་དུ་ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱང་ཡོངས་སུ་ཤེས་པར་བྱ་བ་མ་ཡིན། སྤང་བར་བྱ་བ་མ་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Likewise, no phenomenon is something to be realized or abandoned.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.100.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདི་ལྟ་སྟེ། དཔེར་ན་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>It may be illustrated as follows:</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.100.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ནམ་མཁའ་ནི་བསྒོམ་པར་བྱ་བ་མ་ཡིན། མངོན་དུ་བྱ་བ་མ་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Space is not something to be cultivated, nor is it something to be actualized.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.100.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་བཞིན་དུ་ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱང་བསྒོམ་པར་བྱ་བ་མ་ཡིན། མངོན་དུ་བྱ་བ་<tei:ref folio="F.100.b"/>མ་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Likewise, no phenomenon is something to be cultivated or actualized. </seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.100.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདི་ལྟ་སྟེ། དཔེར་ན་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>It may be illustrated as follows:</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.100.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ནམ་མཁའ་ནི་མུན་པ་མ་ཡིན། སྣང་བ་མ་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Space is not obscurity, nor is it light.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.100.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་བཞིན་དུ་ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱང་མུན་པ་མ་ཡིན། སྣང་བ་མ་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Likewise, no phenomenon is obscurity or light.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.100.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདི་ལྟ་སྟེ། དཔེར་ན་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>It may be illustrated as follows:</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.100.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ནམ་མཁའ་ནི་ཀུན་ཏུ་གཟུང་བར་བྱ་བ་མ་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Space is not something to be apprehended.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.100.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་བཞིན་དུ་ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱང་ཀུན་ཏུ་གཟུང་བར་བྱ་བ་མ་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Likewise, no phenomenon is something to be apprehended.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.100.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདི་ལྟ་སྟེ། དཔེར་ན་ནམ་མཁའ་ནི་ལམ་གྱིས་ཡང་དག་པར་ཞུགས་པ་མ་ཡིན། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>It may be illustrated as follows:</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.100.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལམ་ངན་པས་མ་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Space is not a destination attained either through the genuine path or through a bad path.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.100.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་བཞིན་དུ་ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱང་ལམ་གྱིས་ཡང་དག་པར་ཞུགས་པ་མ་ཡིན། ལམ་ངན་པས་མ་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Likewise, no phenomenon is a destination attained, either through the genuine path or through a bad path.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.100.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདི་ལྟ་སྟེ། དཔེར་ན་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>It may be illustrated as follows:</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.100.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ནམ་མཁའ་ནི་ཉན་ཐོས་ཀྱི་ཐེག་པས་ཡང་དག་པར་ཞུགས་པ་མ་ཡིན། རང་སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱི་ཐེག་པས་མ་ཡིན། ཐེག་པ་ཆེན་པོས་ཡང་དག་པར་ཞུགས་པ་མ་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Space is not a destination attained through the Hearers’ Vehicle, the Solitary Realizers’ Vehicle, or the Great Vehicle.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.100.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་བཞིན་དུ་ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱང་ཉན་ཐོས་ཀྱི་ཐེག་པས་ཡང་དག་པར་ཞུགས་པ་མ་ཡིན། རང་སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱི་ཐེག་པས་མ་ཡིན། ཐེག་པ་ཆེན་པོས་ཡང་དག་པར་ཞུགས་པ་མ་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Likewise, no phenomenon is a destination attained through the Hearers’ Vehicle, the Solitary Realizers’ Vehicle, or the Great Vehicle.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.100.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདི་ལྟ་སྟེ། དཔེར་ན་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>It may be illustrated as follows:</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.100.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ནམ་མཁའ་ནི་སེམས་པར་བྱེད་པ་མ་ཡིན། ཤེས་པར་བྱེད་པ་མ་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Space is not an agent that reflects or knows.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.100.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་བཞིན་དུ་ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱང་སེམས་པར་བྱེད་པ་མ་ཡིན། ཤེས་པར་བྱེད་པ་མ་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Likewise, no phenomenon is an agent that reflects or knows.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.100.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདི་ལྟ་སྟེ། དཔེར་ན་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>It may be illustrated as follows:</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.100.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ནམ་མཁའ་ནི་ལེན་པར་བྱེད་པ་མ་ཡིན། འདོར་བར་བྱེད་པར་མ་ཡིན། བླང་བར་བྱ་བ་མ་ཡིན། དོར་བར་བྱ་བ་མ་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Space is not an agent that accepts or rejects, nor is it an object to be accepted or rejected.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.100.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་བཞིན་དུ་ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱང་ལེན་པར་བྱེད་པ་མ་ཡིན། འདོར་བར་བྱེད་པ་མ་ཡིན། བླང་བར་བྱ་བ་མ་ཡིན། དོར་བར་བྱ་བ་མ་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Likewise, no phenomenon is an agent that accepts or rejects, nor is it an object to be accepted or rejected.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.100.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདི་ལྟ་སྟེ། དཔེར་ན་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>It may be illustrated as follows:</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.100.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ནམ་མཁའ་ནི་གང་གིས་ཀྱང་ཉོན་མོངས་པར་བྱ་མི་ནུས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Space cannot be defiled by anything whatsoever.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.100.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་བཞིན་དུ་མྱ་ངན་ལས་འདས་པའི་མཐར་གཏོགས་པའི་ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱང་ཀུན་ནས་ཉོན་མོངས་པ་མ་ཡིན་ཏེ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Likewise, no phenomenon belonging to supreme nirvāṇa can be defiled in any possible way.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.100.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་དག་ཞི་བར་ཡང་མི་འགྱུར། ཉེ་བར་ཞི་བར་ཡང་མི་འགྱུར་རོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Thus, it will neither be assuaged nor pacified.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.100.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདི་ལྟ་སྟེ། དཔེར་ན་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>It may be illustrated as follows:</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.100.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ནམ་མཁའ་ནི་མི་གནས་པའི་ཕྱིར་གནས་མ་ཡིན། གནས་པ་མ་ཡིན། གཡོ་བར་མི་བྱེད། འགུལ་བར་མི་བྱེད་དོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Space is not an abode because it is not abiding, nor does it abide, waver, or vacillate.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.100.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔས་དེ་བཞིན་དུ་ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་མི་གནས་པ་ལ་གནས་པར་བལྟའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Likewise, bodhisattvas should regard each and every phenomenon as abiding in non-abidingness.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.100.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་དག་ཡང་དག་པར་ཐོབ་པས་མི་འགུལ། མི་གཡོ། མི་གནས། གནས་པར་མི་བྱེད་དོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Having correct understanding, they do not vacillate, waver, abide, or cause anything to abide. </seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.101.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ལ་འཇམ་དཔལ་ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱི་<tei:ref folio="F.101.a"/>ངོ་བོ་ཉིད་དེ་ལྟ་བུ་ལ་གང་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་ལྟ་བར་འདོད་པ་དེ་དག་ནི་ལོག་པར་ལྟ་བའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-96"/>“Mañjuśrī, since the nature of all phenomena is like this, those who wish to see the Tathāgata hold a mistaken view.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.101.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་ལོག་པར་ལྟ་བ་དེ་དག་ནི་ཡང་དག་པར་ཞུགས་པའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Those who view this as mistaken<tei:note xml:id="UT22084-062-007-97"/> have correct understanding.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.101.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་ཡང་དག་པར་ཞུགས་པ་དེ་དག་ལ་བྱིན་པ་ནི་འབྲས་བུ་ཆེ་བ་མ་ཡིན། ཕན་ཡོན་ཆེ་བ་མ་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>For those who have correct understanding, generosity has neither great result nor great benefit.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.101.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་དག་ལ་བྱིན་ན་འབྲས་བུ་ཆེ་བ་མ་ཡིན། ཕན་ཡོན་ཆེ་བ་མ་ཡིན་པ་དེ་དག་ནི་འཇིག་རྟེན་གྱི་སྦྱིན་གནས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Those for whom generosity has neither great result nor great benefit are objects of generosity in the world.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.101.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་འཇིག་རྟེན་གྱི་སྦྱིན་གནས་ཡིན་པ་དེ་དག་ལ་སྦྱིན་པའི་རྣམ་པར་སྨིན་པ་མེད་དོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>For those who are objects of generosity in the world, there is no karmic ripening from generosity.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.101.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་ལ་སྦྱིན་པའི་རྣམ་པར་སྨིན་པ་མེད་པ་དེ་དག་གིས་འདུ་ཤེས་མེད་པ་ཡོངས་སུ་རྫོགས་པར་བྱས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Those for whom there is no karmic ripening from generosity have perfected non-conception.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.101.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་གི་འདུ་ཤེས་མེད་པ་ཡོངས་སུ་རྫོགས་པར་བྱས་པ་དེ་དག་མྱུར་དུ་མི་སྐྱེ་བའི་ཆོས་ལ་བཟོད་པ་ཐོབ་པར་འགྱུར་རོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Those who have perfected non-conception will quickly attain the acceptance that all phenomena do not arise.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.101.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་འཁོར་དེའི་ནང་ནས་དགེ་སློང་ལྷག་པའི་ང་རྒྱལ་ཅན་དྲུག་ཅུ་བསྟན་པ་འདི་ཐོས་པ་དང་འདི་སྙམ་དུ་གྱུར་ཏེ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-98"/>As sixty arrogant monks in the assembly heard this teaching, they thought to themselves,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.101.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མུན་ནག་གི་ལམ་དུ་གྱུར་ལ་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་ཡང་མུན་ནག་གི་ལམ་དུ་སྟོན་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“This is the path of confusion. Even the Tathāgata teaches the path of confusion.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.101.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདི་ལྟ་སྟེ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>It is as follows:</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.101.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མུ་སྟེགས་ཅན་གཞན་དག་ཀྱང་དེ་སྐད་སྟོན། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Some non-Buddhists also teach these words.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.101.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་ཡང་དེ་སྐད་སྟོན་པས་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་དང་། མུ་སྟེགས་ཅན་གཞན་གང་འོད་སྲུང་དང་། མ་སྐ་རི་འགའ་བ་ཡ་ལ་དང་། མི་དཀར་བ་སྐྲའི་ལ་བ་ཅན་དང་། ཀུན་རྒྱལ་འབེའི་ར་ཏིའི་བུ་དང་། དཔོན་པོ་ཀཱ་ཏྱཱ་ཡ་ན་དང་། གཅེར་བུ་པ་ཉེ་དུའི་བུ་རྣམས་ཀྱི་ཚིག་མཚུངས་སོ་སྙམ་མོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Since the Tathāgata teaches these words too, his speech is comparable to those of some non-Buddhists, such as Kaśyapa, Maskari Gośāliputra, Ajita Keśakambalī, Sañjayi Vairattīputra, Kakuda Kātyāyana, and Nirgrantha Jñatiputra.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.101.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱི་ཐུགས་ཀྱིས་དགེ་སློང་ལྷག་པའི་ང་རྒྱལ་ཅན་དེ་རྣམས་ཀྱི་སེམས་ཀྱི་རྟོག་པ་མཁྱེན་ནས་འཇམ་དཔལ་གཞོན་ནུར་གྱུར་པ་ལ་བཀའ་སྩལ་པ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-99"/>The Blessed One read the thoughts of these sixty arrogant monks, and he remarked to Youthful Mañjuśrī,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.101.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་དེ་དེ་བཞིན་ཏེ། གང་ངས་ཆོས་བཤད་པ་འདི་མུ་སྟེགས་ཅན་གཞན་རྣམས་དང་མཚུངས་ན། མུ་སྟེགས་ཅན་གཞན་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་ནི་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པས་ཆོས་བཤད་པ་མི་ཤེས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Thus, Mañjuśrī, if the Dharma I have expounded is comparable to what those other non-Buddhists teach, then those non-Buddhists do not understand the Dharma taught by the Tathāgata.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.101.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་སྐད་ཅེས་བཀའ་སྩལ་པ་དང་། དགེ་སློང་ལྷག་པའི་ང་རྒྱལ་ཅན་རྣམས་ལྷག་པར་སྡུག་བསྔལ། མི་དགའ། མ་མགུ། མ་རངས། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-100"/>After the Blessed One had spoken these words, the arrogant monks became very distressed, depressed, displeased, and dejected.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.101.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཆོས་བཤད་པ་འདི་ཡང་མ་ཤེས་ནས་སྟན་ལས་ལངས་ཏེ་དོང་ངོ་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Still not understanding this Dharma exposition, they rose from their seats and left.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.101.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་ཚེ་དང་ལྡན་པ་ཤཱ་རིའི་བུས་དགེ་སློང་དེ་དག་ལ་འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་སྨྲས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Then the venerable Śāriputra asked these monks,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.101.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཚེ་དང་ལྡན་པ་ཁྱེད་གར་འདོང་། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Venerable ones, where are you going?” </seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.101.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་དག་གིས་དེ་ལ་འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་སྨྲས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>they answered,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.101.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཙུན་<tei:ref folio="F.101.b"/>པ་ཤཱ་རིའི་བུ་ཆོས་བཤད་པ་འདི་བདག་ཅག་གིས་མ་འཚལ་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Venerable Śāriputra,” “we do not seek this Dharma exposition.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.101.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེས་དེ་དག་ལ་འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་སྨྲས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Śāriputra replied,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.101.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཚེ་དང་ལྡན་པ་དག་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པའི་དགོངས་ཏེ་བསྟན་པ་ཡིན་པར་ཤེས་པར་བྱའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-102"/>“Venerable ones,” “you should know that the Tathāgata is teaching in these ways with an intention.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.101.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེའི་ཕྱིར་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་ཅི་ལས་དགོངས་ཏེ། དེ་སྐད་བསྟན་པ་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་ལ་ཞུ་བའི་བར་དུ་རེ་ཞིག་སྡོད་ཅིག །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Therefore, stay for a while until you ask the Tathāgata what his intention was when he taught in these ways.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.101.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་དགེ་སློང་དེ་དག་ཚེ་དང་ལྡན་པ་ཤཱ་རིའི་བུའི་ཚིག་ཐོས་ནས་སོ་སོའི་སྟན་ལ་སླར་འཁོད་དོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-327"/>After hearing the venerable Śāriputra’s words, the monks went back to their seats.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.101.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ལ་ཚེ་དང་ལྡན་པ་ཤཱ་རིའི་བུས་འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་གསོལ་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>At that point, the venerable Śāriputra made this request:</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.101.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་དགེ་སློང་འདི་དག་གི་ཐེ་ཚོམ་བསལ་བའི་སླད་དུ་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པས་ཅི་ལས་དགོངས་ཏེ་འདི་སྐད་བསྟན་པ་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་བཤད་དུ་གསོལ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Blessed One, in order to clarify these monks’ doubts, I beseech you to explain what the intention of the Tathāgata was when he taught in these ways.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.101.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་བཀའ་སྩལ་པ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>asked the Blessed One.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.101.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཤཱ་རིའི་བུ་དེ་ཇི་སྙམ་དུ་སེམས། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-104"/>“Śāriputra, what do you think?”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.101.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དགེ་སློང་གང་ཉེ་བར་ལེན་པ་མེད་པར་ཟག་པ་ལས་སེམས་རྣམ་པར་གྲོལ་བ་དེ་སྒྲ་གང་གིས་ཀྱང་དངང་བ་དང་། སྐྲག་པ་དང་། ཀུན་ཏུ་སྐྲག་པར་འགྱུར་རམ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Would monks whose minds are liberated from defilements with no further appropriation become apprehensive, frightened, or terrified by any sound?”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.101.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་མ་ལགས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“No, Blessed One, they would not,”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.101.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དགེ་སློང་བདེན་པ་མཐོང་བ་ཡང་སྒྲ་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱིས་མི་དངང་། མི་སྐྲག །ཀུན་ཏུ་སྐྲག་པར་མི་འགྱུར་ན་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Monks who see the truth do not become apprehensive, frightened, or terrified by any sound.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.101.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དགེ་སློང་གང་ཉེ་བར་ལེན་པ་མ་མཆིས་པར་ཟག་པ་ལས་སེམས་རྣམ་པར་གྲོལ་བ་ལྟ་ཅི་སྨོས། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>What need is there to mention those monks whose minds are liberated from defilements with no further appropriation!”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.101.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་བཀའ་སྩལ་པ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>continued the Blessed One,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.101.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཤཱ་རིའི་བུ་འདི་ལ་སྐྱེས་བུ་བླུན་པོ་ཁ་ཅིག་ཡང་དག་པ་མ་ཡིན་པའི་ཆོས་རྣམས་བརྟགས་ནས་ལྷག་པའི་ང་རྒྱལ་ཅན་དུ་གྱུར་ཅིང་གནས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-106"/>“Śāriputra,” “in the present case, some foolish persons have investigated unreal phenomena and have become and remain exceedingly proud.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.101.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཤཱ་རིའི་བུས་གསོལ་པ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-328"/>Śāriputra then made this request:</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.101.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་ཐོས་ནས་འཁོར་ཐམས་ཅད་ཐེ་ཚོམ་མ་མཆིས་པར་འགྱུར་བའི་ཚིག་བཤད་པ་དེ་དག་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་བཀའ་སྩལ་དུ་གསོལ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“I beseech the Blessed One to expound a teaching that, when heard, will remove the doubts of all those present in this assembly.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.101.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་བཀའ་སྩལ་པ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>said the Blessed One,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.101.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཤཱ་རིའི་བུ་གང་གིས་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་རྨི་ལམ་དང་མཚུངས། སྒྱུ་མ་དང་མཚུངས་པར་མཐོང་བ་དེས་ཡང་དག་པར་མཐོང་ངོ་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-108"/>“Śāriputra,” “those who see the Tathāgata as a dream and an illusion see him truly.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.101.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་ཡང་དག་པར་མཐོང་བ་དེ་དག་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་ལ་ཡང་དག་པར་འདུ་ཤེས་མི་བྱེད། སྙིང་པོར་འདུ་ཤེས་དང་། རྫས་སུ་འདུ་ཤེས་དང་། དངོས་པོར་འདུ་ཤེས་དང་། རིལ་པོར་འདུ་ཤེས་མི་བྱེད། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Those who truly see him do not conceive of the Tathāgata in terms of truth, essence, substance, a real entity, or a partless whole.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.102.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་ལ་ཡང་དག་པར་འདུ་ཤེས་པ་མ་ཡིན། སྙིང་པོ་དང་། རྫས་དང་། དངོས་པོ་དང་། རིལ་པོར་འདུ་ཤེས་པ་མ་ཡིན་པ་དེ་དག་<tei:ref folio="F.102.a"/>གིས་འདུ་བྱེད་ཐམས་ཅད་བརྫུན་པར་མཐོང་ངོ་། །གང་གིས་འདུ་བྱེད་ཐམས་ཅད་བརྫུན་པར་མཐོང་བ་དེ་དག་གིས་ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་ལོག་པར་ཤེས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Those who do not conceive of the Tathāgata in terms of truth, essence, substance, a real entity, or a partless whole regard all constructs as false. Those who see all constructs as false know all phenomena to be mistaken.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.102.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་གིས་ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་ལོག་པར་ཤེས་པ་དེ་དག་ཐམས་ཅད་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པས་ལོག་པར་ལྟ་བ་ཡོངས་སུ་རྫོགས་པ་ཡིན་པར་བསྟན་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The Tathāgata has taught that all those who know every phenomenon to be mistaken have perfected the view of mistakenness.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.102.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་དག་གིས་ལྟ་བར་གྱུར་པ་ཐམས་ཅད་ལོག་པ་ཡིན་པར་ཡང་ཤེས་ཏེ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They also understand that all those who have resorted to views are mistaken.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.102.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེའི་ཕྱིར་ཡང་དེ་དག་ལོག་པར་ལྟ་བ་ཞེས་བྱའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>This is why some are referred to as holding a mistaken view.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.102.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཤཱ་རིའི་བུ་རྣམ་གྲངས་དེས་གང་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་ལྟ་བར་འདོད་པ་དེ་དག་ལོག་པར་ལྟ་བ་ཞེས་བྱའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Śāriputra, according to this discourse, those who wish to view the Tathāgata are referred to as holding a mistaken view.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.102.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཤཱ་རིའི་བུ་དེ་དག་ནི་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པའི་སྐུ་མ་འཁྲུགས་པར་ལྟ་བའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Śāriputra, some view the Tathāgata’s body unerringly.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.102.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པའི་སྐུ་ལོག་པ་ཡིན་པར་རྟོག་པ་དེ་དག་ནི་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པའི་འདུ་ཤེས་མེད་པའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>But those who understand the Tathāgata’s body as mistaken have no conception of the Tathāgata.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.102.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཤཱ་རིའི་བུ་གང་འདི་ལྟར་ལོག་པར་ཤེས་པ་དེ་ནི་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་མཐོང་བའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Śāriputra, those who know this to be mistaken see the Tathāgata.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.102.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཇི་ལྟར་ན་གང་ལོག་པར་ལྟ་བ་དེ་དག་ཡང་དག་པར་ཞུགས་པ་ལགས། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-109"/>“Blessed One, how have those who view this as mistaken correctly understood?”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.102.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་བཀའ་སྩལ་པ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The Blessed One replied,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.102.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཤཱ་རིའི་བུ་གང་སོ་སོའི་སྐྱེ་བོ་རྣམས་རྟོག་པ་དང་། རྣམ་པར་རྟོག་པ་དང་། དཔྱོད་པ་དང་། རྣམ་པར་དཔྱོད་པ་དང་། ལྡང་བར་བྱེད་པ་དང་། ཀུན་ཏུ་ལྡང་བར་བྱེད་པ་དང་། རྟེན་པ་དང་། གནས་པ་དང་། ལེན་པ་དང་། འདོར་བ་དང་། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Śāriputra, ordinary beings discriminate and conceptualize, examine and analyze, reveal and thoroughly reveal, rely and dwell, accept and reject.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.102.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བདག་དང་། སེམས་ཅན་དང་། སྲོག་དང་། གང་ཟག་ཏུ་ལྟ་བ་ཉེ་བར་ལེན་པ་དང་། བདག་ཏུ་འཛིན་པ་ལ་མངོན་པར་ཞེན་པ་དང་། བདག་གིར་འཛིན་པ་ལ་ཆགས་པ་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They embrace the view of a self, a being, a life, and a person, and they cling to the belief in ‘I’ and are attached to the belief in ‘mine.’</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.102.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་དག་གི་སྤྱོད་པ་དང་། ཤེས་པ་དང་། གཡོ་བ་དང་། སྤྲོས་པ་དེ་ལྟ་བུ་དག་དེ་དག་གིས་ཤེས་ཏེ</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They conceive their conduct, knowledge, movements, and conceptual elaborations along these lines.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.102.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་དག་ཇི་ལྟ་བུར་ཡོད་པ་མ་ཡིན་པ་དེ་ལྟ་བུ་ཉིད་དུ་ཤེས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They understand these things, which do not actually exist, in just this way.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.102.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཤཱ་རིའི་བུ་མེད་པ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་དེ་ནི་ཡང་དག་པ་མ་ཡིན་པའི་ཚིག་བླ་དགས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Śāriputra, the word nonexistent is a designation for what is unreal.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.102.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡང་དག་པ་མ་ཡིན་པ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་དེ་ནི་བརྫུན་པའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>That which is unreal is a lie.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.102.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བརྫུན་པ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་དེ་ནི་ལོག་པའི་ཚིག་བླ་དགས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The word lie is a designation what is false.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.102.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ལྟར་གང་ཚུལ་འདི་ལྟ་བུ་ཡང་དག་པ་མ་ཡིན་པར་འཛིན་པ་དག་ལོག་པར་མཐོང་བ་དེའི་ཕྱིར་དེ་དག་ཡང་དག་པར་ཞུགས་པ་ཞེས་བྱའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Those who see how mistaken those beings are, who believe in the unreal, are said to have discerned reality.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.102.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཤཱ་རིའི་བུ་རྣམ་གྲངས་དེ་ཉིད་ཀྱིས་གང་ལོག་པར་ལྟ་བ་དེ་དག་ཡང་དག་པར་ཞུགས་པའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Śāriputra, according to this very explanation, those who see this as wrong have correct understanding.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.102.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-111"/>“Blessed One,”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.102.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཇི་ལྟར་ན་གང་ཡང་དག་པར་ཞུགས་པ་དེ་དག་ལ་སྩལ་ན་འབྲས་བུ་ཆེ་བ་མ་ལགས། <tei:ref folio="F.102.b"/>ཕན་ཡོན་ཆེ་བ་མ་ལགས། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“in what way do those with correct understanding neither reap great result nor receive great benefit when they are generous?” </seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.102.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་བཀའ་སྩལ་པ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>replied the Blessed One,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.102.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཤཱ་རིའི་བུ་གང་ཚུལ་འདི་ལྟ་བུས་ཡང་དག་པར་ཞུགས་པ་དང་ལྡན་པར་གྱུར་པ་དེ་དག་ལ་སྦྱིན་པ་ནི་མྱ་ངན་ལས་འདའ་བ་ལ་གཞོལ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Śāriputra,” “for those who have correct understanding through this approach, generosity is directed toward nirvāṇa.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.102.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མྱ་ངན་ལས་འདའ་བ་ལ་འབབ། མྱ་ངན་ལས་འདའ་བ་ལ་བབ། མྱ་ངན་ལས་འདའ་བའི་མཐར་ཐུག་པར་འགྱུར་ཏེ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>It flows and has flowed into nirvāṇa, and it will culminate in nirvāṇa.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.102.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མྱ་ངན་ལས་འདའ་བ་ཡང་འབྲས་བུ་ཆུང་བ་ཡང་མ་ཡིན། འབྲས་བུ་ཆེ་བ་ཡང་མ་ཡིན། ཕན་ཡོན་ཆུང་བ་ཡང་མ་ཡིན། ཕན་ཡོན་ཆེ་བ་ཡང་མ་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>However, nirvāṇa is neither a small nor a great result, neither a small nor a great benefit.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.102.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ཅིའི་ཕྱིར་ཞེ་ན། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Why?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.102.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མྱ་ངན་ལས་འདས་པ་ནི་འབྲས་བུ་ཐམས་ཅད་དང་བྲལ་ཞིང་བཏགས་པ་མ་ཡིན། གདགས་པར་བྱ་བ་མ་ཡིན་པའི་ཕྱིར་རོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Because nirvāṇa is free from all results and is therefore neither a designation nor an object of designation.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.102.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་འོ་ན་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-113"/>“Well then, Blessed One,”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.102.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པས་མྱ་ངན་ལས་འདས་པ། གདགས་སུ་མ་མཆིས་པ་ལ་ཇི་ལྟར་ཡོན་ཏན་མཐའ་ཡས་པའི་སྨན་ཡོན་གྱི་བྱེ་བྲག་བསྟན། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“how did the Tathāgata teach the particular advantages of infinite virtuous qualities with respect to nirvāṇa that does not exist for designation?”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.102.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་བཀའ་སྩལ་པ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>replied the Blessed One,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.102.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཤཱ་རིའི་བུ་སྐྱེ་བའི་སྤྱོད་ཡུལ་ཅན་གྱི་སེམས་ཅན་བདག་དང་། སེམས་ཅན་དང་། སྲོག་དང་། གང་ཟག་ཏུ་སྨྲ་བ་རྣམས་མོས་པ་བསྐྱེད་པའི་ཕྱིར་མྱ་ངན་ལས་འདས་པ་གདགས་སུ་མེད་པ་ལ་ཡང་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པས་ཡོན་ཏན་མཐའ་ཡས་པའི་ཕན་ཡོན་གྱི་བྱེ་བྲག་བསྟན་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Śāriputra,” “the Tathāgata taught particular advantages of infinite virtuous qualities with respect to nirvāṇa, even though it does not exist for designation, in order to inspire beings subject to the world of birth who assert selfhood, beings, life forms, and persons.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.102.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཤཱ་རིའི་བུ་འོན་ཀྱང་འཕགས་པ་རྣམས་ནི་སྦྱིན་པ་ལ་འཇུག་པར་མི་བལྟའི། འཕགས་པ་རྣམས་འདོད་ཆགས་དང་བྲལ་བ་དང་། སྦྱིན་པ་ལས་ལྡོག་པར་བལྟའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>However, Śāriputra, one should not consider noble beings to be those who engage in generosity, but rather those who are free from attachment and who turn away from generosity.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.102.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཤཱ་རིའི་བུ་འདི་ལྟ་སྟེ། དཔེར་ན་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Śāriputra, it may be illustrated as follows:</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.102.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཞིང་པ་དག་ཞིང་ལ་ནས་ཀྱི་ས་བོན་བཏབ་སྟེ། དེའི་ནས་དེ་ཉིད་ལ་བརྟེན་ནས་སྲེ་ད་དང་། རྩྭ་དང་། སྔོ་རྣམས་སྐྱེ་ན། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>When farmers have planted barley seeds in a field, husks, stalks, and leaves are produced from the barley. In that case,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.102.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཤཱ་རིའི་བུ་དེ་ཇི་སྙམ་དུ་སེམས། སྲེ་ད་དང་རྩྭ་དང་། སྔོ་འདི་དག་ཞིང་པ་དེའི་ལས་བྱས་པའི་འབྲས་བུ་ཡིན་ནམ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Śāriputra, do you think that the husks, stalks, and leaves are the fruits produced by the actions of those farmers?”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.102.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་མ་ལགས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“No, Blessed One, I do not,”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.102.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་བཀའ་སྩལ་པ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>continued the Blessed One,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.102.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཤཱ་རིའི་བུ་འདི་ལྟ་སྟེ། དཔེར་ན་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-116"/>“Śāriputra,” “it may be illustrated as follows:</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.102.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཞིང་པས་ནས་ཀྱི་ས་བོན་བཏབ་པ་དེའི་ནས་དེ་དག་ཉིད་ལ་བརྟེན་ནས་སྲེད་རྣམས་འབྱུང་བ་དང་། རྩྭ་དང་། སྔོ་རྣམས་སྐྱེ་བར་འགྱུར་ཏེ། ནས་ཀྱི་སྙི་མ་གཞན་རྣམས་ཀྱང་འབྱུང་ངོ་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>It is on account of the barley itself—namely, those barley seeds planted by the farmers—that the husks, stalks, and leaves are produced, as well as other ears of barley.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.102.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་བཞིན་དུ་འཕགས་པ་རྣམས་ལ་སྦྱིན་པ་བྱིན་པ་ནི་ཚེགས་ཆུང་ངུས་ལོངས་སྤྱོད་ཆེན་པོར་འགྱུར་ལ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Likewise, when noble beings practice generosity, great resources come to them with little difficulty.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.103.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཞན་ཡང་ཟག་པ་ཟད་པ་སྲེད་པའི་འབྲས་བུ་ཐམས་ཅད་སྐེམས་པར་བྱེད་<tei:ref folio="F.103.a"/>དོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>In addition, all fruits resulting from craving for the exhaustion of afflictions wither. </seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.103.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདི་ལྟ་སྟེ། དཔེར་ན་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>It may be illustrated as follows:</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.103.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ནས་འདོད་པ་དག་འདི་ནི་ནས་ཀྱི་ས་བོན་དེའི་འབྲས་བུ་མ་ཡིན། འདི་ནི་ནས་ཀྱི་ས་བོན་དེའི་སྙི་མ་མ་ཡིན་ནོ་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Those who want barley think, ‘This is not the fruits of these barely seeds, nor is this the ears of barley produced by those seeds.’</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.103.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྙམ་ནས་སྲེ་དས་མགུ་བར་མི་འགྱུར་ཞིང་། རྩྭ་དང་། སྔོས་རངས་པར་མི་འགྱུར་བ་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>As a consequence, they are neither pleased by the husks nor delighted by the stalks and leaves.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.103.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་བཞིན་དུ་འདུས་མ་བྱས་པའི་ཞིང་ལ་སྦྱིན་པ་བྱིན་པ་འདུས་བྱས་ཀྱི་འབྲས་བུ་ཡིན་པར་བསྟན་པར་མི་བྱའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Likewise, it should not be taught that practicing generosity in the field of the unconditioned gives a result that is conditioned.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.103.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཤཱ་རིའི་བུ་རྣམ་གྲངས་དེས་གང་ཡང་དག་པར་ཞུགས་པ་དེ་དག་ལ་བྱིན་པ་འབྲས་བུ་ཆེ་བ་མ་ཡིན། ཕན་ཡོན་ཆེ་བ་མ་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Śāriputra, according to this discourse, generosity brings neither great result nor great benefit for those who have correct understanding.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.103.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-117"/>“Blessed One,”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.103.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་དག་ལ་སྩལ་ན་འབྲས་བུ་ཆེ་བ་མ་ལགས་ཤིང་སྨན་ཡོན་ཆེ་བ་མ་ལགས་པ་དེ་དག་ཇི་ལྟར་འཇིག་རྟེན་གྱི་སྦྱིན་གནས་ལགས། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“how can those noble beings be objects of generosity in the world when their generosity yields neither great result nor great benefit?”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.103.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་བཀའ་སྩལ་པ། ཤཱ་རིའི་བུ་གང་འབྲས་བུ་ཆེ་བར་འདུ་ཤེས་པ་ཡང་མ་ཡིན། འབྲས་བུ་ཆུང་བར་འདུ་ཤེས་པ་ཡང་མ་ཡིན་པ་དེ་དག་སྦྱིན་པ་སྐྱེ་བར་མི་འགྱུར་རོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Śāriputra,” replied the Blessed One, “generosity will not arise for those who do not conceive of results as great or small.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.103.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་སྦྱིན་པ་སྐྱེ་བར་མི་འགྱུར་བ་དེ་དག་ནི་ལྷ་དང་བཅས་པའི་འཇིག་རྟེན་གྱི་སྦྱིན་གནས་སུ་འགྱུར་རོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Those for whom generosity does not arise will become objects of generosity in the world with its gods.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.103.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཤཱ་རིའི་བུ་དེ་ལ་ཟད་མི་ཤེས་པའི་ཞིང་ལ་སྦྱིན་པ་བྱིན་པ་ནི་མེ་ཏོག་ཀྱང་མི་ཆགས། འབྲས་བུར་ཡང་མི་འགྱུར་རོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>In that case, Śāriputra, the practice of generosity in the inexhaustible field of generosity neither becomes a flower nor turns into a fruit.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.103.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཤཱ་རིའི་བུ་རྣམ་གྲངས་འདིས་གང་ལ་བྱིན་ན་འབྲས་བུ་ཆེ་བ་ཡང་མ་ཡིན། ཕན་ཡོན་ཆེ་བ་ཡང་མ་ཡིན་པ་དེ་དག་འཇིག་རྟེན་གྱི་སྦྱིན་གནས་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Thus, according to this discourse, Śāriputra, those for whom there is neither a great result nor a great benefit when they are generous are objects of generosity in the world.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.103.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཇི་ལྟར་ན་གང་འཇིག་རྟེན་གྱི་སྦྱིན་གནས་དེ་དག་ལ་བྱིན་པ་རྣམ་པར་སྨིན་པ་མ་མཆིས་པ་ལགས། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-119"/>“Blessed One, why does generosity not ripen for those who are objects of generosity in the world?” asked Śāriputra.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.103.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་བཀའ་སྩལ་པ་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>the Blessed One asked in return.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.103.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཤཱ་རིའི་བུ་དེ་ཇི་སྙམ་དུ་སེམས། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“What do you think, Śāriputra?”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.103.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྦྱིན་པ་གང་མྱ་ངན་ལས་འདའ་བའི་མཐར་ཐུག་པར་འགྱུར་བ་དེ་རྣམ་པར་སྨིན་པའི་ཆོས་ཅན་ཡིན་ནམ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Is the generosity that culminates in nirvāṇa subject to karmic ripening?”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.103.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་མ་ལགས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-121"/>“No, Blessed One, it is not,”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.103.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་སྦྱིན་པ་མྱ་ངན་ལས་འདས་པའི་མཐར་ཐུག་པ་དེ་དེ་སྟེ་སྦྱིན་པའི་ཆོས་ཅན་ལགས་ན། འཕགས་པའི་གང་ཟག་རྣམས་འདུས་མ་བྱས་པས་རབ་ཏུ་ཕྱེ་བར་མི་འགྱུར་རོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Blessed One, if the generosity that culminates in nirvāṇa were subject to karmic ripening, noble beings would not be distinguished as being unconditioned.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.103.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་བཀའ་སྩལ་པ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>said the Blessed One.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.103.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཤཱ་རིའི་བུ་ལེགས་སོ། །ལེགས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Excellent, Śāriputra, excellent,”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.103.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྣམ་གྲངས་འདིས་གང་འཇིག་རྟེན་གྱི་སྦྱིན་གནས་ཡིན་པ་དེ་དག་ལ་བྱིན་པ་རྣམ་པར་སྨིན་པ་མེད་པ་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“According to this discourse, generosity does not entail karmic ripening for those who are objects of generosity in the world.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.103.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གསོལ་པ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-123"/>Śāriputra then asked,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.103.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཇི་ལྟར་ན་གང་སྦྱིན་པའི་རྣམ་པར་སྨིན་པ་མ་མཆིས་པ་དེ་དག་གིས་འདུ་ཤེས་མ་མཆིས་པ་ཡོངས་སུ་རྫོགས་པར་བགྱིས་པ་<tei:ref folio="F.103.b"/>ལགས། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Blessed One, how have those for whom generosity does not ripen perfected non-conception?” </seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.103.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་བཀའ་སྩལ་པ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>the Blessed One asked in return.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.103.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཤཱ་རིའི་བུ་དེ་ཇི་སྙམ་དུ་སེམས། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“What do you think, Śāriputra?”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.103.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་ཆོས་རྣམས་ཀྱི་ངོ་བོ་ཉིད་ཤེས་པ་དེ་ཡོད་དམ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Do those who know the very nature of all phenomena exist?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.103.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འོན་ཏེ་མེད། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Or, do they not exist?”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.103.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་གང་ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱི་ངོ་བོ་ཉིད་འཚལ་བ་དེ་སྒྱུ་མའི་ངོ་བོ་ཉིད་འཚལ་བ་ལགས་ཏེ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-125"/>“Blessed One,” “those who understand the very nature of all phenomena understand the very nature of illusions.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.103.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་དེ་ནི་མ་མཆིས་པ་ལགས་ཏེ། མཆིས་པ་མ་ལགས་སོ། །དེ་ཅིའི་སླད་དུ་ཞེ་ན། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Blessed One, this nature is nonexistent. It does not exist. Why?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.103.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་ནི་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་སྒྱུ་མའི་ངོ་བོ་ཉིད་དུ་བསྟན་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Blessed One, you taught that all phenomena have an illusory nature.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.103.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྒྱུ་མ་ལྟ་བུ་གང་ལགས་པ་དེ་ཡང་མ་མཆིས་པའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>That which is like an illusion is nonexistent.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.103.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱི་ངོ་བོ་ཉིད་འཚལ་བ་འདི་ནི་འདུ་ཤེས་མ་མཆིས་པའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Those who understand the very nature of all phenomena have no conceptions.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.103.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ཅིའི་སླད་དུ་ཞེ་ན། འདི་ལ་གང་ཡང་དག་པར་གྱུར་པའི་ཆོས་གང་ཡང་མི་དམིགས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Why? Because nothing, no actual phenomenon whatsoever, is perceived by them.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.103.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་བཀའ་སྩལ་པ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>said the Blessed One.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.103.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཤཱ་རིའི་བུ་ལེགས་སོ། །ལེགས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-126"/>“Excellent, Śāriputra, excellent,”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.103.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་དེ་བཞིན་ཏེ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“It is just like that.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.103.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཤཱ་རིའི་བུ་འདི་ལ་ཆོས་འགའ་ཞིག་རྫས་སམ། ཡང་དག་པར་ཡོད་པར་གྱུར་ན་སེམས་ཅན་རྣམས་ཕྱིས་ཀྱང་མྱ་ངན་ལས་འདའ་བར་མི་འགྱུར་རོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Śāriputra, if some phenomena were substantially or truly existent, beings would not attain nirvāṇa, even in the future.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.103.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཤཱ་རིའི་བུ་གང་གི་ཕྱིར་ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་ཡང་དག་པ་མ་ཡིན། ཡོད་པ་མ་ཡིན། རྫས་མ་ཡིན་པ་དེའི་ཕྱིར་སེམས་ཅན་གང་གཱའི་ཀླུང་གི་བྱེ་མ་སྙེད་མྱ་ངན་ལས་བཟླས་ཀྱང་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Śāriputra, it is precisely because all phenomena are unreal, nonexistent, and insubstantial that beings as numerous as the grains of sand in the river Ganges have attained nirvāṇa. Yet,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.103.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སེམས་ཅན་མེད་པའི་ཕྱིར་སེམས་ཅན་རྣམས་ལས་གང་ཡང་ཟད་པར་མི་མངོན་ནོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>because beings do not exist, there is nothing at all related to those beings that is brought to an end.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.103.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཤཱ་རིའི་བུ་དེ་ལྟ་བས་ན་གང་སེམས་ཅན་ཐམས་ཅད་མེད་པའི་འདུ་ཤེས་དང་། དེ་དག་ཀྱང་མི་དམིགས་པ་འདི་ནི་འདུ་ཤེས་མེད་པ་ཡོངས་སུ་རྫོགས་པའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Therefore, Śāriputra, whoever neither apprehends the conception of the nonexistence of all beings, nor the beings themselves, has perfected non-conception.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.103.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཤཱ་རིའི་བུ་རྣམ་གྲངས་དེས་གང་དག་ལ་བྱིན་པ་རྣམ་པར་སྨིན་པ་མེད་པ་དེ་དག་གིས་འདུ་ཤེས་མེད་པ་ཡོངས་སུ་རྫོགས་པར་བྱས་པ་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Śāriputra, according to this discourse, those for whom there is no ripening of generosity have perfected non-conception.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.103.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གསོལ་པ། བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཇི་ལྟར་ན་གང་དག་གིས་འདུ་ཤེས་མེད་པ་ཡོངས་སུ་རྫོགས་པར་བགྱིས་པའི་འདུ་ཤེས་དེས་མྱུར་དུ་མི་སྐྱེ་བའི་ཆོས་ལ་བཟོད་པ་ཐོབ་པར་འགྱུར། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-127"/>“Blessed One,” asked Śāriputra, “how will they swiftly accept the non-arising of all phenomena through this conception of having perfected non-conception?”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.103.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་བཀའ་སྩལ་པ། ཤཱ་རིའི་བུ་གང་གིས་མེད་པ་མངོན་སུམ་དུ་བྱས་པ་དེ་དག་ནི་ཤེས་པའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Śāriputra,” replied the Blessed One, “those who have directly realized nonexistence understand this.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.103.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མེད་པ་ཡང་གང་ཞེ་ན། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>But what is nonexistence?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.103.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མེད་པ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་ནི་བདག་ཏུ་ལྟ་བ་དང་། སེམས་ཅན་དུ་ལྟ་བ་དང་། སྲོག་ཏུ་ལྟ་བ་དང་། གང་ཟག་ཏུ་ལྟ་བ་དང་། ཆད་པར་ལྟ་བ་དང་། རྟག་པར་ལྟ་བའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The term nonexistence pertains to the metaphysical views of self, beings, life force, and persons, as well as the views of nihilism and eternalism.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.104.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མེད་པ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་ནི་སངས་རྒྱས་སུ་འདུ་ཤེས་པ་དང་། ཆོས་སུ་འདུ་ཤེས་པ་དང་། དགེ་འདུན་དུ་འདུ་ཤེས་པ་དང་། མྱ་ངན་ལས་འདའ་བར་འདུ་<tei:ref folio="F.104.a"/>ཤེས་པ་དང་། ཇི་ཙམ་དུ་སེམས་ཀྱི་སྦྱོར་བ་དང་། སྤྱོད་པ་དང་། ཤེས་པ་དང་། གཡོ་བ་དང་། སྤྲོས་པ་དེ་དག་ཐམས་ཅད་མེད་པའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The term nonexistence pertains to the conceptions of Buddha, Dharma, Saṅgha, and nirvāṇa. No matter how much one applies one’s mind, practices, understands, acts, or speculates, all this is nonexistent.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.104.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཤཱ་རིའི་བུ་དེ་བས་ན་ཚུལ་དེ་ལྟ་བུར་ཡང་དག་པ་མ་ཡིན་པར་འཛིན་པ་དེ་དག་ལས་ཡོངས་སུ་གྲོལ་བ་དེ་དག་ནི་ཤེས་པའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Therefore, Śāriputra, those who are in this way completely free from such incorrect reifications understand.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.104.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཤཱ་རིའི་བུ་རྣམ་གྲངས་དེས་གང་གིས་འདུ་ཤེས་མེད་པ་ཡོངས་སུ་རྫོགས་པར་བྱས་པ་དེ་དག་མྱུར་དུ་མི་སྐྱེ་བའི་ཆོས་ལ་བཟོད་པ་ཐོབ་པར་འགྱུར་རོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>According to this discourse, Śāriputra, those who have perfected non-conception will quickly accept that all phenomena do not arise.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.104.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དགོངས་ཏེ་གསུངས་པའི་བསྟན་པ་འདི་བསྟན་པའི་ཚེ། བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་བཞི་ཁྲི་ཉིས་སྟོང་གིས་མི་སྐྱེ་བའི་ཆོས་ལ་བཟོད་པ་ཐོབ་པར་གྱུར་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-129"/>When this exposition of the teaching was being presented, forty-two thousand bodhisattvas accepted that all phenomena do not arise.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.104.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དགེ་བསྙེན་དྲུག་སྟོང་གིས་བླ་ན་མེད་པ་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་བྱང་ཆུབ་ཏུ་སེམས་བསྐྱེད་དོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Six thousand male lay vow holders set their minds on unsurpassable, complete, and perfect awakening.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.104.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལྷའི་བུ་སུམ་ཁྲི་དྲུག་སྟོང་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་ཡེ་ཤེས་མངོན་པར་རྟོགས་པར་གྱུར་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Thirty-six thousand sons of the gods gained the realization of wisdom.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.104.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དགེ་སློང་ལྷག་པའི་ང་རྒྱལ་ཅན་དྲུག་ཅུ་པོ་དེ་དག་རྣམས་ཀྱང་ཉེ་བར་ལེན་པ་མེད་པར་ཟག་པ་རྣམས་ལས་སེམས་རྣམ་པར་གྲོལ་ལོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>As for the sixty exceedingly proud monks, their minds became liberated from defilements with no further appropriation.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.104.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་དག་སེམས་རྣམ་པར་གྲོལ་ནས་མགྲིན་གཅིག་ཏུ་ཚིག་སྨྲས་པ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-130"/>With minds free from defilements, these sixty arrogant monks spoke the following words in unison:</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.104.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་བདག་ཅག་ནི་དེང་སླན་ཆད་སྟོན་པ་དྲུག་རྣམས་ཀྱི་རྗེས་སུ་རབ་ཏུ་བྱུང་ངོ་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Blessed One, from this day forth, we shall become renunciants who follow the six teachers.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.104.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེང་སླན་ཅད་བདག་ཅག་གི་སྟོན་པ་སངས་རྒྱས་མ་ལགས། ཆོས་ལ་མི་རྟེན། དགེ་འདུན་ལ་མི་རྟེན་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>From this day forth, our teacher is no longer the Buddha and we shall rely neither on the Dharma nor on the Saṅgha.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.104.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེང་སླན་ཆད་བདག་ཅག་བྱ་བ་མ་མཆིས་པར་སྨྲ་བ། རྒྱུ་མ་མཆིས་པར་སྨྲ་བ། ལས་མ་མཆིས་པར་སྨྲ་བ། རྣམ་པར་སྨིན་པ་མ་མཆིས་པར་སྨྲ་བ། འདུལ་བ་མ་ལགས་པར་སྨྲ་བའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>From this day forth, we shall be proponents of the nonexistence of action, causation, karma, karmic ripening, and moral conduct.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.104.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེའི་ཚེ་འཁོར་དེ་ན་སྲོག་ཆགས་སྟོང་ཕྲག་མང་པོ་རྣམས་འདི་སྙམ་དུ་གྱུར་ཏེ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-131"/>At that moment, several thousand beings in the assembly thought to themselves,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.104.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདི་ལྟར་དགེ་སློང་འདི་དག་འདི་ལྟ་བུ་ཡང་དག་པ་མ་ཡིན་པའི་ཚིག་སྨྲ་བ་ལས་ན། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“These monks have thus become proponents of such untruths!</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.104.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱི་བསླབ་པ་ཕུལ་ནས་མུ་སྟེགས་ཅན་གྱི་མཚན་མ་འཛིན་པར་མི་འགྱུར་རམ་སྙམ་དུ་གྱུར་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Will they now give up the precepts they received from the Blessed One and take up the traits of the non-Buddhists?”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.104.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་ཚེ་དང་ལྡན་པ་ཤཱ་རིའི་བུའི་སེམས་ཀྱིས་འཁོར་དེ་དག་གི་སེམས་ཀྱི་རྟོག་པ་ཤེས་ནས་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-132"/>The venerable Śāriputra clairvoyantly understood what those beings in the retinue were thinking.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.104.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དགེ་སློང་དེ་དག་ལ་སྨྲས་པ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Therefore, he asked the monks,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.104.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཚེ་དང་ལྡན་པ་དག་ཅི་ལས་བསམས་ཏེ། དེང་ཕན་ཆད་བདག་ཅག་སྟོན་པ་དྲུག་གི་རྗེས་སུ་རབ་ཏུ་བྱུང་ངོ་ཞེས་དེ་སྐད་སྨྲ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Venerable ones, what was your intention when you said, ‘From this day forth, we shall become renunciants who follow the six teachers’?”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.104.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་དག་གིས་སྨྲས་པ། ཚེ་དང་ལྡན་པ་ཤཱ་རིའི་བུ་དེང་ཕན་ཆད་བདག་ཅག་གི་སྟོན་པ་ཐམས་ཅད་སྟོན་པ་དྲུག་དང་མཉམ་ཞིང་མཚན་ཉིད་གཅིག་ཅིང་བྱེ་བྲག་མེད་པར་རྣམ་པར་རིག་གོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Venerable Śāriputra,” answered the monks, “from this day forth, we perceive all our teachers as identical to the six teachers, as being of a single character, without any difference. </seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.104.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བདག་ཅག་<tei:ref folio="F.104.b"/>གིས་སྟོན་པ་ཐམས་ཅད་ཐ་དད་པ་མེད་པར་རིག་ནས་རྣམ་པར་མི་རྟོག་པར་རབ་ཏུ་བྱུང་བའི་རྗེས་སུ་རབ་ཏུ་བྱུང་ངོ་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Perceiving all teachers as undifferentiated, we are renunciants following renunciants without conceptualizing.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.104.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྨྲས་པ་ཅི་ལས་བསམས་ནས་དེང་ཕན་ཆད་བདག་ཅག་གི་སྟོན་པ་སངས་རྒྱས་མ་ཡིན་ནོ་ཞེས་དེ་སྐད་སྨྲ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-134"/>Śāriputra then asked, “What was your intention when you said, ‘From this day forth, our teacher is no longer the Buddha’?”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.104.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་དག་གིས་སྨྲས་པ། དེང་ཕན་ཆད་བདག་ཅག་བདག་ལ་རྟེན་གྱི་གཞན་ལ་མི་རྟེན། བདག་ལ་སྐྱབས་སུ་དོང་གི་གཞན་ལ་སྐྱབས་སུ་དོང་བ་མ་ཡིན། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“From this day forth,” they answered, “we will rely on ourselves, but not on others. We will take refuge in ourselves, but not in others.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.104.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བདག་སྟོན་པ་ཡིན་གྱི་སྟོན་པ་གཞན་མ་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>We are our own teachers and no one else is.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.104.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་བས་ན་དེང་ཕན་ཆད་བདག་ཅག་གི་སྟོན་པ་སངས་རྒྱས་མ་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Therefore, from this day forth, our teacher is no longer the Buddha.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.104.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ཅིའི་ཕྱིར་ཞེ་ན། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Why?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.104.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བདག་མ་གཏོགས་པར་སངས་རྒྱས་མེད། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Aside from oneself, there is no buddha.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.104.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སངས་རྒྱས་མ་གཏོགས་པར་བདག་མེད་དོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Aside from a buddha, there is no self.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.104.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཅི་ལས་བསམས་ནས་དེང་ཕན་ཆད་བདག་ཅག་ཆོས་ལ་མི་རྟེན། དགེ་འདུན་ལ་མི་རྟེན་ཅེས་དེ་སྐད་སྨྲ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“What was your intention when you said, ‘From this day forth, we shall rely neither on the Dharma nor on the Saṅgha’?”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.104.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་དག་གིས་སྨྲས་པ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>they answered,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.104.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེང་ཕན་ཆད་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“From this day forth,”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.104.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བདག་ཅག་གིས་གང་ལ་བརྟེན་པ་དང་། གང་དང་ལྷན་ཅིག་འགྲོ་བའི་ཆོས་གང་ཡང་མ་དམིགས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“we do not perceive any phenomenon whatsoever that anyone should rely upon or conform to.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.104.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་བས་ན་བདག་ཅག་དེང་ཕན་ཆད་ཆོས་ལ་མི་རྟེན། དགེ་འདུན་ལ་མི་རྟེན་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Therefore, from this day forth, we shall rely neither on the Dharma nor on the Saṅgha.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.104.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཅི་ལས་བསམས་ཏེ་བདག་ཅག་དེང་ཕན་ཆད་བྱ་བ་མེད་པར་སྨྲའོ་ཞེས་དེ་སྐད་ཅེས་ཟེར། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“What was your intention when you said, ‘From this day forth, we shall be proponents of the nonexistence of action’?”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.104.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་དག་གིས་སྨྲས་པ། བདག་ཅག་གིས་དེང་ཕན་ཆད་ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་མ་བྱས་པར་ཤེས་ཏེ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“From this day forth,” they answered, “we know that all phenomena are unproduced.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.104.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་ན་བྱས་པ་ཡང་མེད། འགྱུར་བ་ཡང་མེད་པའི་ཆོས་དེ་བདག་ཅག་གིས་མངོན་དུ་བྱས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>We have realized that phenomena undergo no production or change anywhere.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.104.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་བས་ན་དེང་ཕན་ཆད་བདག་ཅག་བྱ་བ་མེད་པར་སྨྲའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Therefore, from this day forth, we are proponents of the nonexistence of action.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.104.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཅི་ལས་བསམས་ཏེ་དེང་ཕན་ཆད་བདག་ཅག་རྒྱུ་མེད་པར་སྨྲའོ་ཞེས་དེ་སྐད་ཟེར། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“What was your intention when you said, ‘From this day forth, we shall be proponents of the nonexistence of causation’?”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.104.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་དག་གིས་སྨྲས་པ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>they answered,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.104.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བདག་ཅག་སྲིད་པ་ཐམས་ཅད་དུ་འགྲོ་བར་སྐྱེ་བའི་རྒྱུ་དེང་ཟད་དེ་གང་ན་རྒྱུ་ཡང་མེད་རྐྱེན་ཡང་མེད་པའི་ཆོས་དེ་མངོན་དུ་བྱས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“For us,” “the cause of birth in all destinies of cyclic existence has ended today. We have realized that phenomena are without any causes and conditions anywhere.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.104.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེའི་ཕྱིར་དེང་ཕན་ཆད་བདག་ཅག་རྒྱུ་མེད་པར་སྨྲའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Therefore, from this day forth, we are proponents of the nonexistence of causation.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.104.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཅི་ལས་བསམས་ཏེ་དེང་ཕན་ཆད་བདག་ཅག་རྣམ་པར་སྨིན་པ་མེད་པར་སྨྲའོ་ཞེས་དེ་སྐད་ཟེར། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“What was your intention when you said, ‘From this day forth, we are proponents of the nonexistence of karmic ripening’?”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.104.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་དག་གིས་སྨྲས་པ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>they answered,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.104.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེང་ཕན་ཆད་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“From this day forth,”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.104.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བདག་ཅག་གིས་གང་ན་ལས་ཀྱང་མེད། ལས་ཀྱི་རྣམ་པར་སྨིན་པ་ཡང་མེད་ཅིང་། ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་ཤིན་ཏུ་ཡོངས་སུ་མྱ་ངན་ལས་འདས་པར་ཡོངས་སུ་ཤེས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“we perfectly understand that all phenomena are without any karma nor karmic ripening anywhere and completely beyond suffering.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.104.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེའི་ཕྱིར་བདག་ཅག་དེང་ཕན་ཆད་ལས་ཀྱི་རྣམ་པར་སྨིན་པ་མེད་པར་སྨྲའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Therefore, from this day forth, we are proponents of the nonexistence of karmic ripening.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.105.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཚེ་དང་ལྡན་པ་དག་ཅི་ལས་བསམས་ཏེ་དེང་ཕན་ཆད་བདག་ཅག་འདུལ་བ་མ་ཡིན་པར་<tei:ref folio="F.105.a"/>སྨྲའོ་ཞེས་དེ་སྐད་ཟེར། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Venerable ones, what was your intention when you said, ‘From this day forth, we are proponents of the nonexistence of moral discipline’?” </seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.105.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་དག་གིས་སྨྲས་པ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>they answered,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.105.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཚེ་དང་ལྡན་པ་ཤཱ་རིའི་བུ་དེང་ཕན་ཆད་བདག་ཅག་གིས་གང་ན་འདུལ་བ་ཡང་མེད། གསུང་བ་ཡང་མེད། འདུལ་བ་མ་ཡིན་པ་ཡང་མེད་ཅིང་ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་ཤིན་ཏུ་དུལ་བར་ཡོངས་སུ་ཤེས་ཏེ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Venerable Śāriputra,” “from this day forth, we perfectly understand the fact that there is neither moral discipline, nor discourses on it, nor non-discipline, and that all phenomena are utterly disciplined.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.105.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེའི་ཕྱིར་བདག་ཅག་དེང་ཕན་ཆད་འདུལ་བ་མ་ཡིན་པར་སྨྲའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Therefore, from this day forth, we are proponents of the nonexistence of moral discipline.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.105.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་དགེ་སློང་དེ་དག་གི་ལྷག་པའི་ང་རྒྱལ་བསྟན་པ་འདི་ལྟ་བུ་ཐོས་ནས་དགེ་སློང་སུམ་སྟོང་དྲུག་བརྒྱ་རྣམས་ཉེ་བར་ལེན་པ་མེད་པར་ཟག་པ་ལས་སེམས་རབ་ཏུ་རྣམ་པར་གྲོལ་ལོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-146"/>Having thus heard this teaching regarding these arrogant monks, the minds of three thousand six hundred other monks were liberated from defilements with no further appropriation.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.105.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་དགེ་སློང་དེ་དག་ལ་ལེགས་སོ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་བྱིན་ཏེ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Then the Blessed One said to them, “Excellent!</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.105.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དགེ་སློང་དག་གང་ན་ཆོས་གང་ཡང་རྟོགས་པ་མེད་པ་དེ་ནི་ཡང་དག་པ་ཐོབ་པ་ཡིན་གྱིས་ལེགས་སོ་ལེགས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Monks, that which is devoid of the realization of any phenomenon is the attainment of truth. Thus, it is excellent, excellent.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.105.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ལ་འཇམ་དཔལ་གཞོན་ནུར་གྱུར་པས་འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་གསོལ་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-147"/>Then Youthful Mañjuśrī asked,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.105.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་རྟོགས་པ་རྟོགས་པ་ཞེས་བགྱི་བའི་རྟོགས་པ་དེ་ཆོས་གང་གི་ཚིག་བླ་དགས་ལགས། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Blessed One, what phenomena are designated by that realization termed ‘realization of realization’?”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.105.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་བཀའ་སྩལ་པ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>replied the Blessed One,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.105.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་རྟོགས་པ་རྟོགས་པ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་དེ་ནི་སྐྱེ་བ་མེད་པའི་ཆོས་ལ་བཟོད་པའི་ཚིག་བླ་དགས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Mañjuśrī,” “that term ‘realization of realization’ is a designation for the acceptance that all phenomena do not arise.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.105.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྐྱེ་བ་མ་མཆིས་པའི་ཆོས་ལ་བཟོད་པ་ཐོབ་པར་འཚལ་བའི་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔས་ཇི་ལྟར་བསླབ་པར་བགྱི། ཇི་ལྟར་སྤྱད་པར་བགྱི། ཇི་ལྟར་རྣལ་འབྱོར་དུ་འཇུག་པར་བགྱི། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-149"/>“How should those bodhisattvas, who seek to attain the acceptance that all phenomena do not arise, train, conduct themselves, and engage in practice?”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.105.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་འཇམ་དཔལ་གཞོན་ནུར་གྱུར་པ་མི་སྐྱེ་བའི་ཆོས་ལ་བཟོད་པ་བསླབ་པ་ཤེས་པར་བྱ་བའི་ཕྱིར་དེའི་ཚེ་ཚིགས་སུ་བཅད་པ་འདི་དག་གསུངས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>At that time the Blessed One uttered the following verses in order to explain to Youthful Mañjuśrī the training in accepting that all phenomena do not arise:</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.105.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཐམས་ཅད་མཁྱེན་པ་བླ་མེད་པའི། །སངས་རྒྱས་ཡེ་ཤེས་ཐོབ་འདོད་པས། །ཆོས་རྣམས་གང་ཡང་མི་གཟུང་ཞིང་། །ཆོས་རྣམས་གང་ཡང་མི་འདོར་རོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-151"/>“Those who wish to obtain the wisdom of the Buddha, The unsurpassed omniscience, Should neither take up Nor cast away any phenomenon.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.105.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་ཞིག་སྐྱེ་བར་འགྱུར་བ་ཡི། །ཆོས་ནི་གང་ཡང་མི་རྙེད་དེ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-152"/>“One does not discover any phenomena at all That come into being.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.105.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཆོས་རྣམས་འབྱུང་བ་མེད་པ་ལ། །བྱིས་པ་དག་ནི་འབྱུང་བར་འདོད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Yet childish people accept these phenomena as arising, Although they are devoid of arising.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.105.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཆོས་རྣམས་ཤེས་པར་བྱ་བ་དང་། །སྤང་བར་བྱ་བར་སྲོག་ཆགས་འཆད། །བྱིས་པ་སྐྱེ་བའི་སྤྱོད་ཡུལ་ཅན། །སྐྱེ་བ་མེད་ལ་དད་མི་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-153"/>“When beings are taught that phenomena Are to be understood and rejected, Childish people who experience arising Will not have faith in non-arising.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.105.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱང་ཆུབ་ལམ་ནི་དམ་པ་དང་། །ལམ་གྱི་ཆོས་རྣམས་བཏང་བྱས་ཏེ། །བྱིས་པ་གཉིས་ལ་ཆགས་པ་སྟེ། །གཉིས་སུ་མེད་པ་མི་ཤེས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-155"/>“Having abandoned the noble path to awakening And the teachings pertaining to the path, Childish people cling to duality And do not understand nonduality.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.105.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྒྱུ་མ་སྣ་ཚོགས་གྱུར་པ་ལ། །བྱིས་པ་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་ཐ་དད་<tei:ref folio="F.105.b"/>མཐོང་། །འདི་ལ་ཐ་དད་ཡོད་མ་ཡིན། །དེ་དག་ཐམས་ཅད་མཚན་ཉིད་གཅིག །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-156"/>“In myriad illusions, Childish people perceive distinctions Where there are none, For all these illusions are of a single character.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.105.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སོ་སོའི་སྐྱེ་བོར་གང་བརྗོད་དང་། །འཇིག་རྟེན་སངས་རྒྱས་མཁས་པ་དག །མི་གཉིས་གཉིས་སུ་དབྱེར་མེད་དེ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-157"/>“Those who are called ‘ordinary beings’ And the skillful buddhas of the world systems Are not two and are not separable into two.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.105.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་དག་སྒྱུ་མའི་ཚུལ་དུ་མཉམ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They are the same in their illusory character.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.105.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱིས་པ་ཁ་ཅིག་སྨྲ་བ་ནི། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-158"/>“Some childish people say,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.105.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ནམ་ཞིག་བདག་ཅག་འདོད་ཆགས་ཟད། །ཞེ་སྡང་གཏི་མུག་ཞི་བར་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>‘One day our attachment will end, And our hatred and ignorance will be pacified;</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.105.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ནམ་ཞིག་ཉོན་མོངས་མེད་པར་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>One day there will be no afflictions.’</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.105.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མེད་ལ་ཡོད་པར་འདུ་ཤེས་པའི། །འདོད་ཆགས་ཞེ་སྡང་གཞིག་པའི་ཕྱིར། །གང་དག་སྟོང་པ་ཉིད་སྟོན་པ། །དེ་དག་ཆད་པ་མྱ་ངན་འདས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-159"/>“For those who have taught emptiness In order to annihilate the attachment and hatred That conceive of the nonexistent as existent, Their exhaustion is nirvāṇa.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.105.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཟད་པ་མེད་ཅིང་སྐྱེ་མེད་པར། །མྱ་ངན་འདས་པ་ཡང་དག་བསྟན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-160"/>“Nirvāṇa is perfectly taught As being without cessation or arising.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.105.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཟད་ཅིང་སྐྱེ་མེད་གང་བརྩོན་པ། །དེ་དག་ང་ཡི་བསྟན་ལས་རིང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Yet far from my teaching are those Who strive for something unceasing or unarisen.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.105.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྦྱིན་དང་ཚུལ་ཁྲིམས་འདུ་ཤེས་དང་། །གང་དག་བྱང་ཆུབ་འདུ་ཤེས་དགའ། །དེ་དག་མཚན་མའི་སྤྱོད་ཡུལ་བས། །ང་ཡི་བྱང་ཆུབ་དེས་མི་རྟོགས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-161"/>“Those who delight in conceptions Of generosity, moral conduct, and awakening Remain within the domain of phenomenal appearances, And therefore do not realize my awakening.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.105.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱིས་པ་མེད་པས་རྨོངས་པ་དག ། ཆོས་རྣམས་གསོག་ཏུ་མི་ཤེས་ཏེ། །ཆོས་རྣམས་མཚན་ཉིད་གཅིག་པ་ལ། །དེ་དག་ཐ་དད་འབྱེད་པར་བྱེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-162"/>“Childish people deluded about nonexistence Do not understand that phenomena are hollow, And thus they establish distinctions Regarding phenomena that are of a single character.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.105.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་གིས་ཆོས་འདི་ཤེས་པ་ནི། །ངོ་བོ་ཉིད་ཀྱིས་མཚན་མེད་པ། །སོར་མོ་ལྔ་ཡི་ལག་པ་བཞིན། །དེ་དག་བྱང་ཆུབ་རྙེད་མི་དཀའ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-163"/>“For those who understand these phenomena, Devoid of phenomenal appearance by nature, Just as a hand consists of five fingers, It will not be difficult to attain awakening.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.105.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱང་ཆུབ་གང་དང་ཡང་མི་རིང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-165"/>“Awakening is far from no one.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.105.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་དང་ཡང་ནི་ཉེ་བ་མེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Awakening is close to no one.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.105.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྟོག་དང་རྣམ་རྟོག་གང་ལྡན་པ། །དེ་དག་བྱང་ཆུབ་རབ་ཏུ་རིང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>But far from awakening are those Immersed in discursive and dichotomous thought.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.105.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱིས་པ་ཕན་ཚུན་སྤྱོད་པ་དག །གཅིག་ལ་གཅིག་ནི་སྨོད་བྱེད་པ། །འདི་ནི་ཚུལ་ཁྲིམས་ལྡན་མ་ཡིན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-166"/>“Since childish people denigrate each other When they get involved with one another, They lack self-discipline.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.105.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཚུལ་ཁྲིམས་མི་ལྡན་འདི་མི་སྲུན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Those who lack self-discipline are not tamed.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.105.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཆོས་རྣམས་རྨི་ལམ་ལྟ་བུ་སྟེ། །འདུས་བྱས་ཐམས་ཅད་ཡང་དག་མིན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-167"/>“Phenomena are like dreams And all conditioned things are unreal.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.105.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྒྱུ་མ་བཞིན་དུ་སྐྱེ་མཐོང་ནས། །མཁས་པ་སྙིང་པོར་མི་འཛིན་ཏོ། །བདེན་པར་འདི་ལ་ཚུལ་ཁྲིམས་མེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Considering arising as an illusion, The wise do not grasp them as something essential.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.105.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཚུལ་ཁྲིམས་མི་ལྡན་བདེན་པར་མེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-168"/>“In truth, they have no discipline, And yet they truly have no lack of discipline.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.105.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཆོས་རྣམས་བརྟེན་ཏེ་བྱུང་བས་ན། །འདི་ལ་བདག་ནི་ཡོད་མ་ཡིན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Since phenomena are dependently arisen, They do not have a self.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.105.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བསྐལ་པ་བྱེ་བ་སྟོང་དག་ཏུ། །སྙོམ་ལས་མེད་པར་སྦྱིན་པ་བྱིན། །ཚུལ་ཁྲིམས་དག་ནི་མཆོག་བསྲུངས་ཀྱང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-169"/>“Throughout a million eons, The Guide tirelessly practiced generosity And maintained supreme and stainless discipline.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.105.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདྲེན་པས་ང་ནི་ལུང་མ་བསྟན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Yet he never proclaimed a self.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.105.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་ཚེ་ང་ནི་འདུ་ཤེས་བྲལ། །སྦྱིན་པའི་འདུ་ཤེས་མ་ལུས་དང་། །རྣམ་པར་རྟོག་པ་ཀུན་སྤངས་པ། །དེ་ཚེ་བྱང་ཆུབ་ལུང་བསྟན་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-170"/>“It is taught that awakening has been attained When one is free from any conception about oneself, And when all conceptions of generosity, As well as discursive thought, have been abandoned.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.106.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྦྱིན་པས་ལོངས་སྤྱོད་འགྱུར་བར་བསྟན། །ཚུལ་ཁྲིམས་<tei:ref folio="F.106.a"/>ཀྱིས་ནི་མཐོ་རིས་བསྟན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-171"/>“It is taught that through generosity one will become resourceful, And through discipline one will be reborn in the higher realms.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.106.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་ན་ཆུང་ཟད་མི་དམིགས་པ། །དེ་ནི་བྱང་ཆུབ་བླ་མེད་དོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>However, not observing the slightest thing anywhere Is the unsurpassable awakening.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.106.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱིས་པ་དམིགས་པར་གནས་པ་དག །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-172"/>“Childish people fixate on their perceptions:</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.106.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མི་སྐྱེ་འདུས་མ་བྱས་པ་ཡི། །བཟོད་པ་བདག་གིས་ཐོབ་པོ་ཞེས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>‘I have attained the acceptance that phenomena Do not arise and are not conditioned.’</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.106.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མི་མཁས་པ་དག་རྟོག་པར་བྱེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Such is the way unskilled people think.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.106.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཆོས་རྣམས་སྐྱེ་བ་མེད་པ་ལ། །གང་དག་སྐྱེ་བར་སེམས་པ་ནི། །བསྐལ་པ་བྱེ་བ་སྟོང་དུ་ཡང་། །དེ་ཡི་བཟོད་པ་རྙེད་པར་དཀའ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-173"/>“Yet, even if they strive for ten million eons, This acceptance is difficult to attain For those who believe that those phenomena, Devoid of arising, do arise.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.106.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཆོས་རྣམས་མིང་གིས་ལུང་བསྟན་ཏེ། །ཆོས་རྣམས་ལ་ནི་བྱེད་པ་མེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-174"/>“Phenomena are designated with names, But phenomena are beyond production.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.106.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྩ་བ་མེད་ཅིང་གནས་མེད་དེ། །ཐམས་ཅད་ནམ་མཁའི་མཚན་ཉིད་དོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Devoid of root and foundation, They all have the character of space.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.106.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སངས་རྒྱས་བྱེ་བ་མང་པོ་ཡིས། །འདོད་ཆགས་ཞེ་སྡང་སྤང་བའི་ཕྱིར། །ཆོས་མཆོག་དག་ཀྱང་བཤད་མོད་ཀྱི། །ཆོས་རྣམས་ཟད་པའང་ཡོང་མེད་དོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-175"/>“Even if many tens of millions of buddhas expounded The supremely pure teaching On abandoning attachment and hatred, The teachings would still never come to an end.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.106.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གལ་ཏེ་ཆོས་དེ་ཡང་དག་ན། །ཐམས་ཅད་ཡང་དག་ཟད་པར་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-177"/>“If these phenomena were real, They could all really come to an end.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.106.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་ཕྱིར་དེ་དག་ཡང་དག་མིན། །དེ་བས་མཐའ་ནི་མི་རྙེད་དོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>But since they are not real, An endpoint is never found.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.106.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདོད་ཆགས་ཞེ་སྡང་མཐའ་ཡས་ཏེ། །གཏི་མུག་གི་ནི་མཐའ་ཡང་མེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-178"/>“Endless are attachment and hatred, And so too is delusion.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.106.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་དག་གི་ནི་མཐའ་མེད་པ། །དེ་དག་གི་ནི་རྩ་བ་མེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Devoid of a root are those things That are devoid of an end.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.106.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ས་བོན་མྱུ་གུ་མེད་ན་ནི། །འདབ་མ་འབྲས་བུ་ག་ལ་འབྱུང་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-180"/>“If there are neither seeds nor sprouts, How can leaves and fruits originate?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.106.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདབ་མ་མེད་པ་གང་ཡིན་པ། །དེ་ལ་མེ་ཏོག་ཡོད་མ་ཡིན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>In the same way, that which has no leaves, Has no flowers.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.106.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཆོས་རྣམས་སྐྱེ་བ་མེད་པ་ལ། །སེམས་ཅན་ས་བོན་མི་རྙེད་དོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-181"/>“Within the non-arising of phenomena, The seeds of beings cannot be found.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.106.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སེམས་ཅན་ས་བོན་མེད་པའི་ཕྱིར། །སྐྱེ་མེད་མྱ་ངན་འདའ་བ་མེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Since there are no seeds of beings, There is no arising and no nirvāṇa.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.106.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཇི་ལྟར་བུད་མེད་མོ་ཤམ་དག །དེ་ལ་བུ་ནི་ཡོད་མ་ཡིན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-182"/>“Barren women Have no children.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.106.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ལ་བུ་ནི་ཡོད་མིན་ན། །བུ་ཡི་མྱ་ངན་བྱེད་པ་མེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Thus, if they have no children, They are free from sorrow regarding those children!</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.106.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཆོས་རྣམས་ཐམས་ཅད་མ་སྐྱེས་པར། །དེ་ལྟར་རིག་ཅིང་མཐོང་ནས་ནི། །འཁོར་བ་དག་ཏུ་འཁོར་བ་ན། །སྡུག་བསྔལ་འཇིགས་པ་དེ་ལ་མེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-183"/>“Likewise, those wandering in saṃsāra Who realize and understand That all phenomena are devoid of arising Are free from fear of suffering.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.106.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱིས་པ་མེད་པས་རྨོངས་པ་དག །རྨོངས་པས་ཆོས་ཉིད་མི་ཤེས་ཏེ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-184"/>“Childish people are deluded by nonexistence And therefore do not recognize the nature of phenomena.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.106.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ནམ་མཁའ་ཁུར་དུ་ཐོགས་བྱས་ཏེ། །མི་མཁས་པ་དག་སྐྱོ་བར་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Encumbered by space as if it were a burden, Weary will be those who are unwise!</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.106.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མེད་ཅིང་མཐའ་ཡང་མེད་པ་དང་། །གྲངས་མེད་པ་དང་ཚད་མེད་པར། །གང་གིས་ཆོས་འདི་ཤེས་པ་ནི། །དེ་དག་ལ་ནི་སྐྱོ་བ་མེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-185"/>“But free from sorrow Are those who know phenomena As nonexistent, endless, Innumerable, and measureless.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.106.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཇི་ལྟར་ཐོག་མའི་མཐའ་དག་ནི། །མེད་པ་དག་ཏུ་ངས་བསྟན་པ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-186"/>“I have taught that all limits in the sense of a beginning Or an ending are nonexistent.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.106.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་བཞིན་ཕྱི་མའི་མཐའ་དག་དང་། །དབུས་ཀྱང་མཚན་ཉིད་གཅིག་པ་ཡིན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Likewise, all limits, such as an ending Or a middle, are of a single character.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.106.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྟོག་པའི་མཐའ་ནི་མཐའ་མེད་དེ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-187"/>“Limits resulting from conceptual thought are devoid of limit.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.106.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མཐའ་ནི་གསོབ་དང་མེད་པ་ཡིན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Thus, limits are fictitious and nonexistent.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.106.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དོན་རྣམས་དེ་ལྟར་ཤེས་བྱས་ན། །དངོས་པོ་གཉིས་སུ་མི་འགྱུར་རོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>If all things have been understood in this way, There will never be two separate entities. </seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.106.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>
                    <tei:ref folio="F.106.b"/>མཐའ་ནི་ནམ་མཁའི་མཚན་ཉིད་དེ། །སེམས་ཅན་མཐའ་ནི་བསམ་མི་ཁྱབ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-188"/>“Because limits have the character of space, The limits of beings are inconceivable.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.106.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མཐའ་ནི་མིག་ཡོར་ལྟ་བུ་སྟེ། །དེ་བས་ཡེ་ཤེས་ཤེས་མི་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Because limits are like sensory distortions, One does not realize wisdom.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.106.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྣམ་པར་རྟོག་ལ་སྤྱོད་པ་ན། །སྡིག་པ་ཇི་ལྟར་ཟད་པར་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-189"/>“If one engages in discursive thought, How will negativity ever end?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.106.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ནམ་ཞིག་སངས་རྒྱས་བདག་འགྱུར་ཞེས། །སེམས་ནི་དེ་ལྟར་འཇུག་པར་འགྱུར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>One will likewise fancy, ‘One day I will become a buddha.’</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.106.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སངས་རྒྱས་དག་ནི་མ་སྐྱེས་པས། །དེ་དག་འབྱུང་བ་གང་ཡང་མེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-190"/>“Since buddhas are unborn, For them there is no arising.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.106.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འབྱུང་བ་མེད་པའི་ཆོས་རྣམས་ལ། །བྱིས་པ་རྣམས་ནི་འབྱུང་བར་འདོད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>And yet, childish people accept phenomena That do not arise, as arising.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.106.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ནམ་མཁའ་ལ་ནི་རྟེན་པ་དང་། །གནས་དང་གནས་པར་བྱ་མི་ནུས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-191"/>“One cannot take space as a foundation, Or abide in, or settle in space.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.106.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ནམ་མཁའ་ལ་ནི་གནས་མེད་དེ། །ཐོགས་པ་མེད་ཅིང་དངོས་པོ་མེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Space is without abiding, Obstruction, or substance.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.106.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཇི་ལྟར་ནམ་མཁའ་དངོས་མེད་པ། །དེ་ལྟར་བྱང་ཆུབ་ཤེས་པར་བྱོས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-192"/>“Just as space is not a substantial thing, So too should we understand awakening.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.106.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཇི་ལྟར་བྱང་ཆུབ་ཤེས་བྱ་བ། །དེ་ལྟར་སེམས་ཅན་ཤེས་པར་བྱོས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Just as we should understand awakening, So too should we understand the world.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.106.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ནམ་མཁའི་དབྱིངས་དང་བྱང་ཆུབ་དང་། །སེམས་ཅན་ཁམས་རྣམས་དེ་དག་མཉམ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-193"/>“Identical are the expanse of space, Awakening, and the constitutions of beings.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.106.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་གིས་དེ་དག་མཉམ་ཤེས་པ། །དེ་ཡིས་བྱང་ཆུབ་རྙེད་མི་དཀའ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>For those who know these to be equal, Awakening is easy to attain.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.106.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་དག་བྱང་ཆུབ་མི་བརྩོན་ཞིང་། །ཚུལ་བཞིན་དུ་ཡང་སེམས་མི་བྱེད། །ཆོས་རྣམས་ཚོལ་བར་མི་བྱེད་པ། །དེ་ཡིས་བྱང་ཆུབ་རྙེད་མི་དཀའ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-194"/>“For those who neither strive for awakening, Nor direct their mind in the appropriate way, Nor analyze phenomena, Awakening is easy to attain.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.106.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱང་ཆུབ་བཙལ་དུ་མེད་པ་སྟེ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-195"/>“Awakening cannot be analyzed.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.106.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཇི་ལྟར་ཚོལ་བ་ཐམས་ཅད་ལྟར། །སེམས་ཀྱི་ཐོབ་པ་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་ནི། །བླ་མེད་བྱང་ཆུབ་རྟོགས་མི་ནུས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>However much one analyzes, One can never realize unsurpassable awakening Through the achievements of mind.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.106.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྦྱིན་པས་བྱང་ཆུབ་ཐོབ་སྙམ་ནས། །སྦྱིན་པའི་སེམས་པ་གང་སེམས་པ། །བྱང་ཆུབ་ཐོབ་པ་གང་ཡང་མེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-196"/>“When one thinks that awakening is attained through generosity, There is no attainment of awakening at all, Whether there is a generous intention or any other intention.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.106.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མ་ཐོབ་པ་ནི་བྱང་ཆུབ་མཆོག །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Nonattainment is the supreme awakening!</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.106.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཚུལ་ཁྲིམས་སེམས་ལ་གང་ཆགས་དང་། །བརྩོན་འགྲུས་ཡང་དག་ཉིད་རྟོག་ཅིང་། །གང་དག་འདུ་ཤེས་འཇུག་པར་བྱེད། །ང་ཡི་བསྟན་ལ་དེ་མི་སྦྱོར། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-197"/>“Those who are fixated on having a disciplined mind, Who conceive of diligence as truth itself And become engaged in conceptions, Do not practice my teaching.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.106.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཆོས་ཀུན་སྦྱོར་བ་མེད་པ་ལ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Without attachments to any phenomena.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.106.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ང་ཡིས་སྦྱོར་བ་ཉེ་བསྟན་ཏེ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-198"/>“I have given instructions about the practice</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.106.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཆུང་ཟད་རྩོམ་པ་གང་མེད་པ། །དེ་ནི་སྦྱོར་བ་བླ་མེད་པའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>That which is free from the slightest undertaking Is the unsurpassable practice.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.106.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཆོས་འདི་རྣམས་ནི་ཟག་པ་མེད། །ཆོས་འདི་ཟག་དང་བཅས་པ་ཞེས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>‘These phenomena are undefiled’ Or ‘Those phenomena are defiled.’</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.106.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་ལ་འདུ་ཤེས་དེ་ཡོད་པ། །དེ་ཡི་སེམས་ནི་ཚུལ་བཞིན་མིན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-199"/>“Mistaken are the thoughts Of those who think:</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.106.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་གིས་ཆོས་རྣམས་བསམ་ཡས་པ། །ནམ་མཁའ་འདྲ་བ་མཐོང་བ་དང་། །མ་བཅིངས་པ་དང་མ་གྲོལ་བ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Who regard phenomena as inconceivable, As being similar to space, And who are neither bound nor liberated.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.106.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ཡི་ཤེས་རབ་བླ་ན་མེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-200"/>“But unsurpassed is the insight of those</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.107.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་ཞིག་ཚུལ་ཁྲིམས་ལྡན་པར་རྟོག །ཚུལ་ཁྲིམས་མི་ལྡན་རྣམ་རྟོག་པ། །གཉིས་ནི་ཚུལ་ཁྲིམས་ངན་པར་བཤད། །གཉིས་སུ་མེད་པ་ཚུལ་<tei:ref folio="F.107.a"/>ཁྲིམས་མཆོག །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-201"/>“Conceiving of anyone as having discipline Or lacking discipline Are both explained as inferior discipline. That which is nondual is supreme discipline.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.107.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཆོས་རྣམས་ཐ་དད་བྱ་བ་མེད། །ཁྱད་པར་མེད་ཅིང་མཚན་མེད་པར། །གང་གིས་མཐོང་ཞིང་ཤེས་པ་དག །དེ་དག་ང་ཡི་བསྟན་པ་འཛིན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-202"/>“Thus, those who perceive and understand phenomena As indistinguishable, Without differences or defining characteristics, Uphold my teaching.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.107.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་གིས་སེམས་ནི་ནམ་མཁའ་ལྟར། །མ་ཆགས་བཞིན་དུ་ཕྱོགས་སུ་འགྲོ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-203"/>“Those whose minds are like space Proceed in the direction of nonattachment.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.107.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ལྟར་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Likewise,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.107.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡེ་ཤེས་ཆགས་མེད་པ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>free from attachment to wisdom.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.107.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ཡི་དགེ་སྦྱོང་ཡང་དག་ཉིད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>perfect is the virtuous endeavor Of those</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.107.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་གིས་ཆུང་ཟད་མ་བརྟགས་ཤིང་། །ཐམས་ཅད་དུ་ཡང་སེམས་པ་མེད། །སེམས་ཅན་མེད་ཅིང་ཆོས་མེད་པ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>who do not analyze the slightest thing, Without any kind of deliberation And no ideas of beings or phenomena.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.107.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་དག་བྱང་ཆུབ་རྙེད་མི་དཀའ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-204"/>“Awakening is not hard to attain For those</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.107.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདོད་ཆགས་མཐའ་ལ་གང་མི་གནས། །འདོད་ཆགས་དང་ཡང་བྲལ་མ་གྱུར། །འདོད་ཆགས་ལས་ཀྱང་རྒྱལ་མི་བྱེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>who are not confined to the limits of attachment, Yet are also not separating from attachment Or trying to gain victory over attachment.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.107.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནི་བྱང་ཆུབ་མི་དཀོན་ནོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-205"/>“Awakening is not hard to attain For those</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.107.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་དག་བསྐལ་པར་མི་སྐྱོ་ཞིང་། །མཐས་ཀྱང་འཇིག་པར་མི་འགྱུར་ལ། །འཁོར་བས་སྐྲག་པར་མི་འགྱུར་བ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>who never lose courage throughout the eons, And who neither become afraid of limits, Nor terrified of saṃsāra.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.107.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེས་ནི་བྱང་ཆུབ་རྙེད་མི་དཀའ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-206"/>“Awakening is not hard to attain For those</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.107.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་ཚིགས་སུ་བཅད་པ་འདི་དག་གསུངས་ནས་འཇམ་དཔལ་གཞོན་ནུར་གྱུར་པ་ལ་འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་བཀའ་སྩལ་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-207"/>After the Blessed One had uttered these verses, he said to Youthful Mañjuśrī,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.107.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་གང་ཆོས་ཀྱི་རྣམ་གྲངས་འདི་ལ་མོས་པར་བྱེད། ཐེ་ཙོམ་དུ་མི་བྱེད། ནེམ་ནུར་དུ་མི་བྱེད། ལུང་སྦྱིན་པར་བྱེད། འཛིན་པར་བྱེད། ཀློག་པར་བྱེད། ཀུན་ཆུབ་པར་བྱེད། གཞན་ལ་ཡང་རྒྱ་ཆེར་ཡང་དག་པར་སྟོན་པ་དེའི་ཕན་ཡོན་བསྔགས་པ་ཉི་ཤུ་ཡོད་པར་རེ་བར་བྱའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Mañjuśrī, twenty laudable qualities will certainly be possessed by those who have faith in this Dharma discourse, do not doubt it, do not question it, but transmit it, memorize it, recite it, accomplish it, and also correctly teach it in detail to others.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.107.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཉི་ཤུ་གང་ཞེ་ན། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-329"/>“What are these twenty qualities?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.107.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལྷས་བསྲུངས་པར་འགྱུར། ཀླུས་བསྲུངས་པར་འགྱུར། གནོད་སྦྱིན་གྱིས་བསྲུངས་པར་འགྱུར། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>(1) They will be protected by the gods, (2) the nāgas, (3) and the yakṣas.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.107.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སེམས་གཡེངས་པར་མི་འགྱུར། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>(4) Their minds will remain undistracted.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.107.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཚེ་བརྗེས་ནས་ཀྱང་ཚེ་རབས་དྲན་པར་འགྱུར། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>(5) They will recall their former lives after they are reborn.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.107.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མངོན་པར་ཤེས་པ་ལྔ་ཐོབ་པར་འགྱུར། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>(6) They will obtain the five extrasensory powers.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.107.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཚེ་བརྗེས་མ་ཐག་ཏུ་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་བྱམས་པ་མཐོང་བར་འགྱུར། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>(7) They will immediately see the bodhisattva Maitreya when they die.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.107.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་སྟེ་ཆོས་ཀྱི་རྣམ་གྲངས་འདི་སེམས་མི་གཡེང་བར་ཡིད་ལ་བྱེད་ཅིང་གཉིད་ཀྱི་སྙོམ་པ་སེལ་ན། དེའི་རྨི་ལམ་དུ་སངས་རྒྱས་མཐོང་བར་འགྱུར་ཏེ། བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་མཐོང་བ་ཡང་རེ་བར་བྱའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>(8) If they thus keep this Dharma discourse in mind without any distraction and also eliminate indolence, they should expect to see the Buddha and bodhisattvas in their dreams.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.107.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ཆོས་ཀྱི་རྣམ་གྲངས་འདི་ལ་མོས་ན་རྗེས་སུ་འཐུན་པའི་ཆོས་རྣམས་ལ་བཟོད་པ་རེ་བར་བྱའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>(9) If they have faith in this Dharma discourse, they should expect to accept that phenomena are in complete harmony with it.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.107.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཆོས་ཀྱི་རྣམ་གྲངས་འདི་སེམས་ན་ཚེ་འདི་ཉིད་ལ་གནོད་སེམས་མེད་པར་རེ་བར་བྱའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>(10) If they contemplate this Dharma discourse, they should expect to be free from malicious thoughts in this very life.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.107.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དུག་མྱུར་བའི་ནང་ན་འདུག་ན་ཡང་ཆོས་ཀྱི་རྣམ་གྲངས་འདི་ཡིད་ལ་བྱེད་ན་འཇིགས་པ་<tei:ref folio="F.107.b"/>མེད་པར་རེ་བར་བྱའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>(11) Even if they come into contact with swift-acting venom, they should expect to be free from fear, provided that they keep this Dharma discourse in mind.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.107.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སླར་རྒོལ་བ་ཚར་གཅོད་པར་རེ་བར་བྱའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>(12) Furthermore, they should expect to put an end to all opposition. </seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.107.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཀུན་ཏུ་སྣང་བའི་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་ཀྱང་ཐོབ་པར་རེ་བར་བྱའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>(13) They should also expect to attain the all-illuminating absorption.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.107.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཆོས་ཀྱི་རྣམ་གྲངས་འདི་རྟོགས་པར་བྱེད་པའི་ཚེ་ལས་ཀྱི་སྒྲིབ་པ་ཐམས་ཅད་བྱང་བར་རེ་བར་བྱའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>(14) Once they directly understand this Dharma discourse, they should expect to purify all karmic obscurations.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.107.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཆོས་ཀྱི་རྣམ་གྲངས་འདི་འཆད་པ་ན་ཡང་ཆོས་ཀྱི་སྒོ་བརྒྱ་སྟོང་དུ་མ་ཐོབ་པར་རེ་བར་བྱའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>(15) Moreover, if they explain this Dharma discourse, they should expect to gain access to countless Dharma gates.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.107.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱང་ཆུབ་ཀྱི་སེམས་མི་བརྗེད་པ་དང་། མཐའ་ཡས་འཁྱིལ་བའི་གཟུངས་ཐོབ་པར་ཡང་རེ་བར་བྱའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>(16) They will also certainly remember the thought of awakening and possess the dhāraṇī infinite recitation .</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.107.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཆོས་ཀྱི་རྣམ་གྲངས་འདི་ཡིད་ལ་བྱེད་པ་ན་ཡང་བདུད་ཀྱིས་བསྐོར་བ་མེད་པར་རེ་བར་བྱའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>(17) Furthermore, if they keep in mind this Dharma discourse, they will certainly not be encircled by māras.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.107.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སངས་རྒྱས་མངོན་དུ་བཞུགས་པར་ཡང་སྐྱེ་བར་རེ་བར་བྱའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>(18) They will also certainly be reborn in the presence of the Buddha.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.107.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྨོན་ལམ་ཐམས་ཅད་གྲུབ་པར་ཡང་རེ་བར་བྱའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>(19) All their aspirations will certainly be fulfilled.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.107.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྲོག་ཆགས་ཀྱི་རིགས་རྐང་པ་མེད་པ་དང་། རྐང་གཉིས་པ་དང་། རྐང་བཞི་པ་དང་། རྐང་པ་མང་པོ་དུག་ཅན་རྣམས་ལས་བསྲུངས་པར་རེ་བར་བྱའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>(20) They will certainly be protected from all species of venomous beings, including those without legs, and those with two, four, or more legs.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.107.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ལ་མིའི་རྒྱལ་པོ་འཁྲུགས་པའི་འཇིགས་པ་མེད་པར་རེ་བར་བྱ་སྟེ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-208"/>“Hence, they will certainly be free from fears that upset even human kings.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.107.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་གང་སེམས་ལ་ཐེ་ཚོམ་མེད་པ་དང་། ནེམ་ནུར་མེད་པར་ཆོས་ཀྱི་རྣམ་གྲངས་འདི་འཛིན་པར་བྱེད། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Mañjuśrī, Dharma teachers who do not doubt this Dharma discourse, and who do not question it, but memorize it,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.107.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཆང་བར་བྱེད། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>hold it,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.107.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཀློག་པར་བྱེད། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>recite it,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.107.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཀུན་ཆུབ་པར་བྱེད། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>accomplish it,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.107.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཞན་ལ་ཡང་རྒྱས་པར་ཡང་དག་པར་སྟོན་པའི་ཆོས་སྨྲ་བ་དེ་ལ་ཡོན་ཏན་བསྔགས་པ་ཉི་ཤུ་པོ་འདི་རྣམས་ཡོད་པར་རེ་བར་བྱའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>and further, correctly teach it in detail to others will certainly possess these twenty laudable qualities.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.107.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ལ་འཇམ་དཔལ་གཞོན་ནུར་གྱུར་པས་འདི་སྐད་གསོལ་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-209"/>Youthful Mañjuśrī then spoke these words:</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.107.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་འདི་ལྟ་སྟེ། དཔེར་ན་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Blessed One, it may be illustrated as follows:</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.107.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྨན་གྱི་ཤིང་ཐམས་ཅད་ནི་སེམས་ཅན་རྣམས་ཀྱི་ནད་ཐམས་ཅད་ཞི་བར་བགྱིད་དོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>All medicinal trees pacify the diseases of beings.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.107.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་བཞིན་དུ་ཆོས་ཀྱི་རྣམ་གྲངས་འདི་ཡང་ནད་ཐམས་ཅད་རབ་ཏུ་ཞི་བར་བགྱིད་པར་བལྟ་བར་བགྱིའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Likewise, this Dharma discourse should also be regarded as completely pacifying all diseases.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.107.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་བཀའ་སྩལ་པ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>the Blessed One replied.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.107.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་དེ་བཞིན་ནོ། །འཇམ་དཔལ་དེ་དེ་བཞིན་ཏེ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“So it is, Mañjuśrī, so it is,”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.107.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཁྱོད་ཀྱིས་ཚིག་འདི་ལེགས་པར་སྨྲས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Your words are well spoken.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.107.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཆོས་ཀྱི་རྣམ་གྲངས་འདི་ནད་ཐམས་ཅད་རབ་ཏུ་ཞི་བར་བྱེད་པའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>This Dharma discourse completely pacifies all diseases.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.107.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ཅིའི་ཕྱིར་ཞེ་ན། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Why?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.107.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་སྔོན་འདས་པའི་དུས་བསྐལ་པ་གྲངས་མེད་ཅིང་ཤིན་ཏུ་གྲངས་མེད་པ་དེའི་ཚེ་དེའི་དུས་ན། གང་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་དགྲ་བཅོམ་པ་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་སངས་རྒྱས་སེང་གེའི་སྟབས་སུ་འགྲོ་བ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་ཞིག་འཇིག་རྟེན་དུ་བྱུང་བར་གྱུར་ཏེ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Because, Mañjuśrī, countless eons in the past, a tathāgata, a worthy one, a complete and perfect buddha called Walking Like a Lion appeared in the world.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.108.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེས་སྲོག་ཆགས་སྟོང་ཕྲག་དུ་མ་རྣམས་ལ་རྒྱང་རིང་པོ་ནས་<tei:ref folio="F.108.a"/>ཆོས་ཀྱི་རྣམ་གྲངས་འདི་བཤད་དོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>From afar, he expounded this Dharma discourse to many hundreds of thousands of beings.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.108.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེའི་ཚེ་འཁོར་དེར་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་རྡོ་རྗེའི་རྒྱལ་མཚན་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་འདུས་ཏེ་འདུས་པར་གྱུར་ཏོ། །དེས་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་དེ་ལས་ཆོས་ཀྱི་རྣམ་གྲངས་འདི་མཉན་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>At that time, he summoned and included in his retinue a bodhisattva called Victory Banner of the Vajra, who heard this Dharma discourse from that tathāgata.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.108.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེས་སེམས་གཡེང་བ་མེད་པ་དང་། ཐེ་ཙོམ་མེད་པ་དང་། ནེམ་ནུར་མེད་པས་ཆོས་ཀྱི་རྣམ་གྲངས་འདི་ཡོན་ཏན་བསྔགས་པ་དང་བཅས་པར་བཟུང་ཞིང་ཀུན་ཆུབ་པར་བྱས་ཏེ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Thereupon, with a mind free from distraction, doubt, or disbelief, he retained this Dharma discourse with its twenty laudable qualities and became accomplished in it.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.108.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཀུན་ཆུབ་པར་བྱས་ནས་ཀྱང་མོས་པའི་མཐུ་དང་ལྡན་པར་གྱུར་ཏེ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He came to possess the power of faith.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.108.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གྲོང་དང་གྲོང་ཁྱེར་དང་། ལྗོངས་དང་། ཡུལ་དང་ཡུལ་འཁོར་དང་། ཕོ་བྲང་འཁོར་དུ་འོངས་ནས་བདག་ནི་སྨན་པའོ། །བདག་ནི་སྨན་པའོ་ཞེས་བདག་ཉིད་ཁས་འཆེའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He traveled to towns, villages, valleys, lands, provinces, and royal palaces where he proclaimed himself as a healer.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.108.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་དེ་མ་ཐག་ཏུ་སྲོག་ཆགས་ནད་སྣ་ཚོགས་ཀྱིས་གཟིར་བ་སྟོང་ཕྲག་དུ་མ་སྲོག་གི་སྐྱབས་ཀྱི་ཕྱིར་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་རྡོ་རྗེའི་རྒྱལ་མཚན་ག་ལ་བ་དེར་ལྷགས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Thereafter, thousands of beings tormented by various diseases swiftly arrived where the bodhisattva Victory Banner of the Vajra was staying so that he could save their lives.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.108.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་རྡོ་རྗེའི་རྒྱལ་མཚན་མོས་པའི་མཐུ་ལ་གནས་པའི་སེམས་ཀྱིས་སེམས་ཅན་དེ་དག་ལ་ཆོས་ཀྱི་གཞུང་འདིས་བྲིམས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The bodhisattva, with a mind abiding in the power of faith, offered them this Dharma scripture.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.108.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཆོས་ཀྱི་རྣམ་གྲངས་འདི་ལས་གང་རིག་སྔགས་འབྱུང་བ་དེ་དག་གིས་ཀྱང་བསྲུངས་པ་དང་། བསྐྱབས་པ་དང་། ཡོངས་སུ་བཟུང་བར་བྱས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The mantra syllables of knowledge that arose from this Dharma discourse offered them protection, salvation, and assistance.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.108.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་དེ་ལ་རིག་སྔགས་ཀྱི་ཚིག་དེ་དག་ཀྱང་གང་ཞེ་ན། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-211"/>“Mañjuśrī, what is the sounding of this particular mantra of knowledge?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.108.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཏད་ཡ་ཐཱ། ཨ་ལ་ཏ། བི་ཏཱ་ལ། བི་བྷྲི་ན། ཨ་ཏིརྠ། ཨ་བྷྲི་ད། ཨ་ནུ་ཌ། བི་བྲ་མྷ། ན་ཧི་ཁ་ག་རུ་ང་། མཱ་ཡཱ་སུ་ཁ། ཨཱ་ནན་ད། ཛཱ་ལ་ད། ན་ད་མི་ཏྲ། ཨ་མི་ཏྲ། ཛོ་ཏྲ་ཧི་ཏ། སརྦ་ད་ཏྲ་ལ། ཨྃ་ག་མྃ་ག་ཨརཐ་ཡུ་ཏ། ས་བྲཱ་མཱ་ཨི་ཤ །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>tadyathā alata vitāla vibhrina atirtha abhrida anuḍa vibramha nahikhagarunga māyāsukha ānanda jālada nadamitra amitra jotrahita sarvadatrala aṃgamaṃga arthayuta sabrāmāyiśa</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.108.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རིག་སྔགས་ཀྱི་ཚིག་འདི་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་སེམས་ཅན་དེ་དག་བསྲུང་བ་བྱས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-213"/>“The utterance of this mantra of knowledge protected those beings.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.108.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེས་གལ་ཏེ་གདུག་པས་ཟོས་པའམ། གལ་ཏེ་མི་མ་ཡིན་པས་གཙེས་པའམ། སྲོག་ཆགས་ཀྱི་རིགས་དུག་ཅན་གང་ཡང་རུང་བ་འགའ་ཞིག་གིས་ཟིན་པའམ་གལ་ཏེ་ནད་སྐེམ་པ་དང་། མཛེ་བྱུང་བའམ། གལ་ཏེ་རླུང་དང་། མཁྲིས་པ་དང་། བད་ཀན་དང་འདུས་པའི་ནད་ཀྱིས་བཏབ་པ། ནད་སྣ་ཚོགས་ཀྱིས་རབ་ཏུ་གཟིར་བའི་སེམས་ཅན་དེ་དག་ནད་དེ་དང་དེ་དག་ལས་རབ་ཏུ་ཐར་བར་བྱས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>On account of this, beings intensely tormented by various diseases were fully freed from all their afflictions, whether they had ingested poison, or were harmed by non-humans, possessed by any noxious type of creatures, consumed by a disease, afflicted by leprosy, or struck by a sickness related to wind, bile, or phlegm.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.108.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་དེ་ལྟར་ན་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་རྡོ་རྗེའི་རྒྱལ་མཚན་གྱིས་ཆོས་ཀྱི་རྣམ་གྲངས་འདི་ལ་གནས་<tei:ref folio="F.108.b"/>ནས་སེམས་ཅན་དེ་རྣམས་ནད་ལས་རབ་ཏུ་ཐར་བར་བྱས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Thus, Mañjuśrī, the bodhisattva Victory Banner of the Vajra, who abided by this Dharma discourse, fully freed those beings from disease.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.108.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་ཁྱོད་ཇི་སྙམ་དུ་སེམས། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>What do you think, Mañjuśrī?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.108.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེའི་ཚེ་དེའི་དུས་ན་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་རྡོ་རྗེའི་རྒྱལ་མཚན་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་དེ་གཞན་ཡིན་པ་སྙམ་དུ་སེམས་ན་དེ་དེ་ལྟར་མི་བལྟའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>If you think I was somebody other than the bodhisattva called Victory Banner of the Vajra at that time, in that life, you should abandon that view.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.108.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ཅིའི་ཕྱིར་ཞེ་ན། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Why?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.108.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེའི་ཚེ་དེའི་དུས་ན་ང་ཉིད་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་རྡོ་རྗེའི་རྒྱལ་མཚན་ཞེས་བྱ་བར་གྱུར་ཏེ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Because at that time, in that life, I myself was the bodhisattva called Victory Banner of the Vajra.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.108.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ངས་ཆོས་ཀྱི་རྣམ་གྲངས་འདི་ལ་མོས་ནས་སེམས་ཅན་དེ་སྙེད་ཀྱི་དོན་བྱས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>I had faith in this Dharma discourse and acted for the sake of those very beings.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.108.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་རྣམ་གྲངས་དེས་ཀྱང་ཁྱོད་ཀྱིས་འདི་ལྟར་རིག་པར་བྱ་སྟེ། སྨན་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱི་ཁ་བ་ཇི་ལྟ་བ་དེ་བཞིན་དུ་ཆོས་ཀྱི་རྣམ་གྲངས་འདི་ལ་བལྟ་བར་བྱའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>According to this discourse, Mañjuśrī, you should understand it in this way: regard this Dharma discourse as the source of all medicines.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.108.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་གྱིས་གསོལ་པ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>asked Mañjuśrī,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.108.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་རིག་སྔགས་ཀྱི་ཚིག་འདི་རྣམས་འཛིན་ཅིང་འཆང་བ་དང་། ཀུན་ཆུབ་པར་བགྱིད་པས་ཇི་ལྟ་བུར་ཀུན་ཏུ་སྤྱད་པར་བགྱི། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-214"/>“Blessed One,” “how should bodhisattvas who memorize, keep, and realize the words of this mantra of knowledge put it into practice?”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.108.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་བཀའ་སྩལ་པ། འཇམ་དཔལ་རིག་སྔགས་འདི་དག་འདོན་པའི་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔས་གཙང་སྦྲ་བྱ་བ་དང་། ཤ་མི་བཟའ་བར་ཀུན་ཏུ་སྤྱད་པར་བྱའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The Blessed One answered, “Mañjuśrī, bodhisattvas who recite this mantra of knowledge should practice cleanliness and should not eat meat.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.108.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེས་རྐང་པ་གཉིས་ཀྱང་མི་བསྐུའོ། །འདུ་འཛིའི་ནང་ན་གནས་པར་མི་བྱའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They should not massage their feet or engage in social distractions.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.108.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སེམས་ཅན་ཐམས་ཅད་ལ་ཡང་ཕྱི་ཕྱིར་ཞིང་བྱམས་པའི་སེམས་སུ་བྱའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They should again and again develop feelings of kindness toward all beings.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.108.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་དག་ལས་འཚེ་བ་འོང་བར་འགྱུར་བ་དེ་དག་ལ་སེམས་གདུག་པར་མི་བྱའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They should not resent those who happen to hurt them.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.108.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཆོས་ཀྱི་རྣམ་གྲངས་འདི་ཡང་གཙང་སྦྲ་མ་ཕྱེད་པས་ཁ་ཏོན་མི་བྱའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Furthermore, they should not chant this Dharma discourse without performing ablutions.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.108.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ས་ཕྱོགས་མི་གཙང་བར་གཞག་པར་མི་བྱའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Neither should they keep it in a filthy place.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.108.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་གྱིས་གསོལ་པ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>said Mañjuśrī.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.108.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་བདག་ནི་འདི་སྙམ་བགྱིད་དེ། ཆོས་ཀྱི་རྣམ་གྲངས་འདི་སྟོན་པའི་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔས་བདག་གི་ལུས་དང་སྲོག་ལ་མི་ལྟ་བར་བགྱིའོ་སྙམ་དུ་སེམས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-216"/>“Blessed One, it seems to me that bodhisattvas who teach this Dharma discourse should even disregard their own body and life,”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.108.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་བཀའ་སྩལ་པ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>replied the Blessed One.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.108.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་དེ་དེ་བཞིན་ནོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“So it is, Mañjuśrī,”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.108.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་དེ་བཞིན་ཏེ། ཁྱོད་ཇི་སྐད་ཟེར་བ་དེ་བཞིན་ནོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“It is just as you have said it is.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.108.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་ཚེ་དང་ལྡན་པ་ཀུན་དགའ་བོ་ལ་བཀའ་སྩལ་པ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-218"/>Then, the Blessed One spoke to the venerable Ānanda:</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.108.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཆོས་ཀྱི་རྣམ་གྲངས་འདི་སྐྱེ་བོ་མང་པོའི་དོན་བྱེད་པར་འགྱུར་གྱིས། ཀུན་དགའ་བོ་ཁྱོད་ཀྱིས་ཟུང་ཤིག །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Because this Dharma discourse will benefit many beings, Ānanda, you should remember it.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.108.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཀུན་དགའ་བོ་སེམས་ཅན་གང་ཆོས་ཀྱི་རྣམ་གྲངས་འདི་ལ་མོས་པ་དེ་དག་གླང་པོའི་རྩལ་དང་། གླང་པོ་ཆེན་པོའི་རྩལ་གྱིས་གནོན་པར་འགྱུར། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Ānanda, beings who yearn for this Dharma discourse will be subdued by the strength of the bull and the strength of the elephant.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.109.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཀུན་དགའ་བོ་གང་ཆོས་ཀྱི་རྣམ་གྲངས་<tei:ref folio="F.109.a"/>འདི་ལ་མོས་པ་དེ་དག་སེང་གེའི་འགྲོས་དང་། ཁྱུ་མཆོག་གི་འགྲོས་སུ་འགྲོ་བར་འགྱུར་རོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Ānanda, those who arouse faith in this Dharma discourse will stride like a lion, like a bull.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.109.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཀུན་དགའ་བོ་ཆོས་ཀྱི་རྣམ་གྲངས་འདི་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་རྣམས་རབ་ཏུ་དགའ་བ་དང་། བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་འབྱུང་བར་བྱེད་པར་འགྱུར་རོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Ānanda, this Dharma discourse delights bodhisattvas and makes them appear.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.109.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ང་འདས་པའི་ཕྱི་ན་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའི་ལག་ཏུ་འོང་བར་འགྱུར་རོ། །བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའི་གླེགས་བམ་དུ་འོང་བ་དང་། བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའི་སྒྲོམ་དུ་འོང་བར་འགྱུར་རོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>After I have passed away, it will come into the hands of bodhisattvas, into their scriptures and repositories.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.109.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་གདོལ་པ་རྣམས་ཀྱི་ལག་ཏུ་འོང་བར་མི་འགྱུར། གླེགས་བམ་དུ་འོང་བ་དང་། སྒྲོམ་དུ་འོང་བར་མི་འགྱུར་རོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>It will not come into the hands, scriptures, or repositories of outcast bodhisattvas.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.109.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཚེ་དང་ལྡན་པ་ཀུན་དགའ་བོས་འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་གསོལ་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>promised the venerable Ānanda.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.109.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཆོས་ཀྱི་རྣམ་གྲངས་འདི་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པས་ཇི་སྐད་བཤད་པ་བཞིན་དུ་བདག་གིས་གཟུང་ངོ་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-219"/>“Blessed One, I will hold this Dharma discourse in precisely the way it was explained by the Tathāgata,”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.109.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་བཀའ་སྩལ་པ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>replied the Blessed One.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.109.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཀུན་དགའ་བོ་ཆོས་ཀྱི་རྣམ་གྲངས་འདི་ཇི་ལྟར་ཟིན་པ་བཞིན་དུ་གང་དག་ལ་བྱིན་པའི་སེམས་ཅན་དེ་དག་ལ་ཁྱོད་སྟོན་པའི་བྱ་བ་བྱེད་པ་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Ānanda,” “It is excellent that you will commit yourself to teaching this Dharma discourse, just as you have received it, to the beings for whom it was given.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.109.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལེགས་སོ་ལེགས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Excellent,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.109.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་དེ་སྐད་ཅེས་བཀའ་སྩལ་པ་དང་། ཚེ་དང་ལྡན་པ་ཀུན་དགའ་བོ་དང་། ཚེ་དང་ལྡན་པ་ཤཱ་རིའི་བུ་དང་། འཇམ་དཔལ་གཞོན་ནུར་གྱུར་པ་དང་། ལྷ་དང་། མི་དང་། ལྷ་མ་ཡིན་དང་། དྲི་ཟར་བཅས་པའི་འཇིག་རྟེན་རྣམས་ཡིད་དགའ་སྟེབཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་བཀའ་སྩལ་པ་ལ་མངོན་པར་བསྟོད་དོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-221"/>After the Blessed One had uttered these words, the venerable Ānanda, the venerable Śāriputra, Youthful Mañjuśrī, and the worlds of the gods, humans, demigods, and gandharvas rejoiced and praised the Blessed One’s words.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.109.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གླང་པོའི་རྩལ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་ཐེག་པ་ཆེན་པོའི་མདོ་རྫོགས་སོ།། །།</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-062-007-222"/>This completes the Great Vehicle sūtra “ The Strength of the Elephant .”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
</body>
</tmx>