<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tmx xmlns="http://www.lisa.org/tmx14" xmlns:eft="http://read.84000.co/ns/1.0" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" version="1.4b">
<header creationtool="InterText" creationtoolversion="1.0" datatype="PlainText" segtype="block" adminlang="en-us" srclang="bo" o-tmf="XML aligned text" eft:text-id="UT22084-076-011" eft:text-version="1.0.14 2021"/>
<body>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.220.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཕགས་པ་གླང་རུ་ལུང་བསྟན་པ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་ཐེག་པ་ཆེན་པོའི་མདོ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The Noble Great Vehicle Sūtra The Prophecy on Mount Gośṛṅga</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.220.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བམ་པོ་གཅིག་གོ། །བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་འཇམ་དཔལ་གཞོན་ནུར་གྱུར་པ་ལ་ཕྱག་འཚལ་ལོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Homage to the blessed Mañjuśrī­kumāra­bhūta.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.220.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདི་སྐད་བདག་གིས་ཐོས་པ་དུས་གཅིག་ན། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Thus did I hear at one time.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.220.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལྷའི་ཡང་ལྷ་སངས་རྒྱས་ཤཱཀྱ་ཐུབ་པ་བསྐལ་པ་གྲངས་མེད་པ་གསུམ་ནས་བསོད་ནམས་ཀྱི་ཚོགས་ཀྱི་རྣམ་པར་སྨིན་པས་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་སངས་རྒྱས་བརྙེས་ཏེ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The Buddha Śākyamuni, the god of gods who had attained perfect awakening through the ripening of merit accumulated over three countless eons and then</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.221.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཛམ་བུའི་གླིང་གི་ལྗོངས་ཀྱི་ཡུལ་གཞན་<tei:ref folio="F.221.a"/>དུ་འདུལ་བའི་སེམས་ཅན་ཡོངས་སུ་སྨིན་པར་མཛད་ནས་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>[The Buddha Śākyamuni, the god of gods who had attained perfect awakening through the ripening of merit accumulated over three countless eons and then] brought disciples throughout the various regions of Jambudvīpa to maturity, </seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.221.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡུལ་ཡངས་པ་ཅན་གྱི་ཕྱོགས་ཐུབ་པ་དྲང་སྲོང་ཆེན་པོའི་གནས་རྒྱལ་པོའི་ཁབ་ན། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>[The Buddha Śākyamuni, the god of gods who had attained perfect awakening through the ripening of merit accumulated over three countless eons and then brought disciples throughout the various regions of Jambudvīpa to maturity, ] was residing in Rājagṛha, at the place of the mighty great sages,<tei:note xml:id="UT22084-076-011-51"/> in the direction of the Vaiśalī region.<tei:note xml:id="UT22084-076-011-52"/>
                </seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.221.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོ་འཕགས་པ་བྱམས་པ་ལ་སོགས་པ་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་དུ་མ་དང་། གནས་བརྟན་ཤཱ་རིའི་བུ་དང་། མཽད་གལ་གྱི་བུ་ལ་སོགས་པ་ཉན་ཐོས་ཆེན་པོ་སྟོང་ཉིས་བརྒྱ་ལྔ་བཅུ་དང་། ཚངས་པ་དང་། བརྒྱ་བྱིན་ལ་སོགས་པ་ལྷ་དུ་མ་དང་། ལྷའི་རྒྱལ་པོ་རྣམ་ཐོས་ཀྱི་བུ་ལ་སོགས་པ་འཇིག་རྟེན་སྐྱོང་བ་དུ་མ་དང་། ཀླུའི་རྒྱལ་པོ་ཆེན་པོ་དུ་མ་དང་། གནོད་སྦྱིན་མཐུ་ཆེན་པོ་མང་པོ་དང་། དྲི་ཟའི་རྒྱལ་པོ་གཙུག་ཕུད་ལྔ་པ་ལ་སོགས་པ་དྲི་ཟ་མང་པོ་དང་། མིའམ་ཅིའི་རྒྱལ་པོ་ཡིད་འོང་ལ་སོགས་པ་མིའམ་ཅི་དུ་མ་དང་། རྒྱལ་པོ་གཟུགས་ཅན་སྙིང་པོ་ལ་སོགས་པ་འཛམ་བུའི་གླིང་གི་མིའི་རྒྱལ་པོ་མང་པོའི་འཁོར་དུ་མ་དང་ཐབས་ཅིག་ཏུ་བཞུགས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He was there together with a great retinue of many bodhisattvas, such as the bodhisattva great being noble Maitreya; one thousand two hundred and fifty great hearers, such as the elders Śāriputra and Maudgalyāyana; many gods such as Brahmā and Śakra; many world protectors such as the divine king Vaiśravaṇa; many great nāga kings; many mighty yakṣas; many gandharvas, such as the gandharva king Pañcaśikha; many kinnaras such as the kinnara king Delightful; and many human kings of the Jambudvīpa continent, such as King Bimbisāra.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.221.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་དེའི་ཚེ་ལྷའི་ཡང་ལྷ་སངས་རྒྱས་ཤཱཀྱ་ཐུབ་པས་ཕྱི་མའི་དུས་ཀྱི་ཡུལ་དགེ་བ་ལ་རྗེས་སུ་དགོངས་ཤིང་མངོན་སུམ་དུ་མཛད་ནས་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-011-53"/>At that moment, the Buddha Śākyamuni, the god of gods, had a premonition and foresaw the future of a land called Virtue,<tei:note xml:id="UT22084-076-011-54"/> and thus</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.221.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཁོར་མང་པོ་ལ་བཀའ་སྩལ་པ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>he said to his vast retinue,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.221.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རིགས་ཀྱི་བུ་བྱང་ཕྱོགས་ལོགས་ན། རི་གླང་རུ་དང་ཉེ་བ་ཆུ་བོ་གོ་མའི་འགྲམ་ན་ཐུབ་པ་དྲང་སྲོང་ཆེན་པོའི་ཕོ་བྲང་མཆོད་རྟེན་གོ་མ་ས་ལ་གན་ད་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་ཞིག་ཡོད་དེ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Noble children, in the north on the shore of River Goma, near Mount Gośṛṅga, is the palace of the mighty great sages—a stūpa called Gomasalaganda.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.221.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེར་གདོན་མི་ཟ་བར་བྱ་དགོས་པའི་ཕྲིན་ལས་ཤིག་ཡོད་པས་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>There are deeds that must, without doubt, be performed there.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.221.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ད་གཤེགས་པའི་དུས་ལ་བབ་བོ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Now the time to travel there has come.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.221.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>།དེ་ནས་དེའི་ཚེ་ལྷའི་ཡང་ལྷ་སངས་རྒྱས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་འཁོར་ཕལ་མོ་ཆེ་དང་ནམ་མཁའ་ལ་འཕགས་ཏེ</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-011-55"/>The Blessed Buddha, the god of gods, together with most of his retinue then rose up into the sky.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.221.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དྲི་ཟའི་རྒྱལ་པོ་གཙུག་ཕུད་ལྔ་པ་ལ་སོགས་པ་དྲི་ཟ་གྲངས་མེད་པ་ནི་མདུན་ན་ལྷའི་རོལ་མོ་སྣ་ཚོགས་བྱེད། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The gandharva king Pañcaśikha and countless other gandharvas played many divine instruments in front,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.221.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མིའམ་ཅིའི་རྒྱལ་པོ་ཡིད་འོང་ལ་སོགས་པ་མིའམ་ཅི་དུ་མ་ནི་སྟེང་ནས་མཆོད་པའི་ལས་བྱེད་ཅིང་། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>and the kinnara king Delightful and many other kinnaras made offerings from above as</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.221.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སངས་རྒྱས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ལ་དབྱངས་དང་ལྷའི་སྐད་ཡིད་དུ་འོང་བས་བསྟོད་བཞིན་དུ་འཁོར་དེ་དག་དང་། མཆོད་པ་དེ་དག་དང་བཅས་ཏེརི་གླང་རུ་ག་ལ་བ་དེར་གཤེགས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>the Blessed Buddha was praised in enchanting tunes and divine voices. In the midst of that retinue and their homage he proceeded to Mount Gośṛṅga.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.221.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཤེགས་ནས་ལྷའི་ཡང་ལྷ་སངས་རྒྱས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་བཞེངས་བཞིན་དུ་ཞལ་བྱང་ཕྱོགས་སུ་མཚོ་ཆེན་པོ་ཡུན་རིང་པོ་ནས་རྒྱ་མཚོ་ལྟར་འདུག་པ་ལ་གཟིགས་ཏེ། <tei:ref folio="F.221.b"/>
                </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Having arrived there, the Blessed Buddha, the god of gods, stood facing north and gazed for a long time at the large ocean-like lake. </seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.221.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྐུ་དྲང་པོར་བསྲངས་ནས་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པའི་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་བྱེ་བ་ཕྲག་བརྒྱ་སྟོང་དུ་མ་ལ་སྙོམས་པར་ཞུགས་ཏེ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>With his body upright, he immersed himself in many billions of meditative absorptions of the thus-gone ones.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.221.b</prop>
            <prop name="alternative-source"/>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>!བསྐལ་པ་གྲངས་མེད་པ་གསུམ་ནས་བདག་ཉིད་ཀྱི་སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱི་སྤྱོད་པ་སྨོན་ལམ་དང་བསོད་ནམས་མངོན་སུམ་དུ་མཛད་དོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>After three countless eons, he had<tei:note xml:id="UT22084-076-011-56"/> actualized the conduct, aspirations, and merit of a buddha.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.221.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་དེའི་ཚེ་ལྷའི་ཡང་ལྷ་སངས་རྒྱས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་རི་གླང་རུ་དང་། ཡུལ་དགེ་བ་དང་། གསེར་གྱི་དཀྱིལ་འཁོར་ནས་སྲིད་པའི་རྩེ་མོའི་བར་དུ་བྱིན་གྱིས་བརླབས་ཏེ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Right then, the Blessed Buddha, the god of gods, blessed Mount Gośṛṅga, the land of Virtue, and everything else from the golden base all the way up to the peak of existence.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.221.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བསྲུང་བ་དང་། གཙང་བ་དང་། བཀྲ་ཤིས་པ་དང་། མཚམས་བཅད་པ་དང་། བཟླས་བརྗོད་དང་། དགེ་བར་མཛད་དོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He granted it protection, purified it, established auspiciousness, secured its boundaries, engaged in recitation,<tei:note xml:id="UT22084-076-011-57"/> and performed virtue.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.221.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་དེའི་ཚེ་ལྷའི་ཡང་ལྷ་སངས་རྒྱས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་འཁོར་དེ་དག་ཐམས་ཅད་ལ་བཀའ་སྩལ་པ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-011-58"/>The Blessed Buddha, the god of gods, then announced to the entire retinue,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.221.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རི་གླང་རུ་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱི་ཕོ་བྲང་མཆོད་རྟེན་གོ་མ་ས་ལ་གན་ད་དང་བཅས། ཡུལ་དགེ་བ་དང་བཅས་པ་འདི་ནི་བསྐལ་པ་བཟང་པོའི་སངས་རྒྱས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱི་ཕྱག་མཚན་དང་། མ་འདྲེས་པ་དང་། ཐུན་མོང་མ་ཡིན་པ་དང་། དབེན་པ་ཡིན་ཏེ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Mount Gośṛṅga, along with the Gomasalaganda stūpa—the palace of the blessed ones—and this land of Virtue constitute insignia, distinctions, hallmarks, and distinctive features of all the blessed buddhas of the excellent eon.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.221.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྒྱུ་དེས་ན་ཡུལ་འདི་ནི་དགེ་བ་ཞེས་བྱའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>It is for that reason that this land is called Virtue.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.221.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་དེའི་ཚེ་ལྷའི་ཡང་ལྷ་སངས་རྒྱས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་ཡུལ་དགེ་བ་དང་། མཁར་དགེ་བ་ཅན་དང་། དགེ་འདུན་སོ་སོའི་ཀུན་དགའ་ར་བ་དང་། གཙུག་ལག་ཁང་དང་། དགོན་པའི་གནས་དང་། ཡུལ་དེར་སོ་སོ་ནས་བསོད་ནམས་བྱ་བའི་དངོས་པོ་དགེ་བ་བྱེད་པར་འགྱུར་བའི་རྒྱལ་པོ་དང་། ཆོས་དང་ལྡན་པའི་དད་པ་ཅན་དང་། སྦྱིན་བདག་དང་། ལི་ཐམས་ཅད་འབྱུང་བར་ལུང་བསྟན་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-011-59"/>The Blessed Buddha, the god of gods, next prophesied the coming of all the meritorious and virtue-performing kings, the faithful ones endowed with the Dharma, the patrons, and all the people of Khotan yet to appear in the land of Virtue, Virtuous Castle, as well as the individual saṅgha enclaves, temples, and hermitages.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.221.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་རྣམས་ལ་བཀའ་སྩལ་པ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-011-60"/>At this point, the Blessed One told the bodhisattvas,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.221.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རིགས་ཀྱི་བུ་ཁྱེད་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་ཀྱང་མ་འོངས་པའི་དུས་ན་འབྱུང་བའི་ཡུལ་འདིར་ཅི་ནས་ཀྱང་སེམས་ཅན་རྣམས་དམ་པ་ཆེན་པོ་མྱུར་དུ་ཐོབ་པར་འགྱུར་བ་དང་། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Noble children, you must also by all means bless this place so that, in the future, beings here may swiftly attain the utterly sublime and</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.221.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་འགྲུབ་པར་འགྱུར་བར་བྱིན་གྱིས་རློབས་ཤིག །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>so that they will accomplish meditative absorption.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.221.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་དེའི་ཚེ་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་མཚོ་རོལ་ནས་ཅུང་ཟད་ཅིག་སླར་བཀྱེད་དེ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-011-61"/>Having said these words, the Blessed One retreated slightly from the lake shore.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.221.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེའི་མོད་ལ་རི་གླང་རུའི་སྟེང་ན་གདན་ཁྲི་བཤམས་པ་ལ་སྐྱིལ་མོ་ཀྲུང་བཅས་ཏེ་བཞུགས་ནས་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Immediately he was seated cross-legged upon a throne arranged at the peak of Mount Gośṛṅga.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.222.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཞལ་ནུབ་ཕྱོགས་སུ་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱི་ཕོ་བྲང་མཆོད་རྟེན་གོ་མ་ས་ལ་གན་ད་གང་ན་བ་དེ་ལོགས་སུ་<tei:ref folio="F.222.a"/>གཟིགས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Facing west, he looked toward the Gomasalaganda stūpa, the palace of the blessed ones. </seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.222.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་དེའི་ཚེ་འཇིག་རྟེན་གྱི་ཁམས་གཞན་དང་གཞན་ནས་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཉི་ཁྲི་མངོན་པར་ཤེས་པ་ལྔ་དང་ལྡན་པའི་དྲང་སྲོང་མང་པོ་དང་ཐབས་ཅིག་ཏུ་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་གང་ན་བ་དེ་ལོགས་སུ་ལྷགས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>At that moment, twenty thousand bodhisattvas from other world systems and many sages endowed with the five superknowledges arrived together before the Blessed One.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.222.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལྷགས་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱི་ཕོ་བྲང་མཆོད་རྟེན་གོ་མ་ས་ལ་གན་ད་ལ་ཡང་ཕྱག་འཚལ་སྐྱབས་སུ་སོང་། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Having arrived, they prostrated to the Gomasalaganda stūpa, the palace of the blessed ones, and went there to take refuge.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.222.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སངས་རྒྱས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་འཁོར་དང་བཅས་པ་ལ་ཡང་ཕྱག་འཚལ། སྐྱབས་སུ་སོང་ནས་ཕྱོགས་གཅིག་ཏུ་འཁོད་དོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They also prostrated and went for refuge to the Blessed Buddha and his retinue, and then stood together to one side.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.222.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་དེའི་ཚེ་ན་སངས་རྒྱས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་འཁོར་ཕལ་མོ་ཆེ་འདུས་པར་མཁྱེན་ནས་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-011-62"/>At that moment the Blessed Buddha was aware that the majority of the retinue had gathered, so</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.222.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཁོར་དེ་དག་ལ་འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་བཀའ་སྩལ་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>he addressed the retinue:</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.222.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བསྐལ་པ་བཟང་པོ་འདི་ལ་སྔོན་སངས་རྒྱས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་བཞི་བྱུང་སྟེ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Previously in this excellent eon four blessed ones appeared and</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.222.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་དག་གིས་ཀྱང་མཆོད་རྟེན་གོ་མ་ས་ལ་གན་ད་ཡུལ་དང་བཅས་པ་བྱིན་གྱིས་བརླབས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>they too blessed this Gomasalaganda stūpa as well as this country.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.222.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བསྐལ་པ་བཟང་པོ་འདི་ཉིད་ལ། མ་འོངས་པའི་དུས་ནའང་སངས་རྒྱས་སྟོང་རྩ་གཅིག་འབྱུང་བར་འགྱུར་ཏེ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>In the future, during this excellent eon, one thousand and one buddhas will appear, and</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.222.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་དག་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱང་འཁོར་དང་བཅས་ཏེ་འདིར་གཤེགས་ནས་མཆོད་རྟེན་གོ་མ་ས་ལ་གན་ད་ཡུལ་དང་བཅས་པ་བྱིན་གྱིས་རློབ་ཅིང་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>they too will all come here with their retinues and bless this Gomasalaganda stūpa and this country.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.222.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མཚམས་གཅད་པ་དང་། བཀྲ་ཤིས་པ་དང་། དགེ་བར་མཛད་པར་འགྱུར་རོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They will secure its boundaries and establish auspiciousness and virtue.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.222.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ང་ཡང་ད་ལྟར་བྱིན་གྱིས་རློབ་པའི་དུས་ལ་བབ་པས་བྱིན་གྱིས་རློབ་པར་མཛད་དོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Now the time has come for me too to bless it, so I will do so.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.222.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་དེའི་ཚེ་ལྷའི་ཡང་ལྷ་སངས་རྒྱས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་ད་ལྟར་གྱི་སངས་རྒྱས་མངོན་སུམ་དུ་བཞུགས་པ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་དང་། གཞན་ཡང་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པའི་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་གྲངས་མེད་པ་ལ་སྙོམས་པར་ཞུགས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-011-63"/>The Blessed Buddha, the god of gods, now rested in the meditative absorption called the presence of present buddhas and countless other absorptions of the thus-gone ones.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.222.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེའི་ཚེ་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་ལ་སྙོམས་པར་འཇུག་པ་རྣམས་དང་། བསམ་གཏན་པ་རྣམས་ཡོངས་སུ་སྐྱོང་བར་བྱེད་པ་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་མཐུ་ཆེན་ཐོབ་ཀྱིས་ཀྱང་སངས་རྒྱས་འོད་སྲུང་གི་མཆོད་རྟེན་གྱི་དྲུང་དུ་བཞུགས་ཏེ</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>At that time, the bodhisattva Mahā­sthāmprāpta, nurturer of those who are resting in absorption and engaged in the concentrations, sat in front of the Buddha Kāśyapa’s stūpa.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.222.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡུལ་དེ་བྱུང་བར་གྱུར་པའི་ཚེ་བདག་གི་གཟུགས་བརྙན་བྱེད་པར་འགྱུར་བར་ས་གཞི་དེ་བྱིན་གྱིས་བརླབས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He blessed that area so that in the future people would construct an image of him in that region.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.222.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་བཞིན་དུ་སྨོན་ལམ་ཆེན་པོས་གནས་པ་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་འཇམ་དཔལ་གཞོན་ནུར་གྱུར་པས་ཀྱང་རི་གླང་རུ་ལ་གཙུག་<tei:ref folio="F.222.b"/>ལག་ཁང་སྤོང་བྱེད་ཅེས་བྱ་བ་འབྱུང་བར་འགྱུར་བའི་ས་གཞི་དེར་བསྙེན་པ་བྱེད་པ་རྣམས་འགྲུབ་པར་འགྱུར་བར་བྱིན་གྱིས་བརླབས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Likewise, the bodhisattva Mañjuśrī­kumāra­bhūta, who engages in vast aspirations, blessed the ground on Mount Gośṛṅga where a temple called Relinquishing was to appear, so that all those who come to that place could fulfill their aims. </seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.222.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་བཞིན་དུ་ནམ་མཁའ་ལྟར་སྟོབས་དཔག་ཏུ་མེད་པ་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་ནམ་མཁའི་སྙིང་པོས་ཀྱང་གཙུག་ལག་ཁང་འཇིག་ཚོགས་སྤོང་བྱེད་ཅེས་བྱ་བ་འབྱུང་བར་འགྱུར་བའི་ས་གཞི་དེ་མཆོད་གནས་སུ་འགྱུར་བར་བྱིན་གྱིས་བརླབས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Likewise, the bodhisattva Ākāśagarbha, who has strength that is as immeasurable as space, blessed the area where a temple called Relinquishing the Personality was to appear, so that it could become a place of worship.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.222.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་བཞིན་དུ་ཐུགས་རྗེ་ཆེན་པོ་དང་ལྡན་པ་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་འཕགས་པ་སྤྱན་རས་གཟིགས་ཀྱི་དབང་ཕྱུག་གིས་ཀྱང་གཙུག་ལག་ཁང་འོད་ཅན་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་འབྱུང་བར་འགྱུར་བའི་ས་གཞི་དེར་དངོས་གྲུབ་འགྲུབ་པར་བྱིན་གྱིས་བརླབས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Likewise, the bodhisattva noble Avalokiteśvara, who is endowed with great compassion, blessed the ground where a temple called Radiant was to appear, so that the attainments could be accomplished there.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.222.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་བཞིན་དུ་རྟག་ཏུ་བྱམས་པ་དང་ལྡན་པ་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་བྱམས་པས་ཀྱང་གཙུག་ལག་ཁང་བི་སི་མོ་ཉ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་འབྱུང་བར་འགྱུར་བའི་ས་གཞི་དེར་བདག་ཉིད་བཞུགས་པར་བྱིན་གྱིས་བརླབས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Likewise, the bodhisattva Maitreya, who is endowed with constant love, blessed the ground where a temple called Visimonya was to appear, so that he could reside there.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.222.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་བཞིན་དུ་སྤྱོད་པ་ཤིན་དུ་རྣམ་པར་དག་པ་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སའི་སྙིང་པོས་ཀྱང་གཙུག་ལག་ཁང་ཡེ་ཤེས་རི་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་འབྱུང་བར་འགྱུར་བའི་ས་གཞི་དེ་ཕྱག་བྱ་བར་འོས་པར་འགྱུར་བར་བྱིན་གྱིས་བརླབས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Likewise, the bodhisattva Kṣitigarbha, who has impeccable conduct, blessed the ground where a temple called Wisdom Mountain was to appear, so that that place would be worthy of homage.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.222.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་བཞིན་དུ་འདུལ་བའི་སྐྱེ་བོ་རྣམས་གྲོལ་བར་མཛད་པ་ལ་ཐགས་ཐོགས་མི་མངའ་བ་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སྨན་གྱི་རྒྱལ་པོས་ཀྱང་གཙུག་ལག་ཁང་བ་ནོ་ཅོ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་འབྱུང་བར་འགྱུར་བའི་ས་གཞི་དེར་དངོས་གྲུབ་འགྲུབ་པར་འགྱུར་བར་བྱིན་གྱིས་བརླབས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Likewise, the bodhisattva Bhaiṣajyarāja, who possesses an unlimited ability to liberate beings to be trained, blessed the ground where a temple called Vanoco was to appear, so that the attainments could be accomplished there.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.222.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་བཞིན་དུ་རྫུ་འཕྲུལ་ཆེན་པོ་དང་ལྡན་པ་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཀུན་དུ་བཟང་པོས་ཀྱང་གཙུག་ལག་ཁང་དགེ་འདུན་སྐྱོང་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་འབྱུང་བར་འགྱུར་བའི་ས་གཞི་དེར་དངོས་གྲུབ་འགྲུབ་པར་འགྱུར་བར་བྱིན་གྱིས་བརླབས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Likewise, the bodhisattva Samantabhadra, who possesses great miraculous powers, blessed the ground where a temple called Sustaining the Saṅgha was to appear, so that the attainments could be accomplished there.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.223.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་བཞིན་དུ་སངས་རྒྱས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ལ་སོགས་པ་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་གཞན་དག་དང་། དགྲ་བཅོམ་པ་ཆེན་པོ་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་ཀྱང་ལི་ཡུལ་གང་དང་གང་དུ་གཙུག་ལག་ཁང་དང་། སྐྱེད་མོས་ཚལ་དང་། དགོན་པའི་གནས་འབྱུང་བར་འགྱུར་བའི་ས་གཞི་ཐམས་ཅད་དཔེར་ན་ཟླ་བ་ཉ་བ་ལ་སྐར་མའི་ཚོགས་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་ཡོངས་སུ་བསྐོར་ནས་སྟེང་གི་བར་སྣང་དག་པ་ལ་རྒྱུ་<tei:ref folio="F.223.a"/>བ་བཞིན་དུ་མཛེས་པ་དང་། ཡིད་དུ་འོང་བ་དང་། རྒྱས་པ་དང་། དགའ་དགའ་ལྟར་འདུག་པར་བྱིན་གྱིས་བརླབས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-011-64"/>In this way, the Blessed Buddha, the other bodhisattvas, and all of the great worthy ones blessed the ground for all the temples, parks, and hermitages that were to appear throughout the land of Khotan so that they would be as beautiful, delightful, prosperous, and enchanting as the full moon encircled by the constellations of stars, orbiting through a clear sky. </seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.223.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡང་དེའི་ཚེ་རི་གླང་རུ་ལ་སངས་རྒྱས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་བཞུགས་པ་དང་། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-011-65"/>While the Blessed Buddha was present at Mount Gośṛṅga,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.223.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོ་རྣམས་དང་། དགྲ་བཅོམ་པ་ཆེན་པོ་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་འོད་ཟེར་རྣམ་པ་སྣ་ཚོགས་དུ་མ་བཀྱེ་བས་ལི་ཡུལ་ཐམས་ཅད་སྣང་བ་ཆེན་པོས་ཁྱབ་པར་བྱས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>all the bodhisattva great beings and the great worthy ones projected an array of light rays that illuminated the entire land of Khotan.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.223.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་སྐད་ཅིག་དེ་ཉིད་ལ་མཚོ་ཆེན་པོ་དེའི་ནང་ན་པད་མ་སུམ་བརྒྱ་ལྔ་བཅུ་རྩ་གསུམ་བྱུང་བར་གྱུར་ཏེ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>At that very moment, three hundred and fifty-three lotuses emerged from the vast lake there.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.223.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>པད་མ་རེ་རེའི་ནང་ན་ཡང་སངས་རྒྱས་དང་། བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའི་སྐུ་གཟུགས་འོད་དང་བཅས་པ་བཞུགས་པ་སྣང་བར་གྱུར་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Inside each of these lotuses appeared the bodies of buddhas and bodhisattvas glowing with light.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.223.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་དེའི་ཚེ་ལྷ་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་སྔོན་མ་མཐོང་བའི་མཚན་མ་མཐོང་ནས་སངས་རྒྱས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ལ་ཞུས་པ་དང་། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>At that moment, the gods, seeing these signs—signs the likes of which they had never seen before—inquired of the Blessed Buddha as to their meaning.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.223.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་བཀའ་སྩལ་པ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-011-66"/>The Blessed One replied,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.223.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རིགས་ཀྱི་བུ་མཚོའི་ནང་ནས་པད་མ་སུམ་བརྒྱ་ལྔ་བཅུ་རྩ་གསུམ་སངས་རྒྱས་དང་། བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའི་སྐུ་གཟུགས་དང་བཅས་ཏེ་བྱུང་བ་འདི་ནི་མ་འོངས་པའི་དུས་ན་ཡུལ་འདི་བྱུང་བར་གྱུར་པའི་ཚེ་ཡུལ་འདི་ཉིད་དུ་པད་མ་ཇི་སྙེད་པའི་དགོན་པའི་གནས་དང་། གཙུག་ལག་ཁང་ན་གཎ་ཌཱི་བརྡུང་བར་འགྱུར་བ་དང་། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Noble children, the appearance of these three hundred and fifty-three lotuses containing the bodies of the buddhas and bodhisattvas is a portent that in the future, when this land manifests, there will appear here, equal in number to these lotuses, hermitages and temples where the gong will be struck.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.223.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གནས་གང་དང་གང་ན་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོ་རྣམས་དང་། ཉན་ཐོས་ཆེན་པོ་རྣམས་དང་། འོད་ཟེར་རྣམ་པ་སྣ་ཚོགས་འགྱེད་ཅིང་ཡུལ་བྱིན་གྱིས་བརླབས་པའི་ས་གཞི་དེ་དག་དང་། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>This is a portent that in all of these places—the places where the land has been blessed by bodhisattva great beings, great hearers, and the array of projected light rays, and</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.223.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་བཞིན་དུ་ངས་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པའི་ཕོ་བྲང་མཆོད་རྟེན་གོ་མ་ས་ལ་གན་ད་ཡུལ་དགེ་བ་དང་བཅས་པ་བྱིན་གྱིས་བརླབས་པའི་ས་གཞི་འདིར་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>[This is a portent that in all of these places—the places where the land has been blessed by bodhisattva great beings, great hearers, and the array of projected light rays, and] where I have blessed the Gomasalaganda stūpa, the palace of the thus-gone ones, and this land of Virtue—</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.223.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དད་པ་ཅན་གྱི་སྦྱིན་བདག་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་སོ་སོ་ནས་སངས་རྒྱས་ལ་སོགས་པའི་གཟུགས་བརྙན་བྱེད་པར་འགྱུར་ཞིང་། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>[This is a portent that in all of these places—the places where the land has been blessed by bodhisattva great beings, great hearers, and the array of projected light rays, and where I have blessed the Gomasalaganda stūpa, the palace of the thus-gone ones, and this land of Virtue—] faithful patrons will all fashion images of the Buddha and others, and that</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.223.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གནས་དེ་དང་དེ་དག་ཏུ་བསྙེན་པར་བྱས་ན་ཅི་དང་ཅི་འདོད་པ་འགྲུབ་པར་འགྱུར་བའི་སྔ་ལྟས་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>[This is a portent that in all of these places—the places where the land has been blessed by bodhisattva great beings, great hearers, and the array of projected light rays, and where I have blessed the Gomasalaganda stūpa, the palace of the thus-gone ones, and this land of Virtue—faithful patrons will all fashion images of the Buddha and others, and that] whoever arrives in these places will accomplish all their wishes.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.223.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡང་དེའི་ཚེ་ལྷ་རྣམས་སྟན་ལས་ལངས་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ལ་འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་གསོལ་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-011-67"/>At this point, the gods rose from their seats and asked the Blessed One,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.223.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཙུན་པ་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཡུལ་འདི་དུས་ཇི་ཙམ་ཞིག་ན་ནི་འབྱུང་བར་འགྱུར། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Respected Blessed One, at what point in time will this land appear?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.223.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སུ་ཞིག་གིས་ནི་<tei:ref folio="F.223.b"/>འབྱིན་པར་བགྱིད་པ་ལགས། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Who will be its founders? </seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.223.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཙུན་པ་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ད་ལྟར་ནི་དགོན་པ་ཆབ་ཆེན་པོའི་གཏེར་ལགས་ན། སུ་ཞིག་གིས་ཇི་ལྟར་འབྱིན་པ་བཀའ་སྩལ་དུ་གསོལ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Esteemed Blessed One, it is now a wilderness with an abundance of water, so who will be the founders, and how?”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.223.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་བཀའ་སྩལ་པ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-011-68"/>The Blessed One replied,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.223.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རིགས་ཀྱི་བུ་ཉོན་ཅིག །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Noble children, listen.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.223.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ང་མྱ་ངན་ལས་འདས་ནས་ལོ་བརྒྱ་ལོན་པའི་ཚེ་རྒྱའི་ཡུལ་དུ་རྒྱའི་རྒྱལ་པོ་ཅ་ཡང་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་བུ་སྟོང་ཚང་བར་བདོག་པ་ཞིག་འབྱུང་བར་འགྱུར་ཏེ</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>One hundred years after my nirvāṇa, there will appear in China a king called Cayang, who will have a thousand sons.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.223.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བུ་རེ་རེ་ལ་ཡང་ཡུལ་རེ་རེ་གསར་དུ་ཚོལ་དུ་བཅུག་གོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He will order each of his sons to search for a piece of virgin land.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.223.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཕྱིས་ནུབ་ཕྱོགས་ལོགས་ནས་རི་གླང་རུ་དང་། བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱི་ཕོ་བྲང་མཆོད་རྟེན་གོ་མ་ས་ལ་གན་ད་ཡོད་པའི་ཡུལ་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་དུ་མས་བྱིན་གྱིས་བརླབས་བརླབས་པ་ཞིག་ཡོད་དོ་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Later on, he will hear that in the west there is a hill called Gośṛṅga and a land containing the Gomasalaganda stūpa, the palace of the thus-gone ones, which have been blessed by many thus-gone ones.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.223.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཞེས་ཐོས་ནས་དེ་འདི་སྙམ་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Hearing this, he will think,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.223.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དུ་མ་ལ་བདག་ལ་བུ་ཅིག་ཡོད་ན་སངས་རྒྱས་ཕལ་མོ་ཆེས་བྱིན་གྱིས་བརླབས་པའི་གནས་དེར་ཡུལ་འདེབས་སུ་གཞུག་གོ་སྙམ་དུ་བསམས་ནས།</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>‘Oh, if only I had another son, I would send him to cultivate that land, which has been blessed by so many buddhas.’</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.223.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེའི་ཚེ་རྒྱའི་རྒྱལ་པོས་རྣམ་ཐོས་ཀྱི་བུ་ལ་བུ་ཅིག་བསླངས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>At that time, that Chinese king will request Vaiśravaṇa to grant him a son.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.223.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྣམ་ཐོས་ཀྱི་བུས་ཀྱང་འཛམ་བུའི་གླིང་འདི་ན་རྒྱལ་པོ་མྱ་ངན་མེད་ཅེས་བྱ་བའི་བུ་ཞིག་བཙས་པ་བྱིན་ཏེ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>But Vaiśravaṇa will grant him a son of King Aśoka, here in Jambudvīpa.<tei:note xml:id="UT22084-076-011-69"/>
                </seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.223.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བུ་དེ་ནི་གཟུགས་བཟང་བ། དབྱིབས་མཛེས་པ། བལྟ་ན་སྡུག་པ་ཞིག་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>This boy will have an excellent body, a beautiful appearance, and he will be a delight to the eyes.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.223.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བུ་དེའི་དོན་དུ་ས་ལས་ནུ་མ་ཞིག་བྱུང་བ་དང་། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>For this boy, a breast will appear from the ground and,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.223.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བུ་དེ་སྔོན་གྱི་བསོད་ནམས་དང་དགེ་བའི་རྩ་བའི་མཐུས་ནུ་མ་དེ་ལ་ནུ་བར་བྱེད་པས་དེས་ན་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>through the strength of his previous merits and roots of virtue, he will suckle this breast. As a result,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.223.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བུ་དེའི་མིང་ས་ལས་ནུ་མ་ནུ་ཞེས་བྱ་བའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>he will become known by the name Suckler of the Earth Breast.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.223.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བུ་དེ་མྱུར་བར་སྐྱེས་ནས་ཕ་རྒྱའི་རྒྱལ་པོས་རྒྱལ་སྲིད་ཀྱི་དབང་ནི་བསྐུར། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He will mature quickly, and his father, the Chinese king, will confer royal power upon him,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.223.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ནོར་མང་པོ་ནི་བྱིན། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>[He will mature quickly, and his father, the Chinese king, will confer royal power upon him,] bestow upon him a mass of wealth, and</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.223.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བློན་པོ་ཕལ་མོ་ཆེ་ནི་ལུས་ཀྱི་རིམ་གྲོ་བར་བསྐོས་ནས། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>[He will mature quickly, and his father, the Chinese king, will confer royal power upon him, bestow upon him a mass of wealth, and] assign most of the ministers as his servants.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.223.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྒྱལ་བུ་ས་ལས་ནུ་མ་ནུ་དེ་བློན་པོ་ཆེན་པོ་ཇང་ཤོ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་ལ་སོགས་པ་དམག་དུ་མ་དང་ལྷན་ཅིག་ཏུ་རྒྱའི་ཡུལ་ནས་བྱུང་སྟེ་ཡུལ་འདིར་འོང་བར་འགྱུར་རོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The prince Suckler of the Earth Breast, together with a senior minister called Jangsho and many soldiers, will then leave China and come to this land.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.223.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འོངས་ནས་འདིར་ཡུལ་འདེབས་པར་འགྱུར་ཏེ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Arriving here, they will cultivate the land and,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.223.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྒྱལ་བུ་ས་ལས་ནུ་མ་ནུ་དེས་ཡུལ་བཏབ་པའི་ཕྱིར་རྒྱུ་དེས་ན་ཡུལ་འདིའི་མིང་ནི་ས་ལས་ནུ་མ་ནུའི་ཡུལ་ཞེས་བྱ་བར་འགྱུར་རོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>in order to found the country, Prince Suckler of the Earth Breast will name the place Land of Suckler of the Earth Breast.<tei:note xml:id="UT22084-076-011-70"/>
                </seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.223.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དུས་དེའི་ཚེ་ན་ནུབ་ཕྱོགས་ལོགས་ནས་རྒྱ་གར་གྱི་མི་ཕལ་མོ་ཆེ་འདིར་འོང་བར་འགྱུར་ཏེ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-011-71"/>“At that time, many Indian people will travel here from the west and</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.223.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྒྱལ་པོ་ས་ལས་ནུ་མ་ནུའི་འབངས་སུ་མཆིད་ཀྱིས་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>request to become subjects of King Suckler of the Earth Breast.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.224.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཚལ་ཞིང་ཆུ་སྲིད་གཅིག་པར་དུམ་<tei:ref folio="F.224.a"/>བར་གྱུར་ནས། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Thus, that single kingdom will contain various people. </seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.224.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྒྱའི་བློན་པོ་ཆེན་པོ་ཇང་ཤོ་ལ་སོགས་པས་རིམ་གྱིས་རྒྱ་དང་། རྒྱ་གར་གྱི་གྲོང་དང་། གྲོང་ཁྱེར་དང་། གྲོང་རྡལ་འདེབས་པར་འགྱུར་རོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The Chinese senior minister Jangsho, together with others, will then gradually found both Chinese and Indian villages, towns, and markets.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.224.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ལྟར་རྒྱལ་པོ་ས་ལས་ནུ་མ་ནུ་དེ་མི་རབས་དུ་མའི་བར་དུ་ཡུལ་འདིའི་རྒྱལ་པོ་བྱེད་པར་འགྱུར་རོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>In that way, King Suckler of the Earth Breast and his descendants will rule over these lands for many generations.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.224.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྒྱལ་པོ་དེ་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་ཀྱང་རིམ་གྱིས་སོ་སོ་ནས་ཡུལ་འདིར་དགོན་པའི་གནས་དང་གཙུག་ལག་ཁང་བྱས་ན་ཞིང་ཆུ་དང་། འབངས་དང་། ཞལ་ཏ་བྱེད་པ་ཡང་འབུལ་ཞིང་། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Each of these kings will, in turn, build hermitages and temples and offer them irrigation water, subjects, and counsel.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.224.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལ་ལ་ཡང་བདག་ཉིད་ཀྱང་རབ་ཏུ་འབྱུང་བར་བྱེད་དོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Some of them will even take ordination themselves.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.224.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལ་ལ་ནི་བུ་དང་བུ་མོ་རབ་ཏུ་འབྱིན་པར་བྱེད་དོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Some of them will have their sons and daughters take ordination.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.224.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལ་ལ་ནི་འབངས་ལས་གྲངས་མེད་པ་ཞིག་རབ་ཏུ་འབྱུང་བར་གནང་བར་བྱེད་དོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Some of them will allow countless numbers of their subjects to take ordination.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.224.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡུལ་འདིར་མི་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའི་རིགས་ཅན་མང་པོ་ཞིག་འབྱུང་སྟེ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>In this land, there will appear many people with the nature of bodhisattvas,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.224.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྟག་ཏུ་དཀོན་མཆོག་གསུམ་ལས་དགེ་བའི་རྩ་བ་སོགས་ཤིང་བསོད་ནམས་བྱ་བའི་དངོས་པོ་བྱེད་པར་འགྱུར་རོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>who will constantly gather roots of virtue and engage in meritorious deeds based on the Three Jewels.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.224.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ལྟར་ན་ཡུལ་འདི་ནི་རྒྱལ་པོ་ས་ལས་ནུ་མ་ནུས་ཡུལ་གཏོད་པའི་ཚུལ་དེ་ལྟ་བུས་འབྱུང་བར་འགྱུར་རོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>In this way, King Suckler of the Earth Breast will establish this land.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.224.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡུལ་འདི་ནི་སངས་རྒྱས་འབྱུང་བ་རེ་རེའི་ཚེ་ཡང་འབྱུང་ཞིང་རྒྱས་པར་འགྱུར་རོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-011-72"/>“Each time a buddha appears, this land will appear and flourish.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.224.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཅིའི་ཕྱིར་ཡུལ་གཞན་དང་གཞན་དག་གི་ནི་ཞིག་ནས་ཡུན་རིང་མོ་ཞིག་ཏུ་སྟོང་ཞིང་དགོན་པར་འདུག་ལ་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Why is it that, while other lands deteriorate and then remain empty and desolate for a long time,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.224.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡུལ་དགེ་བ་ནི་སངས་རྒྱས་འབྱུང་བ་རེ་རེའི་ཚེ་མི་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་བརྒྱན་ཅིང་མཛེས་པར་འགྱུར་ཞེ་ན</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>[Why is it that, while other lands deteriorate and then remain empty and desolate for a long time,] the land Virtue is adorned and beautified by people each time a buddha appears?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.224.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདི་ལྟར་ཡུལ་འདི་ནི་ཐུབ་པ་དྲང་སྲོང་ཆེན་པོའི་གནས། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>It is because this land is the dwelling place of the saintly great sage,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.224.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པའི་སྤྱོད་ཡུལ་མཆོད་རྟེན་གོ་མ་ས་ལ་གན་ད་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་རི་གླང་རུ་དང་ཉེ་བ་ཆུ་བོ་གོ་མའི་འགྲམ་ན་ཡོད་པའི་ཕྱིར་རོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>[It is because this land is the dwelling place of the saintly great sage,] the domain of the thus-gone ones, the locale of the Gomasalaganda stūpa, which is near Mount Gośṛṅga and on the banks of the River Goma.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.224.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མཆོད་རྟེན་འདི་མདོ་སྡེའི་ནང་ནས་ནི་མིང་གོ་མ་ས་ལ་གན་ད་ཞེས་བྱའི། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>This stūpa is called Gomasalaganda in the sūtras.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.224.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇིག་རྟེན་ཕལ་གྱི་ཐ་སྙད་དུ་ནི་ཆུ་བོ་གོ་མའི་འགྲམ་ཞེས་བྱ་བར་འདོགས་པར་འགྱུར་ཏེ</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>In ordinary parlance, however, it is called ‘On the Bank of River Goma.’</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.224.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདི་ལྟར་ཇི་སྲིད་དུ་མཆོད་རྟེན་ཆུ་བོ་གོ་མའི་འགྲམ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་དང་། འོད་སྲུང་གི་མཆོད་རྟེན་འདི་གཉིས་རྒྱས་ཤིང་མཆོད་གནས་སུ་བྱེད་པ་དེ་སྲིད་དུ་ནི་ཡུལ་དགེ་བ་ཡང་རྒྱས་ཤིང་བཟང་པོར་འགྱུར་རོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Thus, for as long as that stūpa called On the Bank of River Goma, as well as Kāśyapa’s stūpa, flourish and are sites of worship, the land of Virtue will also flourish and prosper.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.224.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ནམ་མཆོད་རྟེན་འདི་གཉིས་རྒུད་པ་དེའི་ཚེ་ཡུལ་ཡང་རྒུད་ཅིང་སྟོངས་པར་འགྱུར་རོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Whenever these two stūpas fall into decline, this land will also fall into decline and become empty.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.224.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་དེའི་ཚེ་འཁོར་དེར་འདུས་པའི་ལྷ་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་བཅོམ་<tei:ref folio="F.224.b"/>ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་བཀའ་སྩལ་པའི་གསུང་དེ་ཐོས་ནས་མཆོད་རྟེན་གོ་མ་ས་ལ་གན་ད་དང་། རི་གླང་རུ་ལ་དད་པ་དང་གུས་པ་ཆེན་པོ་རྙེད་དེ</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-011-73"/>Having heard the Blessed One’s explanation, the retinue of gods gathered there gained great faith and veneration for the Gomasalaganda stūpa and Mount Gośṛṅga.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.224.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སངས་རྒྱས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ལ་མགོ་བོས་ཕྱག་འཚལ་སྐྱབས་སུ་སོང་ནས་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They bowed down to the Blessed Buddha and went to him to take refuge. Then,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.224.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྤྱན་སྔར་འདི་སྐད་དུ་བདག་ཅག་ཀྱང་དུས་དེའི་ཚེ་ཡུལ་འདིར་རིགས་མཐོན་པོར་སྐྱེས་ནས་བདེ་བར་གཤེགས་པའི་བསྟན་པ་སྲུང་ཞིང་། ཡུལ་ཆོས་ཀྱི་བཀའ་ཁྲིམས་མི་ཉམས་པར་གྱུར་ཅིག་ཅེས་སྨོན་ལམ་བཏབ་བོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>in the Blessed One’s presence they made this aspiration: “At that time, may we take birth in that land within eminent families and guard the Well-Gone One’s teaching so that the righteous laws of the land never weaken!”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.224.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་དེའི་ཚེ་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་ལྷའི་རྒྱལ་པོ་རྣམ་ཐོས་ཀྱི་བུ་དང་། བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོ་འདུ་ཤེས་ཅན་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་དང་། ལྷའི་ལྷ་མི་ཕམ་པ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་དང་། ཀླུའི་རྒྱལ་པོ་ཁྱིམ་འཚིག་ཅེས་བྱ་བ་དང་། ལྷ་ནམ་མཁའི་དབྱངས་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་དང་། ལྷ་གསེར་གྱི་ཕྲེང་བ་ཅན་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་དང་། ལྷ་མོ་ལྕགས་ཀྱུ་ཅན་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་དང་། ལྷ་མོ་གནས་ཅན་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་རྣམས་ལ་འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་བཀའ་སྩལ་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-011-74"/>At that moment the Blessed One addressed the divine king Vaiśravaṇa, the bodhisattva great being Perceptive, the god of gods Ajita, the nāga king Gṛhadāha, the god Song of the Sky, the god Golden Garland, the goddess Hook Bearer, and the goddess Stable:</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.224.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རིགས་ཀྱི་བུ་ཁྱེད་རྣམས་ལ་མཆོད་རྟེན་གོ་མ་ས་ལ་གན་ད་དང་། རི་གླང་རུ་ཡུལ་དང་བཅས་པ་དང་། ངའི་བསྟན་པ་དང་། སྲས་རྣམས་ཡོངས་སུ་གཏད་ཀྱིས་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Noble children, I entrust to you the Gomasalaganda stūpa, Mount Gośṛṅga and its land, together with my teachings and my offspring.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.224.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡོངས་སུ་བསྲུང་བ་དང་། བསྐྱབ་པ་དང་། བསྐྱང་བ་དང་། མཆོད་གནས་སུ་འགྱུར་བར་གྱིས་ཤིག །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Be sure to guard them, protect them, nurture them, and pay homage to them!</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.224.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡུལ་འདིའི་རྒྱལ་པོ་དང་། ཡུལ་འཛིན་པའི་བློན་པོ་དང་། སྦྱིན་བདག་ཆོས་དང་འཐུན་པ་རྣམས་ཀྱང་ཡོངས་སུ་གཏད་ཀྱིས་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>I entrust to you the monarchs of this land, the governing ministers, and all the patrons who act in accord with the Dharma.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.224.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་བཞིན་དུ་གྱིས་ཤིག །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Protect them accordingly!</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.224.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རི་གླང་རུ་ལུང་བསྟན་པའི་མདོ་འདི་ཡང་ཡོངས་སུ་གཏད་ཀྱིས་འཕེལ་ཞིང་རྒྱས་པར་གྱིས་ཤིག །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>I also entrust to you this discourse that describes Mount Gośṛṅga, so you must propagate and spread it!</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.224.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་གི་ཚེ་ཡུལ་འདི་མེའམ་ཆུའམ་ཕ་རོལ་གྱི་དམག་གིས་ཉེན་ཅིང་ཕོངས་པར་གྱུར་པ་ན་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>If at some point this land is endangered and ravaged by fire, water, or foreign armies,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.224.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མདོ་འདི་བཀླག་པ་དང་། ཁ་ཏོན་དང་། མཆོད་པ་དང་། བསམ་པ་དང་། བསྒོམ་པ་བྱས་ན་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>if you read this discourse, or recite it, pay homage to it, reflect upon it, and meditate upon it,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.224.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེས་ན་ཡུལ་དེའི་གནོད་པ་ཞི་བར་འགྱུར་རོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>the destructive forces afflicting this land will be pacified.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.224.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མ་འོངས་པའི་དུས་ན་སེམས་ཅན་རྣམས་ཀྱི་ལས་ཀྱི་རྣམ་པར་སྨིན་པས་ཡུལ་འདིར་སུམ་པ་རྣམས་དང་བོད་རྣམས་འོང་བར་འགྱུར་གྱིས་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-011-75"/>“In the future, due to the ripening of sentient beings’ former actions, the Sumpa and Tibetan people will come to this land.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.224.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེའི་ཚེ་མདོ་འདི་ལྷོགས་ཤིག་དང་། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>At that time, you must propound this discourse, for</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.225.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མདོ་འདི་ཐོས་ནས་མདོ་འདིའི་མཐུ་དང་། ལྷ་རྣམས་ཀྱི་བྱིན་གྱིས་དད་པ་མེད་པ་དེ་རྣམས་<tei:ref folio="F.225.a"/>ཡུལ་འཇིག་པར་མི་བྱེད་ཅིང་ཡིད་ཀྱང་འགྱོད་པར་འགྱུར་རོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>when they hear this discourse, then through its inherent power and the blessings of the gods, those faithless people will not devastate the land but rather feel remorse.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.225.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མ་འོངས་པའི་དུས་ན་ཡུལ་འདིར་རྒྱ་རྣམས་ཀྱང་འོང་བར་འགྱུར་གྱིས་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>In the future, the Chinese will also come to this land.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.225.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེའི་ཚེ་མདོ་འདི་ལྷོགས་ཤིག་དང་། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>At that time, you must propound this discourse, for</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.225.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མདོ་འདི་ཐོས་ནས་དད་པ་སྐྱེ་བར་འགྱུར་རོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>upon hearing it, they will give rise to faith,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.225.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དད་པའི་སྟོབས་ཀྱིས་ཡུལ་མི་འཇིག་ཅིང་ཕྱིར་ཞིང་བསྲུང་བ་དང་། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>and through the strength of their faith, they will not inflict any harm on this land. Rather, they will grant it protection and</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.225.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བསོད་ནམས་བྱ་བའི་དངོས་པོ་ཡང་བྱེད་པར་འགྱུར་ཏེ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>engage in meritorious deeds.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.225.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྒྱུ་དེས་ན་མདོ་འདི་ནི་ཡུལ་ལ་ཕན་འདོགས་པར་བྱེད་པ་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>This being so, this discourse will be of benefit for this land.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.225.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མདོ་འདིའི་ཕན་ཡོན་གཞན་ཡང་མང་དུ་ཡོད་དེ་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>There are so many other benefits of this discourse, but</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.225.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡུན་ཐུང་ངུས་ནི་བརྗོད་པར་མི་ནུས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>it is not possible to mention them all in a short time.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.225.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེའི་ཕྱིར་མདོ་འདི་ཁྱེད་རྣམས་ལ་ཡོངས་སུ་གཏད་དོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Therefore, I entrust this discourse to you.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.225.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་དེའི་ཚེ་རྣམ་ཐོས་ཀྱི་བུ་ལ་སོགས་པ་ལྷ་རྣམས་དང་། ཀླུའི་རྒྱལ་པོ་དང་། ལྷ་མོ་དེ་དག་ཐམས་ཅད་འཁོར་དང་བཅས་ཏེ་ལངས་ནས་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-011-76"/>Vaiśravaṇa and the other gods, the nāga king, and the goddesses together with their retinues stood up.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.225.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱི་སྤྱན་སྔར་པུས་མོའི་ལྷ་ང་ས་ལ་བཙུགས་ཏེ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They kneeled down before the Blessed One and</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.225.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཐལ་མོ་སྦྱར་ནས་འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་གསོལ་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>with their palms joined, exclaimed,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.225.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཙུན་པ་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་བདག་ཅག་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱི་བཀའ་སྤྱི་བོས་ལེན་པར་འཚལ་ལོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Respected Blessed One, we place the Blessed One’s commandment on the crown of our heads!”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.225.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡང་གསོལ་པ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They then continued,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.225.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྟོན་པ་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་ཇི་སྐད་བཀའ་སྩལ་པ་བཞིན་དུ་མཆོད་རྟེན་གོ་མ་ས་ལ་གན་ད་དང་། རི་གླང་རུ་ཡུལ་དང་བཅས་པ་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱང་ཡོངས་སུ་བསྲུང་བར་འཚལ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Just as the Teacher, the Blessed One, has instructed, we will guard the Gomasalaganda stūpa, Mount Gośṛṅga, and its land.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.225.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བདེ་བར་གཤེགས་པའི་བསྟན་པ་དང་ཆོས་དང་འཐུན་པའི་རྒྱལ་པོ་དང་། རབ་ཏུ་བྱུང་བ་དང་། ཆོས་དང་འཐུན་པར་ཡུལ་འཛིན་པ་དང་། ཆོས་དང་འཐུན་པའི་སྦྱིན་བདག་དང་། གང་ཞིག་བསོད་ནམས་བྱ་བའི་དངོས་པོ་བགྱིད་པར་འགྱུར་བ་དེ་དག་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱང་ཡོངས་སུ་བསྲུང་བར་ནི་འཚལ་ན</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>We will guard the Well-Gone One’s teaching, the monarchs who act in accord with the Dharma, those who have gone forth, governors who act in accord with the Dharma, patrons who act in accord with the Dharma, and all those engaged in meritorious deeds.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.225.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཇི་སྲིད་དུ་ཡུལ་འདིར་དཀོན་མཆོག་གསུམ་མཆོད་གནས་སུ་བགྱིད་པ་དང་། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Blessed One, for as long as the Three Jewels are venerated in this land and</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.225.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡུལ་འཛིན་པས་ཀྱང་ཆོས་དང་འཐུན་པར་ཡུལ་སྐྱོང་ཞིང་ཆོས་དང་མི་འཐུན་པའི་སེམས་ཅན་རྣམས་ཀྱི་མགོན་མི་བགྱིད་པ་དེ་སྲིད་དུ་ནི་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>for as long as the governors rule the land in accord with the Dharma and do not protect those who act in ways contrary to the Dharma,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.225.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བདག་ཅག་གིས་ཡོངས་སུ་བསྲུང་བར་རྔོ་ཐོགས་ཏེ</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>we will be able to guard this land.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.225.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མདོ་འདི་ཡང་ལི་ཡུལ་ཡུན་རིང་དུ་གནས་པར་བགྱི་བའི་སླད་དུ་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>To ensure that this discourse may remain in the land of Khotan for a long time,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.225.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལི་ཡུལ་ལས་ཉི་འོག་ཏུ་གྱུར་པའི་རྒྱལ་པོ་དང་། བློན་པོ་རྣམས་ལ་མདོ་སྡེ་འདི་ནི་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་ལི་<tei:ref folio="F.225.b"/>ཡུལ་གྱི་ཆེད་དུ་རི་གླང་རུ་ལ་བཤད་པ་ཡིན་ནོ་ཞེས་རྣར་གྲགས་པར་བགྱི། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>we will make sure that the kings and ministers in the border regions surrounding Khotan hear that the Blessed One has taught this discourse at Mount Gośṛṅga for the benefit of the land of Khotan.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.225.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སུག་པར་ཐོབ་པར་བགྱི། སེམས་བསྒྱུར་བར་བགྱིའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>We will make sure that they receive it in their hands and that their minds are transformed. </seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.225.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ནམ་ཡུལ་འདིར་དཀོན་མཆོག་གསུམ་མཆོད་གནས་སུ་མི་བགྱིད་ཅིང་། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-011-77"/>“Blessed One, when the Three Jewels are no longer venerated in this land and</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.225.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཆོས་དང་མི་འཐུན་པ་རྣམས་ཀྱི་མགོན་ལྷག་པར་བགྱིད་པ་དེའི་ཚེ་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>when those who act in ways contrary to the Dharma are protected here,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.225.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བདག་ཅག་རྣམས་ཀྱི་གཟི་བརྗིད་དང་མཐུ་སྟོབས་ཉམས་པར་འགྱུར་བས་ཡུལ་འདིའི་ཆེད་དང་བསྲུང་བར་ནི་རྔོ་མི་ཐོགས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>our splendor and might will decline so that we are no longer able to guard this land.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.225.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ཅིའི་སླད་དུ་ཞེ་ན། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Why?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.225.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བདག་ཅག་གི་མཐུ་སྟོབས་དང་གཟི་བརྗིད་ནི་བདེ་བར་གཤེགས་པའི་བསྟན་པ་དང་། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Because our might and splendor grow from the Well-Gone One’s teaching, from</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.225.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཆོས་དང་འཐུན་པར་ཡུལ་ཚུལ་བཞིན་དུ་སྐྱོང་བ་དང་། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>[our might and splendor grow from the Well-Gone One’s teaching, from] the land being correctly governed in accord with the Dharma, and from</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.225.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བསོད་ནམས་བྱ་བའི་དངོས་པོ་དགེ་བའི་རྩ་བའི་མཐུས་འཕེལ་བར་འགྱུར་བ་ལགས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>[our might and splendor grow from the Well-Gone One’s teaching, from the land being correctly governed in accord with the Dharma, and from] the roots of virtue engendered through meritorious deeds.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.225.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་དེའི་ཚེ་སངས་རྒྱས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་གདན་ལས་བཞེངས་ནས་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-011-78"/>Right then, the Blessed Buddha rose from his seat and</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.225.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རི་གླང་རུའི་སྟེང་གི་འགྲམ་ནས་མཆོད་རྟེན་གོ་མ་ས་ལ་གན་ད་གང་ན་བ་དེ་ལོགས་སུ་གཟིགས་ནས</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>from the edge of the peak of Mount Gośṛṅga he gazed toward the Gomasalaganda stūpa.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.225.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡང་ནས་ཡང་དུ་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པའི་སྤྱོད་ཡུལ་མཆོད་རྟེན་གོ་མ་ས་ལ་གན་ད་རི་གླང་རུ་དང་བཅས་པ་ལན་གཉིས་ལན་གསུམ་གྱི་བར་དུ་བྱིན་གྱིས་བརླབས་ནས་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Repeatedly—twice, thrice—he blessed the Gomasalaganda stūpa, the domain of the thus-gone ones, as well as Mount Gośṛṅga and the whole region.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.225.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལི་ཡུལ་ཐམས་ཅད་དང་། མཚོའི་ནང་ན་གནས་པའི་སེམས་ཅན་གྲངས་མེད་པ་རྣམས་ལ་འོད་ཟེར་དང་ཐུགས་རྗེ་ཆེན་པོས་ཁྱབ་པར་མཛད་དེ</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>He thus suffused the entire land of Khotan and all the countless beings dwelling in the lake there with light rays and great compassion.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.225.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འོད་ཟེར་དེ་དང་ཐུགས་རྗེ་ཆེན་པོ་དེས་ཆུ་ན་གནས་པའི་སེམས་ཅན་དེ་དག་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱི་སྡུག་བསྔལ་ནི་ཞི་བར་འགྱུར། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The light rays and his great compassion quelled all the sufferings of those beings dwelling in the water,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.225.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཁྲོ་བ་དང་འཁོན་དུ་འཛིན་པ་དང་ནི་བྲལ་ཏེ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>freed them from anger and resentment,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.225.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱམས་པའི་སེམས་དང་ལྡན་པར་གྱུར་ཅིང་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>imbued them with loving kindness, and</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.225.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལྷའི་བདེ་བ་དང་ལྡན་ནས་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>endowed them with the happiness of the gods.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.225.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྐད་ཅིག་དེ་ཉིད་ལ་སེམས་ཅན་དེ་དག་ལས་གྲངས་མེད་པ་ཞིག་ཚེ་འཕོས་ནས་ལྷ་དང་མི་རྣམས་ཀྱི་ནང་དུ་སྐྱེས་ཏེ</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>In that very instant, an uncountable number of those beings changed lives and were reborn as gods and humans.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.225.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སངས་རྒྱས་ཉིད་དུ་འགྱུར་བའི་ས་བོན་རྙེད་ཅིང་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They acquired the seed for awakening, and</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.225.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱང་ཆུབ་ལས་ཕྱིར་མི་ལྡོག་པར་གྱུར་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>their progress toward awakening became irreversible.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.225.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་དེའི་ཚེ་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་ལྷ་རྣམས་ལ་ལན་གསུམ་གྱི་བར་དུ་བོས་ནས་འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་བཀའ་སྩལ་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-011-79"/>The Blessed One then called out to the gods three times and addressed them thus:</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.225.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རིགས་ཀྱི་བུ་ཁྱེད་ཀྱིས་དམ་བཅས་པ་རྣམས་ནི་བརྩོན་འགྲུས་མེད་པར་མི་འགྲུབ་བོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Noble children, these pledges of yours will not be fulfilled without perseverance.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.226.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རིགས་ཀྱི་བུ་ངས་བསྐལ་པ་གྲངས་མེད་པ་གསུམ་གྱི་བར་དུ་དཀའ་བ་སྤྱད་པའི་བསྟན་པ་འདི་དང་མཆོད་རྟེན་གོ་མ་ས་ལ་<tei:ref folio="F.226.a"/>གན་ད་ཡུལ་དང་བཅས་པ་ཁྱེད་རྣམས་ལ་ཡོངས་སུ་གཏད་ཀྱིས་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Noble children, I entrust to you this teaching of mine for which I underwent hardships for three countless eons. I also entrust to you the Gomasalaganda stūpa and its land.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.226.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡོངས་སུ་སྲུངས་ཤིག །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Guard them closely. </seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.226.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཁྱེད་རྣམས་ལས་གང་ཞིག་གིས་ང་རྗེས་སུ་དྲན་ཞིང་གཟུངས་ཡོད་པ་དང་། བསྟན་པ་བསྲུང་བ་དེས་ནི་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>All of you, in whatever you do, should recall me, retain and protect the teachings, and thereby</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.226.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བསྟན་པ་འདི་ལ་རབ་ཏུ་བྱུང་བ་རྣམས་ཡོངས་སུ་བསྲུང་བར་གྱིས་ཤིག །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>closely guard all those who have taken ordination under this teaching.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.226.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ཅིའི་ཕྱིར་ཞེ་ན། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Why, you may wonder?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.226.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མི་ཁྱིམ་པ་ལ་ལ་ཞིག་ལོ་བརྒྱའི་བར་དུ་ཉིན་རེ་ཞིང་དགེ་བའི་རྩ་བ་བསོད་ནམས་ཆེན་པོ་བྱེད་ལ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Some householders might gather roots of virtue and create vast amounts of merit each day for a hundred years, yet</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.226.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འགའ་ཞིག་ཉིན་གཅིག་རབ་ཏུ་བྱུང་ནས་བསྟན་པ་ལ་གནས་ན་སྔ་མས་ཕྱི་མའི་བསོད་ནམས་ཀྱི་བརྒྱའི་ཆར་ཡང་མི་ཆོག་གོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>this would not amount to even one percent of the merit of someone who abides by the teachings for just a single day after going forth.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.226.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ཅིའི་ཕྱིར་ཞེ་ན། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Why is that?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.226.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སངས་རྒྱས་གང་གཱའི་ཀླུང་གི་བྱེ་མ་སྙེད་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱང་སྔར་ཁྱིམ་གྱི་གནས་སྤངས་ཏེ་རབ་ཏུ་བྱུང་ནས་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Because all of the buddhas, who are equal in number to the grains of sand in the Ganges River, have first given up their life as householders and gone forth, and</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.226.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྤྱོད་ལམ་དེ་ཉིད་ཀྱིས་བྱང་ཆུབ་ཆེན་པོ་བརྙེས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>attained awakening through that lifestyle.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.226.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ང་ཡང་ཕ་རོལ་ཏུ་ཕྱིན་པ་དྲུག་ཡོངས་སུ་རྫོགས་ཏེ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-011-80"/>“I too—having completed the six perfections,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.226.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ས་བཅུ་བརྙེས་ནས་སྲིད་པ་ཐ་མའི་ཚེ་ན་མ་ཕྱེད་ན་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>attained the tenth level, and entered my last life in cyclic existence—</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.226.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྒྱལ་པོའི་ཁབ་ནས་བྱུང་སྟེ་ནགས་ཚལ་དུ་གཤེགས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>left the royal compound at midnight and went to the forest.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.226.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ནགས་ཚལ་ནས་བཞོན་པ་རྒྱལ་པོ་ཡབ་ཀྱི་ཐོག་ཏུ་དཀྲི་ནས་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>From the forest I sent my mount to my father, the king.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.226.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རང་གི་སྐྲ་རལ་གྲིས་བྲེགས་ཏེ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>I then cut off my hair with my sword and</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.226.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ངའི་གོས་གྱ་ནོམ་པ་རིན་ཐང་མེད་པ་རྔོན་པ་དེ་དག་ལས་ཆོས་གོས་ངུར་སྨྲིག་ཏུ་བརྗེས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>gave hunters my fine, priceless clothes in exchange for saffron-colored Dharma robes.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.226.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ངས་ཆོས་གོས་དེ་གྱོན་ནས་དུས་གསུམ་གྱི་སངས་རྒྱས་ཐམས་ཅད་ལ་ཕྱག་འཚལ་སྐྱབས་སུ་སོང་ནས་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Donning those Dharma robes, I paid homage to all the buddhas of the three times, went to them for refuge, and then</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.226.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རབ་ཏུ་བྱུང་བའི་སྤྱོད་ལམ་བཟུང་བ་དང་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>assumed the lifestyle of one who has gone forth.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.226.a</prop>
            <prop name="alternative-source"/>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>!ལྷ་ཐམས་ཅད་ལ་ཕྱག་འཚལ་སྐྱབས་སུ་སོང་ནས་ཕྱི་བཞིན་དུ་འབྲང་ངོ་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>All of the gods then paid homage to me,<tei:note xml:id="UT22084-076-011-81"/> went to me for refuge, and followed my lead.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.226.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ང་ཡང་སྤྱོད་ལམ་དེ་ཉིད་ཀྱིས་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་སངས་རྒྱས་བརྙེས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Thus, I too attained perfect awakening through that lifestyle.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.226.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེའི་ཕྱིར་བདེ་བར་གཤེགས་པའི་བསྟན་པ་ནི་དམ་པ་ཡིན་པར་ཤེས་པར་བྱའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>For this reason, understand that the Well-Gone One’s teaching is sublime.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.226.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རབ་ཏུ་བྱུང་བ་ནི་བསོད་ནམས་དང་ལྡན་པར་ཤེས་པར་བྱའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Understand that to go forth is to possess merit.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.226.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇིག་རྟེན་ན་རབ་ཏུ་བྱུང་བས་ཐོབ་པ་མ་གཏོགས་པར་ཁྱིམ་པའི་ཆ་ལུགས་ཀྱིས་དགྲ་བཅོམ་པའམ། རང་སངས་རྒྱས་སམ། བླ་ན་མེད་པའི་བྱང་ཆུབ་ཐོབ་པ་ནི་སུས་ཀྱང་མ་ཐོས་མ་མཐོང་ངོ་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>In this world it has never been seen or heard that someone with the trappings of a householder attained the states of a worthy one, a self-realized buddha, or unsurpassable awakening; such states are only attained by going forth.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.226.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རབ་ཏུ་བྱུང་བའི་སྤྱོད་ལམ་དམ་པ་འདི་ནི་འཇིག་རྟེན་ན་ལྷ་ལ་སོགས་པ་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱི་མཆོད་གནས་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The sublime lifestyle of one who has gone forth is an object of veneration by all the gods and others in this world.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.226.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་དེའི་ཚེ་ལྷ་དང་ལྷ་མོ་དེ་ཐམས་ཅད་སྟན་ལས་ལངས་ནས་དབྱངས་གཅིག་ཏུ་སངས་རྒྱས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ལ་འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་<tei:ref folio="F.226.b"/>གསོལ་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-011-82"/>All of the gods and goddesses now rose from their seats and pledged to the Blessed Buddha in unison, </seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.226.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཙུན་པ་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་བདག་ཅག་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་ཇི་ལྟར་བཀའ་སྩལ་པ་བཞིན་འཚལ་ཞིང་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Respected Blessed One, we will do as the Blessed One has instructed.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.226.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བསམས་བཞིན་དུ་ནི་བཀའ་ལས་འགལ་བ་མི་འཚལ་ལོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>We will not intentionally transgress your instructions.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.226.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡུལ་འདི་སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱིས་བསྟན་པ་དང་། དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པའི་སྤྱོད་ཡུལ་མཆོད་རྟེན་དང་བཅས་པ་ཡང་ཀུན་དུ་བསྲུང་བ་དང་། བསྐྱང་བ་དང་། རྗེས་སུ་གཟུང་བར་འཚལ་གྱིས། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Here in this land we will fully guard, nurture, and uphold the Buddha’s teaching and the stūpa that is the domain of the thus-gone ones.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.226.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་ཀྱང་བདག་ཅག་རྣམས་ལ་མཐུ་བསྟང་དུ་གསོལ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Blessed One, please endow us with strength!</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.226.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ཅིའི་སླད་དུ་ཞེ་ན། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Why?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.226.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མ་འོངས་པ་རྩོད་པའི་དུས་ན་བྱིན་གྱིས་བརླབས་བརླབས་པའི་ཡུལ་འདིར་དགྲ་མང་པོ་དང་། མ་དད་པ་དང་། ཕྱིར་རྒོལ་བ་བདེ་བར་གཤེགས་པའི་བསྟན་པ་ལ་དད་པའི་ཁྱད་པར་མི་རྙེད་ཅིང་། བསྟན་པ་གཞིག་པའི་སླད་དུ་བརྩོན་པ་དག་འབྱུང་བའི་སླད་དུའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Because in the future age of conflict, many enemies, faithless people, and adversaries who have yet to gain the special quality of faith in the Well-Gone One’s teaching will come to this blessed land and persistently attempt to destroy the teaching.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.226.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་དེའི་ཚེ་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་ལྷ་དེ་དག་ལ་ལེགས་སོ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་གནང་སྟེ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-011-83"/>The Blessed One then expressed his approval to the gods, saying,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.226.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྐྱེས་བུ་དམ་པ་རྣམས་ལེགས་སོ་ལེགས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Sublime beings, excellent! Excellent!</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.226.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ངས་ཀྱང་ཡུལ་འདི་བྱིན་གྱིས་བརླབས་ཟིན་ཏེ། བྱིན་གྱིས་བརླབས་པ་དེ་ཉིད་ཀྱིས་མཚམས་བཅད་པ་ཡང་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>I have blessed this land and due to those blessings its boundaries have been secured.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.226.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མ་འོངས་པ་རྩོད་པའི་དུས་ན་ཡུལ་འདི་གཞོམ་པའི་ཕྱིར་སུམ་པའི་དམག་ཕལ་མོ་ཆེ་དང་། གྲུ་གུ་རུས་སྣ་ཚོགས་དང་། ཧོར་དང་། གཞན་ཡང་དད་པ་མེད་པ་དག་འོང་བར་འགྱུར་ཏེ</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>In the future age of conflict, great armies of the Sumpa people, different clans of Drugu people, people from Hor, and other faithless people will come to destroy this land.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.226.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེའི་ཚེ་ཡུལ་གཞན་དང་གཞན་དག་ནས་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པའི་གཟུགས་བརྙན་བྱིན་གྱིས་བརླབས་པ་དག་ཡུལ་འདིར་གཤེགས་ནས་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>At that time, blessed images of thus-gone ones will arrive here from other lands and</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.226.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡུལ་གྱི་ས་མཚམས་བསྲུང་བར་མཛད་དེ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>they will guard the land’s borders.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.226.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བསོད་ནམས་ཀྱི་སྟོབས་དེས་ན་ཡུལ་འདི་གཏན་བརླག་པར་མི་འགྱུར་རོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Through the strength of that merit, this land will never be completely destroyed.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.226.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཟུགས་བརྙན་དེ་དག་གི་ཕྱི་བཞིན་དུ་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་དང་། ལྷ་དང་། ཀླུ་མཐུ་སྟོབས་དང་ལྡན་པ་མང་པོ་དག་འོང་ཞིང་ཡུལ་ཡུལ་དུ་གནོད་པ་རྣམས་ཟློག་པར་བྱེད། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Many bodhisattvas, gods, and mighty nāgas will follow these images and they will help avert harm in many regions.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.226.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དགྲ་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་ཡུལ་མི་ཆོམས་པར་བྱེད་དེ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Enemies will be unable to destroy the land.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.226.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བདེ་བ་ཅན་ཞེས་བྱ་བའི་མཁར་ནས་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་བདེ་བའི་འབྱུང་གནས་ཞེས་བྱ་བའི་གཟུགས་བརྙན་གཤེགས་ནས་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>From Blissful Castle an image of the thus-gone Source of Bliss will appear.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.226.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ནུབ་ཕྱོགས་མཁར་ཀོ་ཤེད་དུ་བཞུགས་ཤིང་ཡུལ་གྱི་ས་མཚམས་བསྲུང་བར་འགྱུར་རོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>It will then reside at Koshé Castle<tei:note xml:id="UT22084-076-011-84"/> and thereby guard the borders of the land. </seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.227.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱང་ཕྱོགས་ཡུལ་ཤེ་ན་ཞ་ཞེས་བྱ་བའི་དེ་བཞིན་<tei:ref folio="F.227.a"/>གཤེགས་པའི་གཟུགས་བརྙན་ཤེ་ན་ཞ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་སའི་འོག་ནས་འབྱུང་བར་འགྱུར་ཞིང་ཡུལ་གྱི་ས་མཚམས་བསྲུང་བར་འགྱུར་རོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>In the northern lands, an image called Shenazha of the thus-gone Shenazha will emerge from underground and guard the land’s borders.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.227.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པའི་གཟུགས་བརྙན་ཀིའུ་ལང་ཞེས་བྱ་བར་གཤེགས་ནས་ཤར་ཕྱོགས་ཡུལ་ཕྱེ་མ་ཞེས་བྱ་བའི་མཁར་དུ་ཞུགས་ཤིང་ཡུལ་གྱི་ས་མཚམས་བསྲུང་བར་འགྱུར་རོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>An image of the Thus-Gone One, called Kiulang, will appear and reside in the eastern region at Sand Castle and guard the land’s borders.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.227.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པའི་གཟུགས་བརྙན་ཕྱི་སེ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་གཤེགས་ནས། བྱང་ཕྱོགས་ཀྱི་རི་གླང་རུ་ལ་འོད་སྲུང་གི་མཆོད་རྟེན་གྱི་དྲུང་དུ་བཞུགས་ཤིང་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>An image of the Thus-Gone One, called Chisé, will appear and remain in front of Kāśyapa’s stūpa on Mount Gośṛṅga in the north.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.227.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དགེ་སློང་དགོན་པ་པ་རྣམས་ཀྱི་དགེ་བའི་རྩ་བ་བསྐྱེད་ཅིང་། དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པའི་བསྟན་པ་དང་། ཡུལ་གྱི་ས་མཚམས་བསྲུང་བར་འགྱུར་རོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>It will generate roots of virtue for the monks living in hermitages there and will guard the Thus-Gone One’s teaching and the land’s borders.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.227.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མཁར་དགེ་བ་ཅན་ཞེས་བྱ་བའི་ནང་ན་ཚོང་འདུས་ཀ་ས་དི་ཟེ་ཞེས་བྱ་བར་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པའི་གཟུགས་བརྙན་རྒྱལ་པོའི་ཕོ་བྲང་གནས་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་བཞུགས་ཤིང་མཁར་དགེ་བ་ཡུལ་དང་བཅས་པའི་ས་མཚམས་བསྲུང་བར་འགྱུར་རོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>In Virtuous Castle, an image of the Thus-Gone One, called Abiding in the Royal Palace, will remain in the Kasadizé market and guard Virtuous Castle and the borders of its land.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.227.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ས་གཞི་ཉོ་མོ་ཉ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་གང་དུ་རྒྱལ་པོ་ཡོ་ལ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་ས་མཁར་བརྩིག་པའི་གྲོས་བྱེད་པར་འགྱུར་བ་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>King Yola will discuss plans to build a castle on the land called Nyomonya.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.227.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེར་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པའི་གཟུགས་བརྙན་ཅུ་གོན་པ་ན་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་བཞུགས་ཤིང་མཁར་དགེ་བ་ཅན་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་ཡུལ་དང་བཅས་པའི་ས་མཚམས་བསྲུང་བར་འགྱུར་རོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>There, an image of the Thus-Gone One, called Chugönpana, will abide and guard Virtuous Castle and the borders of its land.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.227.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཙུག་ལག་ཁང་དི་ན་ཛྱ་ཞེས་བྱ་བར་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་མར་མེ་མཛད་ཀྱི་གཟུགས་བརྙན་ཐོར་ཁོང་དུ་བྱས་པ་གཤེགས་པར་འགྱུར་ཏེ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-011-85"/>“In Dinadzya Temple a cast image<tei:note xml:id="UT22084-076-011-86"/> of the thus-gone Dīpaṅkara will arrive.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.227.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཟུགས་བརྙན་དེ་ནི་འཛམ་བུའི་གླིང་གི་གཟུགས་བརྙན་ཐོར་ཁོང་དུ་བྱས་པ་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱི་ཐོག་མར་འབྱུང་བ་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>This image will be the first cast image made in Jambudvīpa.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.227.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཟུགས་བརྙན་དེ་ལ་མི་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་ནི་མཚན་བཀོར་བའི་མར་མེ་མཛད་ཅེས་བྱ་བར་འདོགས་པར་འགྱུར་ཏེ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>People will name this image ‘the circulating Dīpaṅkara.’</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.227.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནི་ལི་ཡུལ་གྱི་གཟུགས་བརྙན་ཐོར་ཁོང་དུ་བྱེད་པ་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱི་དཔེར་འབྱུང་ཞིང་། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>It will become an example for all other cast images made throughout Khotan and</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.227.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བདེ་བར་གཤེགས་པའི་བསྟན་པ་ཡུལ་དང་བཅས་པ་ཡོངས་སུ་བསྲུང་བར་འགྱུར་རོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>it will guard the Well-Gone One’s teaching and the land.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.227.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཞན་ཡང་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་རིན་ཆེན་མང་གི་གཟུགས་བརྙན་ཡུལ་འདིའི་དབུས་སུ་གཤེགས་ནས་ཕྱོགས་བཅུའི་མཚམས་གཅད་པར་མཛད་དེ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Moreover, an image of the thus-gone Prabhūtaratna will come to the center of the land and secure the boundaries in all ten directions.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.227.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཇི་སྲིད་དུ་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པའི་གཟུགས་བརྙན་ཕྱོགས་ཕྱོགས་ན་བཞུགས་པ་<tei:ref folio="F.227.b"/>དེ་དག་མཆོད་གནས་སུ་བྱེད་པ་དེ་སྲིད་དུ་ཡུལ་འདི་བརླག་པར་མི་འགྱུར་རོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>For as long as images of the thus-gone ones abide in the various directions and are venerated, this land will not be destroyed.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.227.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡུལ་འདི་ནས་སྐྱེས་པའི་མིའམ། ཡུལ་གཞན་ནས་སྐྱེས་པའི་མི་ལ་ལ་ཞིག་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པའི་གཟུགས་བརྙན་དེ་དག་ལ་སྙིང་ཐག་པ་ནས་དད་པ་དང་གུས་པ་དང་རབ་ཏུ་དང་བར་བྱེད་ཅིང་། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>If the people born in this land, or people from other lands feel heartfelt faith and devotion for these images of the thus-gone ones, feel deeply inspired by them, and</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.227.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདི་སྙམ་དུ་བདེ་བར་གཤེགས་པའི་གཟུགས་བརྙན་འདི་དག་ནི་ཡུལ་འདི་བསྲུང་བའི་སླད་དུ་གཤེགས་སོ་སྙམ་དུ་ཡང་སེམས་ན། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>think, “These images of the thus-gone ones have come here to guard this land,”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.227.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཟུགས་བརྙན་དེ་དག་ཀྱང་སངས་རྒྱས་བཞུགས་པ་བཞིན་དུ་དོན་མཛད་པར་འགྱུར་རོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>the images will benefit them as if they were the Buddha in person.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.227.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ཅིའི་ཕྱིར་ཞེ་ན། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Why?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.227.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཟུགས་བརྙན་དེ་དག་ང་དང་དུས་གསུམ་དུ་གཏོགས་པའི་སངས་རྒྱས་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱིས་བྱིན་གྱིས་བརླབས་པའི་ཕྱིར་རོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Because these images are blessed by me and by all the buddhas of the three times.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.227.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཞན་ཡང་ཡུལ་འདིར་ངའི་གཟུགས་བརྙན་ཆེན་པོ་ཤིང་རྟས་འདྲེན་པ་བྱས་ཏེ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-011-87"/>“Furthermore, a large image of me will be brought to this land by chariot.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.227.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མཁར་དགེ་བ་ཅན་ཞེས་བྱ་བའི་ནང་དུ་བཞག་ནས་མཆོད་གནས་ཆེན་པོར་བྱེད་པར་འགྱུར་རོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>It will be installed in Virtuous Castle and be taken as a major object of veneration.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.227.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེས་ན་ཡུལ་འདིར་ཕྱོགས་དང་ཕྱོགས་མཚམས་ནས་ཚོང་དཔོན་ཆེན་པོ་རྣམས་འོང་བར་འགྱུར་ཞིང་གནོད་པ་རྣམས་ཀྱང་ཞི་བར་འགྱུར་རོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>As a result, wealthy merchants from other lands in all directions will come here and all negative forces will be pacified.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.227.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཞན་ཡང་ཡུལ་འདིར་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པའི་གཟུགས་བརྙན་ཉིས་བརྒྱ་རྩ་བརྒྱད་འོད་སྲུང་གི་མཆོད་རྟེན་དང་བཅས་པར་འབྱུང་བར་འགྱུར་ཏེ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Two hundred and eight images of the thus-gone ones, together with the Kāśyapa stūpa, will appear in this land.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.227.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་དག་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱང་ཆོ་འཕྲུལ་ཆེན་པོ་སྟོན་ཅིང་སེམས་ཅན་རྣམས་ཀྱི་སྡིག་པ་ཆེན་པོ་ཡོངས་སུ་སྦྱོང་བ་དང་། གནོད་པ་སེལ་བར་མཛད་པར་འགྱུར་རོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Each of them will display great miracles, purify the grave misdeeds of sentient beings, and dispel negative forces.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.227.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡུལ་འདིར་གནོད་པ་དང་། འཇིགས་པ་དང་། སྐྲག་པ་འགའ་ཞིག་བྱུང་ན་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-011-88"/>“If it so happens that some negative forces and causes of fear and terror do appear in this land,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.227.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡུལ་འདིའི་ཆེད་དུ་ཕྱོགས་ལྔར་སྦྱོར་བ་བྱས་ཏེ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>people should resort to the five regions for the sake of the country.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.227.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྒྱལ་པོ་དང་བློན་པོ་རྣམས་ཡུལ་འཛིན་པ་གང་ཞིག་འཇིགས་པ་དང་བྲལ་བར་བྱ་བའི་ཕྱིར་བདེ་བར་གཤེགས་པའི་བསྟན་པ་ལས་བསོད་ནམས་བསྐྱེད་པར་འདོད་ན་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>If the king, or the ministers and governors of the land wish to create merit through the Well-Gone One’s teachings in order to free the land from fear,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.227.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཙུག་ལག་ཁང་ཚར་མ་ཞེས་བྱ་བར་བསོད་ནམས་བྱའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>they should create merit at Tsarma Temple.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.227.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ཅིའི་ཕྱིར་ཞེ་ན། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Why?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.227.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡུལ་འདིའི་མི་རྣམས་ཀྱི་དད་པ་དང་། ཡང་དག་པའི་ལྟ་བ་ནི་དང་པོའི་གཙུག་ལག་ཁང་དེ་ནས་སྐྱེ་བར་འགྱུར་རོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Because the faith and correct view of the people of this land are born in that temple.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.227.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ནམ་ཞིག་ལིའི་རྒྱལ་པོ་དང་། བློན་པོ་དང་། ཡུལ་འཛིན་པ་རྣམས་ལ་གནོད་པ་རྣམ་པ་སྣ་ཚོགས་ཤིག་བྱུང་ན། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>If at some point the king, or the ministers and governors of Khotan are faced with many kinds of negative forces,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.228.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རི་གླང་རུ་ལ་སྔོན་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་སངས་རྒྱས་གང་ན་བཞུགས་བཞུགས་པའི་གཞི་དེ་ལ་བསྐོར་<tei:ref folio="F.228.a"/>བར་བྱའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>they should circumambulate Mount Gośṛṅga—that place where in the past the perfect buddhas were seated. </seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.228.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡུལ་འདིའི་སེམས་ཅན་རྣམས་ལས་མི་དགེ་བ་འཆགས་པར་འདོད་ན་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>If the people of this land wish to purify their negative karma,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.228.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མཆོད་རྟེན་གོ་མ་ས་ལ་གན་དའི་དྲུང་དུ་བཤགས་པར་བྱའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>they should make confessions before the Gomasalaganda stūpa.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.228.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ཅིའི་ཕྱིར་ཞེ་ན། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Why?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.228.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མཆོད་རྟེན་དེ་ནི་སངས་རྒྱས་བཞུགས་པ་བཞིན་དུ་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Because this stūpa is like the buddha in person;</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.228.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་དག་གིས་བསྐོར་བའམ། མེ་ཏོག་གམ། བདུག་པའམ། དབྱངས་སམ། རོལ་མོའི་སྒྲས་མཆོད་པ་བྱས་ན་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>whoever circumambulates it, or venerates it with flowers, incense, song, or music</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.228.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེའི་མཚམས་མེད་པ་ལྔ་ཡང་ཉམས་དམས་པར་འགྱུར་ནགཞན་ལྟ་སྨོས་ཀྱང་ཅི་དགོས། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>can diminish even the five inexpiable deeds, not to mention other negative acts.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.228.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡུལ་འདིའི་རྒྱལ་པོ་དང་། བློན་པོ་དང་། ཡུལ་འཛིན་པ་གང་ཞིག་བརྟུལ་ཞུགས་ཆེན་པོའི་སྡོམ་པ་ལེན་པར་འདོད་པ་དེས་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>If the king, ministers, and governors of this land wish to take a vow of great discipline,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.228.a</prop>
            <prop name="alternative-source"/>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>!རི་གླང་རུ་ལ་གང་ན་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པའི་གཟུགས་བརྙན་པི་སེ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་དང་། འོད་སྲུང་གི་མཆོད་རྟེན་ཡོད་པ་དེའི་དགེ་འདུན་ལས་མནོད་པར་བྱའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>they should take such a vow from the saṅgha<tei:note xml:id="UT22084-076-011-89"/> at Mount Gośṛṅga, where the Thus-Gone One’s image called Chisé<tei:note xml:id="UT22084-076-011-275"/> and the Kāśyapa stūpa are.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.228.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ཅིའི་ཕྱིར་ཞེ་ན། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Why?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.228.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡུལ་འདིར་ཆོས་ཀྱི་སྤྱོད་པ་ཡོངས་སུ་རྫོགས་པ་དང་། ཚུལ་ཁྲིམས་ཡོངས་སུ་དག་པ་ནི་དེ་ནས་འབྱུང་བར་འགྱུར་བའི་ཕྱིར་རོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Because in this land, perfect Dharma conduct<tei:note xml:id="UT22084-076-011-90"/> and impeccable discipline will arise there.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.228.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡུལ་འདིའི་མི་ལ་ལ་ཞིག་ཆད་པ་ཆེན་པོ་ཞིག་ལ་ཐུག་ན་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>If some people in this land find themselves facing grave privation,<tei:note xml:id="UT22084-076-011-91"/>
                </seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.228.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེས་རི་གླང་རུ་ལ་གནས་པའི་འཕགས་པའི་དགེ་འདུན་ལ་སྐྱབས་སུ་འགྲོ་བར་བྱས་ཏེ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>they should go for refuge to the noble saṅgha living at Mount Gośṛṅga.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.228.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེས་ན་ཆད་པ་དེ་ལས་ཐར་བར་འགྱུར་རོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Thereby they will be freed from their privation.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.228.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ཅིའི་ཕྱིར་ཞེ་ན། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Why?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.228.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གནས་དེ་ན་ཐར་པ་ཐོབ་པ་སྟོང་ཕྲག་དུ་མ་ཕྱི་མའི་མཐའི་བར་དུ་གནས་ཤིང་མི་སྟོངས་པའི་ཕྱིར་རོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Because many thousands of people will gain liberation in that locale and it will remain until the end of time and not disappear.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.228.a</prop>
            <prop name="alternative-source"/>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>!རྒྱུ་དེས་ན་རི་གླང་རུ་དང་མཆོད་རྟེན་གོ་མ་ས་ལ་གན་ད་ཡུལ་དང་བཅས་པ་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་རྣམས་ཀྱི་ཆང་བྱུ་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>For these reasons, Mount Gośṛṅga, the Gomasalaganda stūpa, and its land are the site where the thus-gone ones assemble.”<tei:note xml:id="UT22084-076-011-92"/>
                </seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.228.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་དེའི་ཚེ་ཕྱོགས་བཅུའི་སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱི་ཞིང་དག་ནས་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཉི་ཁྲི་ལྷགས་ནས། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-011-93"/>At that moment, twenty thousand bodhisattvas arrived from the buddha realms in the ten directions.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.228.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་གང་ན་བ་དེ་ལོགས་སུ་ཐལ་མོ་སྦྱར་བ་བཏུད་དེ་དབྱངས་གཅིག་ཏུ་འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་གསོལ་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They bowed toward the Blessed One with palms joined, and in a single voice said,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.228.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་བདག་ཅག་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་ཀྱང་ཐབས་སྣ་ཚོགས་ཀྱིས་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པའི་སྤྱོད་ཡུལ་དང་ཡུལ་འདི་ཡོངས་སུ་བསྐྱང་བར་བགྱི། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Blessed One, we too will sustain and guard this land and the Thus-Gone One’s domain of activities<tei:note xml:id="UT22084-076-011-94"/> here in a variety of ways.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.228.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བསྲུང་བར་བགྱི་ཞིང་ཇི་སྲིད་དུ་བདེ་བར་གཤེགས་པའི་བསྟན་པ་དང་། དཀོན་མཆོག་གསུམ་ལ་གནས་ཤིང་། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>For as long as the Well-Gone One’s teachings and the Three Jewels remain, and</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.228.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྒྱལ་པོ་དང་བློན་པོ་ལ་སོགས་པ་མིའི་ཚུལ་ཁྲིམས་དང་ལྡན་པ་དད་པ་ཅན་དང་། ཡུལ་ཆོས་དང་འཐུན་པར་བགྱིད་པ་མཆིས་པ་དེ་སྲིད་དུ་ཡོངས་སུ་མི་<tei:ref folio="F.228.b"/>གཏང་ཞིང་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>for as long as the kings, ministers, and others maintain discipline, have faith, and rule the land in accord with the Dharma, we will not forsake this land. </seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.228.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡུལ་འདིར་དུས་དུས་སྤྱོད་ལམ་དང་ཆ་ལུགས་ཅི་དང་ཇི་ལྟ་བུས་སེམས་ཅན་མང་པོའི་བསོད་ནམས་ཆེན་པོ་ཡོངས་སུ་སྨིན་པར་འགྱུར་བ་དང་། སངས་རྒྱས་ཉིད་དུ་སེམས་བསྐྱེད་པར་འགྱུར་བ་དང་། བསམ་གཏན་དང་། ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་ལ་སྙོམས་པར་འཇུག་པར་འགྱུར་བ་དང་། སངས་རྒྱས་ཉིད་ལས་ཕྱིར་མི་ལྡོག་པར་འགྱུར་བ་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>We will continue to come here and, assuming whatever behavior and attire may be appropriate, we will fully ripen vast merit in a great number of beings, generate within them the wish to attain buddhahood, help them rest in concentration and absorption, and establish them irreversibly in buddhahood.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.228.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ལྟ་བུའི་སྐྱེ་བ་བླང་བའི་སླད་དུ་ཁ་ཅིག་གིས་ནི་རྒྱལ་རིགས་ཡོངས་སུ་གཟུང་བར་བགྱི། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>In order to take these kinds of rebirth, some will take birth in the royal line,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.228.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཁ་ཅིག་གིས་ནི་རབ་ཏུ་བྱུང་བ་དང་། ཁྱིམ་པ་གཞན་གྱི་ཆ་ལུགས་ཡོངས་སུ་གཟུང་བར་བགྱིའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>some will take ordination, while still others will assume the attire of householders.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.228.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་བཀའ་སྩལ་པ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-011-95"/>The Blessed One replied,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.228.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རིགས་ཀྱི་བུ་ལེགས་སོ་ལེགས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Noble children, excellent! Excellent!</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.228.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རིགས་ཀྱི་བུ་ཁྱེད་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་འདི་ལྟར་བསྐལ་པ་བཟང་པོའི་སངས་རྒྱས་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱི་སྤྱོད་ཡུལ་དང་ཡུལ་འདི་གང་དུ་སེམས་ཅན་རྣམས་སངས་རྒྱས་ཉིད་ལས་ཕྱིར་མི་ལྡོག་པར་འགྱུར་བ་དེ་ལྟ་བུར་ཆུ་གང་ཐོབ་ཤིག །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Noble children, may you gain the strength to do this—to ensure that all sentient beings within this land, the domain of all the buddhas of the Excellent Eon, proceed irreversibly to buddhahood!”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.228.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡང་དེའི་ཚེ་ལྷ་རྣམ་ཐོས་ཀྱི་བུ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་དང་། མི་ཕམ་པ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་ལ་སོགས་པ་ལྷ་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱིས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ལ་འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་གསོལ་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-011-96"/>The gods Vaiśravaṇa and Ajita, together with all of the other gods present, then said to the Blessed One,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.228.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ད་ནི་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོ་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་ཡུལ་འདི་བསྲུང་བའི་སླད་དུ་མཐུ་བསྟངས་པ་དང་། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Blessed One, please imbue these bodhisattva great beings with strength so that they may guard this land.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.228.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་བྱིན་གྱིས་བརླབས་པ་དང་མཐུས་བདག་ཅག་གིས་ཀྱང་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པའི་སྤྱོད་ཡུལ་དང་། བྱིན་གྱིས་བརླབས་བརླབས་པའི་ཡུལ་འདི་ཀུན་ཏུ་བསྲུང་ཞིང་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Blessed One, through your blessings and power we too will guard the thus-gone ones’ domain and this land that has been blessed.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.228.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡལ་བར་མི་གཏང་བར་བགྱི་བའི་སླད་དུ་བརྩོན་འགྲུས་ཆེན་པོའི་ཤུགས་ཀྱིས་འབད་པར་འཚལ་ལོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>We will not let it disappear. We will exert ourselves in this with great perseverance.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.228.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གལ་ཏེ་ཡུལ་འདིར་གྲུ་གུ་ལ་སོགས་པ་གཏུམ་པོ་དད་པ་མ་མཆིས་པ་རྣམས་དང་། ཧོར་དང་། སུམ་པའི་དམག་དག་མཆི་བར་འགྱུར་ན། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>If wild people, such as the faithless Drugu, or if armies from Hor and Sumpa come here,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.228.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་དག་ཕན་ཚུན་ནང་འཁྲུག་འབྱུང་བ་དང་། དེ་དག་གི་འཁོར་ནང་མི་འཐུན་པར་འགྱུར་བ་དང་། འགུམ་པར་འགྱུར་བར་བགྱིའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>we will cause infighting between them, incite discord within their own troops, and make them perish.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.228.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡང་ན་དེ་དག་ཅི་ནས་ཀྱང་འདིར་མཆི་ཞིང་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པའི་བསྟན་པ་འཇིག་མི་ནུས་པར་བགྱི་བའི་སླད་དུ་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Alternatively, to ensure that they do not come here under any circumstances, so that they are unable to destroy the Thus-Gone One’s teachings,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.228.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཞན་གྱི་དབང་དུ་འགྱུར་བར་བགྱིའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>we will cause them to fall under the control of others.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.229.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གལ་ཏེ་རྒྱའི་དམག་དག་མཆིས་པར་གྱུར་ན་དེ་དག་གི་སེམས་དད་པར་བགྱི་ཞིང་། སླར་ཡུལ་འདི་ལ་ཕན་<tei:ref folio="F.229.a"/>འདོགས་པ་དང་ཕྱིས་ཡུལ་འདིར་བསོད་ནམས་བྱ་བའི་དངོས་པོ་དགེ་བ་རྒྱ་ཆེན་པོ་བགྱིད་དུ་སྩལ་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>If Chinese armies come here, we will inspire them with faith, and ensure that they bring benefit to this land and in the future create great virtue through performing meritorious deeds here. </seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.229.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ནམ་ཞིག་ཡུལ་འདིའི་སེམས་ཅན་རྣམས་ལ་གནོད་པ་བགྱིད་པ་དེའི་ཚེ་ན་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>When at some point they inflict harm upon the beings of this land,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.229.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡང་ཕྱིར་དད་པར་བགྱི་ཞིང་། མདོ་འདི་ཡང་ཁོང་དུ་ཆུད་པར་བགྱིད་དུ་སྩལ་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>we will once more engender faith in them and ensure that they comprehend this discourse.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.229.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་གི་ཚེ་དེ་དག་མ་འོངས་པའི་དཀོན་མཆོག་གསུམ་གྱི་ཡོ་བྱད་ལ་དབང་འཚལ་ཞིང་། མངའ་འཕྲོག་པ་དང་། སེམས་ཅན་བསོད་ནམས་དང་ལྡན་པ་རྣམས་ལ་འཚེ་བ་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>When in the future they seek control over the objects of the Three Jewels, seize power, and cause harm to meritorious beings,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.229.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེའི་ཚེ་ནི་བདག་ཅག་གི་འཁོར་གནོད་སྦྱིན་དད་པ་ཅན་དང་དད་པ་མ་མཆིས་པ་དུ་མ་ཞིག་དབང་བསྐུར་ཏེ་བཀྱེ་ནས་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>at that time we will empower and dispatch many of the yakṣas in our retinue—those who have faith as well as some who lack faith—</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.229.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡུལ་དེར་ཅི་ནས་ཀྱང་ཡུན་རིང་ཞིག་གི་བར་དུ་རྒུད་པར་བགྱི་ཞིང་ཡུལ་འདི་འཇིག་མི་ནུས་པར་བགྱི་བའི་སླད་དུ་མུ་གེ་དང་ནད་དང་ཕ་རོལ་གྱི་དམག་མཆི་བར་བགྱིད་དུ་སྩལ་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>[at that time we will empower and dispatch many of the yakṣas in our retinue—those who have faith as well as some who lack faith—]to ensure that prolonged decline occurs in that country, and that they experience famine, disease, and attacks from foreign armies that make them unable to destroy this land.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.229.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལི་ཡུལ་གྱི་ནོར་རྫས་དེ་དག་གིས་འཚལ་བ་རྣམས་ཀྱང་བཀྲ་མི་ཤིས་པར་བགྱི་ཞིང་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Even if they should plunder any wealth from the land of Khotan, we shall ensure that it brings them bad luck.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.229.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གང་དང་གང་དུ་ཕྱིན་པའི་ཡུལ་དེ་ཐམས་ཅད་དུ་ཡང་སྨན་ཡོན་མི་ཐོགས་ཤིང་འཁྲུག་པར་བགྱིའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Whichever country they visit, we will ensure that they are met not with hospitality but with rebellion.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.229.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་དག་གི་ཡུལ་འཛིན་པ་དང་དམག་དཔོན་ཡང་རྒུད་པར་བགྱིའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>We will ensure that their governors and military leaders face decline.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.229.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བོད་ཀྱི་དམག་རྣམས་ལ་ཡང་དེ་བཞིན་དུ་རིག་པར་བགྱི་སྟེ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>It should be known that it will be the same for the Tibetan army.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.229.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་གང་གི་ཚེ་དེ་དག་ཆོས་དང་འཐུན་པར་ཡུལ་འདི་འཛིན་ཅིང་སྲུང་ན་ནི་བདག་ཅག་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་ཀྱང་དེ་དག་ཡོངས་སུ་བསྐྱང་ཞིང་རྒྱལ་བར་འགྱུར་བར་བགྱིའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>When the land is ruled and protected in harmony with the Dharma, we will nurture it and make it victorious.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.229.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ནམ་ཞིག་དེ་དག་བདེ་བར་གཤེགས་པའི་བསྟན་པ་འཇིག་པ་དང་ཡུལ་གྱི་མི་ལ་གནོད་པར་བགྱིད་པ་དེའི་ཚེ་ནི་དམག་རྣམས་ནང་འཁྲུག་འབྱུང་བ་དང་། དམག་གི་དཔོན་པོ་ཡང་ཆེ་ཐང་དུ་རྒུད་པར་བགྱི་སྟེ</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>However, when the Well-Gone One’s teaching is destroyed and the people of the land are harmed, we will ensure that the army will be riven by internal strife and that the military leaders will suffer a great decline.<tei:note xml:id="UT22084-076-011-98"/>
                </seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.229.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྒྱས་པར་ནི་སྔ་མ་བཞིན་ནོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>As for the details, it will occur just as already explained.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.229.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མ་འོངས་པའི་དུས་ན་ཡུལ་འདིའི་རྒྱལ་པོ་དང་བློན་པོ་སེམས་གྱ་གྱུ་ཅན། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-011-99"/>“In the future, there will be some kings and ministers of this land who will be full of deceit.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.229.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བསོད་ནམས་ཆུང་བ་དང་། དད་པ་མེད་པ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They will have little merit and no faith.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.229.a</prop>
            <prop name="alternative-source"/>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>!དཀོན་མཆོག་གསུམ་གྱི་དཀོར་ལ་འཇོལ་ཉག་ཏུ་རློམ་ཞིང་། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They will lust insatiably<tei:note xml:id="UT22084-076-011-100"/> after the property of the Three Jewels.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.229.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡུལ་གྱི་རྩིས་མགོ་དང་འགལ་བར་བགྱིད་པ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They will contravene the rules of the country.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.229.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ནོར་རྫས་མ་བརྟགས་པས་གོ་འཕང་ཚོལ་ལ་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They will pursue grandeur without paying attention to their wealth, and</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.229.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སེམས་ཅན་བསོད་ནམས་དང་ལྡན་པ་རྣམས་ལ་སུན་འབྱིན་ཏུ་རྒོལ་བ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>they will oppose those with merit by discrediting them.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.229.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ངོ་ཚ་མེད་པ། མངན་དུས་ཅན། འདོད་པའི་ཡོན་ཏན་གྱིས་ངོམས་མི་མྱོང་བ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They will be shameless, flawed, and insatiable when it comes to sensual pleasures.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.229.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རབ་ཏུ་འབྱུང་བ་དག་གིས་སེམས་སྐྱོ་བ་ལ་ལ་དག་<tei:ref folio="F.229.b"/>འབྱུང་བར་འགྱུར་ན་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They will feel offended by those who have gone forth.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.229.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་དག་ནི་བདག་ཅག་གིས་ཀྱང་ཡུལ་འདི་ནས་དབྱུང་ཞིང་ཡུལ་ངན་པ་གཞན་དང་གཞན་དག་ཏུ་སྤྱུགས་པར་བགྱི་སྟེ</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>When these things happen we will drive them out from this land and expel them to other inferior lands.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.229.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཚུལ་དེ་ལྟ་བུས་ཡུལ་འདི་ཡོངས་སུ་བསྐྱང་བ་དང་བསྲུང་བར་བགྱིའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>In these ways, we will sustain and guard this land.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.229.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་སླད་མ་རྩོད་པའི་དུས་ན་ཡུལ་འདི་གཞིག་པར་བརྩོན་པའི་སེམས་ཅན་བདུད་ཀྱི་ཕྱོགས་སྡིག་པ་བགྱིད་པ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-011-101"/>“Blessed One, in the future, during the age of conflict, there will appear demonic beings who will seek to destroy this land.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.229.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མཐུ་སྟོབས་དང་ལྡན་པ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>[<tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-011-101"/>“Blessed One, in the future, during the age of conflict, there will appear demonic beings who will seek to destroy this land.] These evildoers will be powerful.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.229.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡུལ་དག་ཏུ་སེམས་ཅན་རྣམས་ཀྱི་དད་པ་ཟློག་པར་བགྱིད་པ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They will cause beings throughout the lands to lose their faith.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.229.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སེམས་གདུག་ཅིང་བརླང་བའི་ལྷ་དང་། ཀླུ་དང་། གནོད་སྦྱིན་དང་། སྲིན་པོ་དུ་མ་ཞིག་འབྱུང་བར་འགྱུར་ལ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>There will be many of them—gods, nāgas, yakṣas, and rākṣasas—all with wicked and savage minds.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.229.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་དག་ཀྱང་བདག་ཅག་གི་དབང་དུ་མི་འགྱུར་ན་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>If we are unable to bring these beings under our control,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.229.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ལ་བདག་ཅག་གིས་ཐབས་ཇི་ལྟར་འཚལ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>to what means should we turn?”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.229.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་བཀའ་སྩལ་པ། རིགས་ཀྱི་བུ་ཁྱེད་ཡིད་སྐྱོ་བར་མ་བྱེད་ཅིག །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-011-102"/>“Noble children,” the Blessed One replied, “do not be disheartened.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.229.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ཅིའི་ཕྱིར་ཞེ་ན། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Why not?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.229.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གླིང་བཞི་པ་འདི་ན་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་རྣམས་དང་། ལྷ་མཐུ་སྟོབས་ཆེ་བ་དང་། ཀླུ་དང་། གནོད་སྦྱིན་ས་ཐོབ་པ་དུ་མ་ཞིག་གནས་པ་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>In this world of the four continents there live many bodhisattvas, mighty gods, nāgas, and yakṣas who have attained the levels.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.229.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་དག་ལ་སེམས་འཇམ་པོས་མཆོད་པ་ཆེན་པོ་བྱས་ཏེ</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Make elaborate offerings to them with a gentle state of mind, and</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.229.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མཆོད་རྟེན་གོ་མ་ས་ལ་གན་ད་དང་། གཙུག་ལག་ཁང་ཚར་མ་ལ་སོགས་པ་ཡུལ་བྱིན་གྱིས་བརླབས་བརླབས་པ་རྣམས་སུ་ཐེག་པ་ཆེན་པོའི་སྡེ་སྣོད་ཤེས་རབ་ཀྱི་ཕ་རོལ་ཏུ་ཕྱིན་པ་དང་། འདུས་པ་ཆེན་པོ་དང་། སངས་རྒྱས་ཕལ་པོ་ཆེ་དང་། དཀོན་མཆོག་བརྩེགས་པ་ལ་སོགས་པ་ཤིན་དུ་རྒྱས་པའི་སྡེ་མང་པོ་ལྷོགས་ཤིག་དང་། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>at blessed places, such as the Gomasalaganda stūpa and the Tsarma Temple, you should resound a great number of the extensive Great Vehicle discourses, such as the Perfection of Wisdom, the Great Assembly, the Ornaments of the Buddhas, and the Heap of Jewels.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.229.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡུལ་སོ་སོ་ནས་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་ས་བཅུ་པ་ལ་སོགས་པ་དང་། མཐུ་སྟོབས་ཆེ་བའི་སེམས་ཅན་དེ་དག་ཡུལ་འདིར་འོངས་ནས་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Bodhisattvas on the ten levels—such beings with power and might— from other lands will then come to this land.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.229.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཆོས་ཀྱི་རོ་མནོས་ཤིང་དུས་གསུམ་དུ་གཏོགས་པའི་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་རྣམས་ཀྱི་དམ་ཚིག་ལས་མི་འགལ་བར་བྱེད། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Here they will let beings savor the taste of the Dharma and ensure they do not transgress the commitments of the thus-gone ones of the three times.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.229.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བསྐལ་པ་བཟང་པོའི་སངས་རྒྱས་རྣམས་ཀྱི་སྤྱོད་ཡུལ་དང་ཡུལ་ཡང་སྲུང་བར་བྱེད། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They will guard the domain and the land of the buddhas of the Excellent Eon.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.229.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡུལ་འདིའི་མི་དང་བསྟན་པ་ཡང་སྲུང་བར་བྱེད་པར་འགྱུར་རོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They will also guard the people and teachings in this land.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.229.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཞན་ཡང་མ་འོངས་པའི་དུས་ན་ཡུལ་དགེ་བ་འདིའི་རྒྱལ་པོ་མཐུ་ཆུང་བར་འགྱུར་ཏེ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-011-103"/>“Moreover, in the future, the king of this land Virtue will grow weak, and</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.229.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མཐུ་ཆུང་བ་དེས་ན་རང་གི་མཐུ་སྟོབས་ཀྱིས་ཡུལ་མི་ཐུབ་པས་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>this infirmity will render him unable to rule the land independently. As a result,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.230.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྒྱལ་པོ་དད་པ་ཅན་གཞན་འདི་ལྟ་སྟེ། བོད་ཀྱི་རྒྱལ་པོ་དང་། <tei:ref folio="F.230.a"/>རྒྱའི་རྒྱལ་པོ་ལ་སོགས་པ་ལ་སྐྱབས་བཙལ་ནས་ཡུལ་སྲུང་བར་བྱེད་དོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>the king will seek protection from other faithful monarchs, such as the Tibetan and Chinese kings, and they will proceed to protect the land. </seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.230.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ཅིའི་ཕྱིར་ཞེ་ན། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Why?</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.230.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མ་འོངས་པའི་དུས་ན་རྒྱ་དང་བོད་ཀྱི་ཡུལ་དུ་དཀོན་མཆོག་གསུམ་གནས་ཤིང་མཆོད་གནས་ཆེན་པོར་བྱེད་པ་དང་། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Because in the future, the Three Jewels will be present and widely venerated in the lands of China and Tibet.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.230.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡུལ་དེ་དག་ཀྱང་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོའི་གནས་སུ་འགྱུར་ཞིང་། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Those lands will also become the abodes of bodhisattva great beings.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.230.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སེམས་ཅན་དེ་དག་ཀྱང་བྱང་ཆུབ་ཆེན་པོའི་ལམ་ཚོལ་བའི་ངང་ཚུལ་ཅན་ཐེག་པ་ཆེན་པོ་ལ་དད་པ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The people in those lands will pursue the path of great awakening, have faith in the Great Vehicle, and</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.230.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་ལ་གཞོལ་བར་འགྱུར་ཏེ</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>exert themselves in meditative absorption.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.230.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་དག་གི་མཐུ་སྟོབས་ཀྱིས་ལི་ཡུལ་གྱི་མི་དང་། དཀོན་མཆོག་གསུམ་བརླག་པར་མི་འགྱུར་རོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Through their power and might, the people of Khotan and the Three Jewels will not be destroyed.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.230.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྐྱེས་བུ་དམ་པ་ཁྱེད་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་ཀྱང་བོད་དང་རྒྱའི་རྒྱལ་པོ་དང་བློན་པོ་དག་ཅི་ནས་ཀྱང་མཆོད་རྟེན་གོ་མ་ས་ལ་གན་ད་དང་། ཡུལ་དགེ་བ་འདི་ལ་རི་མོ་བྱེད་པར་འགྱུར་བ་དང་། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-011-104"/>“All of you sublime beings, you must also by all means ensure that the kings and ministers of Tibet and China pay service to the Gomasalaganda stūpa and this land of Virtue.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.230.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡུལ་འདིར་བསོད་ནམས་བྱ་བའི་དངོས་པོ་དགེ་བ་རྒྱ་ཆེན་པོ་བྱེད་པར་འགྱུར་བ་དང་། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>You must cause them to perform extensive virtue through meritorious acts.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.230.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡུལ་འདིའི་མི་ཉི་འོག་དད་པ་མེད་པའི་ཡུལ་གཞན་དུ་འཁྱམས་པ་རྣམས་ཀྱང་སྡུག་བསྔལ་དང་དབྲལ་ཞིང་བདེ་བར་རང་གི་ཡུལ་དུ་བསྐྱལ་ནས་ཕྱིར་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>When people from this land travel to foreign border lands where people lack faith, you must relieve them of their suffering and ensure their easy return to their homeland. Thus,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.230.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡང་དག་པའི་ལྟ་བ་ཅན་དང་། བསོད་ནམས་ལ་དགའ་བར་འགྱུར་བར་སེམས་སྒྱུར་ཅིག་དང་། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>you should transform their minds so they come to adopt the correct view and take delight in merit.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.230.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དགེ་བའི་རྩ་བ་དེའི་སྟོབས་ཀྱིས་སྐྱེས་བུ་དམ་པ་ཁྱེད་རྣམས་ཀྱི་དགེ་བའི་རྩ་བ་དང་། མདངས་དང་། གཟི་བརྗིད་དང་། འཁོར་འཕེལ་བར་འགྱུར་ཞིང་སངས་རྒྱས་ཉིད་དུ་ཡང་ཉེ་བར་འགྱུར་གྱིས། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Through the strength of these roots of virtue, sublime beings, your roots of virtue, and your luster, splendor, and retinues will increase and you will draw closer and closer to buddhahood.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.230.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དུས་གསུམ་དུ་གཏོགས་པའི་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་རྣམས་ཀྱི་གདམས་ངག་ལ་བྱས་པ་གཟོ་བར་གྱིས་ཤིག །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Repay the kindness of the instructions of the thus-gone ones of the three times!</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.230.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདི་ལྟར་ཡུལ་འདིའི་སེམས་ཅན་རྣམས་ནི་ཕྱིར་མི་ལྡོག་པ་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའི་ལས་དང་ལྡན་པ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>In this way, the people of this land will adopt the bodhisattva deeds that make them irreversible.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.230.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སྙིང་རྗེ་དང་ལྡན་པ། བདེན་པ་དང་ལྡན་པ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They will possess compassion and truth.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.230.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཏོང་ཕོད་པ། ཕྲག་དོག་དང་འཁོན་དུ་འཛིན་པ་རྣམ་པར་སྤངས་པ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They will be generous, free of jealousy and resentment,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.230.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱས་པ་གཟོ་བ། ཆོས་ལ་དགའ་བ། ཡང་དག་པའི་ལྟ་བ་ཅན། ལོག་པར་ལྟ་བ་ཐམས་ཅད་རྣམ་པར་སྤངས་པ། སེམས་འཇམ་པར་འགྱུར་ཏེ</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>have gratitude, delight in the Dharma, have the correct view, be free of all wrong views, and be gentle-minded.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.230.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྒྱུ་དེས་ན་དགེ་བ་རྣམས་ཞེས་བྱའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Because of this they shall be called people from the land of Virtue.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.230.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡུལ་འདིའི་མཁར་ཡང་མི་བྱམས་པ་དང་འཇམ་པའི་སེམས་དང་ལྡན་པ་རྣམས་དང་། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Even the castle in this land will be filled with loving and gentle-minded people and</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.230.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མཆོད་རྟེན་དང་གཙུག་ལག་ཁང་དུ་མས་བརྒྱན་<tei:ref folio="F.230.b"/>པར་འགྱུར་ཏེ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>adorned with several stūpas and temples. </seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.230.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེའི་ཕྱིར་མཁར་དགེ་བ་ཅན་ཞེས་བྱའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>For that reason, the castle is called Virtuous Castle.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.230.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཞན་ཡང་ཡུལ་གཞན་དག་ནས་སེམས་ཅན་དད་པ་མེད་པ་སྡང་བ་འཁོན་དུ་འཛིན་པ་དག་ཡུལ་འདིར་འོངས་པ་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-011-105"/>“When faithless beings, hostile and antagonistic, come here from other lands,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.230.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཀུན་ཡུལ་འདིའི་རྡུལ་གྱིས་རེག་ཅིང་། ཡུལ་འདི་ནས་འཁྲུངས་པའི་འཚོ་བ་ལ་ལོངས་སྤྱོད་ན་དེ་དག་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱིས་སེམས་བསྒྱུར་ནས་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>their minds will be transformed simply by touching the sand in this region and by partaking of the food grown in this land.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.230.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སེམས་འཇམ་པ་དང་། མཉེན་པ་དང་། བྱམས་པའི་བསམ་པ་དང་། ཁྲོ་བ་དང་འཁོན་དུ་འཛིན་པ་སྤངས་པ་དང་། དད་པ་དང་། ཡང་ཡུལ་འདིའི་སྡིག་པ་མི་བྱེད་པར་འགྱུར་ཏེ</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>They will become gentle, mild, and loving, free of anger and resentment. They will develop faith and they will not perform misdeeds in this land.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.230.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡུལ་འདི་ནི་ཡོན་ཏན་མང་པོ་དེ་དག་དང་ལྡན་པ་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Such are the numerous qualities of this land.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.230.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་དེའི་ཚེ་སྔར་སངས་རྒྱས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་ལན་གསུམ་གྱི་བར་དུ་བྱིན་གྱིས་བརླབས་ནས་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-011-106"/>The Blessed Buddha, having previously blessed the land three times,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.230.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འོད་ཟེར་ཐུགས་རྗེ་ཆེན་པོ་དང་བཅས་ཏེ་བཀྱེ་བ་དེས་ཆུ་ན་གནས་པའི་སེམས་ཅན་རྣམས་ཀྱི་སེམས་ཡོངས་སུ་དག་པ་དང་། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>now emitted light rays infused with great compassion, which purified the minds of all of the beings there who were living in the water and</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.230.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བདེ་བ་དང་ལྡན་པར་བྱས་ནས་ཆུའི་ནང་ནས་སླར་འཐོན་ཏེ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>filled them with happiness. The light then re-emerged from the water and</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.230.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཕྱོགས་བཅུའི་སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱི་ཞིང་ཐམས་ཅད་དུ་ཁྱབ་པར་གྱུར་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>spread out in all the buddha realms in the ten directions.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.230.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡང་འོད་ཟེར་དེ་དག་སླར་ལོག་ནས་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The light rays then returned and</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.230.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོ་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་ཡུལ་བྱིན་གྱིས་བརླབས་པ་དང་། ཉན་ཐོས་ཆེན་པོ་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་ཡུལ་བྱིན་གྱིས་བརླབས་པ་དང་། མཚོའི་ནང་ནས་བྱུང་བའི་པད་མའི་སྟེང་ན་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པའི་གཟུགས་བརྙན་བཞུགས་པ་དེ་དང་དེ་དག་གི་འོད་ཟེར་དང་འདྲེས་ནས་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>merged with the light rays of the places blessed by the bodhisattva great beings, the light rays of the places blessed by the great hearers, and the light rays of the images of the thus-gone ones seated upon the lotuses that had emerged upon the lake.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.230.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ནམ་མཁའ་ལ་འཕགས་ཏེ་སྟེང་གི་ནམ་མཁའ་ཁེབས་པར་གྱུར་ཅིང་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>At that point, the rays exploded upward into the atmosphere, covering the sky above, and</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.230.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལི་ཡུལ་ཐམས་ཅད་དུ་ལྷའི་མེ་ཏོག་གི་ཆར་ཕབ་བོ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>a rain of divine flowers showered down upon the entire land of Khotan.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.230.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལྷའི་མེ་ཏོག་དེ་དག་ཕན་ཚུན་དུ་རེག་པ་ལས་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-011-107"/>As these divine flowers touched one another,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.231.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཆོས་ཀྱི་སྒོ་མོ་འདི་ལྟ་སྟེ། སངས་རྒྱས་དང་། ཆོས་དང་། དགེ་འདུན་གྱི་མཚན་དང་། ཡང་དག་པའི་ལྟ་བ་དང་། ཤེས་རབ་དང་། ཚུལ་ཁྲིམས་དང་། དགེ་བའི་རྩ་བ་དང་། དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་རྣམས་ཀྱི་དཀའ་བ་སྤྱད་པ་དང་། སྨོན་ལམ་དང་། བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའི་རྫུ་འཕྲུལ་དང་། སེམས་ཅན་ཡོངས་སུ་སྨིན་པར་བྱེད་པ་དང་། དགེ་སྦྱོང་གི་འབྲས་བུ་བཞི་པོ་རྒྱུན་དུ་ཞུགས་པ་དང་། ལན་ཅིག་ཕྱིར་འོང་བ་དང་། ཕྱིར་མི་འོང་བ་དང་། དགྲ་བཅོམ་པ་དང་། ཁམས་གསུམ་གྱི་སྲིད་པ་<tei:ref folio="F.231.a"/>ལས་ངེས་པར་འབྱིན་པ་དང་། རྣམ་པར་ཐར་པའི་སྒོ་གསུམ་དང་། འདུ་བྱེད་འཇིག་པ་དང་། དྲན་པ་ཉེ་བར་གཞག་པ་དང་། འཕགས་པའི་བདེན་པ་དང་། རྫུ་འཕྲུལ་གྱི་རྐང་པ་དང་། བསམ་གཏན་དང་། བསྡུ་བའི་དངོས་པོ་དང་། སོ་སོ་ཡང་དག་པར་རིག་པ་དང་། གཟུགས་མེད་པའི་སྙོམས་པར་འཇུག་པ་བཞི་དང་། དབང་པོ་ཡོངས་སུ་དག་པ་དང་། བྱང་ཆུབ་ཀྱི་ཕྱོགས་དང་འཐུན་པའི་ཆོས་མཐའ་དག་གི་སྒྲ་འབྱིན་པར་གྱུར་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>sounds of the following gateways of Dharma rang out: the names of Buddha, Dharma, and Saṅgha; the correct view; insight; discipline; roots of virtue; the austerities performed by the thus-gone ones; their aspirations; the bodhisattvas’ miraculous feats and the ways they ripen sentient beings; the four results of spiritual practitioners: stream enterer, once-returner, non-returner, and worthy one; escape from the existences of the three realms; the three gateways of liberation; destruction of the karmic formations; the applications of mindfulness; the truths of noble ones; the bases of miraculous absorption; concentration; the means of attracting disciples; correct discrimination; the four formless attainments; the purity of the faculties; and all the teachings that are in accord with the factors of awakening.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.231.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཞན་ཡང་སེམས་ཡོངས་སུ་དག་པ་དང་། བྱང་ཆུབ་ཀྱི་ཡན་ལག་དང་། འཕགས་པའི་ལམ་དང་། སྙོམས་པར་འཇུག་པ་དང་། ས་དང་། སྟོབས་དང་། ཐུགས་རྗེ་དང་། བྱམས་པ་ཆེན་པོ་དང་། རྟེན་ཅིང་འབྲེལ་པར་འབྱུང་བ་དང་། ཐེ་ཚོམ་སེལ་བ་དང་། སངས་རྒྱས་ཉིད་ལས་མི་ལྡོག་པ་དང་། ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་དང་། མངོན་པར་རྟོགས་པ་དང་། མི་སྐྱེ་བའི་ཆོས་ལ་བཟོད་པ་དང་། མ་འདྲེས་པ་དང་། སངས་རྒྱས་ཉིད་དུ་འགྱུར་བ་དང་། མི་རྟག་པ་དང་། སྡུག་བསྔལ་བ་དང་། བདག་མེད་པ་དང་། སྟོང་པ་དང་། མ་བྱས་པ་དང་། མ་སྐྱེས་པ་དང་། ཕྱིན་ཅི་མ་ལོག་པ་དང་། ཡང་དག་པའི་མཐའ་དང་། དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པའི་སྙིང་པོའི་ཁོངས་སུ་གཏོགས་པ་རྣམ་པར་མི་རྟོག་པའི་ཡེ་ཤེས་རྟོགས་པ་དང་། རྣལ་འབྱོར་པ་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་སོ་སོ་རང་གིས་རིག་པའི་སྤྱོད་ཡུལ་དང་། སྐྱེ་བ་སྡུག་བསྔལ་བ་དང་། རྒ་བ་དང་། སྡུག་པ་དང་བྲལ་བ་དང་། མི་སྡུག་པ་དང་ཕྲད་པ་དང་། འདོད་པ་བཙལ་ཏེ་མ་རྙེད་པའི་སྡུག་བསྔལ་གྱི་སྒྲ་ཡང་བྱུང་བར་གྱུར་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-011-108"/>Moreover, there also arose sounds pertaining to the pure mind; the branches of awakening; the noble path; the attainments; the strength of the spiritual levels; great compassion and love; dependent origination; dispelling doubt; proceeding irreversibly toward buddhahood; meditative absorption; clear realization; acceptance that phenomena are unborn; the distinct qualities; the transformation into buddhahood; the impermanent, unsatisfactory, selfless, and empty; the unproduced; the unborn; the unmistaken; the limit of reality; the realization of nonconceptual wisdom that is implicit in buddha nature; the domain of the personally realized self-awareness of practitioners; and the sufferings of birth, aging, parting from what is dear, encountering what is disliked, and being unable to fulfill one’s desires.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.231.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཞན་ཡང་ཕུང་པོ་ལྔ་པོ་དག་ལ་སེམས་ཅན་མེད་པ་དང་། གསོ་བ་དང་། གང་ཟག་དང་། སྲོག་མེད་པ་དང་། ཆོས་བདེན་པ་སྐྱེ་བ་མེད་པ་དང་། འགག་པ་མེད་པ་དང་། རྟག་པ་མེད་པ་དང་། ཆད་པ་མེད་པ། འོང་བ་མེད་པ། འགྲོ་བ་མེད་པ་དང་། དཀོན་མཆོག་གསུམ་གྱི་གདུང་དང་། བྱིན་གྱིས་བརླབས་དང་། འགྲོ་བ་ལྔ་པོ་དག་གི་འཁྲུལ་བ་རྨི་ལམ་ལྟ་བུ་དང་། འཁོར་བའི་འདུ་བྱེད་བཙོན་ར་ལྟ་བུ་དང་། སྒྱུ་མ་དང་། སྨིག་རྒྱུ་དང་། ཆུ་ཟླ་དང་། བྲག་ཅ་ལྟ་བུའོ་ཞེས་བྱ་བའི་སྒྲ་བྱུང་བར་གྱུར་ཏེ</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-011-109"/>Moreover, the following sounds occurred: “within the five aggregates there is no sentient being, nor any soul, person, or life-force”; “the truth of phenomena is that all things are without birth, without cessation, without permanence, without annihilation, without coming, and without going”; the lineage of the Three Jewels; blessings; and “the delusion of the five types of beings is like a dream, and the formations of cyclic existence are like a prison, and like an illusion, a mirage, a reflection of the moon in water, and an echo.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.231.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>གཞན་ཡང་དད་པ་དང་མངོན་པར་རྟོགས་པ་དང་། བརྩོན་འགྲུས་དང་། དགེ་བ་བཅུའི་ལས་ཀྱི་ལམ་དང་། འཁོར་བས་སྐྱོ་བ་དང་། དེ་ལྟ་བུ་ལ་སོགས་པ་སྒྲ་བརྒྱ་སྟོང་དུ་མ་བྱུང་བར་<tei:ref folio="F.231.b"/>གྱུར་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Moreover, the following other sounds occurred: “faith”; “clear realization”; “diligence”; “the path of the ten virtuous deeds”; “disenchantment with saṃsāra”; and hundreds, as well as thousands of other such sounds. </seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.231.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་འཁོར་འདུས་པ་མང་པོ་དེ་དག་དང་། བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཕྱོགས་ཕྱོགས་ནས་ལྷགས་པ་དེ་དག་ཐམས་ཅད་ས་ལ་གནས་པའི་ལྷ་དང་། ཀླུ་དང་། ནམ་མཁའ་ལ་གནས་པའི་ལྷ་དང་། གནོད་སྦྱིན་ཐམས་ཅད་སེམས་ངོ་མཚར་དུ་གྱུར་ནས་རངས་པ་སྐྱེས་ཏེ</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-011-110"/>All of the many assembled retinues, as well as the bodhisattvas who had arrived there from various other places, the gods and nāgas living on the earth, and the celestial gods and yakṣas, were all filled with wonder and rapture and</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.231.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཆོས་ཀྱི་སྒོ་མོའི་སྒྲ་དེ་དག་ལ་ཡིད་མི་ཕྱེད་པར་གྱུར་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>they gained confidence in those sounds of gateways of Dharma.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.231.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་དེའི་ཚེ་འཁོར་དེ་དག་གི་ཁོང་དུ་ཆུད་པར་བྱ་བའི་ཕྱིར་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོ་འཇམ་དཔལ་གཞོན་ནུར་གྱུར་པས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ལ་འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་གསོལ་ཏོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-011-111"/>In order to facilitate their understanding, the bodhisattva great being Mañjuśrī­kumāra­bhūta then asked the Blessed One,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.231.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཅིའི་སླད་དུ་ཆོ་འཕྲུལ་ཆེན་པོ་འདི་ལྟ་བུ་བསྟན་པ་ལགས། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Blessed One, for what purpose was this great miracle displayed?”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.231.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་ཚངས་པའི་དབྱངས་ཀྱིས་བཀའ་སྩལ་པ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The Blessed One replied in a voice like that of Brahmā:</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.231.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་ཆོས་ཀྱི་སྒོ་མོ་འདི་དག་ནི་ཡུལ་དགེ་བ་ནས་སྐྱེ་བའི་སེམས་ཅན་རྣམས་ཀྱི་ཆེད་དང་། འཁོར་བཞི་པོ་རྣམས་ཀྱི་ཆེད་དུ་ཡང་ལྷག་པར་བྱིན་གྱིས་བརླབས་ནས་བསྟན་པ་ཡིན་ཏེ</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Mañjuśrī, these gateways of Dharma, which yield great blessings, were taught for the benefit of those who are to be born in the land of Virtue and for the benefit of the fourfold retinue.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.231.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཆོས་ཀྱི་སྒོ་མོ་འདིས་ནི་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་རྣམས་ཚེགས་ཆུང་ངུ་དང་། འབད་པ་ཆུང་ངུས་དབང་པོ་དང་། ཤེས་པ་ཡོངས་སུ་དག་པར་འགྱུར་ཞིང་། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Through these gateways of Dharma, bodhisattvas will purify their faculties and consciousness with only a little hardship and a little effort and</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.231.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཆོས་ཀྱི་སྒོ་མོ་དེ་དང་དེ་དག་ཀྱང་མངོན་པར་རྟོགས་པར་འགྱུར་རོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>they will come to directly realize these gateways of Dharma.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.231.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མ་འོངས་པའི་སྐྱེ་བོ་དེ་དག་ནི་བྱིས་པ་ཆུང་ངུ་ཡན་ཅད་ཆོས་མངོན་པར་རྟོགས་པར་དགའ་ཞིང་རྩེད་མོར་ཡང་ཆོས་ཀྱི་སྒོ་མོ་འདི་དག་སྨྲ་བར་འགྱུར་རོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Beings of the future, from young children upward, will take joy in the realization of the Dharma and they will talk about these gateways of Dharma even in their games.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.231.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སེམས་ཅན་དེ་དག་དབང་པོ་ཡོངས་སུ་བརྟས་ནས་ཆོས་ཀྱི་མིག་རྣམ་པར་དག་པས་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པའི་སྐུ་ཡང་མཐོང་བར་འགྱུར། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Such sentient beings, by developing their faculties in this way, will purify the eye of Dharma and will thereby behold the bodies of the thus-gone ones.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.231.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཆོས་ཀྱི་རྣ་བ་རྣམ་པར་དག་པས་ཆོས་ཡང་དག་པར་ནོད་པ་ཡང་ཐོས་པར་འགྱུར། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Purifying the ear of Dharma, they will hear and receive the Dharma.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.231.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་དག་འཁོར་བ་ན་འདུ་བྱེད་དང་ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་ལས་ཀྱང་སེམས་རྣམ་པར་གྲོལ་བར་འགྱུར་ཏེ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Their minds will be freed from all the formations and phenomena in saṃsāra.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.231.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>སེམས་དེ་ལྟ་བུ་དེས་ན་ཡུལ་དགོན་པ་བྱིན་གྱིས་བརླབས་པ་འདིར་དགེ་བའི་ཕྱོགས་ལ་བརྩོན་པའམ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>With such minds, they will exert themselves in virtue here in this blessed wilderness, or</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.231.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡང་ན་རི་གླང་རུ་ལ་གནས་པ་དེ་དག་ཐམས་ཅད་དངོས་གྲུབ་ཐོབ་པར་འགྱུར་ཏེ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>they will live on Mount Gośṛṅga and will all gain realization there.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.231.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བདུད་སྡིག་ཅན་གྱིས་ཀྱང་གླགས་མི་རྙེད་ན་གཞན་དག་གིས་ལྟ་སྨོས་ཀྱང་ཅི་དགོས། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Evil Māra himself will be unable to harm them, let alone anyone else.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.231.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འདི་ལྟ་སྟེ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>It is like this.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.231.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལྷ་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་འཁོར་གནོད་སྦྱིན་ནམ། དྲི་ཟའམ། མིའམ་ཅི་ཆད་པས་བཅད་པར་འགྱུར་ན</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Even if the gods were to penalize and punish the retinues of yakṣas, gandharvas, or kinnaras,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.231.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འང་མཆོད་རྟེན་གོ་མ་ས་ལ་གན་ད་དང་། རི་གླང་རུ་ལ་འཁྲས་ན་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>if these beings were to take shelter at the Gomasalaganda stūpa and Mount Gośṛṅga,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.231.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་དག་གིས་མི་མཐོང་བར་འགྱུར་རོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>the gods would be unable to see them.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.231.b</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བརྒྱ་ལ་མཐོང་ན་ཡང་སེམས་ཞི་བར་འགྱུར་ཏེ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Even if they should happen to see them, their minds would become peaceful.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.232.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྒྱུ་དེས་ན་རི་གླང་རུ་དང་། མཆོད་རྟེན་གོ་མ་ས་ལ་གན་ད་ནི་མཚམས་<tei:ref folio="F.232.a"/>བཅད་པ་དང་། གཙང་བྱེད་དང་། སྐྱབས་དང་། འཇིག་རྟེན་གྱི་ཁམས་གཞན་དག་ན་གནས་པའི་སེམས་ཅན་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་ཀྱང་ཕྱག་བྱ་བར་འོས་པ་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>For this reason, Mount Gośṛṅga and the Gomasalaganda stūpa are an asylum, a sanctuary, and a haven. They are worthy of homage by beings living in other worlds.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.232.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>མཆོད་རྟེན་གོ་མ་ས་ལ་གན་ད་དང་། རི་གླང་རུ་དང་། ཡུལ་དགེ་བ་དང་། མཁར་དགེ་བ་ཅན་དང་། དགོན་པ་བྱིན་གྱིས་བརླབས་བརླབས་པའི་མིང་ཐོས་ནས་དད་པ་སྐྱེས་པ་ཙམ་གྱིས་ཀྱང་སྡིག་པ་ཆེན་པོ་འབྱང་བར་འགྱུར་རོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Simply to feel faith upon hearing the names of the Gomasalaganda stūpa, Mount Gośṛṅga, the land of Virtue, Virtuous Castle, and the blessed hermitages will purify grave misdeeds.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.232.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་དེའི་ཚེ་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་ཚེ་དང་ལྡན་པ་ཤཱ་རིའི་བུ་དང་། རྣམ་ཐོས་ཀྱི་བུ་ལ་བཀའ་སྩལ་པ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-011-113"/>The Blessed One then told venerable Śāriputra and Vaiśravaṇa,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.232.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རིགས་ཀྱི་བུ་ཁྱེད་གཉིས་སོང་ལ་མཚོ་ཆེན་པོ་འདི་ཤའི་རི་དྲོལ་ཏེ། བྱང་ཕྱོགས་ལོགས་སུ་གྱི་ཤོ་གཙང་པོའི་ནང་དུ་ཕོ་ལ་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>“Noble sons, you two go and cut down Sha Mountain and transfer this large lake into the Gyisho River in the north.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.232.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཆུ་ན་གནས་པའི་སེམས་ཅན་རྣམས་ལ་མི་གནོད་པར་སྲུང་བ་དང་། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Thus, without harming any beings living in the water,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.232.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཡུལ་འདིས་མཚམས་མངོན་པར་གྱིས་ཤིག །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>you must guard and demarcate this land.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.232.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་ཉན་ཐོས་ཆེན་པོ་ཤཱ་རིའི་བུ་དང་རྣམ་ཐོས་ཀྱི་བུས་དེ་བཞིན་འཚལ་ལོ་ཞེས་གསོལ་ནས་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-011-114"/>The great hearer Śāriputra and Vaiśravaṇa said in response, “We shall do as you instruct.” Then</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.232.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྫུ་འཕྲུལ་གྱིས་ནམ་མཁའ་ལས་ཤའི་རི་གང་ན་བ་དེ་ལོགས་སུ་ཆས་ཏེ</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>they flew miraculously through the sky in the direction of Sha Mountain.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.232.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཤཱ་རིའི་བུས་ནི་ལག་ན་ཁར་གསིལ་ཐོགས། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Śāriputra held in his hand a staff and</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.232.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>རྣམ་ཐོས་ཀྱི་བུས་ནི་ལག་ན་མདུང་ཐོགས་ནས་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>Vaiśravaṇa held a spear, and</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.232.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཤའི་རི་ཕྱེད་སྟམ་པས་བླངས་ཏེ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>with these they cleaved Sha Mountain into two, picked up the pieces, and</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.232.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ནུབ་ཕྱོགས་ལོགས་སུ་བཞག་ནས་</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>placed them down in the west. Thus,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.232.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཆུ་སྲོལ་ཆེན་པོ་བཏོད་དེ་མཚོ་སྲོག་ཆགས་དང་བཅས་པར་གྱི་ཤོ་གཙང་པོའི་ནང་དུ་ཕོ་སྟེ། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>they created a large riverbank through which the lake with all the animals living therein was diverted into the Gyisho River.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.232.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ཚུལ་དེ་ལྟ་བུས་མཆོད་རྟེན་གོ་མ་ས་ལ་གན་ད་དང་། རི་གླང་རུ་དང་། ལི་ཡུལ་དེ་མངོན་པར་བྱས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>In this manner, the Gomasalaganda stūpa, Mount Gośṛṅga, and the land of Khotan were brought into being.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.232.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་འཕགས་པ་སྤྱན་རས་གཟིགས་དབང་ཕྱུག་དང་། བྱམས་པ་ལ་སོགས་པ་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོ་བརྒྱད་དང་། བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཉི་ཁྲི་དྲང་སྲོང་དང་བཅས་པ་དང་། རྣམ་ཐོས་ཀྱི་བུ་དང་ཁྱིམ་གཅིག་ལ་སོགས་པ་ལྷ་ཆེན་པོ་བརྒྱད་དང་། འཁོར་སུམ་ཁྲི་ལྔ་སྟོང་ལྔ་བརྒྱ་དང་བཅས་པ་ལ་མཆོད་རྟེན་གོ་མ་ས་ལ་གན་ད་ལ་སོགས་པ་ཡོངས་སུ་གཏད་དེ</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-011-115"/>At this point, the Blessed One entrusted the Gomasalaganda stūpa and the other places to the eight bodhisattva great beings such as noble Avalokiteśvara and Maitreya, the twenty thousand bodhisattvas, the sages, the eight great gods such as Vaiśravaṇa and Gṛhadāha, and the remaining retinue of thirty-five thousand five hundred beings.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.232.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>ལྷ་དེ་དག་གིས་ཀྱང་དེ་བཞིན་དུ་མནོས་སོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>All of the gods also accepted this entrustment.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.232.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་ཀྱང་དེ་བཞིན་དུ་གནང་ངོ་། །</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>The Blessed One bestowed it accordingly.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.232.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་དེ་སྐད་ཅེས་བཀའ་སྩལ་པ་དང་། </seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-011-116"/>When the Blessed One had thus spoken,</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.232.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཁོར་དེ་དག་ཐམས་ཅད་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་གསུངས་པ་ལ་ཡི་རངས་ཏེ་མངོན་པར་བསྟོད་དོ།། །།</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>the entire assembly rejoiced and praised what the Blessed One had said.</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
            <prop name="folio">F.232.a</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo">
                <seg>འཕགས་པ་གླང་རུ་ལུང་བསྟན་པ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་ཐེག་པ་ཆེན་པོའི་མདོ་རྫོགས་སོ།། །།</seg>
            </tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en">
                <seg>
                    <tei:milestone xml:id="UT22084-076-011-117"/>This completes The Noble Great Vehicle Sūtra “The Prophecy on Mount Gośṛṅga.”</seg>
            </tuv>
</tu>
</body>
</tmx>